SPEAKER_0:  This is nuts.
SPEAKER_0:  and nice Islamic.
SPEAKER_0:  Fatherly.
SPEAKER_0:  Regime
SPEAKER_0:  clear signs of fascism.
SPEAKER_0:  Clear, Sansif.
SPEAKER_0:  the state control and
SPEAKER_0:  pay any price to stay in power.
SPEAKER_0:  So even violence, extreme violence.
SPEAKER_1:  The following is a conversation with Abbas Ammanah.
SPEAKER_1:  a historian at Yale University specializing in.
SPEAKER_1:  the modern history of Iran.
SPEAKER_1:  my love and my heart.
SPEAKER_1:  goes out to the Iranian people in their current struggle for freedom.
SPEAKER_1:  I hope that this conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  helps.
SPEAKER_1:  folks who listen.
SPEAKER_1:  understand the nature.
SPEAKER_1:  and the importance.
SPEAKER_1:  of the struggle.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the Lex Friedman Podcast.
SPEAKER_1:  support it please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now...
SPEAKER_1:  Dear friends.
SPEAKER_1:  Here's Abbas.
SPEAKER_1:  Amen.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's start with the current situation in Iran.
SPEAKER_1:  On September 16th, protests broke out in Tehran and quickly spread.
SPEAKER_1:  or the death of a 22 year old.
SPEAKER_1:  Maxa.
SPEAKER_1:  A mini.
SPEAKER_1:  Eyewitnesses saw her beaten to death by the morality police.
SPEAKER_1:  This is a heavy topic, but it's a really important topic.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you explain?
SPEAKER_0:  What happened?
SPEAKER_0:  The protests are now in their sixth week.
SPEAKER_0:  the death of that young woman.
SPEAKER_0:  occurred.
SPEAKER_0:  who was visiting Tehran as a tourist.
SPEAKER_0:  PIKED!
SPEAKER_0:  something very deep.
SPEAKER_0:  that particularly concerned the younger generations. That is what.
SPEAKER_0:  you would call the equivalent of the...
SPEAKER_0:  Z generation in this country. Yes. They call themselves the hey hashtadi.
SPEAKER_0:  in Persia.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  Iran follows the
SPEAKER_0:  solar calendar of its own.
SPEAKER_0:  It's an ancient story calendar.
SPEAKER_0:  And the time that they were born, they were in the...
SPEAKER_0:  1380s, that's what they call themselves, H-30.
SPEAKER_0:  80s hashtag for the 80s.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Well, the circumstances that surrounds the...
SPEAKER_0:  unfortunate death of this young...
SPEAKER_0:  Beautiful.
SPEAKER_0:  a Kurdish woman.
SPEAKER_0:  is really tragic. She was arrested by what is referred to as the morality police.
SPEAKER_0:  morality patrol.
SPEAKER_0:  called...
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, the air shot
SPEAKER_0:  and guidance.
SPEAKER_0:  Police, that is.
SPEAKER_0:  Presumably there were two women.
SPEAKER_0:  fully clad that these officers serving on that force.
SPEAKER_0:  and two men.
SPEAKER_0:  and nobody exactly knows what had happened. She had been...
SPEAKER_0:  Beaten up.
SPEAKER_0:  And apparently there was no...
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  sign of any...
SPEAKER_0:  wrongdoing on her side. She was.
SPEAKER_0:  fully covered.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  It seems that...
SPEAKER_0:  there was some altercation in the process.
SPEAKER_0:  And the outcome was that she was unconscious.
SPEAKER_0:  not necessarily when she was arrested.
SPEAKER_0:  but in the course of the detention.
SPEAKER_0:  when they take them to a center, presumably to re-educate them.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  she apparently collapsed.
SPEAKER_0:  and maybe my sense is that she must have had some kind of a...
SPEAKER_0:  problem because of the skull being broken or something get happened.
SPEAKER_0:  And she died in the hospital the next day.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's...
SPEAKER_0:  through the social media.
SPEAKER_0:  was widely spread throughout.
SPEAKER_0:  Iran and almost the next day, surprisingly, you could see this.
SPEAKER_0:  Outburst.
SPEAKER_0:  of sympathy for her.
SPEAKER_0:  People are in the streets weeping.
SPEAKER_0:  because she was seen as such an innocent young woman, 22 years old.
SPEAKER_0:  and the family, the mother and the father, also mourning for her.
SPEAKER_0:  and being a Kurd visiting Tehran.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  This all added up to...
SPEAKER_0:  really turn her into some kind of a martyr of disguise.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's what it is.
SPEAKER_0:  Hell.
SPEAKER_0:  picture.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  graphics that were artistically produced.
SPEAKER_0:  based on her portrait.
SPEAKER_0:  has now dominates basically as the symbol of this.
SPEAKER_0:  protest movement.
SPEAKER_0:  And the protest movement goes on. Everybody was thinking, or at least the authorities were thinking that is going to die out in a matter of a few days.
SPEAKER_0:  but it became more intense.
SPEAKER_0:  in the streets of Tehran by young women.
SPEAKER_0:  Mostly probably between.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say 17, 18 teenagers to 22, 23.
SPEAKER_0:  or thereabouts, and then to university campuses.
SPEAKER_0:  all around the country.
SPEAKER_0:  and then even to high school.
SPEAKER_0:  And that also made it a very remarkable protest movement.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  First of all, it involves the youth.
SPEAKER_0:  and not necessarily the older generations.
SPEAKER_0:  You see them around, but not as many.
SPEAKER_0:  also
SPEAKER_0:  You see men and women together, young.
SPEAKER_0:  girls and boys.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  They are adamant.
SPEAKER_0:  They are desperate in the sense of...
SPEAKER_0:  Horn of the protest.
SPEAKER_0:  And they are extremely courageous because they stand against the...
SPEAKER_0:  our security forces.
SPEAKER_0:  that were immediately.
SPEAKER_0:  were sent off to the streets.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  and in full gear, that is.
SPEAKER_1:  So what are the currents of pain, emotion?
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  What is this?
SPEAKER_1:  turmoil that rose to the surface that resulted in these big protests.
SPEAKER_1:  What are the different?
SPEAKER_1:  Feelings.
SPEAKER_1:  ideas that came to the surface here that resulted in such quick scaling of this protest.
SPEAKER_0:  Well...
SPEAKER_0:  If you...
SPEAKER_0:  Listen to the...
SPEAKER_0:  main slogan, which is the message of this movement.
SPEAKER_0:  It's called women.
SPEAKER_0:  Life.
SPEAKER_0:  freedom.
SPEAKER_0:  Zan zindegi azadi.
SPEAKER_0:  which is a translation of actually...
SPEAKER_0:  The Kurdish equivalent, which is close to Persian being in the European language.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's apparently initiated.
SPEAKER_0:  First.
SPEAKER_0:  in the Syrian Kurdistan.
SPEAKER_0:  where they were fighting against the Islamic...
SPEAKER_0:  Daesh.
SPEAKER_0:  forces.
SPEAKER_0:  because they were attacking the...
SPEAKER_0:  Yazidis there.
SPEAKER_0:  and the women being enslaved.
SPEAKER_0:  But the message as it moved, historians are interested in this kind of thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Friends
SPEAKER_0:  So it has moved to Kurdistan and from Kurdistan, now being the message of this movement.
SPEAKER_0:  Reflex.
SPEAKER_0:  pretty much.
SPEAKER_0:  Thumbs up!
SPEAKER_0:  Watch.
SPEAKER_0:  this movement is all about. Women?
SPEAKER_0:  and the forefront.
SPEAKER_0:  because of all the...
SPEAKER_0:  One might say discriminations, the treatment, the humiliation.
SPEAKER_0:  that this younger generation feels, well, not only the younger generations, but...
SPEAKER_0:  most of the Iranian secular middle classes since 1979.
SPEAKER_0:  for the past 43 years.
SPEAKER_0:  And they would think that...
SPEAKER_0:  They these
SPEAKER_0:  All.
SPEAKER_0:  basically symbolized or...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  represented by
SPEAKER_0:  the wearing the mandatory wearing of the hijab.
SPEAKER_0:  which is at the core.
SPEAKER_0:  of this protest.
SPEAKER_0:  You see the young women, if you look at many of these clips that comes through in the past six weeks.
SPEAKER_0:  Women in streets take off their mandatory.
SPEAKER_0:  scarves which is a young shawl.
SPEAKER_0:  or some kind of a head covering, that's all.
SPEAKER_0:  and they throw it into the...
SPEAKER_0:  bonfire in the middle of the street and they dance around it.
SPEAKER_0:  and slogans.
SPEAKER_0:  So there is a sense of complete rejection.
SPEAKER_0:  of what this regime for 43 years... 43 years.
SPEAKER_0:  have been imposing on women.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not as it's sometimes been portrayed, a movement.
SPEAKER_0:  against her job.
SPEAKER_0:  through and through.
SPEAKER_0:  But it basically says, you know, there has to be.
SPEAKER_0:  The choice.
SPEAKER_0:  for those who want to wear hijab and those...
SPEAKER_0:  want to remain without a job.
SPEAKER_1:  Hijab is a symbol of something much deeper.
SPEAKER_0:  much deeper.
SPEAKER_0:  And actually, before we get into that, it's interesting to note.
SPEAKER_0:  that in many of these demonstrations we see in the university campuses or in the streets.
SPEAKER_0:  You see women with hijab.
SPEAKER_0:  young women with hijabs.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't-
SPEAKER_0:  next to those have to remove their hijab and they're...
SPEAKER_0:  together basically protesting. That's the most interesting feature.
SPEAKER_0:  of these demonstrations and then men and women together.
SPEAKER_0:  against the segregation that the regime.
SPEAKER_0:  has imposed upon them all these years.
SPEAKER_0:  Now in terms of
SPEAKER_0:  what it represents.
SPEAKER_0:  As I pointed out, one is the question of the whole series of what might say civil and legal.
SPEAKER_0:  discriminations against women.
SPEAKER_0:  you are considered as a kind of a second class citizen.
SPEAKER_0:  You depend on your men.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a kind of f-
SPEAKER_0:  Patriarchy.
SPEAKER_0:  that has been institutionalized in the Islamic Republic in a very profound fashion.
SPEAKER_0:  And that means that probably.
SPEAKER_0:  in matters of divorce.
SPEAKER_0:  marriage and divorce.
SPEAKER_0:  in matters of custody of your children, in matters of inheritance.
SPEAKER_0:  in matter of
SPEAKER_0:  freedom of movement.
SPEAKER_0:  You depend.
SPEAKER_0:  on your husband, your father, your brother.
SPEAKER_0:  A male member of your
SPEAKER_0:  family, your child even.
SPEAKER_0:  your son.
SPEAKER_0:  could be the case.
SPEAKER_0:  And because of that...
SPEAKER_0:  Obviously a younger generation who is so...
SPEAKER_0:  well informed through social media.
SPEAKER_0:  knows about the world.
SPEAKER_0:  As much as an American does, American kid does, probably sometimes more.
SPEAKER_0:  They're very, very curious.
SPEAKER_0:  It's from what I hear or sometimes that I met a few of them outside Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  You'll see that how they this.
SPEAKER_0:  a new generation is.
SPEAKER_0:  completely different from what the Islamic Republic wanted to create in its social engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  It's basically the failure.
SPEAKER_0:  of 43 years.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Islamic Republic's acts of.
SPEAKER_0:  imposition of certain so-called Islamic values.
SPEAKER_0:  on women.
SPEAKER_0:  Then it's a matter of education.
SPEAKER_0:  you would see that there is segregation in the schools.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  One of the issues that now, right now, is at the heart of this demonstration is that
SPEAKER_0:  self-services in many of the campuses of Iranian universities are segregated.
SPEAKER_0:  male and female, two different.
SPEAKER_0:  rooms to different doors.
SPEAKER_0:  Not your f-
SPEAKER_0:  Breaking through the walls.
SPEAKER_0:  virtually everywhere and sit together.
SPEAKER_0:  in order to
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, basically...
SPEAKER_0:  resist.
SPEAKER_0:  the authorities who wants to
SPEAKER_0:  in post segregation.
SPEAKER_0:  in matters of...
SPEAKER_0:  appearance in the public. Retard?
SPEAKER_0:  It may seem to us as a kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  trivial and secondary, but appearance is important.
SPEAKER_0:  Clothing is important.
SPEAKER_0:  how you would imagine yourself is important.
SPEAKER_0:  They don't want to be.
SPEAKER_0:  seen in the way that the authorities would like to impose upon them as this kind of an idea of a chase.
SPEAKER_0:  Islamic woman who is
SPEAKER_0:  Fully covered.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's fully protected.
SPEAKER_0:  the idea of a male member of the family protects.
SPEAKER_0:  the female.
SPEAKER_0:  That is.
SPEAKER_0:  what you would see at the heart of this.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't have a link.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course...
SPEAKER_0:  That goes with everything else. The second part of this message, the idea of life.
SPEAKER_0:  basically means...
SPEAKER_0:  if you like to use the American equivalent of this pursuit of the happiness. That's what they want.
SPEAKER_0:  It was fun.
SPEAKER_0:  They want music.
SPEAKER_0:  They want dancing, they want to be free in the street, they want to have girl boyfriends.
SPEAKER_0:  and live.
SPEAKER_0:  Really?
SPEAKER_0:  and don't be constantly looked by the big brother to tell them what to do.
SPEAKER_0:  and not to do or not to do.
SPEAKER_0:  So
SPEAKER_0:  That is, that they share virtually with the entire.
SPEAKER_0:  with the entire Iranian society as a whole.
SPEAKER_0:  Although the older generations, that's a big puzzle.
SPEAKER_0:  But you would see that the older generation don't, so far at least.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't take part.
SPEAKER_0:  as extensively as one might imagine.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is.
SPEAKER_0:  variety of reasons perhaps you can get to that.
SPEAKER_0:  Later on if you like.
SPEAKER_0:  But as far as this younger generation, they don't care. They don't listen even.
SPEAKER_0:  as much.
SPEAKER_0:  to their parents as the older generations did.
SPEAKER_0:  or one might say even the nature of the relationship between the...
SPEAKER_0:  parents and the
SPEAKER_0:  Youth has changed.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not the concept of, again, a patriarchy.
SPEAKER_0:  that a father or even a mother.
SPEAKER_0:  would tell the...
SPEAKER_0:  No terrorist sign. What to do?
SPEAKER_0:  as basically they have to negotiate.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_1:  of the power of authority.
SPEAKER_1:  Parents.
SPEAKER_1:  government.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, it's that every person can decide their own fate and there's no, uh,
SPEAKER_1:  Lessening of value of the wisdom of old age and old institutes.
SPEAKER_0:  Precisely that's what it is.
SPEAKER_0:  they are surprisingly aware.
SPEAKER_0:  that where they are as a generation. So it's a sense of pride as a-
SPEAKER_0:  We are.
SPEAKER_0:  different from the older generation.
SPEAKER_0:  from your parents to compromise.
SPEAKER_0:  and lived with the restrictions that the Islamic regime put on you.
SPEAKER_0:  Your grandparents was the generation that actually involved in the revolution of 79.
SPEAKER_0:  the parents, which were the middle generation.
SPEAKER_0:  And these are the third generation of the revolution of 1979.
SPEAKER_0:  And therefore the...
SPEAKER_0:  differentiate themselves in terms of their identity from the older generation.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the life part of it. One can go more and more, they want to access, and they see on social media.
SPEAKER_0:  What happens in the rest of the world? Well, I'm there.
SPEAKER_0:  They're much better digitally.
SPEAKER_0:  skilled.
SPEAKER_0:  than my generation, for instance.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  They know about all the personalities. They know about all the celebrities. They know about all the trends that goes out.
SPEAKER_0:  Outside Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the second part of this message. And then of course the third part is the word Azadi.
SPEAKER_0:  meaning freedom or liberty.
SPEAKER_0:  which is this long...
SPEAKER_0:  standing demand of the
SPEAKER_0:  Iranians, I would say for the whole
SPEAKER_0:  century, ever since the Constitutional...
SPEAKER_0:  Revolution of 1906.
SPEAKER_0:  Iran has witnessed this problem.
SPEAKER_0:  of a.
SPEAKER_0:  authorities that usually emerged at the end of a revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  narrative and
SPEAKER_0:  basically impose its own image.
SPEAKER_0:  on the population and the youth.
SPEAKER_0:  and create authoritarian regimes of which, over the course of time...
SPEAKER_0:  I would say that the Islamic Republic is the worst.
SPEAKER_0:  in the sense that it's...
SPEAKER_0:  uh... it's intrusion is not only
SPEAKER_0:  in the political sense in the...
SPEAKER_0:  for instance, banning the freedom of speech.
SPEAKER_0:  meddling with the elections, banning political parties, all kinds of that things which are that
SPEAKER_0:  political or civil freedoms
SPEAKER_0:  but it's intrusion into the personal life of the individual.
SPEAKER_0:  which is the worst kind in a sense as
SPEAKER_0:  you would see that there is always an authority that basically...
SPEAKER_0:  dominates their life or monitors their life.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I, and they do it.
SPEAKER_0:  in a kind of a very consistent fashion, which makes this idea.
SPEAKER_0:  of freedom so important.
SPEAKER_0:  as part of the message of this new movement.
SPEAKER_0:  you would see that in today's Iran, there are no independent political parties.
SPEAKER_0:  There's...
SPEAKER_0:  Very little.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  probably freedom of the press. I wouldn't say that it's entirely gone.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's very...
SPEAKER_0:  and when you are tmd alert and remember our
SPEAKER_0:  There's enormous amount of propaganda machine.
SPEAKER_0:  which dominates the entire...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  radio and TV system in Iran. It's completely in the hands of the government.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course you would see this.
SPEAKER_0:  variety of other tools.
SPEAKER_0:  FOOL
SPEAKER_0:  trying to indoctrinate.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  Iranian population across the board.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's another sign of this kind of a sense of.
SPEAKER_0:  a sense of.
SPEAKER_0:  being.
SPEAKER_0:  totally.
SPEAKER_0:  Left out.
SPEAKER_0:  You're not belonging.
SPEAKER_0:  to what's going on.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of
SPEAKER_0:  Hover.
SPEAKER_0:  empowerment and disempowerment.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the situation as far as the idea of a freedom of cancer.
SPEAKER_0:  And this three.
SPEAKER_0:  somewhat miraculously.
SPEAKER_0:  and perhaps
SPEAKER_0:  unintentionally.
SPEAKER_0:  and the three parts of this message.
SPEAKER_0:  complement each other.
SPEAKER_0:  Because...
SPEAKER_0:  Perhaps for the first time we see that women.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm in the forefront.
SPEAKER_0:  Offer.
SPEAKER_0:  of a movement. I hesitate to say revolution because I'm not particularly happy with revolutions.
SPEAKER_0: 恨
SPEAKER_0:  The revolutions worldwide in Iran have always been so...
SPEAKER_0:  miserable in terms of their outcome that we have to be careful not to use the word revolution again.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's where it stands now.
SPEAKER_0:  And the regime was thinking that, well, these are kids.
SPEAKER_0:  they're going to go away and then of course they're completely...
SPEAKER_0:  conspiratorially in their thinking.
SPEAKER_0:  They constantly think that.
SPEAKER_0:  These are all the...
SPEAKER_0:  instigations and provocations of foreign powers. I have once also been made a Greek reference.ın
SPEAKER_0:  the great Satan in the United States, this is Israel.
SPEAKER_0:  or these are actually the supreme data sets in so many words.
SPEAKER_0:  His only response so far that he had
SPEAKER_0:  in the past six weeks with regard to this demonstration is that
SPEAKER_0:  These are the children of the SAVAK, SAVAK being the security forces.
SPEAKER_0:  of the show is done.
SPEAKER_0:  43 years later.
SPEAKER_0:  He claims that the children...
SPEAKER_0:  16, 17 years, 20 years old.
SPEAKER_0:  Kids in the street are the grandchildren or children of
SPEAKER_0:  some imaginary
SPEAKER_0:  survival of the short security force. So there's the idea is that.
SPEAKER_1:  These protests are internal.
SPEAKER_1:  and external.
SPEAKER_1:  saboteurs so people trying to sabotage the government.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, and they are misled as far as they can go.
SPEAKER_1:  And then there's the great state in the United States and other places are.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Controlling.
SPEAKER_1:  Sort of a...
SPEAKER_1:  either controlling the narrative, feeding propaganda, or literally.
SPEAKER_1:  sending people.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think that they have, I don't think even they have.
SPEAKER_0:  that kind of imagination.
SPEAKER_0:  precise to say what you have said.
SPEAKER_0:  they would say that they're controlling the narrative. They basically say, no, these are agents.
SPEAKER_0:  of the foreign powers.
SPEAKER_0:  and their families are all sold out and they are basically lost their loyalties to the great Islamic.
SPEAKER_0:  Republic.
SPEAKER_0:  And therefore...
SPEAKER_0:  they can be treated so brutally, they can be suppressed so brutally.
SPEAKER_0:  which I haven't actually said what they're doing because.
SPEAKER_0:  I thought perhaps.
SPEAKER_0:  First, we should talk about who these kids are in the street.
SPEAKER_0:  before we move on about the response of the government.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  One major factor.
SPEAKER_0:  which seems to add to the anxiety.
SPEAKER_0:  of, well, the regime is extremely anxious now because they're in a position.
SPEAKER_0:  It shows that they don't have the lack of confidence in a sense, that they would see them.
SPEAKER_0:  reacting in a very forceful way.
SPEAKER_0:  because basically they don't seem to have.
SPEAKER_0:  that kind of a confidence to allow this.
SPEAKER_0:  this message or the movement to air.
SPEAKER_0:  Be aired.
SPEAKER_0:  But the one element which...
SPEAKER_0:  corresponds to that is that there is a
SPEAKER_0:  expatriate population.
SPEAKER_0:  of Iranians worldwide.
SPEAKER_0:  They are probably now, according to some estimates, close to 4 million, even more.
SPEAKER_0:  Iranians abroad and they're all over the world from Australia and New Zealand.
SPEAKER_0:  Japan.
SPEAKER_0:  Western Europe.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, uh, techie.
SPEAKER_0:  and United States and Canada.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Just to give you one example, last Saturday,
SPEAKER_0:  There was a mass demonstration in Berlin.
SPEAKER_0:  by the Iranians from...
SPEAKER_0:  Germany and all over Europe.
SPEAKER_0:  Western Europe.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was at least, I think, probably the conservative estimate was about 100,000.
SPEAKER_0:  So 100,000 Iranians showed up.
SPEAKER_0:  in Berlin demonstrating against
SPEAKER_0:  the treatment of the...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, we may need to unword.
SPEAKER_0:  the movement in Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  The government.
SPEAKER_0:  I think obviously this must have been some...
SPEAKER_0:  Instigation by...
SPEAKER_0:  foreign powers and they want to destroy the Islamic Republic.
SPEAKER_0:  And not only that, but their propaganda is kind of ridiculous.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  I listened actually to how they portrayed it in the newspapers. I listened to the...
SPEAKER_0:  Iranian news.
SPEAKER_0:  This is officially controlled, government-controlled news.
SPEAKER_0:  And in the papers, much of the papers that are in the control of the government.
SPEAKER_0:  One of them or actually the...
SPEAKER_0:  the major news program.
SPEAKER_0:  portrayed the demonstrations that
SPEAKER_0:  10,000 people.
SPEAKER_0:  showed up in Berlin and protested against the rising
SPEAKER_0:  prices, rising rates for gas and oil.
SPEAKER_0:  in Germany.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's how they mislead.
SPEAKER_0:  in a very rather stupid fashion because...
SPEAKER_0:  probably 95% if not.
SPEAKER_0:  100% of the Iranians.
SPEAKER_0:  are listening.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  Passion speaking.
SPEAKER_0:  Media outside Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a BBC.
SPEAKER_0:  passion.
SPEAKER_0:  There is Iran International, at least five or six of them.
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_1:  probably really important to highlight that.
SPEAKER_1:  Iran.
SPEAKER_1:  is a very modern and tech savvy nation.
SPEAKER_0:  not just the young people. Probably more than.
SPEAKER_0:  More than I feel sometimes
SPEAKER_0:  when I compare myself to what they are doing. It's 1979, the earlier years.
SPEAKER_0:  for a decade or two.
SPEAKER_0:  They tried in a very crude fashion to...
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  Access to.
SPEAKER_0:  media outside Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  because this is all through dishes, okay?
SPEAKER_0:  And satellite dishes are everywhere. If you look at the...
SPEAKER_0:  You know
SPEAKER_0:  buildings, small houses, small...
SPEAKER_0:  towns and villages in Iran. There is always a.
SPEAKER_0:  dish.
SPEAKER_0:  and they watch all kinds of things through this.
SPEAKER_0:  and particularly because of what's happening now.
SPEAKER_0:  They listen to all the news.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Broadcast from
SPEAKER_0:  all this media and they're extremely active.
SPEAKER_0:  There are...
SPEAKER_0:  probably some of them even 24 hours or close, very extensive coverage.
SPEAKER_0:  of every clip that comes through.
SPEAKER_0:  So what the government is doing now...
SPEAKER_0:  Islamic Republic.
SPEAKER_0:  is that they restrict.
SPEAKER_0:  the entire internet. They shut down the internet. They shut down the internet.
SPEAKER_0:  But they cannot afford shutting the internet because much of the business, much of the...
SPEAKER_0:  everyday life, much of the government.
SPEAKER_0:  At first depends on the
SPEAKER_0:  internet like everywhere else.
SPEAKER_0:  And Iran is extremely...
SPEAKER_0:  If I hear from many of the colleagues and friends...
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like in certain respects, it's like Sweden.
SPEAKER_0:  Where you go there?
SPEAKER_0:  There is no more currency and for a very good reason because there is so much inflation.
SPEAKER_0:  that the banknotes are...
SPEAKER_0:  Worthless in SS.
SPEAKER_0:  So everything is true.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  sweeping your card.
SPEAKER_0:  And that entire system is in standstill because...
SPEAKER_0:  People cannot buy food.
SPEAKER_0:  You go to the supermarket, that's how you would do it.
SPEAKER_0:  You-
SPEAKER_0:  You.
SPEAKER_0:  order food to come to your house.
SPEAKER_0:  which Iranians were at least the middle classes.
SPEAKER_0:  more prosperous with that crisis doing all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  So they...
SPEAKER_0:  deliver everything and because of the COVID it became even more.
SPEAKER_0:  and they have to pay all through this.
SPEAKER_0:  system.
SPEAKER_0:  So what happens is that now they're estimating that every day $50 million, the Iranian government.
SPEAKER_0:  or the Iranian economy is losing because of slowing the internet.
SPEAKER_0:  plus the frustration.
SPEAKER_1:  is growing.
SPEAKER_1:  because
SPEAKER_0:  You can't order food.
SPEAKER_0:  Among others. Right. I mean, they are-
SPEAKER_0:  They are in touch with...
SPEAKER_0:  What's up?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, every Iranian.
SPEAKER_0:  virtually every run yet
SPEAKER_0:  that has education and education in the sense that has gone through.
SPEAKER_0:  the high schools and universities knows how to use the WhatsApp.
SPEAKER_1:  big middle class.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you said, secular class in Iran and there.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot of at least capacity for, if not revolution, then.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  political, ideological.
SPEAKER_1:  turmoil.
SPEAKER_0:  and a huge amount of hatred.
SPEAKER_0:  So the hatred has grown. Yes, hatred of the-
SPEAKER_0:  of the policies.
SPEAKER_0:  of the regime.
SPEAKER_0:  of isolation?
SPEAKER_0:  That's a huge point that you hear a great deal about.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't want to be isolated. We don't want to be humiliated. Iran is not about...
SPEAKER_0:  this.
SPEAKER_0:  this miserable regime.
SPEAKER_0:  that is ruling over us.
SPEAKER_0:  We have a great culture, so there's a sense of pride.
SPEAKER_0:  in their own...
SPEAKER_0:  culture some of it, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Islamic, somewhat pre-Islamic.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's a huge...
SPEAKER_0:  a sense of pride in that.
SPEAKER_0:  and they see that.
SPEAKER_0:  They cannot.
SPEAKER_0:  communicate with the outside world.
SPEAKER_0:  They want to travel.
SPEAKER_0:  abroad which they do.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, for one thing...
SPEAKER_0:  The Iranian regime never actually...
SPEAKER_0:  for the majority of the population.
SPEAKER_0:  never put restrictions. it's not like
SPEAKER_0:  Where is it? Union, where you have to-
SPEAKER_0:  Have it.
SPEAKER_0:  used to have it.
SPEAKER_0:  permission to move from one place to another.
SPEAKER_0:  And then of course...
SPEAKER_0:  deep.
SPEAKER_0:  The Islamic regime since 1979 basically...
SPEAKER_0:  I chased away or destroyed the old middle class. It's my generation basically.
SPEAKER_0:  My parents, they are the shit.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the D.
SPEAKER_0:  secular middle class of the Pahlavi era.
SPEAKER_0:  in the hope that they can do this social engineering and create this.
SPEAKER_0:  Islamic
SPEAKER_0:  Alright.
SPEAKER_0:  society of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  The bad news for them.
SPEAKER_0:  was that that didn't happen.
SPEAKER_0:  and that memory.
SPEAKER_0:  Persistent.
SPEAKER_0:  the middle class that was created since past 40 years.
SPEAKER_0:  is much larger in size.
SPEAKER_0:  than what it was because there was...
SPEAKER_0:  Of course, the demographic revolution. That's the, that's the big.
SPEAKER_0:  there's a very foundation of it, it's the demographic revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  population in Iran, I've written an article about it actually.
SPEAKER_0:  population in Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  Rip
SPEAKER_0:  The turn of the century, last century, that's 20th century.
SPEAKER_0:  Population of Iran was about 9 million or so.
SPEAKER_0:  is now 83 million.
SPEAKER_0:  And that is.
SPEAKER_0:  Since 1979, the population was 35 million.
SPEAKER_0:  between the past 40 years, it's...
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, double.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's 83 million.
SPEAKER_0:  Although...
SPEAKER_0:  One of the great successes, I don't want to bore you with the details about the
SPEAKER_0:  Demography, but it's important in demographics is not born. You will you can see that.
SPEAKER_0:  The birth rate was very high.
SPEAKER_0:  Otherwise, you wouldn't have doubled your population in a matter of four decades.
SPEAKER_0:  But Iranians...
SPEAKER_0:  because of the AirBan.
SPEAKER_0:  shift to an urban population.
SPEAKER_0:  because of the growth of them.
SPEAKER_0:  be there for us.
SPEAKER_0:  Because of the education.
SPEAKER_0:  day.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically.
SPEAKER_0:  the pattern of the...
SPEAKER_0:  of population growth change.
SPEAKER_0:  Iran used to be...
SPEAKER_0:  2.8 or 3%?
SPEAKER_0:  Best rates?
SPEAKER_0:  in around 1980s.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say 1970s, 1980s.
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  It is 1.1.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's probably the most successful country in the...
SPEAKER_0:  Middle East in terms of the
SPEAKER_0:  population control.
SPEAKER_0:  despite the government.
SPEAKER_0:  a consistent.
SPEAKER_0:  I attempt to try to
SPEAKER_0:  encourage people to have more kids.
SPEAKER_0:  middle-class refuses to do that.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is middle class not only anymore in the capital.
SPEAKER_0:  but this is very smaller towns and cities, places that used to be villages.
SPEAKER_0:  Now you look at them, they have a-
SPEAKER_0:  decent population, 50,000, 100,000.
SPEAKER_0:  and they live an urban life and they don't want to be.
SPEAKER_0:  subjected to that old pattern of agrarian society.
SPEAKER_0:  when you had 10 children or 8 children.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course it's a much more.
SPEAKER_0:  advanced in
SPEAKER_0:  terms of.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of
SPEAKER_0:  health and medicine.
SPEAKER_0:  so you don't lose children as they used to. The antibiotics, there's always a...
SPEAKER_0:  kids to survive.
SPEAKER_0:  And therefore, if you have 10 kids, you stick with 10 kids.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't.
SPEAKER_0:  end up with four as it used to be in the past.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm s-
SPEAKER_0:  Six of them would have died in the press.
SPEAKER_0:  up to the age of five actually.
SPEAKER_0:  But no, because of that...
SPEAKER_0:  You see that this...
SPEAKER_0:  urban population in the cities have completely different demands.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course the education is important. That's another area of-
SPEAKER_0:  how the social engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Islamic Republic.
SPEAKER_0:  went array because
SPEAKER_0:  They were thinking that, you know, the...
SPEAKER_0:  growth of the population.
SPEAKER_0:  the growth of the educated, higher educated.
SPEAKER_0:  Middle classes in there.
SPEAKER_0:  benefit or they could not even
SPEAKER_0:  control it.
SPEAKER_0:  in a sense.
SPEAKER_0:  No!
SPEAKER_0:  Iran in my time.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Probably had.
SPEAKER_0:  in the...
SPEAKER_0:  1970s.
SPEAKER_0:  probably by the time of the revolution, there are 10, 12 universities.
SPEAKER_0:  And now it has
SPEAKER_0:  56 universities all across the country.
SPEAKER_0:  and there is a-
SPEAKER_0:  something you refer to as the free university, IZAD.
SPEAKER_0:  which has campuses all over the country. It has 324 campuses all around Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  What does that mean?
SPEAKER_0:  In many respects, this youth
SPEAKER_0:  that were brought up in these families.
SPEAKER_0:  even in small towns in very traditional families.
SPEAKER_0:  in families that belong to that kind of a more religious.
SPEAKER_0:  loyal to the...
SPEAKER_0:  clergy or to the clerical classes.
SPEAKER_0:  their children.
SPEAKER_0:  can now move on, particularly women.
SPEAKER_0:  because in my times it would have been...
SPEAKER_0:  unheard of.
SPEAKER_0:  that you would have a young woman of 18 or.
SPEAKER_0:  17, 18, 19.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, from...
SPEAKER_0:  A traditional city such as, for instance, Yazd or in...
SPEAKER_0:  South East and Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  to move on elsewhere for education, as you do in this country.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  No!
SPEAKER_0:  It's completely accepted.
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  A woman?
SPEAKER_0:  wears hijab because he's forced to wear hijab.
SPEAKER_0:  to go to a university.
SPEAKER_0:  completely on the other side of the country.
SPEAKER_0:  And this movement of the population...
SPEAKER_0:  not only because of the universities, but in general.
SPEAKER_0:  If you now visit Iran,
SPEAKER_0:  You hear?
SPEAKER_0:  Accents.
SPEAKER_0:  local accents.
SPEAKER_0:  Provisional accents.
SPEAKER_0:  all over the country.
SPEAKER_0:  That is a
SPEAKER_0:  Azerbaijani Turkish accent.
SPEAKER_0:  from the north.
SPEAKER_0:  the rest of the country, you can hear it in the first province in the south.
SPEAKER_0:  and vice versa.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  and Kurdish for instance, or even more marginal regions such as Sistan province.
SPEAKER_0:  Ehh
SPEAKER_0:  society stuff you know.
SPEAKER_0:  which has been the subject of this recent massacre, when they actually attacked the population when demonstrating.
SPEAKER_0:  and kill the fair number of at least 60 people.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  This movement of the population...
SPEAKER_0:  I think this.
SPEAKER_0:  The creation of a larger middle class, the better educated middle class, much better educated. Iran has-
SPEAKER_0:  86%
SPEAKER_0:  literacy.
SPEAKER_0:  which
SPEAKER_0:  I think probably, I haven't checked that, but probably is better than Turkey even.
SPEAKER_0:  is probably better than anywhere else in the Middle East.
SPEAKER_1:  And it sounds like there's a.
SPEAKER_1:  that's quickly increasing.
SPEAKER_1:  So because of the movement, because of the growth of the education system.
SPEAKER_0:  and that's...... United States Device.
SPEAKER_0:  Iran has one million
SPEAKER_0:  School teachers.
SPEAKER_0:  Which.
SPEAKER_0:  may not seem as much if you're in the United States, but it's a fairly big number.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you linger on the massacre?
SPEAKER_0:  What happened there? The-
SPEAKER_0:  Sistan province is a balooch.
SPEAKER_0:  ethnicity.
SPEAKER_0:  of Paluch ethnicity.
SPEAKER_0:  Palooch is a
SPEAKER_0:  particular ethnic group in southern Iran, which is so nearer to the Shia.
SPEAKER_0:  Majority.
SPEAKER_0:  And we should say that most
SPEAKER_1:  of Iran.
SPEAKER_1:  Is she and those are
SPEAKER_1:  That's a branch of Islam.
SPEAKER_0:  She is M, yes. Let's maybe-
SPEAKER_1:  We just briefly linger Shizam and Suni.
SPEAKER_0:  Just let's not get into it. Yeah, let's do it. Let's do a one sentence summary.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... and
SPEAKER_1:  that maybe which is what most of Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  The majority of the population of the Muslim world
SPEAKER_0:  our sunnies.
SPEAKER_0:  These are main strips if you like.
SPEAKER_0:  Actually, stone now means that kind of a ministry.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you actually linger on the-
SPEAKER_1:  The Sunni Sunnah
SPEAKER_0:  She, she, uh, she, I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  party.
SPEAKER_0:  Miz Dus tomar
SPEAKER_0:  that belongs to a party of Ali.
SPEAKER_0:  which goes back to the early Islamic history of...
SPEAKER_0:  7th century. A minute.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm almost lingering to the silly notion of pronunciation and stuff like that.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah
SPEAKER_0:  the the the the
SPEAKER_1:  part like what what is the extra eye
SPEAKER_0:  at the end.
SPEAKER_0:  She is
SPEAKER_0:  belonging to the Shi'i community.
SPEAKER_0:  She and me is a person.
SPEAKER_0:  of this year.
SPEAKER_0:  that belong to that community. Are you Asian?
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, I'm a Shia.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and she is the community. Community. And in English, when it was anglicized, it becomes Shiite.
SPEAKER_0:  So if you say Shiite in today...
SPEAKER_0:  It's perfectly acceptable.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course, I myself in my writings, I always...
SPEAKER_0:  switch between one and the other. one of my books is always shite.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, the book's always she.
SPEAKER_0:  Ed.
SPEAKER_0:  That hasn't been settled.
SPEAKER_0:  But the sheep population...
SPEAKER_0:  is the smaller compared to the Sunni population in the world. In the world. In the world. But in Iran it's the opposite.
SPEAKER_0:  The Iran and Iraq
SPEAKER_0:  and possibly not Lebanon.
SPEAKER_0:  Are there three countries who...
SPEAKER_0:  Barely.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I can...
SPEAKER_0:  Lebanon have barely majority chi.
SPEAKER_0:  population.
SPEAKER_0:  Whereas the-
SPEAKER_0:  Iran is
SPEAKER_0:  large Shi'i population due to its...
SPEAKER_0:  History of conversion to she's end that by itself is another story.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  in the sense that
SPEAKER_0:  the way that historically it evolved.
SPEAKER_0:  The center.
SPEAKER_0:  became mushy.
SPEAKER_0:  and the peripheries.
SPEAKER_0:  remained.
SPEAKER_0:  Sydney.
SPEAKER_0:  So you have communities of the Baluch in the southeast.
SPEAKER_0:  You have the curds?
SPEAKER_0:  a large portion of the carrots.
SPEAKER_0:  Are sir knees?
SPEAKER_0:  They have she's as well. Then they have the indigenous religion of their own, at least called ah dangerous on
SPEAKER_0:  which is the religion.
SPEAKER_0:  Of indigenous to cooperative style.
SPEAKER_0:  There are Turkiyamans in the northeast of Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  or also
SPEAKER_0:  So nice to other communities in Khorasan region.
SPEAKER_0:  in the peripheries of Afghanistan.
SPEAKER_0:  they are all Serbs.
SPEAKER_0:  and you have some Arab
SPEAKER_0:  population, Arab speaking population in the Khuzestan province.
SPEAKER_0:  in the south-west of Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  which is also all across the Persian Gulf.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there a lot of conflict between these regions? And also.
SPEAKER_1:  Like if I blindfolded you.
SPEAKER_1:  and dropped you off in one of the regions. Would you quickly recognize the region? By the food, by the music, by the accents.
SPEAKER_0:  So on
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, the answer to your...
SPEAKER_0:  lovely question, which I think, I hope it would have happened to me, is that yes?
SPEAKER_0:  You would see different cultures. Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  But-
SPEAKER_0:  different food, most important, different accents.
SPEAKER_0:  or different languages.
SPEAKER_0:  Since they have dialects, there's Baluches and...
SPEAKER_0:  different languages altogether.
SPEAKER_0:  But-
SPEAKER_0:  or so for that matter Kurdish, which is closer to Persian because they are Indo-European languages.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  But Turkish, Azeri Turkish, which is probably closer to the Turkish of Teke.
SPEAKER_0:  Republic of Turkey or to the Republic of Azerbaijan in the North.
SPEAKER_0:  What's there?
SPEAKER_0:  They're the same.
SPEAKER_0:  basically.
SPEAKER_0:  Actually, if you would have looked.
SPEAKER_0:  That's fascinating.
SPEAKER_0:  picture.
SPEAKER_0:  if you have looked at the, let's say even 19th century, early 20th century.
SPEAKER_0:  linguistic map of Iran, you would have been amazed.
SPEAKER_0:  in the number of dialects, in the number of languages that have survived. This is an ancient country, it's an ancient land.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's a lot of mountains all around it or big deserts.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's a sense of isolation. So you would say here and there, you see a different community.
SPEAKER_0:  that speaks differently.
SPEAKER_0:  All ancient.
SPEAKER_0:  Traditions and languages. Yeah. And because of the great number of invasions that Iran witnessed.
SPEAKER_0:  Over.
SPEAKER_0:  more than two and a half.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... millennia
SPEAKER_0:  Of course, there are all kinds of cultures that were introduced into Iran. And, because of the
SPEAKER_0:  Ethnicities were introduced to Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  mostly coming from the north.
SPEAKER_0:  East of Iran from
SPEAKER_0:  from the...
SPEAKER_0:  lowlands of Central Asia and beyond.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm
SPEAKER_0:  and continued into Iran proper.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  But now what has happened, that's my point that I wanted to make.
SPEAKER_0:  century of modernity or modernization.
SPEAKER_0:  has produced.
SPEAKER_0:  a national culture.
SPEAKER_0:  of great strength in a sense. I would say I ended my book.
SPEAKER_0:  the book on Iran, Iran and Modern History.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically saying that despite everything else that has created so much trouble for today's Iran
SPEAKER_0:  There is a sense of a cultural.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  identity.
SPEAKER_0:  that is very strong.
SPEAKER_0:  and they think.
SPEAKER_0:  I can say...
SPEAKER_0:  with.
SPEAKER_0:  with some confidence.
SPEAKER_0:  that despite this
SPEAKER_0:  despite these regional identities that are still there and they're great and they should be celebrated.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh
SPEAKER_0:  This situation.
SPEAKER_0:  Today if you go to...
SPEAKER_0:  to Kurdistan or if you go to
SPEAKER_0:  in the system, they all can speak Persian.
SPEAKER_0:  They all have an education in Persia.
SPEAKER_0:  So they all basically...
SPEAKER_0:  are becoming part of...
SPEAKER_0:  whether they like the regime in power or not.
SPEAKER_0:  They have
SPEAKER_0:  a sense of belonging to a culture and an identity with the center.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course the idea.
SPEAKER_0:  of a center versus periphery in Iran is very old.
SPEAKER_0:  goes back to ancient times because
SPEAKER_0:  even the name of the country.
SPEAKER_0:  was the guarded domains of Iran. This is the.
SPEAKER_0:  This is dude.
SPEAKER_0:  Official name of Mamalek Mahrooseh of Iran
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  It was recognized.
SPEAKER_0:  that this is not just one.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  entity but is the
SPEAKER_0:  It's a collection of entities like the United States of America. Exactly.
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly.
SPEAKER_0:  But the United States of America...
SPEAKER_0:  In a sense, you can say that it was a very successful, well, it remains to be seen how successful.
SPEAKER_0:  to be continued. To be, to, that was basically invented, created.
SPEAKER_0:  you would have this sense of it.
SPEAKER_0:  In the case of an old nation, which has been on the map of the world for
SPEAKER_0:  3,000 years, 2,500 years.
SPEAKER_0:  There's-
SPEAKER_0:  This is not an exaggeration, I'm not it.
SPEAKER_0:  nationalists per se.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, if you look at Persia and the map...
SPEAKER_0:  of the world in ancient times is still there.
SPEAKER_0:  as it is today.
SPEAKER_0:  Very few countries in the world are like that.
SPEAKER_0:  that they would have that kind of a continuity.
SPEAKER_0:  over a course of time.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's not without a reason, because there was this sense of a
SPEAKER_0:  installed, we wanted closely use that rag to prevent it getting stuck
SPEAKER_0:  Center versus periphery.
SPEAKER_0:  that had found
SPEAKER_0:  There is a huge amount of tension, but there is also a sense of belonging.
SPEAKER_0:  to something and state is very much at the center of it.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  That's why the concept of a
SPEAKER_0:  State matters for the creation, for the shaping.
SPEAKER_0:  of this culture. What happened is therefore,
SPEAKER_0:  You can see that today in answer to your
SPEAKER_0:  point about traveling.
SPEAKER_0:  Blindfolded.
SPEAKER_0:  is that...
SPEAKER_0:  you would be surprised to see how much.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  people share.
SPEAKER_0:  and in terms of
SPEAKER_0:  I just give you one anecdote.
SPEAKER_0:  it.
SPEAKER_0:  in 1960.
SPEAKER_0:  8
SPEAKER_0:  I believe, must have been.
SPEAKER_0:  I traveled to Azerbaijan. I used to travel and actually photograph. Not blindfolded.
SPEAKER_0:  Mostly. Well, yeah, not flash-poisoned. Sometimes. Not flash-poisoned, no, no, not flash-poisoned.
SPEAKER_0:  So I went to a bazaar
SPEAKER_0:  in the city of Ghoi, which is in the...
SPEAKER_0:  northwestern Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  on the border with what is today the...
SPEAKER_0:  Republic of Turkey.
SPEAKER_0:  And I went to the bazaar and I was interested in the kind of leather work that they produced.
SPEAKER_0:  So I tried to buy some stuff and they were surprised to see that.
SPEAKER_0:  how few people knew Persia.
SPEAKER_0:  so they could not communicate in Persian with you.
SPEAKER_0:  Either they have to.
SPEAKER_0:  Ask somebody from...
SPEAKER_0:  some other store to come and translate for you.
SPEAKER_0:  This is 1968. So even though it's the official.
SPEAKER_0:  language.
SPEAKER_0:  Especially
SPEAKER_0:  of the country, they're still.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. So what are they teaching school? So it doesn't matter.
SPEAKER_0:  But this guy... He doesn't go to school.
SPEAKER_0:  He hasn't been to the school or he was not fully exposed to it.
SPEAKER_0:  And bazaars usually are very conservative places.
SPEAKER_0:  It's stuck in my mind.
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  in
SPEAKER_0:  Recently in 2004 I was...
SPEAKER_0:  traveling to the same area, not to the same city.
SPEAKER_0:  but to the same area.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I was amazed to see how the youth...
SPEAKER_0:  as soon as they would know that you're coming from somewhere else.
SPEAKER_0:  Opening conversation with you talking about the latest movies that was produced in the West and it's not only Hollywood. Of course there's the huge amount of
SPEAKER_0:  Fascination with Hollywood and Western.
SPEAKER_0:  Cinema. Cinema is a major thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Filmmaking is a major thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Sorry, these kids in the city of Ahar.
SPEAKER_0:  They're asking me if we're having lunch.
SPEAKER_0:  and asking me, okay, then what do you think about?
SPEAKER_0:  producer.
SPEAKER_0:  not producer, this director
SPEAKER_0:  or that actor.
SPEAKER_0:  American. American European as well, but mostly American.
SPEAKER_0:  Were they speaking Persian? It's a complete Persian that's-
SPEAKER_0:  I would converse with them.
SPEAKER_0:  Do they speak English too? Yes, actually you would be surprised to see what percentage of the Iranian youth
SPEAKER_0:  at least in big cities.
SPEAKER_0:  are fascinated with learning language and for a reason.
SPEAKER_0:  because they think that's the way to get access.
SPEAKER_0:  either on social media or eventually leave Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  Unfortunately.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  And because they don't see a future for themselves in the country, either you have to be.
SPEAKER_0:  part of this.
SPEAKER_0:  part of this regime.
SPEAKER_0:  or if you hate them and you don't like the way of their life.
SPEAKER_0:  You look up outside.
SPEAKER_0:  I was having drivers to drive me around the country, in the cities around Tehran.
SPEAKER_0:  And the guy was young, extremely...
SPEAKER_0:  well-educated, well-dressed. We would have looked at him, we could have found him in any street.
SPEAKER_0:  any country in the Western world.
SPEAKER_0:  and his major concern knowing that I'm from outside.
SPEAKER_0:  Major concern is, well, tell me which would be a better place for me to go.
SPEAKER_0:  So what's wrong with the place that you're in right now?
SPEAKER_0:  You are in your own country, you speak your own language.
SPEAKER_0:  So good.
SPEAKER_0:  I have to have a better future. This has no future for me.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it's really interesting because.
SPEAKER_1:  the thing I feel about the protests right now.
SPEAKER_1:  is there's a large number of people.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  instead of giving into sin.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  about
SPEAKER_1:  You know, this government is no good.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  they're actually getting
SPEAKER_1:  this like.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  energy.
SPEAKER_0:  this desire to forever.
SPEAKER_1:  evolution.
SPEAKER_1:  in the sort of non-violent, in the democratic sense of that. Let's.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's actually find the ideas. Let's build a great nation here. This is a great nation. This is my nation. Let's build something great here.
SPEAKER_0:  Well...
SPEAKER_0:  That's my hope. That's the outside. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what I'm hoping for. I share your-
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  aspiration.
SPEAKER_0:  but I'm fearing that.
SPEAKER_0:  I hope it's not a wishful thinking.
SPEAKER_0:  certainly that's what they want.
SPEAKER_0:  Certainly that's what they want to create.
SPEAKER_0:  But the historian always tells you from...
SPEAKER_0:  Where they start?
SPEAKER_0:  to where they finish.
SPEAKER_0:  there is going to be a huge...
SPEAKER_0:  Kinda fake.
SPEAKER_0:  change.
SPEAKER_0:  And in this.
SPEAKER_0:  particular case.
SPEAKER_0:  I wouldn't be...
SPEAKER_0:  I would very much hope that it's not going to be a revolution like the 1979 Islamic revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  and I have my hopes.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's it.
SPEAKER_0:  For one thing, this is a revolution that doesn't have a leader.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  and it seems that they're comfortable with that.
SPEAKER_0:  at least so far, because we are six weeks of this.
SPEAKER_0:  And I hope it's not going to be actually a revolution, as I pointed out.
SPEAKER_0:  I hope it's going to be more of a...
SPEAKER_0:  sense of trying to come.
SPEAKER_0:  to some compromise.
SPEAKER_0:  and gradually moved.
SPEAKER_0:  to a change rather than a collapse of this.
SPEAKER_0:  regime and replacement with what?
SPEAKER_0:  So the anxiety of the...
SPEAKER_1:  regime you hope.
SPEAKER_1:  will turn into.
SPEAKER_1:  a kind of realization that you have to.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to modernize, you have to make progress, you actually have to make certain compromises.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  or constitutional changes, all this kind of stuff. So the basic.
SPEAKER_1:  a process of government and
SPEAKER_0:  lawmaking.
SPEAKER_0:  The problem is...
SPEAKER_0:  that they say we have it all.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  We have our parliament, we have our constitution, we have our
SPEAKER_0:  elections, which has all been, of course.
SPEAKER_0:  FAKE
SPEAKER_0:  But they claim they have all of that.
SPEAKER_0:  But the problem for them is that...
SPEAKER_0:  day
SPEAKER_0:  try to superimpose.
SPEAKER_0:  a certain ideology.
SPEAKER_0:  Like all other ideological
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  autocracies or...
SPEAKER_0:  or tarqueas as in this case.
SPEAKER_0:  that tend to dominate.
SPEAKER_0:  all this.
SPEAKER_0:  institution buildings that
SPEAKER_0:  They have a date.
SPEAKER_0:  They constantly claim we have this, we have that.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course it's a generational thing.
SPEAKER_0:  the upper echelons.
SPEAKER_0:  of this.
SPEAKER_0:  regime.
SPEAKER_0:  or
SPEAKER_0:  mostly older people.
SPEAKER_0:  Tappent!
SPEAKER_0:  They are crazy.
SPEAKER_0:  that are afraid of the fact that they may lose their control.
SPEAKER_0:  over their whole system that is sophisticated, huge.
SPEAKER_0:  System of government.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  They rely on certain tools of control.
SPEAKER_0:  which is the Revolutionary Guards.
SPEAKER_0:  and other.
SPEAKER_0:  other
SPEAKER_0:  institutions.
SPEAKER_0:  that are loyal to.
SPEAKER_0:  to this date.
SPEAKER_0:  and they spend enormous amount of...
SPEAKER_0:  funds that is available to them.
SPEAKER_0:  at least before the sanctions.
SPEAKER_0:  but even during the sanctions they still have.
SPEAKER_0:  Enough.
SPEAKER_0:  funds to do so.
SPEAKER_0:  and in order to remain in power.
SPEAKER_0:  And they are extremely ruthless in that regard.
SPEAKER_0:  This is nuts.
SPEAKER_0:  and nice Islamic
SPEAKER_0:  Fatherly.
SPEAKER_0:  Regime
SPEAKER_0:  This is a regime that's
SPEAKER_0:  I would see easily in it.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  clear signs of fascism.
SPEAKER_0:  Clear, Sansif.
SPEAKER_0:  the state control and
SPEAKER_0:  pay any price to stay in power.
SPEAKER_0:  So even violence. Extreme violence.
SPEAKER_0:  to return to the massacre.
SPEAKER_1:  What were the uses of violence to suppress protests?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, yes, it was actually quite remarkable to see that from the first or the second day of the protest.
SPEAKER_0:  You see out in the streets this riot police.
SPEAKER_0:  which comes out in large numbers.
SPEAKER_0:  Fully geared up.
SPEAKER_0:  Their appearance are rather terrifying.
SPEAKER_0:  like any other riot police, probably more than any other riot police.
SPEAKER_0:  they're violent.
SPEAKER_0:  They stand in the streets when the students are demonstrating, even in smaller numbers.
SPEAKER_0:  Because before I go to that, I should...
SPEAKER_0:  point this point, this ought to...
SPEAKER_0:  you as well.
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  that these demonstrations are not.
SPEAKER_0:  large ones in one place. You don't see 100,000 people in...
SPEAKER_0:  in one place.
SPEAKER_0:  But you see in every neighborhood.
SPEAKER_0:  couple of thousand of kids are.
SPEAKER_0:  demonstrating.
SPEAKER_0:  all over Iran
SPEAKER_1:  all over the world.
SPEAKER_0:  in different parts.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  Actually.
SPEAKER_0:  during the demonstrations three weeks ago.
SPEAKER_0:  They, as I said, they had people in...
SPEAKER_0:  Sydney, Australia, New Zealand, Tokyo.
SPEAKER_0:  all over the world all protests
SPEAKER_1:  sing high gas prices, it's funny.
SPEAKER_0:  Everywhere.
SPEAKER_0:  to the extent that they could be ignored, nothing but if they could not be ignored. And it's actually...
SPEAKER_0:  quite remarkable that this is very embarrassing to them. But somehow they think that this propaganda machine of them is working.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll say you think they don't have a good even sense.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, so there's an incompetence within the problem.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes it is. There is an incompetence across the board.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, despite all of this massive...
SPEAKER_0:  Government.
SPEAKER_0:  administration or whatever you would call it, all these various
SPEAKER_0:  components of it.
SPEAKER_0:  The easy sense of...
SPEAKER_0:  there's a sense of inefficiency and incompetence.
SPEAKER_0:  that is associated with in every action that you see.
SPEAKER_0:  Even in their
SPEAKER_0:  suppression of this street movement.
SPEAKER_0:  But in answer to that question...
SPEAKER_0:  you would see that they're
SPEAKER_0:  This.
SPEAKER_0:  Riot police.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, very-
SPEAKER_0:  it's quite obvious that they were trained for the purpose.
SPEAKER_0:  So this.
SPEAKER_0:  their appearance, everything. This is just...
SPEAKER_0:  Regular.
SPEAKER_0:  army forces or soldiers, conscripts.
SPEAKER_0:  They are.
SPEAKER_0:  professional.
SPEAKER_0:  forces.
SPEAKER_0:  and they come.
SPEAKER_0:  not only on foot number.
SPEAKER_0:  but they come on motorbikes.
SPEAKER_0:  So you would see any of these demonstrations there.
SPEAKER_0:  10, 12, 15, 20 motorbikes.
SPEAKER_0:  with two passengers, one in front riding, one in the back.
SPEAKER_0:  Fully.
SPEAKER_0:  equipped with the button.
SPEAKER_0:  with paint guns, with pellet guns, and with bullets.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's me.
SPEAKER_0:  FOODY!
SPEAKER_0:  equipped.
SPEAKER_0:  and they are terrifying, they go through the...
SPEAKER_0:  demonstrations that hit.
SPEAKER_0:  and with people.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  and then the errors.
SPEAKER_0:  and then you see behind the first line.
SPEAKER_0:  of these riot police, you would see all this latest.
SPEAKER_0:  models of this.
SPEAKER_0:  special
SPEAKER_0:  uh... uh... armored trucks
SPEAKER_0:  FOOL
SPEAKER_0:  moving to the demonstrations and
SPEAKER_0:  arresting people, throwing them into.
SPEAKER_0:  this and then behind that
SPEAKER_0:  water.
SPEAKER_0:  water cannons.
SPEAKER_0:  You see?
SPEAKER_0:  I was looking at that and I was like, okay, this is Tehran, probably.
SPEAKER_0:  they have this. But then you look at the smallest cities, they still have the same thing.
SPEAKER_0:  So all over the country.
SPEAKER_0:  One thing that they had managed to produce extensively...
SPEAKER_0:  irrespective of the fact that whether they are.
SPEAKER_0:  effective or not, but you see them everywhere.
SPEAKER_0:  See you soon, cheers!
SPEAKER_0:  that how afraid this regime is.
SPEAKER_0:  But that also shows that.
SPEAKER_1:  that there's an infrastructure.
SPEAKER_1:  that can implement violence at scale.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  Very much so.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's.
SPEAKER_0:  probably part and parcel of this regime from day one.
SPEAKER_0:  D
SPEAKER_0:  number of prisons that they have.
SPEAKER_0:  according to...
SPEAKER_0:  Perhaps an exaggerated version.
SPEAKER_0:  They said that about 12...
SPEAKER_0:  thousand
SPEAKER_0:  or so.
SPEAKER_0:  Arrested.
SPEAKER_0:  That's all for now.
SPEAKER_0:  Cheers!
SPEAKER_0:  today.
SPEAKER_0:  since past six weeks.
SPEAKER_0:  They were 230 or 240 people were killed, including children.
SPEAKER_0:  I under it.
SPEAKER_0:  18.
SPEAKER_0:  They are.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  day.
SPEAKER_0:  Be top.
SPEAKER_0:  women in the street, which is extremely, actually...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  disturbing when you see these scenes.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's a lot of this is on video.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything is on video. Everybody has a camera.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  and everybody sends.
SPEAKER_0:  to major.
SPEAKER_0:  news outlets outside Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  and they immediately showed every night, if you look at BBC Persia.
SPEAKER_0:  or Iran International, I think it is six of them actually.
SPEAKER_0:  all over the earth in England, they are in Deutsche Welle in Germany.
SPEAKER_0:  which has a particular interest in the Iranian.
SPEAKER_0:  BBC World Service and so forth in London.
SPEAKER_0:  and voice of America, Persian here in this country.
SPEAKER_0:  There is another one, Radio Fadda, which is also funded by...
SPEAKER_0:  the American government.
SPEAKER_0:  Also...
SPEAKER_0:  fully covers all of these events.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  There is no way that these people can.
SPEAKER_0:  that you can miss what's going on in the streets.
SPEAKER_0:  of this.
SPEAKER_0:  demonstrations.
SPEAKER_0:  and the scenes of beating up women.
SPEAKER_0:  which in Iranian culture, as I presume in most cultures.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a certain sanctity that you don't attack women.
SPEAKER_0:  What they do?
SPEAKER_0:  And this is an Islamic regime.
SPEAKER_0:  that supposedly have to have a certain...
SPEAKER_0:  sense of...
SPEAKER_0:  Concern
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Well, like that.
SPEAKER_1:  protection.
SPEAKER_1:  Like a deep respect for women.
SPEAKER_1:  grounded in a tradition of protecting them.
SPEAKER_1:  instead this kind of idea that was instilled in law.
SPEAKER_1:  has turned into a deep dis-
SPEAKER_0:  disrespect of women.
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly.
SPEAKER_0:  or fear.
SPEAKER_0:  that these
SPEAKER_0:  Women are not.
SPEAKER_0:  any longer the girls that we thought we are.
SPEAKER_0:  bringing up in this society.
SPEAKER_1:  you losing your power will be these women.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the fear. Ya.
SPEAKER_0:  And you see, of course...
SPEAKER_0:  This government.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't have it.
SPEAKER_0:  support base. I mean, it would be...
SPEAKER_0:  totally wrong to think that the Islamic Republic has not created its own power base.
SPEAKER_0:  It does.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's-
SPEAKER_0:  Probably if...
SPEAKER_0:  There is no way, there are no statistics that we can...
SPEAKER_0:  what I'm not aware of.
SPEAKER_0:  Any statistics that I can give you in numbers, what's the percentage of support for the regime?
SPEAKER_0:  In it all.
SPEAKER_0:  But-
SPEAKER_0:  Quite frankly, I don't think it's more than probably 10% of the population.
SPEAKER_0:  Be very generous.
SPEAKER_0:  I would be surprised if it's that low.
SPEAKER_1:  I would say.
SPEAKER_1:  So if my understanding because.
SPEAKER_1:  I've been very...
SPEAKER_1:  deeply paying attention to the war in Ukraine, to Ukraine, to Russia.
SPEAKER_1:  and uh to
SPEAKER_1:  support in Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  for Putin.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  without knowing the details.
SPEAKER_1:  without.
SPEAKER_1:  even considering the effects of propaganda and stuff like that.
SPEAKER_1:  is there's probably a large number of people in Iran that...
SPEAKER_1:  don't see this as a battle of human rights, but see it as a battle of human rights.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, conservatism, like tradition.
SPEAKER_1:  versus modernization and they value tradition.
SPEAKER_1:  that what they fear from the throwing away of the hijab.
SPEAKER_1:  is not
SPEAKER_1:  The loss of power and the.
SPEAKER_1:  women getting human rights, what they fear.
SPEAKER_1:  Is this the same stuff you feel you see an apportion saying kids these days.
SPEAKER_1:  Have no respect.
SPEAKER_1:  basically that there's a large number of Iranians that probably.
SPEAKER_0:  value
SPEAKER_1:  value tradition.
SPEAKER_1:  and the beauty of the culture.
SPEAKER_1:  And like they're they fear that.
SPEAKER_1:  Kids.
SPEAKER_1:  with their internet.
SPEAKER_1:  and their videos and their revolution will throw away everything that made this country.
SPEAKER_1:  hold together for millennia.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  Yes and no, I would agree with you in the sense that probably like everywhere else in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  This is a generational thing, you know, every generation thinks.
SPEAKER_0:  differently about the younger generation. No doubt.
SPEAKER_0:  and in Iran is the same.
SPEAKER_0:  But there is another factor here is involved. Those that you would consider them as traditional.
SPEAKER_0:  no longer seem to have their loyalties to this regime. this
SPEAKER_0:  meaning that...
SPEAKER_0:  They diss.
SPEAKER_0:  they consider as a brutal regime.
SPEAKER_0:  that is prepared to kill children in the streets.
SPEAKER_0:  and does a lot of...
SPEAKER_0:  Things wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  Of course, it tries to take care of the...
SPEAKER_0:  It's on Power Base.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a very strong sense of if you start here.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a very strong sense in this regime.
SPEAKER_0:  that there are people that is theirs.
SPEAKER_0:  and their
SPEAKER_0:  Adkin is thicker
SPEAKER_0:  not theirs.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a word for it in Persian, they call it Khodi.
SPEAKER_0:  One of us.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay?
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, so it's the...
SPEAKER_1:  Well, that's very for sure.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, yes, all for that matter.
SPEAKER_0:  Soviet Union, if you were a member of the party.
SPEAKER_0:  and your children would have received this special kind of treatment yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  This
SPEAKER_0:  sense of us versus them.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  for a while worked.
SPEAKER_0:  because the younger people coming from the countryside to the cities.
SPEAKER_0:  certain fact, certain sector of them would have found.
SPEAKER_0:  with our fund protection and support.
SPEAKER_0:  from the government.
SPEAKER_0:  they
SPEAKER_0:  They wanted.
SPEAKER_0:  to belong to something and the mosques and the mornings.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, uh, morning associations in the
SPEAKER_0:  neighborhoods and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  would have given them. There is a I.
SPEAKER_0:  term for it, it's called Basijji.
SPEAKER_0:  those have been recruited.
SPEAKER_0:  by this state.
SPEAKER_0:  and this is the youth.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  vigilante if you like that.
SPEAKER_0:  that you can see them also in these demonstrations.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Sometimes thugs.
SPEAKER_0:  They're called the Siv...
SPEAKER_0:  Civil Cloth
SPEAKER_0:  So the people that comes to these demonstrations that start beating up.
SPEAKER_0:  this young people.
SPEAKER_0:  and they are not in...
SPEAKER_0:  in security police.
SPEAKER_0:  uniforms, but they are just regular clothes.
SPEAKER_0:  These people...
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, they still support.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's the benefit.
SPEAKER_0:  because they get jobs.
SPEAKER_0:  They get.
SPEAKER_0:  the privileges.
SPEAKER_0:  And these are very important for a
SPEAKER_0:  for a state.
SPEAKER_0:  that basically monopolizes
SPEAKER_0:  most of the resources.
SPEAKER_0:  You see?
SPEAKER_0:  Even beef.
SPEAKER_0:  even during the sanction, let alone before the sanction.
SPEAKER_0:  The oil revenue off your arm.
SPEAKER_0:  which is the major source of the state government.
SPEAKER_0:  was the monopoly of the state.
SPEAKER_0:  It was monopoly of the state during the Pahlavi era.
SPEAKER_0:  from this start.
SPEAKER_0:  basic.
SPEAKER_0:  So what does that mean?
SPEAKER_0:  That means that...
SPEAKER_0:  the regime in power is no longer particularly accountable to the majority population.
SPEAKER_0:  because them.
SPEAKER_0:  It extracts wealth from underground.
SPEAKER_0:  and it uses it for its own purposes, in order to make it more powerful.
SPEAKER_0:  in order to make it more repressive.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what it is, the regime today.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's-
SPEAKER_0:  feeds a small
SPEAKER_0:  or I wouldn't say but a fair number of its own supporters.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, the revolutionary guard in Iran is probably about...
SPEAKER_0:  350,000 or something like that is a very big force.
SPEAKER_0:  and this is not the regular army.
SPEAKER_0:  the Revolutionary Guards.
SPEAKER_0:  are independent from the, from the evolution.
SPEAKER_1:  guard.
SPEAKER_1:  is armed forces.
SPEAKER_0:  controlled by the state.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, the same as the army.
SPEAKER_0:  but these are more.
SPEAKER_0:  ideologically.
SPEAKER_0:  hide up with this state.
SPEAKER_1:  And they're also.
SPEAKER_1:  In-facing, internal-facing.
SPEAKER_1:  What's their purpose? What's their stated? What's the stated purpose of
SPEAKER_0:  Well for day one...
SPEAKER_0:  when the revolution succeeded.
SPEAKER_0:  The Islamic regime in power.
SPEAKER_0:  was wonderful.
SPEAKER_0:  to all kinds of forces of opposition.
SPEAKER_0:  within iran itself and the revolution
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that's the Revolutionary Guards and they drop...
SPEAKER_0:  was to try to.
SPEAKER_0:  Make sure that the regime stays in power.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course, over the course of 40 years, they became more powerful.
SPEAKER_0:  more organized, better funded.
SPEAKER_0:  Better trained?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, at least we think they're better trained, but we don't know because the level of...
SPEAKER_0:  Incompetence perhaps can be seen.
SPEAKER_0:  through the Ranked file as well.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, they developed their own.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, in this military industry, I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  those
SPEAKER_0:  drones that you see now.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin's regime are throwing
SPEAKER_0:  on Ukrainians.
SPEAKER_0:  for Ukrainians.
SPEAKER_0:  Those are all built by the Revolutionary Guards, by the military industry under the control.
SPEAKER_0:  After the revolution, you guys.
SPEAKER_0:  and like.
SPEAKER_0:  similar regimes in the Middle East at least.
SPEAKER_0:  These are military industrial complexes. You can find them in Egypt, of course, which is very powerful, very traditional.
SPEAKER_0:  has been in power and still is in power.
SPEAKER_0:  You find him in Pakistan?
SPEAKER_0:  Which is it.
SPEAKER_0:  is extremely powerful.
SPEAKER_0:  and they can...
SPEAKER_0:  change the prime minister's.
SPEAKER_0:  as they did in the case of the last one.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  You can find them.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh
SPEAKER_0:  Probably.
SPEAKER_0:  in Myanmar is the same phenomenon.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  And I can, if you look around, you can find quite a number of them.
SPEAKER_0:  And the Revolutionary Guard is equivalent of that.
SPEAKER_0:  This is a powerful...
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  establishment force.
SPEAKER_0:  which militarily is powerful, industrially is powerful.
SPEAKER_0:  And...
SPEAKER_0:  since the start of the revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  They have been given projects.
SPEAKER_0:  So you want to be dams?
SPEAKER_0:  which they did a major disaster, environmental disaster.
SPEAKER_0:  They built.
SPEAKER_0:  hundred and something dams all across the country.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the revolutionary guard who does it.
SPEAKER_0:  So they have all kinds of...
SPEAKER_0:  tentacles all around the country controlling various things. And because it's their job.
SPEAKER_1:  and they have power, they have prestige.
SPEAKER_0:  there's a huge incentive to.
SPEAKER_0:  Join them.
SPEAKER_0:  to join them and to stay so like
SPEAKER_1:  They.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, when they're having dinner at home with their families.
SPEAKER_1:  There's not an incentive to, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  to join the protests sort of. Well...
SPEAKER_0:  That is the point.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, the evolution, you guys, may be extreme.
SPEAKER_0:  but many of the people who depend on this state for their support.
SPEAKER_0:  Now the younger generation are...
SPEAKER_0:  telling their parents.
SPEAKER_0:  You were wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  you don't provide for us, this society, this-
SPEAKER_0:  State does not provide what we want.
SPEAKER_0:  So there is a descent.
SPEAKER_0:  within the family.
SPEAKER_0:  It seems to me. I hope it's not a wishful thinking.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there is a...
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of a joke going around. You see this.
SPEAKER_0:  A tabard guy is the Kledji, bearded, traditional.
SPEAKER_0:  click or appear as.
SPEAKER_0:  When you see them...
SPEAKER_0:  Talking about women.
SPEAKER_0:  They are very of course.
SPEAKER_0:  politically incorrect.
SPEAKER_0:  very looking down towards women.
SPEAKER_0:  As I said, they have to be.
SPEAKER_0:  Inside they have to be protected, they have not to be seen.
SPEAKER_0:  and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  What if they have a young person?
SPEAKER_0:  young daughter in their family.
SPEAKER_0:  You see that there...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  discourse changes.
SPEAKER_0:  they no longer
SPEAKER_0:  seem to be referring to women as second class citizens.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's very important. That's precisely that point, that when you have this younger generation,
SPEAKER_0:  no matter how privileged they are, and many of them are privileged.
SPEAKER_0:  And there is also...
SPEAKER_0:  the regime has created its own.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, privilege class.
SPEAKER_0:  that are not necessarily.
SPEAKER_0:  directly paid by the regime.
SPEAKER_0:  what they benefit from.
SPEAKER_0:  Contractors!
SPEAKER_0:  certain professions
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  that benefit from
SPEAKER_0:  what this state provides for them.
SPEAKER_0:  And Iran is a...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, the past 40 years, you can see Iran has developed in terms of material culture.
SPEAKER_0:  Remarkably.
SPEAKER_0:  Iran has
SPEAKER_0:  good communication, as roads.
SPEAKER_0:  all over the place it's not like a
SPEAKER_0:  It's more like, I don't know whether you have ever visited Turkey, for instance.
SPEAKER_0:  In certain respects, even...
SPEAKER_0:  more advanced than Turkey but it's closer
SPEAKER_0:  to that rather than if you travel. I don't want to bring.
SPEAKER_0:  particular names in North Africa.
SPEAKER_0:  or parts of the Middle East or other parts of the Islamic world. It's much, much different.
SPEAKER_0:  So in this respect...
SPEAKER_0:  You would see...
SPEAKER_0:  certain contrast or paradoxes here.
SPEAKER_0:  On the second respect, there is the...
SPEAKER_0:  Growth.
SPEAKER_0:  and there is urbanization, there is modern economy.
SPEAKER_0:  On the other hand, you see this superimposed...
SPEAKER_0:  ideological doctrinal.
SPEAKER_0:  aspect that
SPEAKER_0:  has driven the regime over all these years.
SPEAKER_0:  and they cannot get rid of it.
SPEAKER_0:  They cannot, in this respect, they cannot modernize themselves. They think that they are.
SPEAKER_0:  already.
SPEAKER_0:  Perfect.
SPEAKER_0:  In ideological sense, this is the best solution for the world.
SPEAKER_0:  not only for Iran, but for the Muslim world and for the world as a whole.
SPEAKER_0:  We are Anti-Imperialist
SPEAKER_0:  We have managed to survive.
SPEAKER_0:  either under sanctions, this is all part of the rhetoric.
SPEAKER_0:  But of course at a huge expense.
SPEAKER_0:  the huge expense for their own population.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  The point that you have raised is the fact that
SPEAKER_0:  be now witness.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a
SPEAKER_0:  not only a generation gap between the youth.
SPEAKER_0:  and their parents.
SPEAKER_0:  But there is...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  break in a sense from
SPEAKER_0:  the older generations.
SPEAKER_0:  and they are very distinctly the youth.
SPEAKER_0:  that has a different
SPEAKER_0:  view of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  does not want to compromise. Whether they would be able to.
SPEAKER_0:  Succeed or not remains to be seen.
SPEAKER_0:  whether this regime is going to suppress it.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  But it's...
SPEAKER_0:  Actually...
SPEAKER_0:  brought to surface many of aspects of the weaknesses of this regime.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I hear from a lot of people that are in these protests now and so.
SPEAKER_1:  My love goes to them and stay strong.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess.
SPEAKER_1:  It's inspiring to see people fighting for those things.
SPEAKER_1:  Women, life and freedom, especially freedom. Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  because that can only lead to a good thing in the longterm at least. And if possible to.
SPEAKER_1:  avoid a violent revolution.
SPEAKER_1:  Of course that is something that...
SPEAKER_1:  we all want to see.
SPEAKER_1:  Before we return to the present, let's jump around. Let's go to the past.
SPEAKER_1:  We met in 1979.
SPEAKER_1:  What happened in 1979?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, in 1979...
SPEAKER_0:  There was...
SPEAKER_0:  a revolution that eventually came to be known as the Islamic Revolution and even up to this day.
SPEAKER_0:  many of the observers or those who have strong views that would not like to refer to it as an Islamic revolution or even a revolution.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  because the nature of it in the earlier stages of it started really probably around 1977, it took two years.
SPEAKER_0:  was much more...
SPEAKER_0:  all embracing. It was not...
SPEAKER_0:  Islamic
SPEAKER_0:  in a particular fashion or at all in a sense.
SPEAKER_0:  It started with a kind of a very liberal Democrat.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  agenda.
SPEAKER_0:  which required, which demanded mostly.
SPEAKER_0:  by people.
SPEAKER_0:  who were the veterans of the older generations of Iranians.
SPEAKER_0:  liberal nationalists, that's fair.
SPEAKER_0:  Left out.
SPEAKER_0:  in the Pahlavi period.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Shah.
SPEAKER_0:  became increasingly
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  authoritarian.
SPEAKER_0:  Increasing the...
SPEAKER_0:  Suppressive.
SPEAKER_0:  And therefore...
SPEAKER_0:  Basically.
SPEAKER_0:  leaving no space.
SPEAKER_0:  political space.
SPEAKER_0:  open for any kind of a give and take.
SPEAKER_0:  any kind of a conversation or participation. That was in the 70s. 70s, 70s, particularly in the 70s. Can we actually even like?
SPEAKER_1:  Just do a...
SPEAKER_1:  A world wind.
SPEAKER_1:  review from 1906.
SPEAKER_1:  in 1979.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, sure.
SPEAKER_0:  In 1906, there was...
SPEAKER_0:  A period, actually, as you might know, the first decade or so.
SPEAKER_0:  of the 20th century witnessed numerous...
SPEAKER_0:  what we refer to as constitutional revolutions, including Russia 1905.
SPEAKER_0:  The first revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  including the Chinese Revolution in 19,looking back at value, just the rest of the dragon is
SPEAKER_0:  the Young Text revolution in 1908.
SPEAKER_0:  the Iranian Revolution in 1906. do understand
SPEAKER_1:  why.
SPEAKER_1:  The synchronicity of all of it.
SPEAKER_1:  Why in so many different places, very different cultures, very.
SPEAKER_0:  Very different cultures, but all of them in a sense were coming out of...
SPEAKER_0:  the regimes that became...
SPEAKER_0:  progressively.
SPEAKER_0:  powerful.
SPEAKER_0:  without having any kind of a legal system.
SPEAKER_0:  that would protect the individual vis-a-vis the state.
SPEAKER_0:  So the idea of law.
SPEAKER_0:  and the Constitution according to which
SPEAKER_0:  there should be a certain...
SPEAKER_0:  protection.
SPEAKER_0:  or certain civil society.
SPEAKER_0:  became very common. Yeah, but I wonder what
SPEAKER_1:  war that...
SPEAKER_1:  Because that's been that way for a very, very long time.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I wonder...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's funny.
SPEAKER_1:  certain
SPEAKER_1:  ideas just there.
SPEAKER_0:  time comes. Exactly, it's like 1848.
SPEAKER_0:  when you would see that there is a whole range of revolutions.
SPEAKER_0:  across Europe.
SPEAKER_0:  or you would see for instance
SPEAKER_0:  the Arab Spring, you see all these revolutions in the Arab world, which unfortunately...
SPEAKER_0:  Nearly all of them failed.
SPEAKER_0:  So yes, these are.
SPEAKER_0:  very contagious ideas that...
SPEAKER_0:  Moves across.
SPEAKER_0:  frontiers from one culture to another.
SPEAKER_0:  And I presume we can add to that there are two elements.
SPEAKER_0:  which one can say there is positive.
SPEAKER_0:  greater communication, there is a greater sense of it.
SPEAKER_0:  World economy.
SPEAKER_0:  and the 10th of the century witnessed the first decade of the century witnessed
SPEAKER_0:  appeared of
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  volatility.
SPEAKER_0:  particularly in
SPEAKER_0:  in
SPEAKER_0:  currency.
SPEAKER_0:  so many of the countries of the world, particularly non-West.
SPEAKER_0:  suffered.
SPEAKER_0:  in and particularly the businesses suffer.
SPEAKER_0:  and not surprisingly, the business class were in the forefront.
SPEAKER_0:  of many of these constitutional movements.
SPEAKER_0:  requiring this state.
SPEAKER_0:  Give.
SPEAKER_0:  day.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of it.
SPEAKER_0:  created the right kind of institutions.
SPEAKER_0:  to listen to their voices.
SPEAKER_0:  to their concerns and the creation of...
SPEAKER_0:  democratic system, parliamentary and...
SPEAKER_0:  system in which there would be a representation.
SPEAKER_0:  popular representation, proper elections and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  and constitutions.
SPEAKER_0:  And this very much is a kind of him.
SPEAKER_0:  French IDFT.
SPEAKER_0:  Constitution going back all the way perhaps to...
SPEAKER_0:  1789 Revolution, Montesquieu.
SPEAKER_0:  all this kind of philosophy.
SPEAKER_0:  I have very greatly.
SPEAKER_0:  appreciated, particularly if right system.
SPEAKER_1:  So what were the ideas in the 1906?
SPEAKER_1:  Iranian Constitution.
SPEAKER_0:  They
SPEAKER_0:  Precisely the same.
SPEAKER_0:  demanding creation of a legal system with division of power.
SPEAKER_0:  between the three.
SPEAKER_0:  executive.
SPEAKER_0:  legislative and the judiciary.
SPEAKER_0:  Not unlike the American system.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  they requested.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically a certain
SPEAKER_0:  a public space to be created between the two sources of power.
SPEAKER_0:  The state.
SPEAKER_0:  which had this.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of control.
SPEAKER_0:  Over the...
SPEAKER_0:  if you like, the secular aspect of life in the society and the religious establishment that had it.
SPEAKER_0:  full control over the
SPEAKER_0:  religious aspects and both of them from the perspective of the
SPEAKER_0:  and constitutionally this considered as repressive.
SPEAKER_0:  And therefore there has to be a new space open between these two.
SPEAKER_0:  And that was the idea of a constitutional revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  Wait.
SPEAKER_0:  By its very nature, it was an idea of modernity.
SPEAKER_0:  They wanted a modern society.
SPEAKER_0:  They wanted better material.
SPEAKER_0:  life.
SPEAKER_0:  They wanted more representation.
SPEAKER_0:  successful.
SPEAKER_0:  The Christusian Revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  As I always would say is the most...
SPEAKER_0:  much more of it.
SPEAKER_0:  Innocent revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  is a revolution that did not particularly have much violence in it.
SPEAKER_0:  contrary to many other revolutions.
SPEAKER_0:  It did not have a centralized leadership.
SPEAKER_0:  per se. That's why actually I'm getting...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, besides the...
SPEAKER_0:  practices.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm getting a lot of...
SPEAKER_0:  request for interviews to compare.
SPEAKER_0:  what's happening now with the Revolution of 1906.
SPEAKER_0:  1909. Are there any echoes?
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, yes, there are, there are.
SPEAKER_0:  because that was a movement that started without...
SPEAKER_0:  Ayy
SPEAKER_0:  With that a
SPEAKER_0:  centralized leadership.
SPEAKER_0:  What actually values to voice this?
SPEAKER_0:  that emerged in various...
SPEAKER_0:  among the merchants.
SPEAKER_0:  or the businessman in the economic community.
SPEAKER_0:  Among the...
SPEAKER_0:  representatives who came to the first parliament.
SPEAKER_0:  Depressed?
SPEAKER_0:  the new generation of the.
SPEAKER_0:  privilege aristocracy.
SPEAKER_0:  who were educated and...
SPEAKER_0:  believed in the Constitutional.
SPEAKER_0:  Values?
SPEAKER_0:  All of these voices emerged at the same time, and somehow...
SPEAKER_0:  They managed to.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  coexist.
SPEAKER_0:  in the first.
SPEAKER_0:  and the second.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  of parliaments that were created.
SPEAKER_0:  between 1905 and 1906.
SPEAKER_0:  6 and 19.
SPEAKER_0:  10 or 1911.
SPEAKER_0:  but they all face huge problems.
SPEAKER_0:  in the sense that
SPEAKER_0:  Iran was in a dire economic situation. This is before the days of the discovery of oil.
SPEAKER_0:  which actually coincides with the disc. There are two important coincidences.
SPEAKER_0:  One is that oil was discovered in the South.
SPEAKER_0:  in 1909.
SPEAKER_0:  during the course of the constitutional revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  Second is that in 1907...
SPEAKER_0:  the two great powers of the time.
SPEAKER_0:  Russian Empire.
SPEAKER_0:  and the British Empire.
SPEAKER_0:  who always honored Iran as being a buffer state between them.
SPEAKER_0:  because they didn't want to get too close to one another.
SPEAKER_0:  basically came to an agreement.
SPEAKER_0:  facing the fear.
SPEAKER_0:  of the rise of the German Empire.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  This is the period of Entente, as you might know in European history.
SPEAKER_0:  whereby the French, the British and the Russians.
SPEAKER_0:  all create a...
SPEAKER_0:  Alliance.
SPEAKER_0:  ultimately leads to the first world war.
SPEAKER_0:  against Germany.
SPEAKER_1:  And at the same time...
SPEAKER_1:  the discovery of oil that.
SPEAKER_1:  the oil industry being a very powerful defining factor of the 20th century for Iraq. Exactly.
SPEAKER_0:  source of a lot of money.
SPEAKER_0:  lot of money but not all of it in the hands of the Iranians only one fifth of it
SPEAKER_0:  by way of royalties came to Iran. Much of it went to the Anglo-
SPEAKER_0:  person
SPEAKER_0:  oil company which they actually discovered the oil in the...
SPEAKER_0:  province.
SPEAKER_0:  going to buy at MSU alliance. That saves money and COVID. And I will all the most cash I canions that what rolled was momentum he did it. Is this a former beta option you also we also did Michelle Luis for the USA and Australia plenty.
SPEAKER_0:  Southwest of Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  raise the major oil industries today right now.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  This business is extremely profitable.
SPEAKER_0:  enterprise for that company and for the British government. It's actually purchased by the British government.
SPEAKER_0:  Churchill Purchase.
SPEAKER_0:  Anglo-Iranian oil company.
SPEAKER_0:  for the British government.
SPEAKER_0:  So it was not anymore a private company.
SPEAKER_0:  It was the British.
SPEAKER_0:  interest as a matter of fact.
SPEAKER_0:  And in the course of the 20th century, although it helped the modernization in Iran,
SPEAKER_0:  but it also helps the creation.
SPEAKER_0:  often more authoritative.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  strong state if you like to call it.
SPEAKER_0:  that 19th century Iran never had that kind of a power.
SPEAKER_0:  Never had that kind of resources.
SPEAKER_0:  Is it 20th century? even dead?
SPEAKER_0:  One fifth.
SPEAKER_0:  of the income.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a rich day, right? Kerling & Estate
SPEAKER_0:  gave it a greater power.
SPEAKER_0:  That's another
SPEAKER_1:  coincidence.
SPEAKER_1:  So yes, yes, you could say the oil was one of the catalysts.
SPEAKER_1:  for absolute power.
SPEAKER_1:  The 20th century saw.
SPEAKER_1:  quite a few countries.
SPEAKER_1:  um, have dictators with power unlike anything else in human history.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  That's weird too.
SPEAKER_0:  Precisely.
SPEAKER_0:  And you know, you can name them from the beginning of the century with people like...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, Lenin, Stalin.
SPEAKER_0:  Of course, Hitler even...
SPEAKER_0:  Mao, of course.
SPEAKER_0:  You can name them and probably as I would say, is the last of them is Khomeini in that century, that you would see this strong man.
SPEAKER_0:  with a sense of either artificial or real.
SPEAKER_0:  sense of so-called charisma.
SPEAKER_0:  And with this.
SPEAKER_0:  total.
SPEAKER_0:  Power over.
SPEAKER_0:  the regime that they create.
SPEAKER_0:  and some of them do nicer.
SPEAKER_0:  He didn't have much of an oil resources in Egypt.
SPEAKER_0:  but he was also one of these strong men.
SPEAKER_0:  in the 20th century.
SPEAKER_0:  loved by some, hated by others.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  it necessarily does not tie up to.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... it too
SPEAKER_0:  economic resources underground. But in the Iranian case, unfortunately it did.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was a
SPEAKER_0:  It was more than, it created more than one issue for Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  It's created a strong state.
SPEAKER_0:  which is the Pahlavi state from 1920.
SPEAKER_0:  One onward.
SPEAKER_0:  Because in 1921...
SPEAKER_0:  at the end of the First World War.
SPEAKER_0:  Iran was in it.
SPEAKER_0:  almost a state of total bankruptcy.
SPEAKER_0:  And.
SPEAKER_0:  The British
SPEAKER_0:  had a
SPEAKER_0:  desire to try to bring Iran to the system that they created in the Middle East in the post-war era.
SPEAKER_0:  the mandate system.
SPEAKER_0:  Palestine, Iraq.
SPEAKER_0:  And then of course.
SPEAKER_0:  French Bandit of Lebanon and Syria, all of this.
SPEAKER_0:  And Iran was separate because Iran was an independent country. It wasn't part of the Ottoman Empire.
SPEAKER_0:  that collapse.
SPEAKER_0:  So they had to somehow handle it.
SPEAKER_0:  and what they tried to do didn't work.
SPEAKER_0:  As a result...
SPEAKER_0:  partly.
SPEAKER_0:  domestic, partly international issues.
SPEAKER_0:  wrote about the regime.
SPEAKER_0:  which is headed by...
SPEAKER_0:  the founder of the Pahlavi dynasty, Reza Shah.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, the first.
SPEAKER_0:  military officer called Reza Khan.
SPEAKER_0:  actually a military officer of the Cossack forces.
SPEAKER_0:  And the Cossack forces was the...
SPEAKER_0:  that was created in the 19th century model of the...
SPEAKER_0:  Russian Kossacks.
SPEAKER_0:  when
SPEAKER_0:  day.
SPEAKER_0:  ruler in the 19th century visited.
SPEAKER_0:  Russia
SPEAKER_0:  as in a royal tour.
SPEAKER_0:  and the desire should degrade.
SPEAKER_0:  Cossack forces said I like this.
SPEAKER_0:  and he created one for himself.
SPEAKER_0:  with Russian officers, actually.
SPEAKER_0:  So the Russian officers served in Iran from Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  1880s up to the revolution of 1917, the collapse of the...
SPEAKER_0:  So many revolutions.
SPEAKER_0:  and Razorshop was an
SPEAKER_0:  Officer in that.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a Han.
SPEAKER_0:  Was an officer in that force.
SPEAKER_0:  And he created a new monarchy for reasons that we need not to go to it.
SPEAKER_0:  and this is called the Pahlavi regime. The Pahlavi regime was a modernizing regime.
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  In effect.
SPEAKER_0:  fulfilled many of the ambitions.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Constitution, many of the aspirations of the Constitutional Revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  better communication.
SPEAKER_0:  secular education.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  centralized states, centralized army.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  better contact with the outside world.
SPEAKER_0:  greater urbanization. That's what a modern state is all about.
SPEAKER_0:  And in that regard, in a sense for the
SPEAKER_0:  first 20 years up to the Second World War.
SPEAKER_0:  was successful.
SPEAKER_0:  despite and more significant of all
SPEAKER_0:  It managed to keep the
SPEAKER_0:  European powers, which was always interfering in the...
SPEAKER_0:  Local Affairs of Iran
SPEAKER_0:  in an arm-leg.
SPEAKER_0:  So they were there.
SPEAKER_0:  in an arm length.
SPEAKER_0:  but they were also...
SPEAKER_0:  respecting the power of the state.
SPEAKER_0:  Part of the.
SPEAKER_0:  Pala Vista.
SPEAKER_0:  During the second world war, the same phenomenon.
SPEAKER_0:  as earlier interference led to the occupation of Iran by the
SPEAKER_0:  Allied Forces.
SPEAKER_0:  the British from the South, the Russians from the North.
SPEAKER_0:  This is Red Army.
SPEAKER_0:  They took over Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course they said, yes, from 1941.
SPEAKER_0:  up to 1945.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course, when the...
SPEAKER_0:  when the Red Army...
SPEAKER_0:  refuse to.
SPEAKER_0:  withdrew from Iranian Azerbaijan.
SPEAKER_0:  And with some.
SPEAKER_0:  thought of possible.
SPEAKER_0:  annexation.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  That province.
SPEAKER_0:  That was a big issue.
SPEAKER_0:  in the post-war Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  So after 1945. Yes, 1945 to 1946.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a big...
SPEAKER_0:  Soviet Union getting greedy. Yes, but eventually they agree.
SPEAKER_0:  Eventually, Stalin agreed to leave.
SPEAKER_0:  the Azerbaijan province in the hope that it would get some
SPEAKER_0:  concessions from Iran, which in the oil of the
SPEAKER_0:  Caspian Era.
SPEAKER_0:  area.
SPEAKER_0:  which didn't work and it's a different story altogether.
SPEAKER_0:  What happened is that...
SPEAKER_0:  in the post-war era.
SPEAKER_0:  between amazing
SPEAKER_0:  445.
SPEAKER_0:  and 1953.
SPEAKER_0:  is a period of...
SPEAKER_0:  greater.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Democratization.
SPEAKER_0:  What's that?
SPEAKER_0:  Reza Shah's dictatorship, basically.
SPEAKER_0:  disappeared.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is where you would see political parties, free press.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of chaotic really.
SPEAKER_0:  as democracies often are. For something.
SPEAKER_1:  like was it was it official?
SPEAKER_0:  a democracy.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a democracy. It was our elections.
SPEAKER_0:  There were elections, yes, of course. Yes, of course.
SPEAKER_0:  and the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Very diverse.
SPEAKER_0:  political tendencies.
SPEAKER_0:  came to do.
SPEAKER_0:  Picture.
SPEAKER_0:  including the two-party of Iran, which is Communist Party of Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  This Communist Party of Iran is probably the biggest.
SPEAKER_0:  Communist Party.
SPEAKER_0:  of the whole of the Middle East.
SPEAKER_0:  and one of the biggest in the world actually.
SPEAKER_0:  at that time.
SPEAKER_1:  Did the Soviet Union have a significant influence?
SPEAKER_0:  Of course.
SPEAKER_0:  We're basically following.
SPEAKER_0:  Or this one.
SPEAKER_0:  although they deny it, but in reality that's the case.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  What happened? They were seen by the Americans during the Cold War.
SPEAKER_0:  That's it.
SPEAKER_0:  as a threat.
SPEAKER_0:  And Iran was going through a period of...
SPEAKER_0:  demanding nationalization of its oil resources. That's a very important episode with Mossadegh.
SPEAKER_0:  whom you might have heard about his name.
SPEAKER_0:  Dr. Mohammad Musadegh was the prime minister.
SPEAKER_0:  and the National Charismatic Leader.
SPEAKER_0:  from 19.
SPEAKER_0:  1951 to 1953, prior to that it was a famous parliament area.
SPEAKER_0:  But this period was the prime minister, if you don't.
SPEAKER_0:  until Arnoldin doesn't make Going Out link video right there.
SPEAKER_0:  nationalize the Iranian oil industry, and the British didn't like it at all.
SPEAKER_0:  and eventually resulted in a famous coup.
SPEAKER_0:  which.
SPEAKER_0:  at least partly was supported.
SPEAKER_0:  by the funding.
SPEAKER_0:  and by the...
SPEAKER_0:  Moral support.
SPEAKER_0:  of the
SPEAKER_0:  the British and the Americans, particularly by the Americans.
SPEAKER_0:  It was always.
SPEAKER_0:  seen as one of the earliest and the most successful.
SPEAKER_0:  CIA operations during the Cold War.
SPEAKER_0:  So CIA had something to do with it? Yes, of course. That's one of the earliest operations of the CIA.
SPEAKER_0:  Wait a minute.
SPEAKER_1:  What was, yes of course, what was the, what was the...
SPEAKER_0:  doing. CIA, this is the time at the post-war era. In the 50s. In the 50s, 40s and 50s.
SPEAKER_0:  The British Empire...
SPEAKER_0:  which was...
SPEAKER_0:  really the major superpower of the region after the collapse of the Tzari Empire.
SPEAKER_0:  Gradually.
SPEAKER_0:  took the second.
SPEAKER_0:  See ya.
SPEAKER_0:  to the Americans who were the...
SPEAKER_0:  newcomers and the great powers and the...
SPEAKER_0:  victors of the Second World War.
SPEAKER_0:  And the Mekans viewed Iran as an important...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  as an important country.
SPEAKER_0:  since it has the largest
SPEAKER_0:  common borders with the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was.
SPEAKER_0:  I did the start.
SPEAKER_0:  was the Persian Gulf, which at the time...
SPEAKER_0:  was the greatest.
SPEAKER_0:  I
SPEAKER_0:  supplier of
SPEAKER_0:  oil
SPEAKER_0:  to the outside world.
SPEAKER_0:  And therefore the Americans had a particular interest in Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  And in the earlier stages, their interest was in the interest of the Iranian government.
SPEAKER_0:  Because they want it.
SPEAKER_0:  to get rid of.
SPEAKER_0:  Booth.
SPEAKER_0:  the Soviet Union which made a return.
SPEAKER_0:  in the post war era.
SPEAKER_0:  and of course the British that were...
SPEAKER_0:  gradually withdrawing.
SPEAKER_0:  from me.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye-bye.
SPEAKER_0:  They had full control over the Anglo-Iranian oil company. They changed the name.
SPEAKER_0:  to angle Iranian oil company.
SPEAKER_0:  When the name of the country officially changed from Persia to Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  in the West.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  D-
SPEAKER_0:  Name of the company, Chase.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  They got into a huge dispute with the government.
SPEAKER_0:  that eventually led to the...
SPEAKER_0:  of 1953, which eventually created a...
SPEAKER_0:  Very.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, very.
SPEAKER_0:  distressful memory.
SPEAKER_0:  in the minds of many of the Iranian nationalists.
SPEAKER_0:  that this was the betrayal of the great powers.
SPEAKER_0:  the British and Americans.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, CIA played a part.
SPEAKER_0:  because I feared.
SPEAKER_0:  contrary to the British that they were afraid of their.
SPEAKER_0:  and oil in Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  The CIA was afraid of the...
SPEAKER_0:  Soviet penetration.
SPEAKER_0:  in.
SPEAKER_0:  in the start.
SPEAKER_0:  and particularly because it was very powerful.
SPEAKER_0:  for the very powerful communist party to the party of Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  day.
SPEAKER_0:  gradually shifted between the Truman administration and Eisenhower administration. These are early days of the CIA.
SPEAKER_0:  And then
SPEAKER_0:  they actually did.
SPEAKER_0:  Participate.
SPEAKER_0:  to set their agents.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a long story to that.
SPEAKER_0:  and it eventually resulted in a successful coup.
SPEAKER_0:  that removed Musaddegh from power
SPEAKER_1:  What's the United States interest here? Why are they using CIA? Are they trying to make sure...
SPEAKER_1:  there's not too much centralization of power.
SPEAKER_0:  in this region.
SPEAKER_0:  They were afraid of the fact that the...
SPEAKER_0:  that of the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  and during the Cold War, that was their concern.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_1:  They actually almost want to protect Iran and its own sovereign processes from influence of Awad al-Nusra.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  Because they were afraid of the fact.
SPEAKER_0:  If
SPEAKER_0:  Eat on.
SPEAKER_0:  or at least this is part of the.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm simplifying a very complex picture.
SPEAKER_0:  P poisoned?
SPEAKER_0:  but the Americans basically.
SPEAKER_0:  We're thinking that if Iran is going to be lost.
SPEAKER_0:  to Soviet influence.
SPEAKER_0:  then eventually basically all the oil resources in the Persian Gulf are going to be threatened.
SPEAKER_0:  and this would...
SPEAKER_0:  Basically is the...
SPEAKER_0:  National Security of...
SPEAKER_0:  the United States and all of the Western Allies.
SPEAKER_0:  European allies.
SPEAKER_0:  So in a sense.
SPEAKER_0:  This was the long arm of the CIA to try to...
SPEAKER_0:  try to make sure that that's not going to happen.
SPEAKER_0:  And then of course they were persuaded by the British.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the old hand.
SPEAKER_0:  We've been in Iran since the beginning of the...
SPEAKER_0:  Nineteenth century they always had relations with Iran and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  they gradually replace.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course, I don't want to give them this kind of a satanic.
SPEAKER_0:  view that the making of a zip.
SPEAKER_0:  bad influence because they had also some very good influences in Iraq.
SPEAKER_0:  but this particular episode.
SPEAKER_0:  somehow.
SPEAKER_0:  Shit.
SPEAKER_0:  Dark Light.
SPEAKER_0:  on the American presence and was used and abused.
SPEAKER_0:  time and again particularly the revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  1979.
SPEAKER_0:  Was this great Satan idea that Khomeini created?
SPEAKER_0:  basically was based on the fact is.
SPEAKER_0:  1953.
SPEAKER_0:  You were responsible for the downfall of
SPEAKER_0:  a national government in Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  which as a matter of fact, he had no respect for it.
SPEAKER_0:  how many had no respect for it.
SPEAKER_0:  secular, national, liberals.
SPEAKER_0:  including Mohammed Moussaadeh.
SPEAKER_0:  but he was using it as a...
SPEAKER_0:  as a rhetorical tool.
SPEAKER_0:  for his own purposes.
SPEAKER_0:  But what happened is that
SPEAKER_0:  after 1953.
SPEAKER_0:  We see again the rise of
SPEAKER_0:  authoritarian.
SPEAKER_0:  Muhammad Reza Shah is.
SPEAKER_0:  power.
SPEAKER_0:  And then he is, that's the Shah? That's the Shah. That's Bin Nawaz Shah. This is son of Reza Shah.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Technically what is
SPEAKER_0:  shot!
SPEAKER_0:  Shahi is an old term in Persian.
SPEAKER_0:  that comes from a pre-Islamic Persian of
SPEAKER_0:  ancient times in the context of the
SPEAKER_1:  democracy should be seen as like a
SPEAKER_1:  Supreme Leader, King.
SPEAKER_0:  is the head of the executive power.
SPEAKER_0:  according to the constitution of nineteen or six all that's in the constitution the actual term show as a place in the constitution but the to Tris or okay using
SPEAKER_0:  but the Shah is a very old term.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's almost like a monarchic term like a like a
SPEAKER_0:  King.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it is actually is a term.
SPEAKER_0:  peculiar to Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  I've written about it somewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  What?
SPEAKER_0:  because the term that the Western word in the ancient times has been rex.
SPEAKER_0:  for royalty and the king.
SPEAKER_0:  in the Eastern world in
SPEAKER_0:  India is Raj, is the same origin, the same root.
SPEAKER_0:  Iran never shared that. They had the idea of a-
SPEAKER_0:  We'll see.
SPEAKER_0:  Rex and Raj, I don't want to get into too much of etymology, but this is an interesting one.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Both means the one that opens the road.
SPEAKER_0:  for
SPEAKER_0:  basically enforcer of religion.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, in, vidare
SPEAKER_0:  of the right religion.
SPEAKER_0:  Cause Rex and Raj both have the
SPEAKER_0:  After a small logical little
SPEAKER_0:  origin of
SPEAKER_0:  Right
SPEAKER_0:  You see? And right means the right religion.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically. There's some.
SPEAKER_1:  much beautiful language here. I'm just looking at the Persian constitution in 1906.
SPEAKER_1:  and it says it's the constitution of the sublime.
SPEAKER_1:  state of Persia.
SPEAKER_1:  Pajar Iran.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, just.
SPEAKER_1:  Just the extra adjectives on top of this stuff is.
SPEAKER_0:  beautiful. Yeah, because that was actually
SPEAKER_0:  The change that came about, I don't want to go too much into it.
SPEAKER_0:  It was called, as I pointed out before, the guarded domains of Iran. Yes. They changed that to the sublime state of Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  Unique as you should ever be.
SPEAKER_0:  Because
SPEAKER_0:  wanted to give a greater sense of centrality of this state.
SPEAKER_0:  and sublime was the term used.
SPEAKER_1:  What permeates all of this is a poetic.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, there is a history.
SPEAKER_0:  of poetry to the culture, which is fascinating.
SPEAKER_1:  So I mean it's I of course I don't speak the language, but even in Russian there's also
SPEAKER_1:  A music.
SPEAKER_1:  to the soul of the people that represents itself, that presents itself in the form of poetry and literature in the way that it doesn't in the...
SPEAKER_1:  in the English speaking world. I don't know what that is. There's
SPEAKER_0:  um
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, this is a romantic site.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I agree with you.
SPEAKER_0:  In Iran, of course, you know, there's a time of the constitutional revolution, there's a time of great poetry.
SPEAKER_0:  This kind of a...
SPEAKER_0:  patriotic.
SPEAKER_0:  sentiments that comes through.
SPEAKER_0:  poetry plays a very important part.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  Of course.
SPEAKER_0:  These days poetry has...
SPEAKER_0:  kind of decline.
SPEAKER_0:  and instead you see the visual image that is at the center. That's why cinema is so important.
SPEAKER_0:  kids these days with their TikTok.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, let me finish this about the...
SPEAKER_0:  Period of my madresa show.
SPEAKER_0:  EEE
SPEAKER_0:  built up because she received the greater.
SPEAKER_0:  Income.
SPEAKER_0:  from
SPEAKER_0:  the oil revenue and it built up a very strong state with a strong security force.
SPEAKER_0:  It's strange.
SPEAKER_0:  security apparatus, which is this SAVAK.
SPEAKER_0:  Is there?
SPEAKER_0:  which is an acronym for the
SPEAKER_0:  security force in security organization.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  She of course...
SPEAKER_0:  unfortunately in the 1960s and 70s, particularly 1970s.
SPEAKER_0:  basically suppress the voices.
SPEAKER_0:  of or possibility of any kind of a mass.
SPEAKER_0:  participation in the political.
SPEAKER_0:  process.
SPEAKER_0:  It became very much an authoritarian regime with its own technocrats.
SPEAKER_0:  very much a modernist.
SPEAKER_0:  vision of
SPEAKER_0:  off off off
SPEAKER_0:  Iran's future.
SPEAKER_0:  and almost kind of messianic that he was hoping that Iran...
SPEAKER_0:  in a decade would become the fifth.
SPEAKER_0:  most powerful state in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  and the riches, as you would have said.
SPEAKER_0:  the gates of the great civilization.
SPEAKER_0:  very much in the mind.
SPEAKER_0:  at this image of ancient Iran of the Achaemenid Empire.
SPEAKER_0:  And we want to go back to that greatness of the Achaemenid Empire somewhat.
SPEAKER_0:  Rather naïve.
SPEAKER_0:  and very nationalistic in a crude fashion.
SPEAKER_0:  And what happened is that...
SPEAKER_0:  As a result, there was built up some kind of a resistance.
SPEAKER_0:  from the intellectuals, from the left.
SPEAKER_0:  eventually resulting in a kind of a protest movement, as I said by 1977.
SPEAKER_0:  then of course the question that comes to mind and they probably...
SPEAKER_0:  you would like to know about.
SPEAKER_0:  is the fact that white becomes religious, white become Islamic.
SPEAKER_0:  If it's the-
SPEAKER_0:  popular.
SPEAKER_0:  you know.
SPEAKER_0:  National is liberal.
SPEAKER_0:  tendency of opening up the
SPEAKER_0:  political space.
SPEAKER_0:  and allowing greater participation going back to the constitution.
SPEAKER_0:  of 1906, 1907.
SPEAKER_0:  why it's all of a sudden it becomes Khomeini, where the sea comes from.
SPEAKER_0:  The reason for that, at least in a concise fashion.
SPEAKER_0:  is the...
SPEAKER_0:  fact that in one area.
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  after the greater suppression of all the other voices remained.
SPEAKER_0:  Open was religion.
SPEAKER_0:  Masks.
SPEAKER_0:  The mullahs and the
SPEAKER_0:  full pet.
SPEAKER_0:  and the message that gradually shifted.
SPEAKER_0:  from the old traditional message of the Sharia of Islam.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, all the rules and regulations of how one has to live.
SPEAKER_0:  into something very political.
SPEAKER_0:  and not only political.
SPEAKER_0:  but also radical politics.
SPEAKER_0:  Soap.
SPEAKER_0:  in the whole period from the Constitutional Revolution to the Revolution of 1979.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, the religious establishment gradually was pushed to the opposition.
SPEAKER_0:  They were not originated, very conservative.
SPEAKER_0:  support us. update.
SPEAKER_0:  as the Catholic Church, for instance.
SPEAKER_0:  was supported of.
SPEAKER_0:  Majority of the.
SPEAKER_0:  I said Italian.
SPEAKER_0:  governments around the world.
SPEAKER_0:  But the politicization...
SPEAKER_0:  was the result of isolation.
SPEAKER_0:  because they were left out of the...
SPEAKER_0:  system.
SPEAKER_0:  And while in isolation
SPEAKER_0:  They did not.
SPEAKER_0:  They were not successful.
SPEAKER_0:  in
SPEAKER_0:  trying to reform themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  to try to become.
SPEAKER_0:  to try to find answers to many of the questions of modern times.
SPEAKER_0:  What happens to women?
SPEAKER_0:  What happens to civil rights?
SPEAKER_0:  What happens to...
SPEAKER_0:  civil society.
SPEAKER_0:  How?
SPEAKER_0:  modern law and individual
SPEAKER_0:  freedoms have to be.
SPEAKER_0:  defined in Islamic terms.
SPEAKER_1:  how to separate religion and.
SPEAKER_0:  state or how to separate religion and state.
SPEAKER_0:  These issues were never addressed.
SPEAKER_0:  What happened is that
SPEAKER_0:  there was this bypass through political.
SPEAKER_0:  Islam.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  revolutionary Islam as it gradually they learned, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the bypass, bypass to power basically.
SPEAKER_0:  to become again.
SPEAKER_0:  a voice in the society and eventually a prominent voice and eventually monolithic.
SPEAKER_0:  voice.
SPEAKER_0:  in the society. That's the process that led to the
SPEAKER_0:  into the revolution of 1979.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, this period.
SPEAKER_0:  greater attention was paid to religion, even among the secular middle classes.
SPEAKER_0:  who were alienated.
SPEAKER_0:  for a very long time because of this.
SPEAKER_0:  extensive modernization of the Pahlavi period.
SPEAKER_0:  They didn't have a sense of that old...
SPEAKER_0:  Molus with deterbents.
SPEAKER_0:  but they became, they had a kind of aura.
SPEAKER_0:  in this period, yes, they are those who remain.
SPEAKER_0:  and not corrupted.
SPEAKER_0:  They are the people who...
SPEAKER_0:  basically went against the
SPEAKER_0:  suppression of the Pahlavi regime.
SPEAKER_0:  and Khomeini became a leader, a symbol of them.
SPEAKER_0:  Nobody ever thought in the earlier stages.
SPEAKER_0:  and bonk
SPEAKER_0:  This very excited.
SPEAKER_0:  Multitudes that came to the streets.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Iranian cities.
SPEAKER_0:  in 1979.
SPEAKER_0:  or 1978 actually.
SPEAKER_0:  Really thought that this
SPEAKER_0:  This old model is in its 70s.
SPEAKER_0:  that all of a sudden has appeared from Najaf.
SPEAKER_0:  through Paris to Tehran.
SPEAKER_0:  is going to take over and create a autocracy, a religious.
SPEAKER_0:  authoring the
SPEAKER_1:  back up for just a second who who is home any.
SPEAKER_1:  Who you just you just mentioned a few.
SPEAKER_1:  disparate facts about the man.
SPEAKER_1:  He was the person that took power in 1979, the supreme leader of Iran. Some you mentioned something about Paris, something about being in the seventies. I guess.
SPEAKER_0:  what should we know about the guy
SPEAKER_0:  Ayatollah Khomeini
SPEAKER_0:  who eventually was known as Imam Khomeini. He was kind of promoted to a...
SPEAKER_0:  even more sublime position.
SPEAKER_1:  Can we, just a million tangents.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, I told her.
SPEAKER_1:  im imam.
SPEAKER_0:  What do these terms mean? Well Ayatollah means the-
SPEAKER_0:  Sign of God.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh huh.
SPEAKER_0:  in the course of the 19th century.
SPEAKER_0:  or early 20th century.
SPEAKER_0:  as the religious establishment gradually lost its.
SPEAKER_0:  greater presence in the society and its prominent places in society.
SPEAKER_0:  they had some kind of inflation in titles.
SPEAKER_0:  So they gave themselves more grand titles. Yeah, more adjectives. More adjectives, more grand titles such as Ayatollah.
SPEAKER_0:  that became.
SPEAKER_0:  a kind of a highest rank
SPEAKER_0:  of the religious hierarchy.
SPEAKER_0:  which incidentally was in unofficial hierarchy.
SPEAKER_0:  It was not.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not like the-
SPEAKER_0:  like Catholic church that you have.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, bishops and you know.
SPEAKER_0:  further off.
SPEAKER_0:  It was very unofficial, Mother.
SPEAKER_0:  and he was an ayatullah.
SPEAKER_0:  was eventually recognized as an ayatollah.
SPEAKER_0:  He wasn't the first AYATOL?
SPEAKER_0:  No, no, no, not at all. The ayatollahs were before him.
SPEAKER_0:  ever since the beginning of the century.
SPEAKER_0:  What?
SPEAKER_0:  he was eventually recognized as an ayatollah.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  if I want to start it this way.
SPEAKER_0:  Ayatollah Khomeini was born in 1900.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  In a sense, all this
SPEAKER_0:  Tremendous.
SPEAKER_0:  change that Iran witnessed in the course of the...
SPEAKER_0:  20th century.
SPEAKER_0:  was in a sense.
SPEAKER_0:  materializing this person.
SPEAKER_0:  He become.
SPEAKER_0:  Eh.
SPEAKER_0:  Mullah of a lower rank
SPEAKER_0:  went to the...
SPEAKER_0:  traditional madrasas to the traditional...
SPEAKER_0:  centers for the education.
SPEAKER_0:  of these seminarians.
SPEAKER_0:  never had a secular education.
SPEAKER_0:  Hard every.
SPEAKER_0:  complex Islamic education on this one hand jurisprudence on the other hand
SPEAKER_0:  probably a little bit of Islamic philosophy.
SPEAKER_0:  Mysticism which is un-
SPEAKER_0:  Usual for the...
SPEAKER_0:  yours for the
SPEAKER_0:  I'm 40.
SPEAKER_0:  faqih as they call them.
SPEAKER_0:  these religious scholars or...
SPEAKER_0:  or legal scholars of Islam.
SPEAKER_0:  and then he...
SPEAKER_0:  in the 1960s.
SPEAKER_0:  when
SPEAKER_0:  He was residing in Tehran.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  gradually becoming more important.
SPEAKER_0:  He became.
SPEAKER_0:  a voice of opposition against the Shah.
SPEAKER_0:  and the reason for opposition.
SPEAKER_0:  in the early 1960s.
SPEAKER_0:  was the fact that the shark...
SPEAKER_0:  carried through a series of
SPEAKER_0:  extensive
SPEAKER_0:  modernization policies.
SPEAKER_0:  of which the most important was the land reform.
SPEAKER_0:  So in effect, the land distribution.
SPEAKER_0:  that took place.
SPEAKER_0:  in the early 60s.
SPEAKER_0:  removed or weakened greatly that class of landowners.
SPEAKER_0:  from the ancient, from the...
SPEAKER_0:  Nineteenth Century.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  BEE
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  Khomeini saw himself.
SPEAKER_0:  as a voice of death.
SPEAKER_0:  old class.
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  felt that actually declared that this land redistribution is.
SPEAKER_0:  un-Islamic, according to the Islamic law.
SPEAKER_0:  Property is honored.
SPEAKER_0:  and you cannot just...
SPEAKER_0:  No matter how.
SPEAKER_0:  much and how large are these?
SPEAKER_0:  a state that the landowning class has, the government has no right to redistribute it.
SPEAKER_0:  even among the peasants. it day but Lup Coming
SPEAKER_0:  people who are...
SPEAKER_0:  filling the line.
SPEAKER_0:  So that was a major issue. Share also give them.
SPEAKER_0: ...D
SPEAKER_0:  right of...
SPEAKER_0:  Vote.
SPEAKER_0:  to women.
SPEAKER_0:  And that also.
SPEAKER_0:  He objected.
SPEAKER_0:  So is that women?
SPEAKER_0:  Don't have it right.
SPEAKER_1:  Can we just linger on the Islamic law?
SPEAKER_1:  How firm and clear.
SPEAKER_1:  is the Islamic law that he was representing and embodying.
SPEAKER_1:  Is this, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Codify. Yes, it's a good one.
SPEAKER_0:  term.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  That's another issue.
SPEAKER_0:  Not only the hierarchy was unofficial.
SPEAKER_0:  and informal.
SPEAKER_0:  But hold still.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Islamic law, particularly Shi'i law.
SPEAKER_0:  did not have any...
SPEAKER_0:  a codified system.
SPEAKER_0:  because these religious authorities always resisted.
SPEAKER_0:  Becoming under a
SPEAKER_0:  umbrella.
SPEAKER_0:  of a more codified system of.
SPEAKER_0:  Islamic law.
SPEAKER_0:  because they were outside the state in a sense. Simple
SPEAKER_0:  Civil law was in the hand of the religious establishment. They had their own courts.
SPEAKER_0:  independent of the state.
SPEAKER_0:  But other matters of legal matters was in the hand of the government. There was a-
SPEAKER_0:  kind of in.
SPEAKER_0:  the facto division between these two institutions, state versus the religious establishment.
SPEAKER_0:  Therefore it was not codified.
SPEAKER_0:  so he could declare that this is unofficial.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll say illegal according to the Islamic law.
SPEAKER_0:  that you distributed land to the peasants.
SPEAKER_0:  and another mujtahid or another religious society.
SPEAKER_0:  would say no, no, it's perfectly fine, because he would have it.
SPEAKER_0:  different reading of the law.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  That being in mind that
SPEAKER_0:  adds to the complexity of the picture.
SPEAKER_0:  He in the 1960s, free.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a period.
SPEAKER_0:  of uprising of the supporters of Ayatollah Khomeini.
SPEAKER_0:  That was a turning point in a sense to try to.
SPEAKER_0:  politicize the religious.
SPEAKER_0:  supporters of Ayatollah, who were loyal to Ayatollah Khomeini.
SPEAKER_0:  and in a sense.
SPEAKER_0:  all the community of.
SPEAKER_0:  more religiously orientated against.
SPEAKER_0:  the secular.
SPEAKER_0:  policies of the show.
SPEAKER_0:  and against of course
SPEAKER_0:  dictatorship.
SPEAKER_0:  Off the shelf.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's where the religious...
SPEAKER_1:  became a political party.
SPEAKER_0:  In 1963, the first...
SPEAKER_0:  moment is the huge uprising.
SPEAKER_0:  And the government suppressed it.
SPEAKER_0:  But then...
SPEAKER_0:  suppression. Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  would start to build. goal field.
SPEAKER_0:  and he was sent to exile.
SPEAKER_0:  He went to Najaf, which is this great center in southern.
SPEAKER_0:  So became a martyr on top of this. At the martyr.
SPEAKER_0:  He was probably even forgotten, to some extent.
SPEAKER_0:  but not, it was forgotten for the...
SPEAKER_0:  for the secular.
SPEAKER_0:  middle class.
SPEAKER_0:  What not?
SPEAKER_0:  to those supporters of his.
SPEAKER_0:  who were paying him.
SPEAKER_0:  their dues because in Islam you would pay dues.
SPEAKER_0:  to religious leaders.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there's religious views and aahms.
SPEAKER_0:  that you put pay to the...
SPEAKER_0:  Click our authorities.
SPEAKER_0:  and they redistribute them among their own students and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  So they built actually a network of loyalty based on this.
SPEAKER_0:  donations.
SPEAKER_0:  And these donations.
SPEAKER_0:  That's received by a total of how many was very
SPEAKER_0:  effectively through his network.
SPEAKER_0:  was distributed.
SPEAKER_0:  You guys.
SPEAKER_0:  in exile at Sardar.
SPEAKER_0:  The 1977, 1978.
SPEAKER_0:  when the situation
SPEAKER_0:  changed and there was a little bit of opening.
SPEAKER_0:  in the political climate.
SPEAKER_0:  Then you saw that Ayatollah Khomeini...
SPEAKER_0:  start sending.
SPEAKER_0:  cassette messages.
SPEAKER_0:  That was his mean of communication.
SPEAKER_0:  was sending cassettes and cassettes were sent through
SPEAKER_0:  the country by his...
SPEAKER_0:  Network.
SPEAKER_0:  So all declarations and saying first.
SPEAKER_0:  that we would like to see a greater democratization.
SPEAKER_0:  and the Shah has to...
SPEAKER_0:  Abide by...
SPEAKER_0:  the Constitution of 1907.
SPEAKER_0:  this is a constitution, this is a democratic system and so forth. was he charismatic?
SPEAKER_0:  Well it depends who would call.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you call charismatic? The long beard it was
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh YAS
SPEAKER_0:  interban and the
SPEAKER_0:  gown which was
SPEAKER_0:  a very unusual leadership.
SPEAKER_0:  For-
SPEAKER_0:  people who were.
SPEAKER_0:  much more accustomed to the civilian clothing or to the equipment.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Shah's military uniforms.
SPEAKER_0:  that you used to wear.
SPEAKER_1:  like.
SPEAKER_1:  He is a man that was able to take power to become popular, Yeah, good.
SPEAKER_1:  Sorry.
SPEAKER_0:  I
SPEAKER_1:  I would like
SPEAKER_1:  Is it the ideas, is it an accident, or is it the man himself, the charisma?
SPEAKER_1:  or something about the man that led to this particular person.
SPEAKER_1:  basically changing.
SPEAKER_1:  the tide of history in this part of the world.
SPEAKER_1:  in a way that...
SPEAKER_0:  unexpected.
SPEAKER_0:  or was it just the beard?
SPEAKER_0:  No, I think though it's beyond the app era.
SPEAKER_0:  Appearance is greatly helps, as you know.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_1:  In the 20th century, appearance is helpful.
SPEAKER_1:  pictures for propaganda from us.
SPEAKER_0:  That's an important factor.
SPEAKER_0:  and he was an
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of it.
SPEAKER_0:  Adamant.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  very...
SPEAKER_0:  severe
SPEAKER_0:  in his own positions.
SPEAKER_0:  could appear very uncompromising.
SPEAKER_0:  and he had this sense of.
SPEAKER_0:  Confidence, self confidence.
SPEAKER_0:  that virtually everybody else lacked.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  He was a man of opportunity.
SPEAKER_0:  As soon as you would see that...
SPEAKER_0:  a chance and opportunity would open up.
SPEAKER_0:  He would.
SPEAKER_0:  Jump on it.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's what he did basically.
SPEAKER_0:  as more the political space.
SPEAKER_0:  opened.
SPEAKER_0:  the weaknesses of the Shah's government became more evident.
SPEAKER_0:  his indecision became more evident.
SPEAKER_0:  his lack of-
SPEAKER_0:  confidence became more evident.
SPEAKER_0:  Khomeini managed to move further into the center.
SPEAKER_0:  After movement.
SPEAKER_0:  because he was the only
SPEAKER_0:  Authority.
SPEAKER_0:  that had this network.
SPEAKER_0:  of support.
SPEAKER_0:  through the masks.
SPEAKER_0:  through the people.
SPEAKER_0:  who paid.
SPEAKER_0:  homage to him.
SPEAKER_0:  who followed him because there's a sense of following.
SPEAKER_0:  of the religious leader in Shiza.
SPEAKER_0:  You are a follower of this authority.
SPEAKER_0:  follower of that exercise.
SPEAKER_0:  and his
SPEAKER_0:  basically created.
SPEAKER_0:  an environment in which people...
SPEAKER_0:  looked upon him as a kind of a messianic figure.
SPEAKER_0:  that came to save Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  from what they considered at the time.
SPEAKER_0:  the problems of...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  dictatorship under the show.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's not a suspic-
SPEAKER_1:  about Islamic law being the primary law of the land.
SPEAKER_0:  tattoo.
SPEAKER_0:  people had very little sense.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what Islamic law is all about.
SPEAKER_0:  because the secular education.
SPEAKER_0:  has left that into the old...
SPEAKER_0:  religious schools, this is not something that...
SPEAKER_0:  ordinary educated Iranian who go to the universities.
SPEAKER_0:  is going to learn. Therefore, there is a sense of idealization that there is something great there.
SPEAKER_0:  That is good.
SPEAKER_0:  and there were quite a number of intellectuals.
SPEAKER_0:  who also view this.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of an idea.
SPEAKER_0:  they would refer to as West Toxication. That is.
SPEAKER_0:  this.
SPEAKER_0:  Civilization of the West.
SPEAKER_0:  that has brought with it.
SPEAKER_0:  all the modernity that we see around ourselves.
SPEAKER_0:  has its
SPEAKER_0:  enormous sinister features into it.
SPEAKER_0:  and it has taken away from us our authenticity.
SPEAKER_0:  That was the thing, that there is something authentic.
SPEAKER_0:  that should be protected.
SPEAKER_0:  And therefore...
SPEAKER_0:  a man in that kind of a garb and appearance.
SPEAKER_0:  seemed as a source.
SPEAKER_0:  for return to this originality.
SPEAKER_0:  of their own culture, authenticity of their own culture.
SPEAKER_0:  anti-perfectly.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh
SPEAKER_0:  took advantage of that. That is Khomeini.
SPEAKER_0:  Pre-CAD, want to take your feet?
SPEAKER_0:  and the circular around it.
SPEAKER_0:  at the expense of everybody else.
SPEAKER_0:  which he managed in the course of 1979 to 1989.
SPEAKER_0:  Which is-
SPEAKER_0:  passed away, died.
SPEAKER_0:  in the 10 years during this period.
SPEAKER_0:  managed to basically transform.
SPEAKER_0:  the Iranian society.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, two-
SPEAKER_0:  create institutions of the Islamic Republic.
SPEAKER_0:  and to acquire himself the position of the guardian.
SPEAKER_0:  Juris.
SPEAKER_0:  That was something completely new, it didn't ever exist.
SPEAKER_0:  before.
SPEAKER_0:  As a matter of fact...
SPEAKER_0:  As you might know...
SPEAKER_0:  The model of government.
SPEAKER_0:  that a religious establishment takes over the state.
SPEAKER_0:  is unprecedented.
SPEAKER_0:  throughout the course of Iranian history.
SPEAKER_0:  throughout the course of the Islamic history, I would say.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the first example.
SPEAKER_0:  and probably the only example.
SPEAKER_0:  Of a-
SPEAKER_0:  of a regime?
SPEAKER_0:  that religious establishment that has always in the course of Iranian history.
SPEAKER_0:  ever since I would say probably at least 16th century, if not earlier.
SPEAKER_0:  has been always.
SPEAKER_0:  separate from this state.
SPEAKER_0:  and always
SPEAKER_0:  kind of collaborating with this state with the certain tensions in between the two of them.
SPEAKER_0:  David to.
SPEAKER_0:  basically as they would call themselves, the two...
SPEAKER_0:  pillars of stability in the society.
SPEAKER_0:  That situation changed. For the first time, the religious establishment took over.
SPEAKER_0:  the power of this state.
SPEAKER_0:  and that's at the core.
SPEAKER_0:  of what we see today as a major issue.
SPEAKER_0:  for Iranian society.
SPEAKER_0:  because
SPEAKER_0:  These are basically that old balance between the
SPEAKER_0:  Religion.
SPEAKER_0:  and the state which was kind of a de facto.
SPEAKER_0:  separation of the authorities of the two.
SPEAKER_0:  has been violated and now you have in power.
SPEAKER_0:  It's y'all.
SPEAKER_0:  Theocracy in effect.
SPEAKER_0:  which of course only in the set I did.
SPEAKER_0:  and in its appearance is theocracy deep down.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a-
SPEAKER_0:  in my opinion, is a brutal fascist regime.
SPEAKER_0:  that it stays in power, but it has the appearance.
SPEAKER_0:  of religion into it.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is really the story of the revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  And as a result of that...
SPEAKER_0:  The Iranian middle class has greatly suffered. It's not without reason that you see 4 million Iranians abroad.
SPEAKER_0:  because.
SPEAKER_0:  basically the emergence of this new power.
SPEAKER_0:  Gradually.
SPEAKER_0:  isolated.
SPEAKER_0:  All.
SPEAKER_0:  marginalized the secular middle class.
SPEAKER_0:  who could not survive under that regime.
SPEAKER_0:  and gradually moved out.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, uh, in the course of perhaps 30, 40 years up to now, Iran has.
SPEAKER_0:  The largest, I think I'm right to say so.
SPEAKER_0:  has the largest brain drain.
SPEAKER_0:  in any country in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  population.
SPEAKER_1:  So fascinating that...
SPEAKER_1:  How much of a...
SPEAKER_1:  weird quirk of history is it?
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  on.
SPEAKER_1:  that religion
SPEAKER_1:  would take hold in a country.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, does it have to do with the individual?
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like...
SPEAKER_1:  if we re ran the 20th century.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... a thousand times
SPEAKER_1:  when we get the 79 revolution resulting in.
SPEAKER_1:  Islamic law like
SPEAKER_1:  less than.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, 1% of the time it feels like, or no, which, which percent.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I think it has something to do.
SPEAKER_0:  with the very complex nature.
SPEAKER_0:  off.
SPEAKER_0:  how Iran evolved.
SPEAKER_0:  over a long period of time, since the 16th century. That's why.
SPEAKER_0:  If I-
SPEAKER_0:  would.
SPEAKER_0:  for a moment talk about what I have written.
SPEAKER_0:  I've written a book.
SPEAKER_0:  That's called
SPEAKER_0:  Iran and modern history, and it does not start in the 20th century.
SPEAKER_0:  It starts in the 16th century.
SPEAKER_0:  Because it
SPEAKER_0:  That's what I've argued, that this complex process
SPEAKER_0:  that at the end of the day resulted in what we see around us today.
SPEAKER_0:  is something that was in making for a very long time. Religion was a big.
SPEAKER_1:  part of it. She and
SPEAKER_1:  the Messiah complex, the longing for this great vision of a great nation.
SPEAKER_1:  that somehow is a
SPEAKER_1:  sublime nation.
SPEAKER_1:  That can only be...
SPEAKER_1:  Fully sublime.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_0:  religion.
SPEAKER_0:  or at the time it was thought that is true religion. Ever since then,
SPEAKER_0:  It's disillusionment with that image, or at least a process of disillusionment.
SPEAKER_0:  The outcome of it is what we see today.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically.
SPEAKER_0:  That process of 40 years is a process of readjusting.
SPEAKER_0:  to the realities of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  That.
SPEAKER_0:  that great moment of.
SPEAKER_0:  Romantic.
SPEAKER_0:  success of a revolution, like most revolutions of course.
SPEAKER_0:  that is going to change Iran and bring this
SPEAKER_0:  kind of a moment of greatness.
SPEAKER_0:  led into this great disappointment. It's a movement of the great disappointment in a sense.
SPEAKER_0:  Like most messianic movements, by the way, messianic movements in general are...
SPEAKER_0:  always leading into great disappointments.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  What I have here that perhaps...
SPEAKER_0:  should be added to it.
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, it was a peculiarity.
SPEAKER_0:  Of Iran?
SPEAKER_0:  as a society that had to experience.
SPEAKER_0:  this eventual.
SPEAKER_0:  Encounter
SPEAKER_0:  between religion and state.
SPEAKER_0:  That's something to do with the nature of Shiza. That's just one point that should be pointed out.
SPEAKER_0:  Most of Sunni Islam don't have that kind of, I say most because there is something there.
SPEAKER_0:  What?
SPEAKER_0:  Sony Islam in general does not have that kind of an aspiration.
SPEAKER_0:  for the coming of a messianic.
SPEAKER_0:  a leader.
SPEAKER_0:  She's M.D.O.S.
SPEAKER_0:  She's, I mean, it's very shaping.
SPEAKER_0:  Particularly the way that it was.
SPEAKER_0:  set up in Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  was.
SPEAKER_0:  a religion that has always this element of expectation to it.
SPEAKER_0:  for the coming of this.
SPEAKER_0:  Messianic leader.
SPEAKER_0:  Of course.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, between practices.
SPEAKER_0:  All societies look for
SPEAKER_0:  messianic leaders and just look around us.
SPEAKER_1:  but some societies more than others.
SPEAKER_1:  There's certain culture, it might have to do with the room.
SPEAKER_1:  of the romantic poetry that we mentioned earlier.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  Surely.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, not to draw too many parallels, but the Soviet Union, there is romanticism too.
SPEAKER_0:  UGH!
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I don't know. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe idealism?
SPEAKER_0:  a sense of a savior.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Who would?
SPEAKER_0:  who would bring you...
SPEAKER_0:  out of the misery that you're in.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  and air.
SPEAKER_0:  always looking for it.
SPEAKER_0:  full.
SPEAKER_0:  A third party.
SPEAKER_0:  to solve your...
SPEAKER_0:  issues. That's why probably...
SPEAKER_0:  this.
SPEAKER_0:  Movement has a
SPEAKER_0:  particularly significant because it probably doesn't look for it.
SPEAKER_0:  Although I was talking to my brother who is a historian also.
SPEAKER_0:  And he was saying perhaps the Messiah of this movement is that Mahsa Amin.
SPEAKER_0:  the 22 year old girl.
SPEAKER_0:  That was...
SPEAKER_0:  killed.
SPEAKER_0:  7th of March it Messiah.
SPEAKER_0:  Who is-
SPEAKER_0:  now leading a movement which...
SPEAKER_0:  no longer has that.
SPEAKER_0:  charismatic.
SPEAKER_0:  Leadership with it.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, I would say that...
SPEAKER_0:  Iran has been the birthplace, if I might say that.
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  Messiaenich.
SPEAKER_0:  aspirations.
SPEAKER_0:  Going back to the ancient.
SPEAKER_0:  Zoroastrianism, which is the...
SPEAKER_0:  Really, the whole system that you...
SPEAKER_0:  see in major religions, at least so-called Western religions.
SPEAKER_0:  It's Abrahamic religions.
SPEAKER_0:  is.
SPEAKER_0:  HALIL
SPEAKER_0:  or perhaps influence.
SPEAKER_0:  by Zoroastrianism.
SPEAKER_0:  in which there is an idea of.
SPEAKER_0:  out.
SPEAKER_0:  this world and the other world is hereafter.
SPEAKER_0:  There is an idea of a judgment at the end of the time.
SPEAKER_0:  and there is a concept that there is a moment of justice.
SPEAKER_0:  that it's going to.
SPEAKER_0:  Come.
SPEAKER_0:  with the rise of air.
SPEAKER_0:  religious.
SPEAKER_0:  or a
SPEAKER_0:  charismatic figure.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's a very old phenomenon in Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  Very old.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's time and the game repeated itself.
SPEAKER_0:  in the course of its history, but never as powerfully.
SPEAKER_0:  as it happened in 1979.
SPEAKER_0:  and never in the form of
SPEAKER_0:  authority from within the religious establishment.
SPEAKER_0:  It was always the...
SPEAKER_0:  descent movements that were
SPEAKER_0:  kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  Antinomian, they were against the authority of the...
SPEAKER_0:  a religious establishment.
SPEAKER_0:  That changed in the 20th century.
SPEAKER_0:  but...
SPEAKER_1:  The revolution in 1979, that change is still with us today.
SPEAKER_1:  What, can we just linger on the...
SPEAKER_1:  Are there some practical?
SPEAKER_1:  games of power that occurred.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, in the way that Stalin took power and held power in the early days.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there something like this?
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of the establishment of the revolutionary guard and all those kinds of stuff. Yes. So it's the, the man, say on a figure that has some support from the people, but brother,
SPEAKER_1:  Does he have to crush his enemies in competition?
SPEAKER_0:  It certainly did.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably nuts.
SPEAKER_0:  Certainly not as brutal.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of the...
SPEAKER_0:  victims.
SPEAKER_0:  as you would see in Soviet Union under Stalin.
SPEAKER_0:  Bloodshit.
SPEAKER_0:  or deep.
SPEAKER_0:  destruction of the population was far greater.
SPEAKER_0:  than what you would find in
SPEAKER_0:  Iran of the Islamic Republic.
SPEAKER_0:  uncomfortable.
SPEAKER_0:  Perhaps I would find a greater parallel with Mao Zedong.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  particularly because China has a very strong messianic tradition.
SPEAKER_0:  since the ancient times. So they have something.
SPEAKER_0:  and mow it.
SPEAKER_0:  appeared as the kind of a messianic figure.
SPEAKER_0:  There I can see...
SPEAKER_0:  there is a parallel but also
SPEAKER_0:  You can see with any other authoritarian regime with a
SPEAKER_0:  Messiaenig 4.
SPEAKER_0:  at the head of it, that it destroys all the other forces.
SPEAKER_0:  So during the course of the first 10 years of the...
SPEAKER_0:  Islamic revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  It destroyed the liberal
SPEAKER_0:  Nationalists.
SPEAKER_0:  secular
SPEAKER_0:  It's destroyed.
SPEAKER_0:  D.
SPEAKER_0:  Guerrilla movements.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of them Islamic, some of them Marxist.
SPEAKER_0:  who turned into political parties or tendencies.
SPEAKER_0:  in the course of the post-revolution in 1979.
SPEAKER_0:  They were completely destroyed.
SPEAKER_0:  and in a very brutal fashion.
SPEAKER_0:  and their
SPEAKER_0:  opposition even within the religious establishment, because it wasn't it.
SPEAKER_0:  uniform. There were many different
SPEAKER_0:  tendencies.
SPEAKER_0:  those that will.
SPEAKER_0:  close to the authority of Ayatollah Khomeini.
SPEAKER_0:  or now Imam Khomeini, meaning almost a sacred.
SPEAKER_0:  religious figure.
SPEAKER_0:  Above.
SPEAKER_0:  the level of a religious authority.
SPEAKER_0:  He's a saint.
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of a figure.
SPEAKER_0:  Shizm has this idea of Imams. They were.
SPEAKER_0:  11 of them, the 12th.
SPEAKER_0:  is hidden.
SPEAKER_0:  and would come back at the end of the time. In NAV, thank heads,姜生, Coin British, Ethan Forstner and Carsten Reuven.
SPEAKER_0:  So the title that was always used for them only.
SPEAKER_0:  in Sheezer.
SPEAKER_0:  never used for any other person.
SPEAKER_0:  He is the first person.
SPEAKER_0:  in the revolution of 1979.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  The beauty of a mom.
SPEAKER_0:  but the term deputy gradually disappeared and he became Imam Khomeini
SPEAKER_0:  That's his official title. I love human
SPEAKER_1:  being so much.
SPEAKER_1:  It's so beautiful.
SPEAKER_1:  These titles that we give each other, it's...
SPEAKER_0:  But it's marvelous to observe. You love it because you haven't been under that system. No, I...
SPEAKER_0:  I love it in the way.
SPEAKER_0:  I love it in the very dark.
SPEAKER_0:  It's dark vacation!
SPEAKER_1:  kind of way.
SPEAKER_1:  it caricatures itself. It's almost...
SPEAKER_1:  funny in its absurdity.
SPEAKER_1:  if not for the evil that it has led to in human history.
SPEAKER_0:  But also the fact that it's a mani-
SPEAKER_0:  It's in fact fulfillment.
SPEAKER_0:  in a kind of completely
SPEAKER_0:  Um, eh.
SPEAKER_0:  Unintended fashion.
SPEAKER_0:  is a fulfillment of that.
SPEAKER_0:  idea of a Messiah that they've been fighting for.
SPEAKER_0:  This Imam, which is in Ahida for a thousand years.
SPEAKER_0:  is here and not here.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Therefore,
SPEAKER_0:  Khomeini
SPEAKER_0:  would have in effect fulfilled those.
SPEAKER_0:  anticipations.
SPEAKER_0:  But beyond that, I just give you one example I know that you may have other concerns.
SPEAKER_0:  When I say elimination.
SPEAKER_0:  At the end of the Iran-Iraq war
SPEAKER_0:  Bye-D!
SPEAKER_0:  direct order of Ayatollah Khomeini, a fatwa that he wrote.
SPEAKER_0:  group of
SPEAKER_0:  prisoners.
SPEAKER_0:  could belong to...
SPEAKER_0:  variety of
SPEAKER_0:  I...
SPEAKER_0:  political parties, the left.
SPEAKER_0:  He just left.
SPEAKER_0:  majority of them.
SPEAKER_0:  the Marxists left and the religious left.
SPEAKER_0:  in a matter of a few weeks.
SPEAKER_0:  or perhaps a few months I'm not actually quite sure about it.
SPEAKER_0:  time spy.
SPEAKER_0:  in a series of these were people who have already been tried.
SPEAKER_0:  and they were given...
SPEAKER_0:  sentences.
SPEAKER_0:  They were brought back.
SPEAKER_0:  before the...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  summary trials of three judges.
SPEAKER_0:  or more, three, four of them.
SPEAKER_0:  One of them is
SPEAKER_0:  now.
SPEAKER_0:  day.
SPEAKER_0:  a new president of the Islamic Republic, Raisi.
SPEAKER_0:  And if we give them a quick summary sentences.
SPEAKER_0:  Which meant...
SPEAKER_0:  execution.
SPEAKER_0:  So something between probably 6 to 8 thousand.
SPEAKER_0:  were executed in a matter of a month or two months.
SPEAKER_0:  Something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  Mostly in Tehran, but also in provinces.
SPEAKER_0:  And that remained an extreme.
SPEAKER_0:  extraordinary trauma.
SPEAKER_0:  for the families.
SPEAKER_0:  for those who had these kids, they're all young.
SPEAKER_0:  All young.
SPEAKER_0:  So this remains very much.
SPEAKER_0:  Ehh
SPEAKER_0:  kind of a...
SPEAKER_0:  original scene of the Islamic Republic.
SPEAKER_0:  that cannot get rid of.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's in people's memories.
SPEAKER_0:  day.
SPEAKER_0:  didn't allow them even the families.
SPEAKER_0:  to go and mourn.
SPEAKER_0:  They're dead.
SPEAKER_0:  in an official symmetry which they created for them.
SPEAKER_0:  Now the latest thing is...
SPEAKER_0:  That's it.
SPEAKER_0:  They put a huge...
SPEAKER_0:  concrete wall around it so nobody would be able to get into it.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  This is all part of this extra
SPEAKER_0:  extraordinary level of
SPEAKER_0:  level of.
SPEAKER_0:  atrocity.
SPEAKER_0:  brutality that you see that the regime claimed.
SPEAKER_0:  that it comes with the morality of religion and Islam.
SPEAKER_0:  to bring back the justice and
SPEAKER_0:  and be more...
SPEAKER_0:  in SS.
SPEAKER_0:  Kind to people.
SPEAKER_0:  Ended up.
SPEAKER_0:  with what it is in the memory of.
SPEAKER_0:  many of the people in Iran.
SPEAKER_1:  balanced ah Раз, Hazy place
SPEAKER_0:  That's very much so.
SPEAKER_0:  destroying minorities.
SPEAKER_0:  Bahá'ís one of them.
SPEAKER_0:  Hundreds of Baha'is were without any reason, without any involvement.
SPEAKER_0:  We picked up and...
SPEAKER_0:  I
SPEAKER_0:  executed, the properties were taken over.
SPEAKER_0:  Their rights were taken away from them.
SPEAKER_0:  even up to this day.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the largest.
SPEAKER_0:  by the very religious minority in Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  you would see that in many areas.
SPEAKER_0:  This is him.
SPEAKER_0:  acts very much as an
SPEAKER_0:  beyond authoritarianism, it's a kind of really fascistic regime.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  How many?
SPEAKER_1:  held power for 10 years.
SPEAKER_1:  and then took power the next supreme.
SPEAKER_0:  Alright.
SPEAKER_0:  LEADER!
SPEAKER_1:  who is still the leader today for over 30 years.
SPEAKER_1:  Who is he?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, he was one of the... This is Ali Khamenei.
SPEAKER_0:  I told her.
SPEAKER_0:  Ayatollah Ali Khamenei. Imam one day perhaps? No, well, they hesitated to use the term Imam for him.
SPEAKER_0:  But in any other respect, he was given all of that adulation. Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  that they did to Khomeini. He is the guardian jurist.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what's important.
SPEAKER_0:  because the guardian jurist in the constitution of the Islamic Republic.
SPEAKER_0:  is an authority that is above the state.
SPEAKER_0:  He is not.
SPEAKER_0:  Elected.
SPEAKER_0:  quote unquote because
SPEAKER_0:  This is a...
SPEAKER_0:  divine authority.
SPEAKER_0:  although he has been designated by the group of deterrent.
SPEAKER_0:  more less like himself.
SPEAKER_0:  And Russian Fire Italian FunSome
SPEAKER_0:  He has the full power over all.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, ehh...
SPEAKER_0:  institutions of the state.
SPEAKER_0:  The army.
SPEAKER_0:  The, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Media.
SPEAKER_0:  the economy.
SPEAKER_0:  every aspect of the acts that you show.
SPEAKER_0:  He acts like this authoritarian authority. Did that gradually develop?
SPEAKER_1:  or was that very early on? well
SPEAKER_0:  That's part of the constitution of the Islamic Republic.
SPEAKER_0:  The first constitution
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  the first draft of the Constitution.
SPEAKER_0:  did not have the authority.
SPEAKER_0:  of the guardian juries. But then it was added.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  How many anti-supporters?
SPEAKER_1:  Is there actual in the constitution any limits to his power?
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a council of the experts, so to say.
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  would
SPEAKER_0:  would remove him from power, I think theoretically.
SPEAKER_0:  What's that?
SPEAKER_0:  There is so much.
SPEAKER_0:  restrictions to that that I don't think it would have ever happened in reality in this case at least but in terms
SPEAKER_1:  of executive to make decisions and all that kind of stuff. Does he need to check with anybody?
SPEAKER_0:  He does check.
SPEAKER_0:  He's done.
SPEAKER_0:  advisors, but he's, he doesn't have any.
SPEAKER_0:  He doesn't have any constitutional...
SPEAKER_0:  obligation to check.
SPEAKER_0:  on the decisions that he's making.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the supreme leader, but there's been.
SPEAKER_0:  Presidents.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  And what's the role of the president? The president in a sense is the executive power.
SPEAKER_0:  under
SPEAKER_0:  the Islamic Republic.
SPEAKER_0:  Death.
SPEAKER_0:  Three heads of-
SPEAKER_0:  powers.
SPEAKER_0:  This is it.
SPEAKER_0:  President.
SPEAKER_0:  that presumably has the executive power.
SPEAKER_0:  There is the head of the...
SPEAKER_0:  Judiciary.
SPEAKER_0:  and there is the...
SPEAKER_0:  ahead of the...
SPEAKER_0:  the Speaker of the Parliament.
SPEAKER_0:  Much less.
SPEAKER_0:  Islamic by the way.
SPEAKER_0:  which is the...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  the legislative. Comp pole tries De»
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  and executive.
SPEAKER_0:  that he see who is not the president.
SPEAKER_0:  is the-
SPEAKER_0:  head of the executive.
SPEAKER_0:  Above them.
SPEAKER_0:  is the supreme leader.
SPEAKER_0:  or the guardian jurist.
SPEAKER_0:  Cue.
SPEAKER_1:  Give me some insight because I...
SPEAKER_1:  especially
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not exactly sure why, but, uh, the president, uh, Madinah John.
SPEAKER_1:  this.
SPEAKER_1:  somebody I'm
SPEAKER_1:  Is an American really familiar with why is that exactly?
SPEAKER_1:  Why was?
SPEAKER_1:  Why was the president the public-facing person?
SPEAKER_1:  to the world versus the supreme leader.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that just an accident of a particular human's involved or is this by design?
SPEAKER_0:  because the Supreme Leader tries to keep himself out of.
SPEAKER_0:  issues of everyday politics supposedly.
SPEAKER_0:  but therefore he is not coming to the United Nations.
SPEAKER_0:  to give a speech during the.
SPEAKER_0:  session.
SPEAKER_0:  But
SPEAKER_0:  Mr. Ahmadinej Jatoo at the time was the president.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Wood.
SPEAKER_0:  come and make outrageous statements.
SPEAKER_0:  That's why you probably know something about it. So all of them make-
SPEAKER_1:  public statements but yet a pr-
SPEAKER_0:  Clivity for outrageous things
SPEAKER_0:  She does!
SPEAKER_0:  all kinds of things, it makes all kinds of statements.
SPEAKER_0:  But he is.
SPEAKER_0:  somewhat above the everyday politics in theory.
SPEAKER_0:  But of course he's...
SPEAKER_0:  Fully gold strings.
SPEAKER_0:  without doubt in every respect.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It seems that
SPEAKER_0:  You were asked, I thought you were going to ask me this question.
SPEAKER_0:  almost without.
SPEAKER_0:  an exception.
SPEAKER_0:  since the inception of the Islamic Republic in 1979.
SPEAKER_0:  up to the last of the presidents of the Islamic Republic, Rouhani.
SPEAKER_0:  before the
SPEAKER_0:  guy that is.
SPEAKER_0:  last year or a year and a half ago.
SPEAKER_0:  was in a four-year lecture.
SPEAKER_0:  Alright.
SPEAKER_0:  got into the position of the president.
SPEAKER_0:  All of them.
SPEAKER_0:  in the long list.
SPEAKER_0:  All of them eventually fell.
SPEAKER_0:  uh art
SPEAKER_0:  with the regime.
SPEAKER_0:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  So there is no president.
SPEAKER_0:  except perhaps to some extent Rohani, but we'll wait and see what's going to happen to him.
SPEAKER_0:  But prior to him, all of them, including Ahmadinejad.
SPEAKER_0:  fell out with the regime, with the current regime in Iran. Who's ruhan?
SPEAKER_1:  He was officially president for 8-
SPEAKER_0:  years? Yeah, prior to the EC.
SPEAKER_0:  Ibrahim A.C. cars that
SPEAKER_1:  221 the your what you're saying is a phony election
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, it's a phony election. What's the interesting thing about what happened? Because the process of actually...
SPEAKER_0:  Candidacy.
SPEAKER_0:  for presidency is completely controlled.
SPEAKER_0:  YA
SPEAKER_0:  a cancer that is under the control of the...
SPEAKER_0:  a supreme leader.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  They have to.
SPEAKER_0:  Approve!
SPEAKER_0:  Who is going to be the candidate?
SPEAKER_0:  So not everybody can enter and say, I would like to be a candidate.
SPEAKER_1:  So did Rohani fall out of favor?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, he is.
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of out of favor now.
SPEAKER_0:  because he was more moderate than this most recent regime.
SPEAKER_0:  But the point is that...
SPEAKER_0:  If you look, this is something.
SPEAKER_0:  Almost.
SPEAKER_0:  institution...
SPEAKER_0:  constitutional to the regime.
SPEAKER_0:  This is a regime that rejects all of the executive powers.
SPEAKER_0:  Because it's...
SPEAKER_0:  because the division between the
SPEAKER_0:  Supreme Authority.
SPEAKER_0:  as the place of his supreme authority.
SPEAKER_0:  versus the presidency.
SPEAKER_0:  has
SPEAKER_0:  problematic.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  It is as if there would be a...
SPEAKER_0:  a supreme
SPEAKER_0:  leader in the United States above all these three.
SPEAKER_0:  sources of power.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the kind of an e-
SPEAKER_0:  view that we can see in today's era.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course he is at the...
SPEAKER_0:  Focus.
SPEAKER_0:  of all the criticism that he receives.
SPEAKER_0:  from the
SPEAKER_0:  demonstrators in today's...
SPEAKER_0:  Eat on.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  On top of all this.
SPEAKER_1:  Recently and throughout the last several years US and Iran
SPEAKER_1:  are in the midst of nuclear deal negotiations.
SPEAKER_1:  This is another part.
SPEAKER_1:  of the story of Iran.
SPEAKER_1:  is the development of nuclear weapons.
SPEAKER_1:  nuclear program.
SPEAKER_1:  They're looking to restore the nuclear deal known as the Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action, JCPOA.
SPEAKER_0:  day.
SPEAKER_1:  What is the history?
SPEAKER_1:  the present.
SPEAKER_1:  and the future of these negotiations over nuclear weapons.
SPEAKER_1:  What is interesting to you in this?
SPEAKER_1:  full context from the 16th century of the messianic.
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, journey.
SPEAKER_1:  out
SPEAKER_0:  What's interesting to you here?
SPEAKER_0:  You can argue.
SPEAKER_0:  That's it.
SPEAKER_0:  for a long time even under the shaw.
SPEAKER_0:  but much more.
SPEAKER_0:  expressively.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  decisively under the Islamic Republic. That was it.
SPEAKER_0:  determination to...
SPEAKER_0:  Have a...
SPEAKER_0:  Nuclear.
SPEAKER_0:  Power.
SPEAKER_0:  nuclear weapon.
SPEAKER_0:  In a sense.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the bottom line of...
SPEAKER_0:  all the negotiations, everything else is that Iran...
SPEAKER_0:  of the Islamic Republic had the tendency of...
SPEAKER_0:  having its own nuclear weapon.
SPEAKER_0:  Reason for that.
SPEAKER_0:  is that Iran was subject of.
SPEAKER_0:  nearly nine years, eight and a half years of...
SPEAKER_0:  Iran-Iraq war.
SPEAKER_0:  then
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  not only run face.
SPEAKER_0:  an aggressor Iraq that actually attacked
SPEAKER_0:  Iran at a very critical time at the very beginning of the Iranian Revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  But the fact that...
SPEAKER_0:  Iran felt kind of it.
SPEAKER_0:  a helpless.
SPEAKER_0:  in the course of this war.
SPEAKER_0:  and has to make great sacrifices actually, which supported the Islamic regime.
SPEAKER_0:  consolidated.
SPEAKER_0:  Islamic regime.
SPEAKER_0:  because of this war.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  most of the time.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh
SPEAKER_0:  There.
SPEAKER_0:  support of the United States was behind.
SPEAKER_0:  Iraq v. Iran
SPEAKER_0:  and Iran felt that it's been.
SPEAKER_0:  isolated and has to...
SPEAKER_0:  protect itself.
SPEAKER_0:  So there is some argument.
SPEAKER_0:  for.
SPEAKER_0:  having nuclear capabilities.
SPEAKER_0:  But in reality...
SPEAKER_0:  This has resulted in a completely mindless
SPEAKER_0:  Crazy.
SPEAKER_0:  Wasteful.
SPEAKER_0:  attempt on the side of the Iranian
SPEAKER_0:  Regime.
SPEAKER_0:  to try to develop a nuclear power.
SPEAKER_0:  and therefore the rest of the world, particularly in this region,
SPEAKER_0:  They're very worried.
SPEAKER_0:  that if Iran would get access.
SPEAKER_0:  a nuclear weapon.
SPEAKER_0:  then the entire region of the Persian Gulf.
SPEAKER_0:  might
SPEAKER_0:  particularly Saudi Arabia, possibly Turkey.
SPEAKER_0:  possibly Egypt, all of them may require.
SPEAKER_0:  may demand to have also nuclear weapons, given the fact that Pakistan...
SPEAKER_0:  and India has already have it.
SPEAKER_0:  So there was a determined attempt, as you might know.
SPEAKER_0:  on the side of the Western communities or now gradually world communities to try to...
SPEAKER_0:  as much as possible to control Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  from getting access.
SPEAKER_0:  to a nuclear capability.
SPEAKER_0:  or actually limit Iran's nuclear capabilities.
SPEAKER_0:  to what was defined usually.
SPEAKER_0:  in a euphemism as a
SPEAKER_0:  peaceful fashion.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  That being said...
SPEAKER_0:  There was also Israel.
SPEAKER_0:  which viewed the Islamic Republic as a...
SPEAKER_0:  Arch Enemy.
SPEAKER_0:  And some of it might be due to the Israelis own.
SPEAKER_0:  exaggeration
SPEAKER_0:  off
SPEAKER_0:  Iran's
SPEAKER_0:  threat.
SPEAKER_0:  And some of it is because Iran has developed.
SPEAKER_0:  a fairly strong military.
SPEAKER_0:  as we see today.
SPEAKER_0:  and as such
SPEAKER_0:  this attempt to try to
SPEAKER_0:  prevent E-DARN.
SPEAKER_0:  from ever getting access to them.
SPEAKER_0:  nuclear.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  with it.
SPEAKER_0:  which resulted as you might know in this massive.
SPEAKER_0:  sanctions that were imposed upon Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  ever since the beginning of the revolution in 1979.
SPEAKER_0:  and of course more intensively.
SPEAKER_0:  since 2015, 2016.
SPEAKER_0:  Even prior to that, probably a little bit earlier.
SPEAKER_0:  This agreement, the nuclear agreement was supposed to...
SPEAKER_0:  control or monitor.
SPEAKER_0:  Iranian Nuclear Industry
SPEAKER_0:  or nuclear.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  set up.
SPEAKER_0:  in exchange for removing the sanctions.
SPEAKER_0:  But this never worked, as a matter of fact, in a very successful...
SPEAKER_0:  Satisfactory.
SPEAKER_0:  a way for the Iranians or for the Americans.
SPEAKER_0:  particularly under
SPEAKER_0:  Trump administration, which I think foolishly.
SPEAKER_0:  decided to scrap.
SPEAKER_0:  day.
SPEAKER_0:  agreement that was reached under President Obama.
SPEAKER_0:  Like many other.
SPEAKER_0:  policies that was implemented under
SPEAKER_0:  Trump administration.
SPEAKER_0:  This created a major problem.
SPEAKER_0:  that is hard to...
SPEAKER_0:  under Biden how to try to
SPEAKER_0:  come up with an
SPEAKER_0:  New.
SPEAKER_0:  Nuclear
SPEAKER_0:  agreement with Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  In this process,
SPEAKER_0:  Since 2016.
SPEAKER_0:  where the United States withdrew from the agreement.
SPEAKER_0:  Iran felt
SPEAKER_0:  comfortable to try to.
SPEAKER_0:  Goob.
SPEAKER_0:  and do whatever they want.
SPEAKER_0:  without any kind of monitor.
SPEAKER_0:  being monitored by the international community.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's the situation now.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  whether Iran is really
SPEAKER_0:  Sincere.
SPEAKER_0:  under the present regime.
SPEAKER_0:  to negotiate a deal.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't know that it was the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  willing to do so.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It seems that now...
SPEAKER_0:  What is happening in terms of the protests in the Iranian streets?
SPEAKER_0:  makes it even harder.
SPEAKER_0:  in
SPEAKER_0:  a public eye.
SPEAKER_0:  to try to negotiate a deal.
SPEAKER_0:  with Eron.
SPEAKER_0:  because that means in the minds of many.
SPEAKER_0:  and with some justification.
SPEAKER_0:  That's...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  If
SPEAKER_0:  the nuclear agreement would result in the removal of many of these sanctions.
SPEAKER_0:  millions.
SPEAKER_0:  billions.
SPEAKER_0:  as the result of the removal of the sanctions and
SPEAKER_0:  Iran's ability to sell it.
SPEAKER_0:  It's oil in the international market without any restrictions.
SPEAKER_0:  means
SPEAKER_0:  that the Iranian government is going to become even more.
SPEAKER_0:  powerful
SPEAKER_0:  more financially secure in order to suppress its own people.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's the agreement that goes.
SPEAKER_0:  against
SPEAKER_0:  coming to terms.
SPEAKER_0:  With, uh, with, uh,
SPEAKER_0:  Iran. But the problem is
SPEAKER_0:  that there is no...
SPEAKER_0:  clear alternative, even I'm not particularly personally favorable.
SPEAKER_0:  for this agreement to be.
SPEAKER_0:  to be ratified.
SPEAKER_0:  But the alternative is very difficult. There is no way to try to see.
SPEAKER_0:  What can be done?
SPEAKER_0:  geopolitics.
SPEAKER_1:  where every alternative is terrible.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask you...
SPEAKER_1:  about
SPEAKER_1:  one of the most complex geopolitical situations in history.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  One aspect of it is the Cold War between Iran and Israel.
SPEAKER_1:  The bigger picture of it is sometimes referred to as a.
SPEAKER_1:  Israel-Palestine conflict.
SPEAKER_1:  What are all...
SPEAKER_1:  parties.
SPEAKER_1:  nations involved.
SPEAKER_1:  What are the interests that are involved? What's the rhetoric?
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Can you?
SPEAKER_1:  understand, make the case for each side of this conflict.
SPEAKER_0:  You're opening a new can of worms that it takes.
SPEAKER_0:  another three hours.
SPEAKER_0:  conversation. Just three hours.
SPEAKER_0:  at least.
SPEAKER_0:  But what I can tell you is this.
SPEAKER_0:  Iran prior to 1979.
SPEAKER_0:  viewed itself under the shower.
SPEAKER_0:  as a kind of a...
SPEAKER_0:  if not supported by Israel.
SPEAKER_0:  was in very good terms with Israel.
SPEAKER_0:  They had an embassy in Iran, an unofficial embassy in Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  that's it in projects that...
SPEAKER_0:  helping with the agriculture and so forth in Iraq.
SPEAKER_0:  But since 1979...
SPEAKER_0:  that completely.
SPEAKER_0:  reverse.
SPEAKER_0:  Part of it is that the issue of the Palestinian...
SPEAKER_0:  fly.
SPEAKER_0:  remained very much at the heart.
SPEAKER_0:  of.
SPEAKER_0:  the revolutionary Iranians would see that.
SPEAKER_0:  part of the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  is to support.
SPEAKER_0:  part of the United States guilt.
SPEAKER_0:  SIN
SPEAKER_0:  is to support Israel.
SPEAKER_0:  vis-à-vis.
SPEAKER_0:  It's very suppressive.
SPEAKER_0:  very...
SPEAKER_0:  Oppressive.
SPEAKER_0:  treatment of the
SPEAKER_0:  Palestinians?
SPEAKER_0:  completely illegal taking over.
SPEAKER_0:  of the territories which is not theirs since 1967.
SPEAKER_0:  and therefore it is upon the Iranian regime, the Iranian Islamic Republic,
SPEAKER_0:  to support the cause of the Palestinians.
SPEAKER_0:  This came about at the time
SPEAKER_0:  When?
SPEAKER_0:  the rest of the support for the Palestinians, including Arab nationalism.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically.
SPEAKER_0:  reach this stage of bankruptcy.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, much of the regimes of the Arab world either are now coming to terms with Israel.
SPEAKER_0:  or in one way or another because of their own contingencies, because of their own.
SPEAKER_0:  concerns and interests.
SPEAKER_0:  R
SPEAKER_0:  really nearly accepting.
SPEAKER_0:  Israel in the
SPEAKER_0:  in the region.
SPEAKER_0:  Now, that old husk of...
SPEAKER_0:  rhetorically supporting the Palestinians.
SPEAKER_0:  for the Islamic Republic.
SPEAKER_0:  that sees itself as the champion of the Palestinians now.
SPEAKER_0:  We thought as a matter of fact.
SPEAKER_0:  having either the support of the Iranian people behind him. If you ask.
SPEAKER_0:  Tomorrow there would be...
SPEAKER_0:  A pole or a-
SPEAKER_0:  referendum.
SPEAKER_0:  I would doubt that.
SPEAKER_0:  80% of the Iranian people would approve of the policies.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Islamic Republic vis-a-vis the issue of Palestine.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  nor the Palestinians themselves because they're...
SPEAKER_0:  Islamic Republic is only supporting those...
SPEAKER_0:  factions within the
SPEAKER_0:  Palestinian.
SPEAKER_0: ... movement which are Islamic, quote unquote.
SPEAKER_0:  And even within that, there is problems with Hamas.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  But nevertheless...
SPEAKER_0:  It's.
SPEAKER_0:  for the Islamic Republic some kind of a
SPEAKER_0:  propaganda tool.
SPEAKER_0:  to be able to use it for its own sake.
SPEAKER_0:  and claim that.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  We are the champions of the Palestinian people.
SPEAKER_0:  What did they have?
SPEAKER_0:  a solution.
SPEAKER_0:  If you look at the rhetoric, if you listen to the rhetoric.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the destruction of the...
SPEAKER_0:  State of Israel.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  it seems to me creates a certain anxiety in the minds of the...
SPEAKER_0:  Israelis, Israeli population, and Israeli government.
SPEAKER_0:  particularly those...
SPEAKER_0:  who are now in power.
SPEAKER_0:  not an Yahoo the liquid
SPEAKER_0:  and more kind of a right wing.
SPEAKER_0:  politics of
SPEAKER_0:  Polity of...
SPEAKER_0:  Today's Israel.
SPEAKER_0:  That being said...
SPEAKER_0:  I think also the Israelis...
SPEAKER_0:  try to
SPEAKER_0:  get an extra mileage out of.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  threat of Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  quote unquote.
SPEAKER_0:  in order to...
SPEAKER_0:  present themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  a rightful to.
SPEAKER_0:  for terms of security and whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  else.
SPEAKER_0:  the way that they're treating the Palestinians, which I think is extremely unjust.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's extremely unwise.
SPEAKER_0:  for Israel.
SPEAKER_0:  carry on with these policies as they did since 1967 at least.
SPEAKER_0:  and not to try to come to terms with it.
SPEAKER_0:  Of course, there's a huge amount of
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not denying that at all.
SPEAKER_0:  the huge amount of
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  failures.
SPEAKER_0:  Mistakes.
SPEAKER_0:  and stupidity on the side of the Palestinian leadership.
SPEAKER_0:  in various stages.
SPEAKER_0:  not to try to.
SPEAKER_0:  Make a deal.
SPEAKER_0:  or try to come to terms in some...
SPEAKER_0:  uh... fashion
SPEAKER_0:  But it's a very complex picture, and it's rather unfair to the Palestinians.
SPEAKER_0:  to accuse them.
SPEAKER_0:  For nuts.
SPEAKER_0:  coming to terms with Israel under a very...
SPEAKER_0:  on even circumstances.
SPEAKER_0:  when they are not in a position to try.
SPEAKER_0:  to make a fair deal.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of the territories.
SPEAKER_0:  or in terms of their security in future vis-a-vis Israel.
SPEAKER_1:  So I think there is, as you probably know.
SPEAKER_1:  quite a lot of people that would.
SPEAKER_1:  have a different perspective than you just stated.
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of
SPEAKER_1:  you know, taking the perspective of Israel.
SPEAKER_1:  in characterizing the situation.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you steal Man Neck at their side?
SPEAKER_1:  Can you still man Israel's side?
SPEAKER_1:  that they're
SPEAKER_1:  trying to be a sovereign nation.
SPEAKER_1:  trying to protect themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  against threats.
SPEAKER_1:  Ultimately...
SPEAKER_1:  wanting to create a place of safety, a place where people can pursue.
SPEAKER_1:  all the things that you want to pursue in life, including.
SPEAKER_1:  for most happiness.
SPEAKER_0:  I tend to agree with you.
SPEAKER_0:  and they have all the respect for the fact that...
SPEAKER_0:  Israel would like to create security and happiness for its own people.
SPEAKER_0:  But there are two arguments. One is a moral argument.
SPEAKER_0:  to my mind as a historian.
SPEAKER_0:  E-
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Jews.
SPEAKER_0:  across around the world.
SPEAKER_0:  for all through their history suffered.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is a history of suffering.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a memory of some.
SPEAKER_0:  and I find it enormously difficult to believe.
SPEAKER_0:  Detonation.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the product of so much.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  sacrifice, suffering.
SPEAKER_0:  Loss of life.
SPEAKER_0:  and variety of...
SPEAKER_0:  Holocaust.
SPEAKER_0:  Above all.
SPEAKER_0:  would be.
SPEAKER_0:  find itself in a position.
SPEAKER_0:  not to give the proper justice.
SPEAKER_0:  to a people who could be their neighbors.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  is a moral argument which I cannot believe.
SPEAKER_0:  under any circumstances can be accepted.
SPEAKER_0:  Second.
SPEAKER_0:  in real terms.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you want to, you want to commit a genocide?
SPEAKER_0:  you have a population there.
SPEAKER_0:  that you have to come to terms with it.
SPEAKER_0:  and you cannot just postpone as they did.
SPEAKER_0:  667 they are postponing and hoping that it goes away.
SPEAKER_0:  Somehow.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think it's going to.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  and it's going to...
SPEAKER_0:  get worse rather than better.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a long nuance.
SPEAKER_1:  discussion and I look forward to having it.
SPEAKER_1:  So just leave it.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  there for the moment.
SPEAKER_1:  But it is.
SPEAKER_1:  stressful place in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  where the rhetoric
SPEAKER_1:  is
SPEAKER_1:  existential.
SPEAKER_1:  We're on.
SPEAKER_1:  It makes claims that it wants to wipe.
SPEAKER_1:  a country off the face of the earth is just the level.
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  of intensity of rhetoric is unlike anywhere else in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  and extremely dangerous.
SPEAKER_0:  and in-
SPEAKER_1:  in both directions so one
SPEAKER_1:  The real danger?
SPEAKER_1:  of the rhetoric actually being acted upon.
SPEAKER_1:  and then the extreme.
SPEAKER_1:  political parties.
SPEAKER_1:  using the rhetoric.
SPEAKER_1:  to justify.
SPEAKER_1:  even a greater escalation.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  If Iran is...
SPEAKER_1:  saying that this is
SPEAKER_0:  It's...
SPEAKER_1:  saying that they want to wipe up.
SPEAKER_1:  Israel off the face of the earth.
SPEAKER_1:  that justifies any response.
SPEAKER_0:  On the other side. On the other side.
SPEAKER_0:  Of course, I tend to agree with you fully.
SPEAKER_0:  And unfortunately, this is a very critical situation that...
SPEAKER_0:  this region is facing, Iran in particular.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say that...
SPEAKER_0:  I hope that in the minds of the...
SPEAKER_0:  people of Israel.
SPEAKER_0:  There is.
SPEAKER_0:  Eyyy
SPEAKER_0:  Enough.
SPEAKER_0:  or
SPEAKER_0:  common sense to realize that.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably escalation on the Israeli side is not in the favor of anybody.
SPEAKER_0:  try to
SPEAKER_0:  Let the Iranians to go on with their...
SPEAKER_0:  Empty rhetoric.
SPEAKER_0:  as they do.
SPEAKER_0:  so far.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  at the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  I cannot deny the fact that
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a danger on the side of this regime.
SPEAKER_0:  and what it says.
SPEAKER_0:  It cannot be denied. Nobody can justify that.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  particularly because the Iranian population is not behind this.
SPEAKER_0:  Regime.
SPEAKER_0:  certainly in the case of the Palestinians.
SPEAKER_0:  or for that matter it's not Palestine.
SPEAKER_0:  is the...
SPEAKER_0:  the Islamic Republic's involvement in Lebanon with Hezbollah.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the Islamic Republic's.
SPEAKER_0:  involvement in Syria with Bashar Assad.
SPEAKER_0:  its involvement in other parts of the world, perhaps even Yemen.
SPEAKER_0:  that all of them creates extra-territorial
SPEAKER_0:  responsibilities or interventions.
SPEAKER_0:  unnecessary interventions.
SPEAKER_0:  that ultimately is not in favor of.
SPEAKER_0:  best.
SPEAKER_0:  interests of the Iranian people.
SPEAKER_0:  or Iran as a country.
SPEAKER_0:  Iran has never been involved in this kind of politics before.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Islamic Republic.
SPEAKER_0:  So in this sense.
SPEAKER_0:  The Iranian regime, it seems to me...
SPEAKER_0:  by going to the extreme try to create for itself.
SPEAKER_0:  Aye-Yap.
SPEAKER_0:  Peace.
SPEAKER_0:  that it did not have or did not deserve to have.
SPEAKER_0:  within the politics of the region. It says okay.
SPEAKER_0:  in other words
SPEAKER_0:  that has become part of the
SPEAKER_0:  Cool.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of an instrument.
SPEAKER_0:  for if you like to call it some kind of an expansionism.
SPEAKER_0:  of the regime.
SPEAKER_0:  in parts of the world where it can see.
SPEAKER_0:  there is a possibility.
SPEAKER_0:  Poor.
SPEAKER_0:  its presence for its expansion.
SPEAKER_0:  Of course
SPEAKER_0:  Historically speaking.
SPEAKER_0:  Iran
SPEAKER_0:  ever since the 15th century.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's the earliest example I can see.
SPEAKER_0:  in early modern times.
SPEAKER_0:  has always a tendency of moving in the direction.
SPEAKER_0:  of not only what is today the
SPEAKER_0:  in the state of Iraq.
SPEAKER_0:  but further into the eastern coast of Mediterranean.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's a long term ambition.
SPEAKER_0:  that has been in the
SPEAKER_0:  cards as far as.
SPEAKER_0:  Iran as a strategic unit is concerned.
SPEAKER_0:  What?
SPEAKER_0:  by no means justified and by no means
SPEAKER_0:  could be a reasonable...
SPEAKER_0:  could be a sane policy of a...
SPEAKER_0:  nation.
SPEAKER_0:  State as today's Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  What?
SPEAKER_0:  The second point is that.
SPEAKER_0:  Also,
SPEAKER_0:  Regimes are always victims of their own rhetoric.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's.
SPEAKER_0:  Once you...
SPEAKER_0:  Keep.
SPEAKER_0:  repeating something.
SPEAKER_0:  then you become more and more committed to it.
SPEAKER_0:  and it cannot remain anymore in the level of a rhetoric. You have to do something about it.
SPEAKER_0:  See you soon.
SPEAKER_0:  some compelling pressure.
SPEAKER_0:  to try to...
SPEAKER_0:  to materialize.
SPEAKER_0:  what you've been saying in your rhetoric.
SPEAKER_0:  and that is even extremely more dangerous.
SPEAKER_0:  as far as Iran is concerned.
SPEAKER_0:  and it brings it to some unholy alliances.
SPEAKER_0:  that today we are witnessing.
SPEAKER_0:  Iran is getting involved. Even more dangerous.
SPEAKER_0:  than this rhetoric.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of the
SPEAKER_0:  vis-à-vis Israel.
SPEAKER_0:  is its involvement with Russia and to some extent with China.
SPEAKER_0:  which we can talk about.
SPEAKER_1:  about the meeting.
SPEAKER_1:  between Harmony and Vladimir Putin in July.
SPEAKER_1:  What's that alliance? What's that partnership?
SPEAKER_1:  Is it surface level geopolitics? Is there a deep growing connection?
SPEAKER_0:  I cannot see the difference between geopolitics and these deep connections. I see this one and the same.
SPEAKER_0:  Why?
SPEAKER_0:  because I think the experience...
SPEAKER_0:  of 40 years of...
SPEAKER_0:  distancing from the West.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of the Islamic Republic.
SPEAKER_0:  and the fact that there is a...
SPEAKER_0:  self-life to imperial.
SPEAKER_0:  presence.
SPEAKER_0:  for any empire anywhere in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  after the terrible experience of...
SPEAKER_0:  of the United States in
SPEAKER_0:  uh, E-Doc.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  in.
SPEAKER_0:  AFRANISTAN
SPEAKER_0:  pretty much like the British Empire.
SPEAKER_0:  that after the Suez experience in 56.
SPEAKER_0:  decided to withdraw from
SPEAKER_0:  East of Suez.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe there is a moment here that we are witnessing.
SPEAKER_0:  or it may come.
SPEAKER_0:  that a great power like the United States sees in its benefit.
SPEAKER_0:  not to get too much involved into nitty-gritty things.
SPEAKER_0:  in other parts of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  that it's not its immediate concept.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think that's.
SPEAKER_0:  Part of the reason, not the entire reason.
SPEAKER_0:  Part of the reason why we see the emergence of a new
SPEAKER_0:  geopolitical.
SPEAKER_0:  environment.
SPEAKER_0:  in this part of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  of which China
SPEAKER_0:  Russia?
SPEAKER_0:  possibly Iran, possibly Turkey.
SPEAKER_0:  Possibly both of them.
SPEAKER_0:  are going to be part.
SPEAKER_0:  Perhaps Saudis also.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  I-
SPEAKER_0:  Dota the Saudis.
SPEAKER_0:  under the present circumstances, although we've witnessed.
SPEAKER_0:  some remarkable issue.
SPEAKER_0:  course of the past few weeks.
SPEAKER_0:  Where the Saudis?
SPEAKER_0:  giving assurances to.
SPEAKER_0:  American administration and then shifting.
SPEAKER_0:  and getting along with.
SPEAKER_0:  put in.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of the oil production, I think it's more than.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's not only them.
SPEAKER_0:  but also the Emirates are doing the same thing.
SPEAKER_0:  So what does that tell us? And that's another-
SPEAKER_1:  Many our conversation about the world industry in Iran and the.
SPEAKER_0:  the whole region in emerging.
SPEAKER_0:  this kind of a world.
SPEAKER_0:  which was perhaps even 10 years ago unimaginable.
SPEAKER_0:  that you see now a great power.
SPEAKER_0:  China
SPEAKER_0:  That's it.
SPEAKER_0:  going to remain.
SPEAKER_0:  from what we see around us.
SPEAKER_0:  as a great power.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Russia
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, adventurous?
SPEAKER_0:  Foolish.
SPEAKER_0:  but nevertheless would remain.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  Criminal, I would say, as far as the...
SPEAKER_0:  It's.
SPEAKER_0:  behavior in
SPEAKER_0:  Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  But actually...
SPEAKER_0:  It's a rogue nation that attracts another rogue nation.
SPEAKER_0:  So, Eid on.
SPEAKER_0:  finds itself.
SPEAKER_0:  No!
SPEAKER_0:  in a greater place of security.
SPEAKER_0:  in alliance with Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  in the hope
SPEAKER_0:  that this would give.
SPEAKER_0:  Eat on.
SPEAKER_0:  a greater security in this part of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  whether this is...
SPEAKER_0:  realistic or illusion.
SPEAKER_0:  I think remains to be seen. I think Iran-China relation makes more sense.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Although, if you ask ordinary Iranians, they don't like it.
SPEAKER_0:  They would tell, why should we be?
SPEAKER_0:  Hide up.
SPEAKER_0:  with.
SPEAKER_0:  with China.
SPEAKER_0:  as the only
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  straight party with America because of the IT.
SPEAKER_0:  foolish isolations that you have created for us.
SPEAKER_0:  because of all the sanctions that you have created for us.
SPEAKER_0:  Islamic Republic.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  In a sense, it's a very difficult question.
SPEAKER_0:  to answer, probably Iranians also like to be more at the other camp.
SPEAKER_0:  But what happens is that in real term.
SPEAKER_0:  What surprises me most?
SPEAKER_0:  is not this other is.
SPEAKER_0:  China but it's
SPEAKER_0:  kind of becoming.
SPEAKER_0:  a lucky or...
SPEAKER_0:  subservient.
SPEAKER_0:  to Putin's regime.
SPEAKER_0:  in Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  since if you look at it.
SPEAKER_0:  Iran
SPEAKER_0:  ever since at least the 19th century, not going further back.
SPEAKER_0:  The beginning of the 19th century.
SPEAKER_0:  always viewed Russia as the greatest threat.
SPEAKER_0:  strategically.
SPEAKER_0:  because it was sitting right at the top of Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  was.
SPEAKER_0:  It was...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  infinitely more powerful than Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  has ever been.
SPEAKER_0:  and it runs for two
SPEAKER_0:  rounds of war at the beginning of the century.
SPEAKER_0:  Lost the entire Caucasus.
SPEAKER_0:  To Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  and learned its lesson.
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to be mindful of Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  and you have to keep it as an arm's length.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's what was Iran's policy throughout the...
SPEAKER_0:  course of the 20th century.
SPEAKER_0:  19th and 20th century.
SPEAKER_0:  up to what we see now.
SPEAKER_0:  around us.
SPEAKER_0:  which is a very strange situation.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  What?
SPEAKER_0:  Weather
SPEAKER_0:  Balance has changed.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of
SPEAKER_0:  If this...
SPEAKER_0:  if Russia is purchasing weapons from...
SPEAKER_0:  from Iran, which was unheard of.
SPEAKER_0:  and means that there is a...
SPEAKER_0:  new
SPEAKER_0:  Balance is emerging, a new relationship is emerging.
SPEAKER_0:  perhaps remains to be seen.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  If you look at the historical precedence.
SPEAKER_0:  it would have been enormously
SPEAKER_0:  on voice.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  be an ally of.
SPEAKER_0:  Russia given its long history of aggression in Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  Russians
SPEAKER_0:  Part of the reason why it's actually Iran
SPEAKER_0:  allied itself with the British Empire.
SPEAKER_0:  was the fact that it was so much afraid of the...
SPEAKER_0:  Russian Expansion.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  As such.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know what's going to be the future of this relationship.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a big.
SPEAKER_1:  big disconnect between governments and the people. And I think ultimately,
SPEAKER_1:  I have faith that there's a love across the different cultures, across the different religions.
SPEAKER_1:  amongst the people.
SPEAKER_1:  and the governments are the source of the division and the conflict and the wars and all the geopolitics.
SPEAKER_1:  that is in part grounded in the battle for resources and all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  Nevertheless, this is the world we live in.
SPEAKER_1:  So you looked at the modern history of Iran.
SPEAKER_1:  the past few centuries.
SPEAKER_1:  if you look into the future of this region.
SPEAKER_1:  Now you kind of implied that a historian...
SPEAKER_1:  has a bit of a cynical.
SPEAKER_1:  view.
SPEAKER_1:  of protests and things like this.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  that are fueled, at least in the minds of young people, with hope.
SPEAKER_1:  if you were to just for a while.
SPEAKER_1:  Have a bit of hope in your heart and your mind.
SPEAKER_1:  What is a hopeful future for the next 10, 20, 30 years of a...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not cynical.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm trying to be realistic.
SPEAKER_0:  And I actually may be critical, but I have great hopes.
SPEAKER_0:  in
SPEAKER_0:  Iran's future for a variety of reasons.
SPEAKER_0:  I actually did write an article only if...
SPEAKER_0:  The last version of it is going to go out today.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  in which the title of it is the...
SPEAKER_0:  time of fear and women of hope.
SPEAKER_0:  which in a sense is this whole
SPEAKER_0:  coverage but.
SPEAKER_0:  What this?
SPEAKER_0:  movement means.
SPEAKER_0:  that we see today.
SPEAKER_0:  Keep in May Fizzle.
SPEAKER_0:  in a few weeks time.
SPEAKER_0:  or it may just go on and create a new...
SPEAKER_0:  dynamics in Iranian society.
SPEAKER_0:  that would hopefully.
SPEAKER_0:  Results.
SPEAKER_0:  in a
SPEAKER_0:  peaceful process of greater
SPEAKER_0:  accommodation and the greater tolerance.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh
SPEAKER_0:  within the Iranian society and with the outside world.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think the majority of the Iranian people...
SPEAKER_0:  Don't want tension.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't fund confrontation.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't want.
SPEAKER_0:  crisis.
SPEAKER_0:  day if
SPEAKER_0:  40 years they have suffered.
SPEAKER_0:  from.
SPEAKER_0:  a regime that have dictated an ideology that it's...
SPEAKER_0:  regressive.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  impractical.
SPEAKER_0:  They want to go back to a life.
SPEAKER_0:  in which they don't.
SPEAKER_0:  they don't really create trouble for their neighbors or for the world.
SPEAKER_0:  And therefore
SPEAKER_0:  I would see if.
SPEAKER_0:  Better future for you.
SPEAKER_0:  That's for-
SPEAKER_0:  One reason.
SPEAKER_0:  strategically.
SPEAKER_0:  or geopolitically, maybe in Iran's...
SPEAKER_0:  advantage in a peaceful fashion.
SPEAKER_0:  negotiate.
SPEAKER_0:  as it's the fate of all the nations.
SPEAKER_0:  rather than
SPEAKER_0:  commit itself.
SPEAKER_0:  or
SPEAKER_0:  sworn to a particular
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Poor stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  policy.
SPEAKER_0:  So, this give and take as the nature of politics is art of possible.
SPEAKER_0:  as it been said.
SPEAKER_0:  So probably Iran is going to be hopefully move in that direction.
SPEAKER_0:  I think there is a generational thing. That's the third reason.
SPEAKER_0:  no matter how much
SPEAKER_0:  Islamic Republic.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  to Islamize the Iranian society in its own image.
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  kind of radical.
SPEAKER_0:  ideological indoctrination.
SPEAKER_0:  It has failed.
SPEAKER_0:  It has failed up.
SPEAKER_0:  to...
SPEAKER_0:  what we see today in the Iranian streets.
SPEAKER_0:  and the Iranian population said no to it.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think...
SPEAKER_0:  if there would have been and there very much hope there will be.
SPEAKER_0:  a possibility for a...
SPEAKER_0:  more open environment more open
SPEAKER_0:  space where they would be able to speak them.
SPEAKER_0:  their views out.
SPEAKER_0:  Iranians are not on this side of
SPEAKER_0:  moving in the
SPEAKER_0:  extreme directions.
SPEAKER_0:  We are in the side of greater...
SPEAKER_0:  Accommodation.
SPEAKER_0:  and the greater interest in the outside world.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  if you look at every aspect of today's beside the government.
SPEAKER_0:  every aspect of life in today's Iran, we can see that.
SPEAKER_0:  from the.
SPEAKER_0:  way that people dress.
SPEAKER_0:  to the way that they try to live their lives.
SPEAKER_0:  to the way that they're educating themselves or being educated in the institutions.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you see a desire, an intention?
SPEAKER_0:  to move forward. And I'm optimistic.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, in that s-
SPEAKER_1:  Struggle for freedom.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I told you offline.
SPEAKER_1:  One of my close childhood friends is Iranian.
SPEAKER_1:  Just a beautiful person, his family is a wonderful family. On a personal level is.
SPEAKER_1:  one of them.
SPEAKER_1:  deeper windows into the Iranian spirit and soul that I've gotten a chance to witness. I really appreciate it.
SPEAKER_1:  but in the recent times I've gotten to hear from a lot of people.
SPEAKER_1:  that are currently living in Iran, that are currently.
SPEAKER_1:  have that burning hope for the future of the country.
SPEAKER_1:  My love goes out to them in this struggle for free
SPEAKER_0:  That's so nice of you to say so.
SPEAKER_0:  and they very much hope so.
SPEAKER_0:  There are moments of despair.
SPEAKER_0:  and there are moments that you would think that...
SPEAKER_0:  There is no hope.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  but.
SPEAKER_0:  but then again something
SPEAKER_0:  triggers and you see...
SPEAKER_0:  hundred thousand people in the streets of
SPEAKER_0:  Berlin
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  that are hoping for a better future for Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  and I very much hope it eventually emerges even
SPEAKER_0:  I'm hoping at the same time there is not going to be a...
SPEAKER_0:  very strong leadership.
SPEAKER_0:  as it was the case in the past.
SPEAKER_0:  We started with hope.
SPEAKER_1:  We ended with hope.
SPEAKER_1:  This was a real honor. This is an incredible conversation. Thank you for.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for giving such a deep.
SPEAKER_1:  and wide.
SPEAKER_1:  story of this great nation, one of the great nations in history.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, that's kind of what you should say. Thank you for sitting.
SPEAKER_1:  down to date.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, a history that's...
SPEAKER_0:  as I've said in the start of my book.
SPEAKER_0:  I say it's the history of a nation which has learned a huge amount from...
SPEAKER_0:  from the outside world by force of...
SPEAKER_0:  It's geography.
SPEAKER_0:  It was always located somewhere that people would invade. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  or come for trade or...
SPEAKER_0:  something happened to it that is diffused culture.
SPEAKER_0:  continue to...
SPEAKER_0:  and they were not afraid of learning or adopting.
SPEAKER_0:  as they do right now today.
SPEAKER_0:  This is a very different society.
SPEAKER_1:  Never a boring moment in its history as you write about.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you so much. This is all. Thank you.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with Abba Samana.
SPEAKER_1:  Support this podcast. Please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now, let me leave you.
SPEAKER_1:  with a few words from Martin Luther King Jr.
SPEAKER_1:  from every mountainside.
SPEAKER_1:  Let freedom ring.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for listening.
SPEAKER_1:  and hope to see you.
SPEAKER_1:  next time.