SPEAKER_0:  We've got to have strategic empathy about Putin as well. We've got to understand how the guy thinks and why he thinks like he does.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, he has got his own context and his own frame.
SPEAKER_0:  and his own rationale.
SPEAKER_0:  And he is rational, he is a rational actor.
SPEAKER_0:  in his own context, we've got to understand that. We've got to understand that he would take offense as something he would take action over something.
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't mean to say that.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, we are.
SPEAKER_0:  necessary to blame by taking actions, but we are to blame when we don't understand the consequences of things that we do.
SPEAKER_0:  and act accordingly.
SPEAKER_0:  or take preventative action or recognize that something might happen as a result of something.
SPEAKER_1:  What is the probability that Russia attacks Ukraine with a tactical nuclear weapon?
SPEAKER_1:  The following is a conversation with Fiona Hill.
SPEAKER_1:  presidential advisor and foreign policy expert specializing in Russia.
SPEAKER_1:  She has served.
SPEAKER_1:  the Bush, Obama and Trump administrations, including being a top advisor on Russia to Donald Trump.
SPEAKER_1:  She has made it to the White House.
SPEAKER_1:  from humble beginnings in the North of England.
SPEAKER_1:  story.
SPEAKER_1:  She tells in her book.
SPEAKER_1:  There's nothing for you here.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the Lex Friedman podcast. Thanks for watching.
SPEAKER_1:  Please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now...
SPEAKER_1:  Dear friends.
SPEAKER_1:  Here's Fiona.
SPEAKER_1:  Hill.
SPEAKER_1:  You came from humble beginning.
SPEAKER_1:  in a coal mining town in Northeast England.
SPEAKER_1:  So what were some formative moments in your young life?
SPEAKER_1:  that made you the...
SPEAKER_0:  woman you are today.
SPEAKER_0:  I was born in 1965.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was the period where...
SPEAKER_0:  the whole coal sector in Britain was in decline already.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  unabasically.
SPEAKER_0:  My father, by the time I came along, had lost his job multiple times. Every coal mine he worked in was closing down.
SPEAKER_0:  was looking constantly for the work and he had no qualifications because at age 14 he'd gone down the mines.
SPEAKER_0:  His father had gone down the mines at 13, his great grandfather around the same kind of age.
SPEAKER_0:  people at different points going down coal mines at 12, 13, 14, they didn't get educated.
SPEAKER_0:  beyond that period because the expectation was, are you gonna go down the mine like everybody else in your family?
SPEAKER_0:  And then he didn't really have any other qualifications.
SPEAKER_0:  too.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, basically find.
SPEAKER_0:  another job beyond something in manual labor. So I worked in a.
SPEAKER_0:  steelworks, that didn't work out, a brickworks that closed down, and then he went to work in the local hospital.
SPEAKER_0:  of the National Health Service in the United Kingdom as a porter, an orderly, physically somebody's just pushing people around.
SPEAKER_0:  There was no opportunity to retrain.
SPEAKER_0:  So the big issue in my family was education.
SPEAKER_0:  You've gotta have one.
SPEAKER_0:  and you've got to have some qualifications.
SPEAKER_0:  The world is changing, it's changing really quickly.
SPEAKER_0:  And for you to kind of keep up with it, you're going to have to.
SPEAKER_0:  Get educated.
SPEAKER_0:  and find a way out of this.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm very early on, my father had basically said to me.
SPEAKER_0:  There's nothing for you here.
SPEAKER_0:  you're going to have to, if you want to get ahead.
SPEAKER_0:  And he didn't have any kind of idea that as a girl I wouldn't. I mean, actually, in many respects, I think I benefited from being a girl rather than a boy. There was no expectation that I would go into industry.
SPEAKER_0:  There was some kind of idea that maybe if I got qualifications, I could be a nurse. My mother was a midwife.
SPEAKER_0:  And so she'd at age 16 left school and gone to train.
SPEAKER_0:  as a nurse and then as a midwife.
SPEAKER_0:  I had other relatives who'd gone to teach in local schools.
SPEAKER_0:  And so there was an idea that women could get educated.
SPEAKER_0:  and there was a kind of a range of things that you could do.
SPEAKER_0:  Well the expectation then was...
SPEAKER_0:  Go out there.
SPEAKER_0:  Do something with your life.
SPEAKER_0:  but also a sense that you'd probably have to leave. So all the thought was-
SPEAKER_0:  circling around me, particularly in my teenage years, as I was trying to find my way through.
SPEAKER_0:  life and.
SPEAKER_0:  Looking forward.
SPEAKER_1:  First of all, what does that even look like?
SPEAKER_1:  getting educated, given the context of that place, you don't know, there's a whole world of mystery out there.
SPEAKER_1:  So how do you figure out what to actually do out there?
SPEAKER_1:  Poster moments.
SPEAKER_1:  formative moments either challenging or just inspiring.
SPEAKER_1:  where you wondered about what you wanna be.
SPEAKER_0:  where you wanna go. Yeah, I mean, there are a number of things. I mean, I think like a lot of kids, you know, you talk to people, and particularly from blue collar backgrounds, so what did you wanna do? Boys might say I wanted to be a fireman.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, all you got, you know, kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  At one point, as a little girl, I wanted to be a nurse in a little nurse's uniform like my mother. I didn't really know what that meant, but I used to go around pretending to be a nurse. I even had a little magazine called Nurse Nancy, and I used to read this.
SPEAKER_0:  And you know, kind of that was one of the formative ideas. We also, it was a rural area, semi-rural area. And, you know, I'd be out in the fields all the time and I'd watch farmers.
SPEAKER_0:  with their animals and I'd see vets coming along and watching people deal with the livestock. And there was a kind of a famous story at the time.
SPEAKER_0:  about a vet called James Herriot. It became here in the United States as well and was a sort of a TV mini series. He'd written a book and he was the vet for my.
SPEAKER_0:  one of my great aunt's dogs.
SPEAKER_0:  and people were always talking about him and I thought, oh, I could be a vet.
SPEAKER_0:  And then one day I saw one of the local vets with his hand up the...
SPEAKER_0:  backside of a cow in a field and he got his hand stuck and the cow was kicking him and I thought yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe not actually, no, I don't think I want to be a vet.
SPEAKER_0:  So I cycled through all of these things about, okay, I could get an education. But the whole sense was you had to apply your education.
SPEAKER_0:  It wasn't an education for education's sake.
SPEAKER_0:  It was an education to do something.
SPEAKER_0:  And when I was about 14 or 15, my local member of parliament came to the school.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was one of these pep talks for kids in these deprived areas.
SPEAKER_0:  He had been quite prominent in local education.
SPEAKER_0:  And now he was a member of parliament. He himself had come from a really hard, scrabble background and had risen up through education. He had even gone to Oxford and done.
SPEAKER_0:  philosophy, politics and economics.
SPEAKER_0:  He basically told my class, even though it was highly unlikely any of us were really going to get ahead and go to elite institutions.
SPEAKER_0:  Look, you can get an education, you don't have to be held back by your circumstances.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you do get an education, it's a privilege and you need to do something with it.
SPEAKER_0:  So then I'm thinking...
SPEAKER_0:  what could I do? Okay, an education is a qualification, it's to do something. Most people around me I didn't.
SPEAKER_0:  I knew he didn't have careers. I mean, my dad didn't really have a career. He had jobs.
SPEAKER_0:  My mom thought of her nursing as a career though, and it genuinely was, and she was out there trying to help women.
SPEAKER_0:  survive childbirth.
SPEAKER_0:  My mother had these.
SPEAKER_0:  Horrific stories.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, basically over the dining room table, I wish she'd stop. She'd leave out her nursing books. And I tell you, if everyone had had my mum as a mother, there'd be no reproduction on the planet. It was just these grim, horrific stories of breached births and fistulas and all kinds of horrors.
SPEAKER_0:  that my sister and I would just go, oh my god, you know what, please stop.
SPEAKER_0:  So I thought, well, you know, I don't necessarily want to go in that term.
SPEAKER_0:  in that direction.
SPEAKER_0:  But it was the timing.
SPEAKER_0:  that really...
SPEAKER_0:  cinch things for me.
SPEAKER_0:  I was very lucky that the region that I grew up, County Durham, despite the massive decline, industrialization and the...
SPEAKER_0:  complete collapse of...
SPEAKER_0:  local government system around me still maintain money for education.
SPEAKER_0:  And they also paid for exchanges. We had exchange programs with.
SPEAKER_0:  up.
SPEAKER_0:  cities in Germany and France, also in Russia and Kostroma near Yaroslavl, for example, an old textile town, similar down in its region, but quite historic.
SPEAKER_0:  the Russian context, in fact, the original birthplace of the Romanov dynasty in Kostroma, just as County Durham was quite a distinguished historic area in the British context. So there was an idea that I could go on exchanges, I could learn languages, I studied German, I studied French.
SPEAKER_0:  And then in 1983...
SPEAKER_0:  there was the war scare.
SPEAKER_0:  basically provoked by the Euro missile crisis. So the stationing of new categories of strategic nuclear weapons and intermediate.
SPEAKER_0:  nuclear weapons.
SPEAKER_0:  in Western Europe.
SPEAKER_0:  and in Eastern Europe.
SPEAKER_0:  during the height of the Cold War.
SPEAKER_0:  and the zero missile crisis over SS-20 and Pershing missiles.
SPEAKER_0:  went on from 1977, so when I was about 11 or 12.
SPEAKER_0:  all the way through into the later part of the 1980s.
SPEAKER_0:  and in 1983.
SPEAKER_0:  we came extraordinarily close.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  nuclear conflict. It was very much another rerun of the Cuban Missile Crisis of 1962, 20 years on, same kind of thing.
SPEAKER_0:  the Soviets misread, although I didn't know this at the time. I know a lot of this, you know, after the fact.
SPEAKER_0:  See you next time.
SPEAKER_0:  Tension was palpable, but what happened was the Soviets misread the intentions of a series.
SPEAKER_0:  of exercises.
SPEAKER_0:  Operation Able Archer that the United States was conducting and actually thought that the United States might be preparing for a first nuclear strike.
SPEAKER_0:  and that then set up a whole set of literal chain reactions.
SPEAKER_0:  in the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  Eventually it was recognized that all of this was.
SPEAKER_0:  really based on misperceptions.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course, that later led to negotiations between.
SPEAKER_0:  Gorbachev and Reagan for the Intermediate Nuclear Forces, the INF Treaty. But in 1983 that tension was just...
SPEAKER_0:  acute.
SPEAKER_0:  And for as a teenager, we were basically being prepped the whole time.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  the inevitability of nuclear Armageddon.
SPEAKER_0:  TV series, films in the United States and the UK, threads the day after.
SPEAKER_0:  We had all these public service announcements telling us to.
SPEAKER_0:  Seek.
SPEAKER_0:  sanctuary or cover.
SPEAKER_0:  and the inevitability of a nuclear blast. And my house was so small, they said, look for a room without a window. There were no rooms without windows. My dad put on these really thick curtains over the window.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, instead of there was a nuclear flash, you know, we'd have to get down on the floor, not look up, but the curtains would help. And we'd be like, this is ridiculous, Dad.
SPEAKER_0:  and we would all try to see if we could squeeze in the space under the stairs, a cupboard under the stairs like Harry Potter.
SPEAKER_0:  I was all just, you know, totally nuts.
SPEAKER_0:  or you had to throw yourself in a ditch if you were outside.
SPEAKER_0:  I thought, well, this isn't going to work.
SPEAKER_0:  And one of my great uncles who had fought in World War II said, Well look, you're good at languages Fiona.
SPEAKER_0:  Why don't you go and study Russian? Try to figure it out. Figure out why the Russians are trying to blow us up. Because you know, during the- Go talk to them. Exactly, during World War II.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  United Kingdom, the United States, and the Soviet Union had all been wartime allies and my uncle Charlie thought well there's something going wrong here maybe you can figure it out and as you said go talk to them.
SPEAKER_0:  So I thought, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll study Russian.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's really how this came about. Applying education.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll just do my very best to understand everything I possibly can about the Russian language and the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  and I'll see what I can do. And I thought, well, maybe I could become a translator. So I had visions of myself sitting around.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, listening to things in a.
SPEAKER_0:  big headset.
SPEAKER_0:  and in a best view translating perhaps at some.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, future arms control summits.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  How did the journey?
SPEAKER_1:  continue with learning Russian.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  This is early dream of being a translator.
SPEAKER_1:  and thinking how can I actually.
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh
SPEAKER_1:  help understand or maybe help even deeper way with this conflict.
SPEAKER_1:  that threatens the existence of the human species.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  How did it actually continue?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I mean, I read everything I possibly could about nuclear weapons and nuclear war and I started to try to teach myself Russian a little bit.
SPEAKER_1:  It was always in context of nuclear war. It was...
SPEAKER_0:  very much in the context of nuclear war at this particular point.
SPEAKER_0:  but also in historical context, because I knew that the United States and the United Kingdom and the Soviet Union had been wartime allies in World War II, so I'll try to understand all of that.
SPEAKER_0:  And also, you know, I, like many other people.
SPEAKER_0:  read Russian literature in translation, I'd read War and Peace. And I'd loved the book, actually. I mean, particularly the story parts of it. I wasn't one really at that time when I was a teenager. I thought Tolstoy went on a bit in terms of his theories of the great man and of history and kind of social change. Although now I appreciate it more. But when I was about 14, I was like, this man needed an editor. Could he have just gone on with the story? What an amazing story, what an incredible kind of book this is.
SPEAKER_1:  I still think he needs an ender but.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I think his wife tried, didn't she? He got quite upset with her.
SPEAKER_0:  And then I kind of thought to myself, well, how do I study Russian? Because there were very few schools in my region, you know, given the impoverishment of the region, where you could study Russian. It's not that tough to take.
SPEAKER_0:  Russian from scratch.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is where things get...
SPEAKER_0:  really quite interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  because there were opportunities to study Russian at universities, but I would need to have.
SPEAKER_0:  First of all.
SPEAKER_0:  an intensive Russian language course in the summer.
SPEAKER_0:  and I didn't have the money for that.
SPEAKER_0:  and the period is around the minus strike.
SPEAKER_0:  in the United Kingdom in 1984.
SPEAKER_0:  Now.
SPEAKER_0:  The miners of County Durham.
SPEAKER_0:  that very interestingly had exchanges and ties with the miners of Donbass.
SPEAKER_0:  going back to the 1920s.
SPEAKER_0:  And as I studied Russian history, I discovered there was lots of contacts.
SPEAKER_0:  between.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, Bolshevik.
SPEAKER_0:  Soviet Union in the early period after the Russian Revolution, but even before that.
SPEAKER_0:  during the imperial period in Russia between the Northern England.
SPEAKER_0:  and the Russian Empire in the old industrial areas.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically big industrial areas like the northeast of England.
SPEAKER_0:  and plays like Don Bass were built up at the same time, often by the same sets of industrialists.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Donetsk.
SPEAKER_0:  in the Donbass region used to be called Husevka.
SPEAKER_0:  because it was established by a Welsh industrialist who brought in miners from Wales.
SPEAKER_0:  to help develop the coal mines there and also the steelworks and others that we've been working with.
SPEAKER_0:  we're hearing about all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  So I got very fascinated in all these linkages and you know, famous.
SPEAKER_0:  writers from the early parts of the Soviet Union like Yevgeny Zamyatin.
SPEAKER_0:  I worked in the shipyards in Newcastle, Pontine.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  there was just this whole set of connections.
SPEAKER_0:  And in 1984...
SPEAKER_0:  When the miners strike took place, the miners of Donbass along with other miners from
SPEAKER_0:  famous coal regions like the Ruhr Valley, for example, in Germany or miners in Poland.
SPEAKER_0:  sent money in solidarity to the miners of Candidurum.
SPEAKER_0:  And there've been these exchanges, as I said, going back and forth since the 1920s, formal exchanges between miners.
SPEAKER_0:  the region of miners unions.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I heard again from the same.
SPEAKER_0:  great uncle who told me to...
SPEAKER_0:  study Russian.
SPEAKER_0:  So there were actually scholarships for the children of minors, and it could be former minors as well.
SPEAKER_0:  for their education.
SPEAKER_0:  And I should go along to the miners' hall, a place called Red Hills, where the miners of County Durham are actually.
SPEAKER_0:  pooled all of their resources and built up their own parliament.
SPEAKER_0:  and their own kind of place that they could.
SPEAKER_0:  talk among themselves to figure out how to
SPEAKER_0:  enhance the welfare and wellbeing of their communities.
SPEAKER_0:  and they'd put money aside for education for minors. There was all kinds of lecture series from the minors and all kinds of other activities supporting soccer teams and...
SPEAKER_0:  artistic circles and writing circles, for example. People like George Orwell, you know, were involved in some of these writer's circles and other parts of.
SPEAKER_0:  Bretton and Minnan communities for example.
SPEAKER_0:  And so the.
SPEAKER_0:  tell me I could go along.
SPEAKER_0:  and basically.
SPEAKER_0:  Apply for a grant?
SPEAKER_0:  to go to study Russian, so I show up.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was the easiest application I've ever come across. So just ask me to, my dad came along with me.
SPEAKER_0:  They asked me to verify that my dad had been a miner, and they looked up his employment record on little cards.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of a little a little trace somewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  and then they asked me how much I needed.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, to basically pay for the...
SPEAKER_0:  travel.
SPEAKER_0:  and some of the basic expenses for the...
SPEAKER_0:  the study and they wrote me a check.
SPEAKER_0:  And so thanks to the miners of Donbass.
SPEAKER_0:  and this money that was deposited with the miners of County Durham with the Durham Miners Association.
SPEAKER_0:  I got the money to study Russian for the first time.
SPEAKER_0:  before I embarked on my studies at university.
SPEAKER_1:  as you're speaking now.
SPEAKER_1:  It's reminding me that there's a different way to look both at history.
SPEAKER_1:  and a geography in a different places.
SPEAKER_1:  is um
SPEAKER_1:  you know, this is an industrial region.
SPEAKER_1:  That's right. And it echoes in the experience of living there.
SPEAKER_1:  is more captured.
SPEAKER_1:  not by Moscow or Kiev.
SPEAKER_1:  by at least historically.
SPEAKER_1:  or by just being...
SPEAKER_1:  mining town and
SPEAKER_0:  That's right, in the place itself. Yeah, I mean, there are places in the United States, in Appalachia, in West Virginia and in Pennsylvania, like the Lehigh Valley.
SPEAKER_0:  that have the same sense of place.
SPEAKER_0:  And the northeast of England was the...
SPEAKER_0:  cradle of the Industrial Revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  It was the industrial version of Silicon Valley, which has its own.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say contours and frames.
SPEAKER_0:  And when you come to those industrial areas, your previous identities get submerged in that larger.
SPEAKER_0:  framework. I've always looked at the world through that lens.
SPEAKER_0:  of being.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, someone from the working class, the blue collar communities from a very specific place with lots of historical.
SPEAKER_0:  and economic connotations.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's also a melting pot, which is the problems that the Donbass has experienced.
SPEAKER_0:  over the last 30 years, that people came from all over the place to work there. Of course, there was a population that one might say is indigenous, might have gone back centuries there.
SPEAKER_0:  but they would have been in the smaller rural farming communities just like it was the same in the northeast of England.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  People in the case of the northeast of England came from Wales, they came from further in the south of England, the Midlands, they came from Scotland, they came from Ireland.
SPEAKER_0:  I have all of that heritage in my own personal background.
SPEAKER_0:  and you've got a different identity.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's when somebody else tries to impose an identity on you from the outside that things go awry. And I think that that's kind of what we've really seen.
SPEAKER_0:  In the case of Donbass, it's a place that's a part in many respects historically and in terms of its evolution and development over time.
SPEAKER_0:  and particularly in the case of Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  The Russians have tried to say, well look, you know, because most people speak Russian, there is the lingua franca.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, in the North East Ring, of course, everyone spoke English, but lots of people were Irish speakers, you know, Gaelic Irish speakers or, you know, some of them might have.
SPEAKER_0:  certainly been Welsh speakers. There was lots of Welsh miners who spoke Welsh as their first language who came there.
SPEAKER_0:  But they created an identity. It's the same in Belfast and Ulster.
SPEAKER_0:  the northern province of...
SPEAKER_0:  of the whole of the Irish island.
SPEAKER_0:  and are the part of Ireland that is still part of the United Kingdom.
SPEAKER_0:  That was also a heavily industrialized area.
SPEAKER_0:  high manufacturing, mass manufacturing.
SPEAKER_0:  shipbuilding for example, people came from all over there too.
SPEAKER_0:  which is why I went Ireland.
SPEAKER_0:  got its independence from the United Kingdom.
SPEAKER_0:  Ulster.
SPEAKER_0:  Belfast and that whole region.
SPEAKER_0:  and I kind of clung on because it was again that melting pot.
SPEAKER_0:  It was kind of intertwined with the larger.
SPEAKER_0:  industrial economy.
SPEAKER_0:  and had a very different identity.
SPEAKER_0:  And so that, for me, growing up in such a specific place with such a...
SPEAKER_0:  special in many respects.
SPEAKER_0:  Heritage.
SPEAKER_0:  gave me a different perspective on things when I first went to the Soviet Union in 1987.
SPEAKER_0:  to study there. I actually went to a translators institute, what was then called the Maurice Therese, which is now the Institute of Foreign Languages.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I was immediately struck by how similar.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything was to the north of England.
SPEAKER_0:  because it was just like one big working class culture that sort of broken out onto the national stage. Everything in Northern England was nationalized.
SPEAKER_0:  We had British steel, British coal, British rail, British shipbuilding.
SPEAKER_0:  because after World War II, the private sector had been devastated.
SPEAKER_0:  and the state had to step in.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course, the Soviet Union is one big giant.
SPEAKER_0:  nationalised economy when I get there.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's just.
SPEAKER_0:  The people's attitudes and outlooks are the same. People didn't work for themselves, they always worked for somebody else.
SPEAKER_0:  and it had a quite a...
SPEAKER_0:  a distortion on the way that people looked at the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you still speak Russian?
SPEAKER_0:  I do.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you speak Russian? Yes, of course, if you want.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, then I need to say something and everyone will think about what we are talking about now.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it would be a big mystery for everybody. You have an advantage on me because it's your native language as well.
SPEAKER_1:  For people wondering, the English speakers in the audience, you're really missing a lot from the few sentences we said there.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's a fascinating language that stretches actually geographically across a very large part of this world.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  There you are in 1987, exchange student in the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_1:  What was that world like?
SPEAKER_0:  Well that was absolutely...
SPEAKER_0:  fascinating in that period because it's the period.
SPEAKER_0:  that's just around the time of the peak of perestroika Mikhail Gorbachev's
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  role as president, well he wasn't quite president at that point, he was Secretary General of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union trying to transform the whole place.
SPEAKER_0:  That's why I arrived there.
SPEAKER_0:  in September of 1987.
SPEAKER_0:  Justice.
SPEAKER_0:  Gorbachev and Reagan's sign.
SPEAKER_0:  the INF Treaty.
SPEAKER_0:  was just within weeks of them about to sign that, which really ends that whole period that it
SPEAKER_0:  shit my entire
SPEAKER_0:  teenage years of the end of the Euro Missile Crisis by...
SPEAKER_0:  finally having agreement on basically the rejection and constraints on intermediate nuclear forces.
SPEAKER_0:  And also, at this point, Gorbachev
SPEAKER_0:  opening the Soviet Union up.
SPEAKER_0:  So we got all kinds of opportunities to travel in ways that we wouldn't have done before.
SPEAKER_0:  not just in Moscow, which is where I was studying its translates into the Caucasus, to Central Asia.
SPEAKER_0:  went all the way to Khabarovsk in the Russian Far East.
SPEAKER_0:  all the way around, you know, kind of Moscow and.
SPEAKER_0:  There was, at this point, it was also the Krescheni Rus, which has become very important now. This is the anniversary, the thousandth anniversary of the Christianization.
SPEAKER_0:  of...
SPEAKER_0:  Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  which of course has become a massive obsession of Vladimir Putin's, but you know, 988.
SPEAKER_0:  because I was there in 1987 to 1988. At this point, the Russian Orthodox Church is undergoing a revival from being repressed during the Soviet period.
SPEAKER_0:  you suddenly have the church stepping out.
SPEAKER_0:  as a non-governmental organization and engaging in discussions with people.
SPEAKER_0:  about the future of religion.
SPEAKER_0:  So that was...
SPEAKER_0:  something that I wasn't expecting to witness.
SPEAKER_0:  Also, I mean, being in Moscow, this is the cultural capital of a vast empire at this point. I'd never lived in a major city before. It's the first big city I lived in. It's the first big city I lived in.
SPEAKER_0:  I'd never been to the opera.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, the first time I got an opera, it's at the Bolshoi.
SPEAKER_0:  I'd never seen a ballet. I mean, I was not exactly steeped in...
SPEAKER_0:  high classical culture, growing up in a mining region.
SPEAKER_0:  There's very limited opportunities for this kind of thing. I'd been in a youth orchestra and a youth choir. My parents signed me up for obviously everything they possibly could education wise, but it wasn't exactly any exposure to this.
SPEAKER_0:  I was kind of astounded by the sort of wealth of the cultural experience that one could have in Moscow. That was amazing.
SPEAKER_0:  was I was really struck by.
SPEAKER_0:  how the Soviet Union was on its last legs.
SPEAKER_0:  because this was Moscow, you know, I got this image about what it would look like. I was quite, to be honest.
SPEAKER_0:  terrified at first about what I would see there, even at the big nuclear superpower. But as soon as I got there...
SPEAKER_0:  It was just this like, as if a huge wedge that I'd been carrying around for years and my teenage years just disappeared because it's just ordinary people in k셔서dさん
SPEAKER_0:  not doing great.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the period.
SPEAKER_0:  of what they call deficitne vremya, the period of deficits, but there's no food in the shops.
SPEAKER_0:  There was very little in terms of commodities because...
SPEAKER_0:  the supply and demand parts of the economic equation were out of luck because this was total central planning. You know, you could go into… you know, use it to
SPEAKER_0:  a shop that was supposed to sell boots and there'd be just one.
SPEAKER_0:  pyre of boots all in the same size and the same color.
SPEAKER_0:  I actually looked out because once I was in this...
SPEAKER_0:  Hungarian boot shop that was right next to where my Hall of Residence was and I was looking for a new pair of boots and every single pair of boots in the shop were my size.
SPEAKER_0:  and they're all women's boots, they're not men's boots at all.
SPEAKER_0:  because there has been an oversupply of boots and that size protection.
SPEAKER_0:  But you could really kind of see here that there was something wrong. And, you know, in the north of England, everything was closed down. The shops were shuttered because there was no demand because everybody lost their jobs. It was just mustered employment.
SPEAKER_0:  When I went off to university in 1984, 90% youth unemployment.
SPEAKER_0:  in the UK, meaning that when kids...
SPEAKER_0:  left school, they didn't have something else to go on to unless they got to university or vocational training or an apprenticeship and most people were still looking, you know, kind of months out.
SPEAKER_0:  of leaving school.
SPEAKER_0:  And so shops were closing because people didn't have any money.
SPEAKER_0:  I had 50% male unemployment in some of the towns.
SPEAKER_0:  the steelworks closed down and the wagon works for the railways, for example, in my area.
SPEAKER_0:  But in Moscow, people in theory did have money, but there was just, there was nothing to buy.
SPEAKER_0:  Also, the place was falling apart, literally. I saw massive sinkholes open up in the street.
SPEAKER_0:  balconies fall off buildings, you know, one accident after another.
SPEAKER_0:  And then there was this real sense, even though the vibrancy and excitement and hope of the Gorbachev period...
SPEAKER_0:  a real sense that the Soviet Union has lost its way.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course it was only a year or so after.
SPEAKER_0:  I left from that exchange program and I'd already started with my degree program.
SPEAKER_0:  and Soviet studies at Talbot.
SPEAKER_0:  that the Soviet Union basically unraveled.
SPEAKER_0:  And it really did unravel. It wasn't like it collapsed.
SPEAKER_0:  It was basically that there were so many debates that Gorbachev had sparked off about how to reform the country, how to put it on a different path.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, no one was in agreement, especially all these fights and-
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  debates and disputes among the elites at the centre.
SPEAKER_0:  as well as.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, basically a loss of faith in the system.
SPEAKER_0:  in the periphery and among the general population.
SPEAKER_0:  then in fact pulled it apart and of course.
SPEAKER_0:  1991.
SPEAKER_0:  you get...
SPEAKER_0:  Boris Yeltsin as the head of the Russian Federation, then a constituent part of the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  together with the presidents of Ukraine and Belarus.
SPEAKER_0:  all of these being individual.
SPEAKER_0:  parts of the Soviet Union getting together and agreeing and essentially ending it.
SPEAKER_0:  And Gorbachev, you know, so basically I'm there at the peak of this whole kind of period of experimentation and thinking about the future.
SPEAKER_0:  And within a couple of years, it's all kind of gone and it's on a different track entirely.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I wonder if we reran the 20th century.
SPEAKER_1:  a thousand times.
SPEAKER_1:  if how many times the Soviet Union will collapse.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I wonder about that too. And I also wonder about what would have happened if it didn't collapse and Gorbachev had found a different direction.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, we see a very divisive time now in.
SPEAKER_1:  American history.
SPEAKER_1:  the United States of America.
SPEAKER_1:  It's very different cultures, very different.
SPEAKER_1:  beliefs, ideologies within those states. but those are
SPEAKER_1:  That's kind of the strength of America, there's these little laboratories.
SPEAKER_1:  of ideas.
SPEAKER_0:  until though that they don't keep together. I mean, I've had colleagues who have described what's happening in the West right now as a kind of soft secession.
SPEAKER_0:  with states going off in their own direction. The center of
SPEAKER_0:  Well, these kinds of conceptions that we have now are divisions between red and blue states because of the fracturing of our politics.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'd always thought that that wouldn't be possible in somewhere like the United States or, you know, many other countries as well, because there wasn't that ethnic
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think we will get the
SPEAKER_0:  But in fact, many of the way that people talk about politics has given it.
SPEAKER_0:  that kind of appearance in many respects. This is what a company we know from
SPEAKER_0:  the Soviet Union and the Soviet period.
SPEAKER_0:  and from where you're from, you know, originally in Ukraine, that language.
SPEAKER_0:  is not the man to signify of identity.
SPEAKER_0:  and that identity can take all kinds of other forms.
SPEAKER_1:  That's really interesting, I mean, but.
SPEAKER_1:  There has to be a deep grievance of some kind.
SPEAKER_1:  If you took a poll.
SPEAKER_1:  in any other states in the United States, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  a very small minority of people would want to actually succeed.
SPEAKER_1:  even in Texas where I spend a lot of my time.
SPEAKER_1:  I just think that there is a...
SPEAKER_1:  common kind of pride of nation.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there's a lot of people complain.
SPEAKER_1:  about government and about...
SPEAKER_1:  how the country's going.
SPEAKER_1:  the way people complain about the weather when it's raining. They say, oh, this stupid weather is raining again. But really what they mean is...
SPEAKER_1:  We're in the smock together.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a together there.
SPEAKER_0:  I also feel that when I go around, because I mean, I've spent a lot of time since I wrote my book in last October, and this last year going around, I find the same feeling.
SPEAKER_0:  But you know, when I traveled around the Soviet Union...
SPEAKER_0:  in the late 1980s. I didn't get any kind of sense that people wanted to see the end of the Soviet Union either.
SPEAKER_0:  It was an elite project.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a really great book called Collapse by Vladislav Zubok, who is a professor.
SPEAKER_0:  at
SPEAKER_0:  London School of Economics at LSE.
SPEAKER_0:  And Zubok is pretty much my age and he's from the former Soviet Union, he's Russian.
SPEAKER_0:  And I mean, he describes it very quite aptly about how it was kind of the elites.
SPEAKER_0:  that basically decided to pull the Soviet Union apart. And there is a risk of that here as well when you get partisan politics.
SPEAKER_0:  and people forgetting.
SPEAKER_0:  they're Americans and they are all in this together like a lot of the population thing.
SPEAKER_0:  but they think that they're own, you know, narrow, partisan or ideological.
SPEAKER_0:  precepts.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, camp for more.
SPEAKER_0:  And in the Soviet case, of course, it was also a power play.
SPEAKER_0:  in a way that's...
SPEAKER_0:  actually can't quite play out in the United States because it was the equivalent of governance.
SPEAKER_0:  in many respects.
SPEAKER_0:  who got together three of them, you know, in the case of.
SPEAKER_0:  the heads of Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  Ukraine and Belarus who then got rid of.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, basically the central.
SPEAKER_0:  the central figure of Mikhail Gorbachev. It would be a little...
SPEAKER_0:  difficult to do that, the dynamic is not the same, but it does worry me of having seen all of that close up.
SPEAKER_0:  in the late 1980s.
SPEAKER_0:  and the early 90s, I spent a lot of time in Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  as well as in Ukraine and the Caucasus, Central Asia and other places after the collapse of the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  but that you kind of see the same.
SPEAKER_0:  elite divisions here.
SPEAKER_0:  in the United States pulling.
SPEAKER_0:  in different directions and straining the overall body politic.
SPEAKER_0:  national politics gets.
SPEAKER_0:  imposed on local politics.
SPEAKER_0:  whereas it certainly wasn't when I first came to the US in 1989. I didn't honestly in 1989 when I first came here. I didn't know anybody's political affiliation.
SPEAKER_0:  I rarely knew that religious affiliation.
SPEAKER_0:  And obviously race was a major phenomenon here that was a shock to me when I first came.
SPEAKER_0:  but many of the kind of the class.
SPEAKER_0:  regional.
SPEAKER_0:  geographic, you know, kind of political dimensions that I've seen in other places. I didn't see them at play in the same way.
SPEAKER_0:  then as I do now.
SPEAKER_1:  and you take a lot of pride.
SPEAKER_1:  to this day of being not partisan.
SPEAKER_1:  That said...
SPEAKER_1:  So you served.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  for the George W. Bush, Barack Obama, and Donald Trump administrations.
SPEAKER_1:  always specializing.
SPEAKER_1:  And uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Eurasia and Russia.
SPEAKER_1:  You were the top presidential advisor to president.
SPEAKER_1:  former president Donald Trump on Russia and Europe, and famously,
SPEAKER_1:  testified in his first impeachment trial.
SPEAKER_1:  in 2019.
SPEAKER_1:  saying
SPEAKER_1:  I take great pride in the fact that I'm nonpartisan foreign policy expert.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  given that context.
SPEAKER_1:  What does nonpartisan mean to you?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I mean, being very careful about not putting any kind of ideological lens on anything that I'm analyzing or looking at or saying about foreign policy, for one thing.
SPEAKER_0:  but also not taking, you know, kind of one stance of one party over another either.
SPEAKER_0:  To be honest, I've always found.
SPEAKER_0:  American politics somewhat confounding.
SPEAKER_0:  Because both the Democratic and the Republican Party are pretty big-tent, some of their coalitions.
SPEAKER_0:  In Europe, it's actually kind of, in some respects, easier to navigate the parameters of political parties because you have quite clear platforms.
SPEAKER_0:  There's also a longer history in many respects, obviously. There's a long history here in the United States of the development of the parties going back to the late 18th century.
SPEAKER_0:  But in the United Kingdom, for example, in the 20th century, the development of the mass parties, it was quite easy to get a handle on.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, at one point.
SPEAKER_0:  in the UK, for example. The parties were real genuine mass parties with people who were properly members and took part in regular meetings and paid dues and...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it was easy to just kind of see what this stood for.
SPEAKER_0:  And the same in Europe, you know, when you look at France and in Germany and Western Germany, of course.
SPEAKER_0:  Italy and elsewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  Here in the United States, it's kind of pretty amorphous.
SPEAKER_0:  the fact that you could kind of register.
SPEAKER_0:  randomly it seems to be a Democrat or Republican, like Trump did. At one point he's Democrat, next thing he's Republican, and then you kind of usurp a party apparatus.
SPEAKER_0:  but you don't have to be, you're not vetted in any way. You're not kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  They don't check you out to see if you have ideological coherence.
SPEAKER_0:  You could have someone like Bernie Sanders on the other side, on the left.
SPEAKER_0:  basically calling himself a socialist and running for the Democratic.
SPEAKER_0:  presidential nomination.
SPEAKER_0:  So, you know, kind of in many respects, parties.
SPEAKER_0:  in the United States are much more loose movements.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's almost like an ala carte menu of different things.
SPEAKER_0:  and that people can pick out.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's more over time, as I've noticed.
SPEAKER_0:  become.
SPEAKER_0:  more like a kind of an affiliation even with a sporting team.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I get very shocked by the way that people say, I couldn't do this because that's my side.
SPEAKER_0:  I couldn't do anything and I couldn't support someone for the other side. I mean, I have a
SPEAKER_0:  a relative in my extended family here.
SPEAKER_0:  who died in the war Republican.
SPEAKER_0:  on a family holiday.
SPEAKER_0:  was a book on their table.
SPEAKER_0:  said a hundred reasons for voting for a Democrat. And I said, hey, are you thinking of shifting party affiliation? And I opened the book and it's blank.
SPEAKER_0:  It was pretty funny. I had to laugh.
SPEAKER_0:  I thought, well, there you go then.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no way that people can pull themselves out of these frames. So for me, it's very important to have that independence of thought.
SPEAKER_0:  I think you can be politically engaged on the issues.
SPEAKER_0:  But, you know, basically without.
SPEAKER_0:  taking a stance that's defined by some ideology or some sense of parties on affiliation.
SPEAKER_1:  I think I tweeted about this, maybe not eloquently.
SPEAKER_1:  in the statement, if I remember correctly, was something like monumental grandpa watching records. But, I guess, I mean, I guess house studied books,
SPEAKER_1:  if you honestly can't.
SPEAKER_1:  Find.
SPEAKER_1:  a good thing that Donald Trump did or a good thing that Joe Biden did.
SPEAKER_1:  You're not.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  You're not thinking about ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  you just picked the tribe. I mean it was more eloquent than that but it was um.
SPEAKER_1:  is basically, this is a really good test to see are you actually thinking.
SPEAKER_1:  about like how to solve problems versus like your red team or blue team.
SPEAKER_1:  like a sporting team.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you?
SPEAKER_1:  find it.
SPEAKER_1:  Good idea of Donald Trump's that you like.
SPEAKER_1:  if you're somebody who is against Donald Trump.
SPEAKER_1:  And like...
SPEAKER_1:  Acknowledge it to yourself privately. Oh, that's a good idea.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm glad he said that.
SPEAKER_0:  Or he's even asking the right kinds of questions, which he often did actually. I mean, obviously put them in a way that most of us wouldn't have done.
SPEAKER_0:  But there was often kind of questions about why is this happening? Why are we doing this? And we have to challenge ourselves all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, actually, why are we doing that?
SPEAKER_0:  And then you have to really inspect it and say whether it's actually worth continuing that way, or they should be doing something differently.
SPEAKER_0:  Now here's a more kind of destructive quality to those kinds of questions.
SPEAKER_0:  know, maybe it's the real estate developer in him that's taking a big wrecking ball to all of these kinds of
SPEAKER_0:  you know, sacred edifices and things like that, but often.
SPEAKER_0:  If you really pay attention, he was asking a valid set of questions.
SPEAKER_0:  about why do we continue to do things like this. Now, we didn't often have answers about what he was gonna do in response.
SPEAKER_0:  but those questions still had to be asked.
SPEAKER_0:  and we shouldn't be just rejecting them.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, out of turn.
SPEAKER_1:  And you know, the, the, another strength.
SPEAKER_1:  The thing that people often, that criticize Donald Trump, will say is a weakness.
SPEAKER_1:  is this lack of...
SPEAKER_1:  civility.
SPEAKER_1:  can be a strength.
SPEAKER_1:  because I feel like sometimes bureaucracy functions on.
SPEAKER_1:  excessive civility.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, actually I've seen this, it's not just, it's bureaucracy in all forms, like, um,
SPEAKER_1:  in tech companies as they grow.
SPEAKER_1:  everybody kind of, you know, you're getting pretty good salary. Everyone's.
SPEAKER_1:  Everyone's comfortable.
SPEAKER_1:  and there's a meeting and you discuss.
SPEAKER_1:  how to move stuff forward.
SPEAKER_1:  And like...
SPEAKER_1:  You don't want to be the asshole in the room.
SPEAKER_1:  that says what?
SPEAKER_1:  This is why are we doing this this way? This is
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  This could be unethical. This is hurting the world.
SPEAKER_1:  This is totally a dumb idea.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, I mean, I could give specific examples that I have on my mind currently that are technical, but the point is oftentimes the person that's needed in that room is an asshole.
SPEAKER_1:  That's why Steve Jobs worked.
SPEAKER_1:  So you know a mosque works, you have to roll in. That's what first principles thinking looks like.
SPEAKER_0:  The one bit when it doesn't work is when they start name calling.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of inciting violence against, you know, the people that they disagree with. So that was kind of your problem because I mean, often one, you know,
SPEAKER_0:  when I was in the administration.
SPEAKER_0:  I had all of Europe in my portfolio as well as Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  And there were many times when we were dealing with our European colleagues where...
SPEAKER_0:  He was asking some pretty valid questions about, well, why should we do this if you're doing that?
SPEAKER_0:  For example, the Nord Stream 2 pipeline, the United States has been opposed to...
SPEAKER_0:  Europe's reliance on gas and oil exports from...
SPEAKER_0:  Russia, you know, the Soviet Union since the 70s and 80s.
SPEAKER_0:  And Trump kept pushing this idea about, so why are we spending so much money on NATO and NATO defense and we're all talking about this?
SPEAKER_0:  If y'all then, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  basically paying billions to Russia for gas.
SPEAKER_0:  isn't this, you know, contradictory? Of course it was!
SPEAKER_0:  But it was the way that he did it. And I actually, you know, one instance had a discussion with a European defense minister, who basically said to me, look, he's saying exactly the same things as people said before him, including, you know, former defense secretary Gates. It's just the way he says it.
SPEAKER_0:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  So they took offense and then as a result of that they wouldn't take action because they took offense at what he said.
SPEAKER_0:  So it was a kind of then a way of.
SPEAKER_0:  Could you find?
SPEAKER_0:  some other means of.
SPEAKER_0:  massaging this communication.
SPEAKER_0:  to go and make it effective, which we would always try to focus on.
SPEAKER_0:  because it's kind of the delivery.
SPEAKER_0:  But the actual message was often spot on.
SPEAKER_0:  in those kinds of issues. I mean, he was actually highlighting.
SPEAKER_0:  these ridiculous discrepancies between what people said and what they actually did.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's the delivery, the charisma in the room too.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm also
SPEAKER_1:  understanding the power of that of a leader. It's not just about what you do at a podium.
SPEAKER_1:  in a room with advisors.
SPEAKER_1:  how you talk about stuff, how you convince others.
SPEAKER_0:  leaders. Yeah, you don't do it through gratuitous insults and incitement to violence. That's one of the things you just you don't get anywhere on that front. Well, it is possible.
SPEAKER_0:  Tough measures and maximum pressure often though does work because there were, you know, often times where...
SPEAKER_0:  You know that.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of relentless.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, nagging about something.
SPEAKER_0:  constantly raising it. actually did have results but it hadn't.
SPEAKER_0:  previously. Right. So there's, you know, the maximum pressure.
SPEAKER_0:  if it kind of kept on it in the right way. And often when we were.
SPEAKER_0:  coming in behind on pushing on issues.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, related to NATO or, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  other.
SPEAKER_0:  things in this same sphere.
SPEAKER_0:  It would actually...
SPEAKER_0:  have an effect.
SPEAKER_0:  It just doesn't get talked about because.
SPEAKER_0:  it gets overshadowed by.
SPEAKER_0:  all of the other stuff around this and the way that he interacted with people.
SPEAKER_0:  cheated people.
SPEAKER_1:  What was the heart, the key insights your testimony in that impeachment?
SPEAKER_0:  Look, I think there is a straight line.
SPEAKER_0:  between.
SPEAKER_0:  that whole series of episodes.
SPEAKER_0:  and the current warranty code.
SPEAKER_0:  because Vladimir Putin and the people around him in the Kremlin.
SPEAKER_0:  concluded that the US did not care one little bit about Ukraine and it was just a game.
SPEAKER_0:  the trumpet was personal game.
SPEAKER_0:  It was best to be trying to get.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  Volodymyr Zelensky, did you have a personal favour?
SPEAKER_0:  related to his desire to stay on and.
SPEAKER_0:  and power.
SPEAKER_0:  in the 2020 election.
SPEAKER_0:  And generally they just thought that we were using Ukraine as some kind of proxy or some kind of
SPEAKER_0:  instrument within our own domestic politics as that's what it looked like.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think that he knows the result of that.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  the idea aware that he could.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, do whatever he wanted. We were constantly being asked, even prior to this, by-
SPEAKER_0:  people around.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  Putin like.
SPEAKER_0:  Nikolai Patrushev, the head of the national.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, security council equivalent in Russia who we met with frequently. What's Ukraine to you? We don't get it.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, why do you even care?
SPEAKER_0:  So they thought that we weren't serious, that we weren't serious about.
SPEAKER_0:  Ukraine's territorial integrity and its independence.
SPEAKER_0:  or it is a national security player.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin also thought that he could just manipulate.
SPEAKER_0:  the political space in the United States actually could.
SPEAKER_0:  because what he was doing was seeding.
SPEAKER_0:  all this dissent.
SPEAKER_0:  and fueling.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, already in a debate inside of US politics, the kinds of things that we see just coming out now.
SPEAKER_0:  this kind of idea that Ukraine was a burden, that Ukraine was...
SPEAKER_0:  basically just trying to extract things.
SPEAKER_0:  from the United States. The Ukraine had somehow played.
SPEAKER_0:  inside of US politics.
SPEAKER_0:  Trump was convinced that the Ukrainians had done something against him, that they had intervened in the elections.
SPEAKER_0:  And that was kind of a combination of people around him trying to find an excuse to
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  what had happened in the election to kind of divert attention away from Russia's interference in 2016 and the Russians themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  poisoning the world against Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  So you had a kind of a confluence of circumstances there.
SPEAKER_0:  and what I was trying to get across.
SPEAKER_0:  in that testimony was the national security imperative of.
SPEAKER_0:  basically getting our act together here and separating out what was going on in our domestic politics from
SPEAKER_0:  what was happening in our national security and foreign policy.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I think we contributed.
SPEAKER_0:  end up.
SPEAKER_0:  whole mess around the impeachment, but this is the whole...
SPEAKER_0:  parallel policies around Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  to the war that we now have.
SPEAKER_0:  them confronting.
SPEAKER_1:  signaling.
SPEAKER_1:  the value we place in peace and stability in that part of the world or the reverse by saying we don't care.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, we seemed to not care. It was just a game.
SPEAKER_1:  But, I mean, the US role.
SPEAKER_1:  in that war is very complicated one. That's one of the variables.
SPEAKER_1:  Just...
SPEAKER_1:  on that.
SPEAKER_1:  testimony.
SPEAKER_1:  Did it.
SPEAKER_1:  in part break your heart that you had to testify.
SPEAKER_1:  essentially against the president of the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  Or is that not how you saw it?
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think...
SPEAKER_0:  I would describe it in that way.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  what I was was deeply disappointed by what I saw.
SPEAKER_0:  happening.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  the American...
SPEAKER_0:  Political spurs? I didn't expect it.
SPEAKER_0:  Look, I was a starry-eyed immigrant.
SPEAKER_0:  I came to the United States with all of these expectations of what the place would be. I'd already been disabused of some of the...
SPEAKER_0:  Let's just say Rosie.
SPEAKER_0:  perspectives I held in the United States. I'd been shocked by...
SPEAKER_0:  the depths.
SPEAKER_0:  of.
SPEAKER_0:  Racial.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, problems doesn't even sum up the problems we have in the United States. I mean, I couldn't get my head around it when I first came.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I'd read about.
SPEAKER_0:  slavery in American history but I hadn't fully fathomed.
SPEAKER_0:  and really the kind of the way that it was ripping apart.
SPEAKER_0:  United States. I mean, I'd read Alex's talk full and he'd commented on this and it obviously hadn't kind of changed the way that one would have expected.
SPEAKER_0:  all this time from the 18th century onwards.
SPEAKER_0:  So that was kind of one thing that I realized, civil rights.
SPEAKER_0:  movement and all of these acts of expansion of suffrage and everything else were imperfect at best.
SPEAKER_0:  I was born in 1965, the same time as the Civil Rights Act. It was a heck of a long way still to go, so I wasn't...
SPEAKER_0:  Let's just say.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, as.
SPEAKER_0:  starry-eyed about everything as I'd been before, but I really saw an incredible competence and professionalism in the US government, in the election system and the integrity of it
SPEAKER_0:  And I mean, I really saw that. So the nicest was the gold standard for.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, come to some of its institutions. I worked in the National Intelligence Council and I'd seen the way that the United States had...
SPEAKER_0:  tried to address the problems that it did.
SPEAKER_0:  it faced and it was just whole botched.
SPEAKER_0:  analysis of Iraq and...
SPEAKER_0:  a terrible strategic blunder of...
SPEAKER_0:  Um, I'll just see.
SPEAKER_0:  crime in my view of invading Iraq, but the way that people were trying to.
SPEAKER_0:  to deal with that in the aftermath. I mean, I went into the National Intelligence Council and the DNI, the office of the Director of National Intelligence when they were coming to terms with what had gone wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  in the whole analysis about Iraq in 2003.
SPEAKER_0:  in the whole work of people trying to pull together after 9-11 to learn all of the lessons from all of this.
SPEAKER_0:  And I saw, you know, just really genuine striving and deliberation about what had gone wrong, what lessons could we learn from this?
SPEAKER_0:  And then suddenly...
SPEAKER_0:  I found myself.
SPEAKER_0:  in this.
SPEAKER_0:  I couldn't really describe it in any words. It's totally crazy looking glass, thinking of Alice in Wonderland, as through the looking glass version.
SPEAKER_0:  of American politics.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I'd seen everything starting to unravel over a kind of a period of time before I'd been asked to be in the administration, but I did not expect it to be that bad. I honestly didn't.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I'd been warned by people that...
SPEAKER_0:  This was.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of really a very...
SPEAKER_0:  serious turn that the United States had taken, but I really thought that national security...
SPEAKER_0:  would still be uppermost in people's minds. And it was, I mean a lot of the people that I work with.
SPEAKER_0:  But what I've found...
SPEAKER_0:  if you want to use that.
SPEAKER_0:  in a term of heart-breaking.
SPEAKER_0:  was the way in which...
SPEAKER_0:  all of these principles.
SPEAKER_0:  that I'd...
SPEAKER_0:  Really?
SPEAKER_0:  bought into and tried to uphold in the United States government and then the things that we were trying to do with me and my colleagues was just being thrown out the window.
SPEAKER_0:  and that I would have to step up.
SPEAKER_0:  in defense of them and in defense of my colleagues who are being lambasted and criticized.
SPEAKER_0:  given death threats for actually standing up and doing their own jobs.
SPEAKER_1:  in particular on the topic of Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  Not just on Ukraine, but on national security overall. So I mean, I'd gone through this whole period even before we got to that point.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm seeing non-partisan.
SPEAKER_0:  government officials being attacked from all sides.
SPEAKER_0:  left and right, but especially the right.
SPEAKER_0:  and being basically accused of being.
SPEAKER_0:  Partisan hacks in a deep state.
SPEAKER_0:  Coup plotters, you know, you name it.
SPEAKER_0:  PEPCHISISM BING
SPEAKER_0:  questions as well.
SPEAKER_0:  And a lot of people I work with in government, like myself, naturalized Americans, a lot of them are immigrants, many were refugees.
SPEAKER_0:  and many people had fought in wars on behalf of the United States in Iraq and Afghanistan being blown up and...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, they put their lives on the line.
SPEAKER_0:  They'd put their family lives on the line.
SPEAKER_0:  because they believed in America.
SPEAKER_0:  And they were just, they were reflections of.
SPEAKER_0:  Americans from all kinds of walks of life. Here's what Breedy made.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, that cliche of America great. It wasn't.
SPEAKER_0:  whatever it was that was being bandied around in these crude, crass political terms.
SPEAKER_0:  It was just the strength of an incredible set of people who've come together from all kinds of places and decided.
SPEAKER_0:  but they're gonna make a go of it.
SPEAKER_0:  and that they're going to.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, try to work towards the whole.
SPEAKER_0:  idea of the parable of the Constitution.
SPEAKER_0:  towards a more perfect union. And I saw people doing that every single day, despite all of the things that they could criticize about the United States, still believing in what they were doing and believing in the promise of the country, which is what I felt like.
SPEAKER_0:  And then here we were.
SPEAKER_0:  People were just treating it like a game.
SPEAKER_0:  and they were treating people like dirt.
SPEAKER_0:  and they were just playing games with people's lives. We all had death threats.
SPEAKER_0:  and people's, you know, whole careers.
SPEAKER_0:  which were not just careers for their own self-aggrandizement, but for...
SPEAKER_0:  Korea's a public service trying to give us something back.
SPEAKER_0:  were being shattered.
SPEAKER_0:  And I just thought to myself, I'm not gonna let that happen.
SPEAKER_0:  Because, you know, I've come from a, well, are they going to send me back to Bishop Auckland in County Durham? Fine. I'm totally fine to go back, you know, because I could do something back there. But I'm not going to let this happen.
SPEAKER_0:  I've made this choice to come to America. I'm all in.
SPEAKER_0:  And these guys are just behaving like a bunch of idiots.
SPEAKER_0:  and the ruining it, you know, the ruining it for everybody.
SPEAKER_1:  no attacks on him.
SPEAKER_1:  un-competent, hard-working, passionate people who have...
SPEAKER_1:  love for what they do in their heart.
SPEAKER_1:  Some more stuff I've seen.
SPEAKER_1:  for virologists and biologists, colleagues, basically scientists in the time of COVID when there's a bunch of cynicism.
SPEAKER_1:  And there was...
SPEAKER_1:  just personal attacks, including death threats on people that work on viruses.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and they're going around basically with protective gear on in case somebody shoots them in the street. That's just absurd.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  Let me zoom out from the individual people.
SPEAKER_1:  and actually look at the situations that we saw in the.
SPEAKER_1:  in the
SPEAKER_1:  to George W. Bush, Obama and Donald Trump.
SPEAKER_1:  presidencies.
SPEAKER_1:  and I'd like to sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  criticize
SPEAKER_1:  each.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  by not the treatment of individual people, but by the results. Right, yeah, I think that's fair. So if we look at George W. Bush...
SPEAKER_1:  and maybe you can give me insights.
SPEAKER_1:  This is what's fascinating to me, when you have extremely competent
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, smart.
SPEAKER_1:  hardworking.
SPEAKER_1:  well-intentioned people.
SPEAKER_1:  How do we?
SPEAKER_1:  as a system.
SPEAKER_1:  make mistakes in foreign policy.
SPEAKER_1:  The big mistake.
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  You can characterize in different ways, but in George W. Bush is.
SPEAKER_1:  invading Iraq.
SPEAKER_1:  Or maybe how.
SPEAKER_1:  it was invaded or maybe how the
SPEAKER_1:  decision process was made to invade it.
SPEAKER_1:  Again, Afghanistan with the
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe not the invasion, but...
SPEAKER_1:  details around.
SPEAKER_1:  like having a plan.
SPEAKER_1:  about how to withdraw all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  Barack Obama
SPEAKER_1:  to me similarly.
SPEAKER_1:  is the man who...
SPEAKER_1:  came.
SPEAKER_1:  fame early on.
SPEAKER_1:  for being somebody who's against.
SPEAKER_1:  a rare voice against the invasion.
SPEAKER_1:  of Iraq, which was actually a
SPEAKER_1:  a brave thing to do.
SPEAKER_1:  at that time.
SPEAKER_1:  end.
SPEAKER_1:  Nevertheless...
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I don't know the numbers, but...
SPEAKER_1:  I think he...
SPEAKER_1:  I was the president for years over.
SPEAKER_1:  increased drone attacks, everything from a foreign policy perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  the military industrial complex.
SPEAKER_1:  That machine grew in power under him.
SPEAKER_1:  not shrunk.
SPEAKER_1:  and did not withdraw.
SPEAKER_1:  from.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, let's go.
SPEAKER_1:  And then.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  with Donald Trump.
SPEAKER_1:  the criticisms that you're presenting sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  the personal attacks.
SPEAKER_1:  the chaos, the partisanship.
SPEAKER_1:  of people that are supposed to be nonpartisan.
SPEAKER_1:  So if you took sort of the steel man, the chaos.
SPEAKER_1:  to make the case for chaos, maybe we need to shake up the machine.
SPEAKER_1:  throw a wrench into the engine, into the gears.
SPEAKER_1:  and then every individual gear is going to be very upset with that.
SPEAKER_1:  because it's the wrench, it's an inefficient process, but maybe leads.
SPEAKER_1:  for government.
SPEAKER_1:  it forces the system as a whole, not the individuals, but the system to reconsider.
SPEAKER_1:  how things are done.
SPEAKER_1:  So obviously all of those things.
SPEAKER_1:  the actual results are not that impressive.
SPEAKER_0:  You could have done that on the latter, you know, shaking things up because I'm all one for questioning and trying to shake things up as well and do things differently.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  The question is if you bring the whole system down with nothing.
SPEAKER_0:  ideas of putting it in a place like home.
SPEAKER_0:  Like many people, I've studied the Bolshevik Revolution and many others as well and kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  What's the pattern here that actually fits into what you're talking about here is a kind of rigidity of thought on the part of revolutionaries in many cases as well.
SPEAKER_0:  and also narcissism.
SPEAKER_0:  In fact, I think the text is pretty...
SPEAKER_0:  strong sense of yourself, you know, kind of an only yourself to want to be president of the United States, for example, and we see that in
SPEAKER_0:  Many of our presidents have been narcissists to different kind of degrees.
SPEAKER_0:  You think about Lenin, for example, and people can go back and read about Lenin.
SPEAKER_0:  He formed his views when he was about 18 and he never shook them off.
SPEAKER_0:  He never evolved.
SPEAKER_0:  He didn't have any kind of diversity of thought.
SPEAKER_0:  and when systems go awry.
SPEAKER_0:  It's when they don't bring in.
SPEAKER_0:  different perspectives.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  Trump, if you brought in different perspectives and actually listened to them and not just believed that he himself knew better than anyone else and then tried to divide everybody against each other, would have been a different matter.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a tragedy of a completely and utterly lost set of opportunities because of the flaws.
SPEAKER_0:  and his own nature.
SPEAKER_0:  Because I mean, again, there was all kinds of things that he could have done to shake things up and so many people around him.
SPEAKER_0:  remained completely disappointed. And of course he divided and pitted people against each other.
SPEAKER_0:  in creating so much factualism.
SPEAKER_0:  in American politics that people have forgotten they're Americans. They think that they're red or blue, you know, parts of teams.
SPEAKER_0:  If you go back over history, that's a kind of a recipe for war and internal conflict.
SPEAKER_0:  You go back to the Byzantine Empire, for example, there's the famous episode of the Nike riots.
SPEAKER_0:  in Constantinople where the whole city gets trashed because the greens, the reds, the blues and these various sporting teams in the hippodrome.
SPEAKER_0:  get whipped up by political forces and they pull the place apart. And that's, you know, kind of where we've been heading on some of these trajectories.
SPEAKER_0:  But the other point is when you look back.
SPEAKER_0:  Bush and Obama as well, there's a very narrow circle of decision making.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, in Bush period, it's the focus on the executive branch.
SPEAKER_0:  with Dick Cheney as the Vice President being very fixated on it.
SPEAKER_0:  In Obama, it's he and the bright young things around him.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, from he himself is, you know, kind of intellectually.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, one might say arrogant in many respects, you know, he was a very smart guy.
SPEAKER_0:  And, you know, he's...
SPEAKER_0:  convinced that he has and he ruminates over a lot of things, but he's the person who makes a lot of decisions.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, George W. Bush used to call himself the decider as well, right? I mean, they're all the people who make the decisions. It's not always as consultative.
SPEAKER_0:  as you might think it is. And for Trump, it's like, I'm not listening to anybody at all.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just me and whatever it is that I'm walking up to today and I've decided to do.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think the problem with all of our systems is why we don't get results because we don't draw.
SPEAKER_0:  upon
SPEAKER_0:  the diversity of opinion and all the ideas of people out there. You do that in science.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, all my friends and relatives are in science. They've got these incredible collaborations with people across the world. I mean, how did we get to these vaccines?
SPEAKER_0:  for the COVID virus because of this incredible years of collaboration and of sharing results and sharing ideas and our whole system.
SPEAKER_0:  has become ossified.
SPEAKER_0:  We think about the congressional system, for example, as well, and there's this kind of rapid...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, turnover that you have in Congress every two years, you know, there's no incentive for people, you know, basically to work with others that constantly campaigning.
SPEAKER_0:  They're constantly trying to appeal to whatever their base is and they don't really care about.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, some do, you know, of their constituents, but a lot of people don't.
SPEAKER_0:  And the Senate, it's all kind of focused on the game of legislation.
SPEAKER_0:  for so many people as well.
SPEAKER_0:  focusing again on that kind of sense about what are we doing like scientists to kind of work together, you know, for the good of the country to push things along.
SPEAKER_0:  and also our government also is siloed.
SPEAKER_0:  there's not a lot of mechanisms for bringing people together. There ought to be, and things like the National Security Council, the National Intelligence Council actually did that quite successfully at times for analysis that I saw.
SPEAKER_0:  But we don't have, we have it within the National Institutes of Health, but we saw the CDC break down on this, you know, kind of front.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't have...
SPEAKER_0:  sufficient to those institutions that bring people together from all kinds of different backgrounds
SPEAKER_0:  and one of the other problems that we have with government.
SPEAKER_0:  with the federal government.
SPEAKER_0:  Over.
SPEAKER_0:  state and local government, it's actually quite small. People think that the federal government's huge.
SPEAKER_0:  because we've got postal service and the military that are part of it. But your actual...
SPEAKER_0:  federal government employees is a very small number.
SPEAKER_0:  And the senior executive service part of that is the older white guys, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of come up all the way over the last several decades.
SPEAKER_0:  We have a really hard time bringing in younger people.
SPEAKER_0:  into that kind of government service, unless they're political hacks, you know, and want to, you know, kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  or they're kind of looking for power and sort of influence.
SPEAKER_0:  We have a hard time getting people like yourself and other younger people kind of coming in.
SPEAKER_0:  to make a career out of public service and also retaining them.
SPEAKER_0:  because.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, people.
SPEAKER_0:  with incredible skills.
SPEAKER_0:  often get poached away into the private sector. And, you know, one of the people that I work with on the national security side are now at...
SPEAKER_0:  all kinds of.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, high end.
SPEAKER_0:  political consultancies or they've gone to Silicon Valley and they've gone to this place and that place.
SPEAKER_0:  Because after a time as a younger person, they're not rising up particularly quickly because there's a pretty rigid way of looking at the...
SPEAKER_0:  the hierarchies and the promotion schemes. And they're also getting lambasted by everybody. People like, ah, you know, public servants. They're not really public servants. There's this whole sentence that mesmo
SPEAKER_0:  Luck
SPEAKER_0:  and loss.
SPEAKER_0:  of a kind of a faith in public service.
SPEAKER_0:  And in the last few years, I've really done a lot of damage.
SPEAKER_0:  We need to revitalize.
SPEAKER_0:  our government system to get better results. We need to bring more people in, even if it's for a period of time, not just...
SPEAKER_0:  through.
SPEAKER_0:  expensive contracts for.
SPEAKER_0:  the big consulting companies and other...
SPEAKER_0:  entities that do government work out there, but getting people in for a period of time, responding to some of these.
SPEAKER_0:  management fellowships and
SPEAKER_0:  the White House fellows and bringing in scientists from the outside, giving that kind of opportunity police to help us solve the problem.
SPEAKER_0:  that we see in other spheres.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that's actually one of the biggest roles.
SPEAKER_1:  for president that.
SPEAKER_1:  for some reason during the election.
SPEAKER_1:  That's never talked about.
SPEAKER_1:  is how good are you at hiring?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. And in creating a culture of.
SPEAKER_1:  bike.
SPEAKER_1:  attracting the right, I mean basically chief hire.
SPEAKER_1:  When you think of a CEO.
SPEAKER_1:  like the great CEOs.
SPEAKER_1:  are.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe people don't talk about it that often, but they do more.
SPEAKER_1:  often.
SPEAKER_1:  for CEOs and they do for presidents is like, how good are your building?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, we make it really difficult because of the political process. I mean, and also because we have so many political appointments.
SPEAKER_0:  We ought to have less, to be honest. I mean, if you look at other governments around the world...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, they're just smaller.
SPEAKER_0:  it's much easier for them to hire people in.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, some of the most successful governments are much smaller.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's not that I say that the government is necessarily too big, but it's just thinking about each unit in a different way. We shouldn't be having so many political appointments.
SPEAKER_0:  We should kind of find more professional appointments, small lawn parties and appointments.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  every single administration that we've had over the last...
SPEAKER_0:  let's say span of presidencies, they have jobs that are unfulfilled.
SPEAKER_0:  because they can't get their candidates.
SPEAKER_0:  through Congress.
SPEAKER_0:  and the Senate.
SPEAKER_0:  because of all the kind of political games that are being played. I know loads of people have just been held up because it's just on the whim of some member of Congress.
SPEAKER_0:  even though that the actual position that they want is really technical.
SPEAKER_0:  doesn't really care about what you know what
SPEAKER_0:  political preference they particularly have. So I think we have to try to.
SPEAKER_0:  Look!
SPEAKER_0:  at the whole system of governments in the way that we would over, you know, other professional
SPEAKER_0:  sectors.
SPEAKER_0:  and to try to think about this as, just as you said there, that this is a government that's actually running our country.
SPEAKER_0:  This is an operating system and you wouldn't operate it like that if you were looking at anything else.
SPEAKER_0:  rational way. It shouldn't be so ideologically.
SPEAKER_0:  or partisan-tented.
SPEAKER_0:  So you're- At every level anyway. I'd actually just say make a bit for-
SPEAKER_0:  a more non-partisan approach to a lot of the parts of government. You can still kind of bring in the political and premature.
SPEAKER_0:  But also you have to explain to people writ large in America as well that this is your government.
SPEAKER_0:  And that actually you could also be part of this, things like the Small Business Administration, the U.S. Department of Agriculture, you know, all these kind of things that actually people...
SPEAKER_0:  interact with but they don't even know it, the postal service, you know, all of these things.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, people actually, when you ask them.
SPEAKER_0:  about different functions of government. They have a lot of support for it, the National Park Service, for example. It's just when you talk about government in an abstract way, like, oh, yeah, too much.
SPEAKER_0:  bloated, not efficient and effective, but if you kind of bring it down more to the kind of local and federal levels.
SPEAKER_0:  That's kind of, you know, when people really see it.
SPEAKER_0:  if people could see kind of themselves reflected.
SPEAKER_0:  and many of the people have gone into public service, I think that they would.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there needs to be. Support for it.
SPEAKER_1:  more like superstars like uh
SPEAKER_1:  individuals that are like...
SPEAKER_1:  Big on social media, big in the public eye.
SPEAKER_1:  and having fun with it and showing cool stuff that it's not.
SPEAKER_1:  Right now a lot of people see.
SPEAKER_1:  government as
SPEAKER_1:  basically partisan.
SPEAKER_1:  warfare and then
SPEAKER_1:  It just, it makes it unpleasant to do the job. It makes it uninspiring for people looking in from outside about what's going on, state government, all of it, the whole thing. But you are, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  With all due respect, you're pretty-
SPEAKER_1:  rare individual in terms of nonpartisanship. I did just actually your whole life story the the humbling aspect of.
SPEAKER_1:  of your upbringing and everything like that.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think it's possible to have a lot of nonpartisan?
SPEAKER_1:  experts.
SPEAKER_1:  government. Like, can you be
SPEAKER_1:  a top presidential advisor on Russia.
SPEAKER_1:  for 10 years.
SPEAKER_1:  for 15 years.
SPEAKER_1:  and remain nonpartisan.
SPEAKER_0:  I think you can. I don't think that's advisable, by the way, because I mean, I don't think anybody should be there. So you're forced to That's the right thing to do. Thank you.
SPEAKER_1:  Advice is to fire yourself after.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you should definitely have term limits, just like you should in everything, right? I mean, it's just like tenure in university. Well, we all have term limits. Yeah, you kind of, you know, we do, we have natural term limits, but you know, you're kind of, you know, basically bottling it up for other people.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm in out.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, what I'm trying to do now, I'm not.
SPEAKER_0:  57 now.
SPEAKER_0:  And I always try to work with, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  people from different generations to me, just like...
SPEAKER_0:  I've really benefited from these kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  mentorship of people older, you can mentor up and well and mentor down. I mean, I would.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, try to get people from different backgrounds and different generations to work together in teams. Honestly, I'd like to more.
SPEAKER_0:  team networked kind of approach to things. The kind of things that you get again in science, right?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, all these ideas are going to come from all kinds of different perspectives.
SPEAKER_0:  Age and experience does count for something.
SPEAKER_0:  but fresh ideas and coming in and looking at a problem from a different perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  and seeing something that somebody else hasn't seen before.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I just kind of love working in a.
SPEAKER_0:  an environment with.
SPEAKER_0:  all kinds of different people and people who don't agree with you. You need people.
SPEAKER_0:  take you on and say, absolute, that's crap. You know, kind of, where did you come up with that from? And they go, hang on.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, explain to me why you think so. And then, you know, you have this kind of iterative process back and forth. I mean, I would always encourage my colleagues to tell me when they thought it was wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, sometimes I didn't agree because I didn't see the...
SPEAKER_0:  the reasoning, but other times they're right.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, that was a complete mistake. I need to admit that and, you know, kind of, we need to figure out a different way of doing things. But the one point I do want to get across is there were a lot of people.
SPEAKER_0:  who were non-partisan that I worked with. I mean, honestly, in most of the jobs that I had, up until more recently, I had no idea about people's political affiliation.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just when you get into this kind of highly charged partisan environment...
SPEAKER_0:  They kind of force people to make decisions.
SPEAKER_0:  And when you have, you know, one...
SPEAKER_0:  political party or political faction that's trying to usurp power, it does make it quite difficult.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, that's the situation that we're in right now. And we're seeing some of the things happen in the United States. We're seeing some of the things that we're seeing in the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  and studied in other settings or seen for myself happening.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, when you have...
SPEAKER_0:  a president who wants to cling onto power.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you've gotta, you've gotta...
SPEAKER_0:  Call it out.
SPEAKER_0:  Is that a partisan act or is that a kind of defense of that larger?
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  political system.
SPEAKER_0:  that you're part of.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think we've got to...
SPEAKER_0:  recognize that
SPEAKER_0:  Even if you're not partisan, you can be politically engaged.
SPEAKER_0:  Sometimes you just have to stand up there and speak out, which is...
SPEAKER_0:  what I did and what others did as well. None of those people who spoke out can initially saw that as a partisan act, even if some of them since then have decided to make political choices they hadn't made before.
SPEAKER_0:  because the situation actually forced people into.
SPEAKER_0:  taking sides, very hard to still stay above the fray when you've got, you know, someone who's trying to perpetrate a coup.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, just a link on that.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's hard.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's the courageous thing to do.
SPEAKER_1:  to criticize the president.
SPEAKER_1:  and not
SPEAKER_1:  fall into partisanship after.
SPEAKER_1:  Because the whole world will assume.
SPEAKER_1:  If you criticize Donald Trump.
SPEAKER_1:  that you're clearly...
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh...
SPEAKER_1:  a Democrat.
SPEAKER_1:  And so they will.
SPEAKER_1:  everybody will criticize you for being a Democrat.
SPEAKER_1:  And then so you're now stuck in that. So you're going to just embrace that role.
SPEAKER_1:  but to still walk the nonpartisan route after the criticism, that's the hard road.
SPEAKER_1:  So not let the criticisms...
SPEAKER_1:  break you into a.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, in.
SPEAKER_1:  into a certain kind of ideological set of...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, our political system needs revitalization. We need to be taking a long, hard look at ourselves here. And I think what people are calling out for, look, there's a vast swath of the population like me who are unaffiliated.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, maybe some lean in one direction over another and...
SPEAKER_0:  Unaffiliated doesn't mean you don't have views about things and political opinions and you know you
SPEAKER_0:  I'm quite extreme on some of those.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, by the, from a left or right perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  What people are looking for is kind of an articulation.
SPEAKER_0:  things in a clear way that they can get a handle on.
SPEAKER_0:  and they're also looking for representation. Somebody's gonna be there for you.
SPEAKER_0:  You're not part of a kind of a rigid team that you're excluded from, you're the ins and the outs.
SPEAKER_0:  What people are looking at now, they're looking at that in the workplace because they're not finding that.
SPEAKER_0:  in politics.
SPEAKER_0:  you're actually getting workers pushing the people talk about the rise of the workers people just saying hang on a sec you know the most important
SPEAKER_0:  space than I'm in right now.
SPEAKER_0:  is my workplace because that's where my benefits are from. They're not coming from the state. I mean, that's a peculiarity of the United States system. You know, in Britain, you've got the National Health Service and you've got all the kind of national wide benefits.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you don't.
SPEAKER_0:  tethered to your employer like you are in the United States. But here now we're asking people.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, people are pushing.
SPEAKER_0:  for more representation, they're asking to be represented within their workplace.
SPEAKER_0:  be it Starbucks where various other Starbucks employees are trying to unionize.
SPEAKER_0:  We have unions among our research assistants, the Brookings Institution where I am, you know, kind of teaching assistants and big universities doing the same kind of thing as well.
SPEAKER_0:  because they won't have their voice heard.
SPEAKER_0:  They want to kind of play a larger role and they want to have change. And they're often pushing their companies or the institutions they work for to make that change because they don't see it happening.
SPEAKER_0:  in the political sphere.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's not just enough to go out there and protest in the street, but if you want something to happen...
SPEAKER_0:  That's why you're seeing big corporations playing a bigger role as well.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and of course there's...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, this is a longer discussion is also criticisms of that mechanisms of unions to achieve.
SPEAKER_1:  the giving of a voice.
SPEAKER_0:  This goes back to my own experience.
SPEAKER_0:  growing up in Northern England.
SPEAKER_0:  The Durham Miners.
SPEAKER_0:  that I was part of for generations.
SPEAKER_0:  Posting my family not in the mines on my dad's side.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  They created their own association. It wasn't a union per se at the very beginning. Later they became part of the National Miners Union. They lost their autonomy and independence as a result of that.
SPEAKER_0:  But what they did was they pulled their resources.
SPEAKER_0:  They set up their own parliament so they could all get together. Literally, they built a parliament.
SPEAKER_0:  and it opened in the same time as World War I and where they all got together because they didn't have the vote, they didn't have
SPEAKER_0:  suffrage at the time because they didn't have any money.
SPEAKER_0:  so they couldn't pay the tax and they couldn't run for Parliament.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is the kind of the origins of the organized labor parties later.
SPEAKER_0:  but they create this association so they could talk about how they could deal with things of their own communities.
SPEAKER_0:  and have a voice.
SPEAKER_0:  in the things that mattered.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, education, you know, improving their work conditions.
SPEAKER_0:  It wasn't like what you think about some kind of like big political trade union with, you know, left-wing, you know, kind of ideas. In fact, they actually tried to root out later after the Bolshevik Revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  in the Soviet Union, even when they were still having ties with players like the miners of Don Bass in the 1920s, Trotskyites and Leninists and communists.
SPEAKER_0:  they were more focused on how to improve.
SPEAKER_0:  their own.
SPEAKER_0:  well-being.
SPEAKER_0:  what they called the welfare, they had some welfare societies where they were kind of trying to think. linen cloth, everything that you make appears to be so fulfilled, but they didn't have
SPEAKER_0:  boosters in Starbucks mods.
SPEAKER_0:  or workers in Amazon.
SPEAKER_0:  They're looking about their own wellbeing. It's not just about pay and work conditions, it's about...
SPEAKER_0:  what it means to be part of this larger entity, because you're not feeling that same kind of connection.
SPEAKER_0:  to politics.
SPEAKER_0:  at the moment because you're being told by a representative, sorry I don't represent you because you didn't vote for me.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're not a Democrat, you're not Republican, you're not red, you're not blue.
SPEAKER_0:  You're not mine.
SPEAKER_0:  And so people say, well, I'm in this work class. This is kind of my collective.
SPEAKER_0:  This is therefore, this is what I'm going to have to try to push to make change.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is kind of happening here and we have to.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, realize that, you know, we've kind of gone and we're full circle back to that, you know, kind of period of the early...
SPEAKER_0:  emergence of sort of mass labor and you know the way that
SPEAKER_0:  That's where the political parties that we know today.
SPEAKER_0:  and the kind of early unions came out of as well, this sort of feeling of.
SPEAKER_0:  a mass society but where people weren't really.
SPEAKER_0:  able to.
SPEAKER_0:  get together and implement or push for change.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  with unions at a small scale and a local scale.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like every good idea.
SPEAKER_1:  on a small scale can.
SPEAKER_1:  become a bad idea on a large scale. Like, uh, marriage is a beautiful thing.
SPEAKER_1:  but at a large scale, it becomes the marriage industrial complex that tries to make money off of it, combined with the lawyers that try to make money off the divorce.
SPEAKER_1:  It just becomes this caricature of a thing.
SPEAKER_1:  or like Christmas and the holidays. It's like.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't disagree, but what I'm saying is people are basically looking for something here. This is why I myself start to think about much more local.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of solutions to a lot of these kind of problems. So again, the team network approach.
SPEAKER_1:  and the impeachment.
SPEAKER_1:  Looking back.
SPEAKER_1:  Excuse you.
SPEAKER_1:  part of it, you get to experience it.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think they strengthen or weaken?
SPEAKER_1:  this nation.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it weakened.
SPEAKER_0:  in many respects, just the way that it was conducted. I mean, there's a new book coming out by...
SPEAKER_0:  Couple of journalists in the Washington Post haven't actually seen it yet, but...
SPEAKER_0:  I really did kind of worry that.
SPEAKER_0:  myself that.
SPEAKER_0:  it became a spectacle.
SPEAKER_0:  And although it actually, I think, in many respects was important in terms of an exercise of civic responsibility and, you know, give people a big massive lesson in civics.
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone's kind of running out and looking up the whole process of impeachment and what that meant.
SPEAKER_0:  congressional prerogatives I was as well. I was running off myself and trying to learn an enormous amount about it because I was in the middle of all of this.
SPEAKER_0:  that it didn't ultimately show responsibility and accountability.
SPEAKER_0:  and that in itself was kind of was weakened because
SPEAKER_0:  on both sides there was a lot of parties on politics.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I think that there was a dereliction of duty.
SPEAKER_0:  in many respects.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, especially I have to say on the part of Republican members of Congress, who were, you know, kind of, they should have been embracing.
SPEAKER_0:  Congress's prerogatives. You could have kind of basically done this in a...
SPEAKER_0:  in something of a different way. But the whole thing-
SPEAKER_0:  is because it was this larger.
SPEAKER_0:  atmosphere.
SPEAKER_0:  of polarized.
SPEAKER_0:  not even polarised but fractured politics.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was deeply disappointed, I have to say, in many of the members.
SPEAKER_0:  of Congress on the Republican side. I mean, there's a lot of grandstanding that I really didn't like a bit on the Democratic side either.
SPEAKER_0:  and not admitting to mistakes and not addressing.
SPEAKER_0:  head on, you know, the fact that they'd.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of been pushing for Trump to be impeached and talking about being an illegitimate president kind of right from the very beginning.
SPEAKER_0:  And as a result of that, a lot of people just saw this as kind of a continuation of political games.
SPEAKER_0:  coming out of the...
SPEAKER_0:  2016 election.
SPEAKER_0:  But on the Republican side, it was just a game.
SPEAKER_0:  There was people I knew who were...
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, at one point, one of them winked at me.
SPEAKER_0:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, in the middle of this, you know, kind of impeachment, it's just like, don't take this personally. You know, this is, this is a game. And I just thought this isn't a game. And that's why I think that it, you know, kind of weakened because I mean, again, on the outside, it weakened us.
SPEAKER_0:  The whole process we can do is in the eyes of the world, because again, the United States was the gold standard.
SPEAKER_0:  And I do think, again, in terms of the larger population, although a lot of people...
SPEAKER_0:  We did actually see the system standing up, trying to do something to help people at camp, but there still was that.
SPEAKER_0:  element of circus.
SPEAKER_0:  and a big political game.
SPEAKER_0:  and people have been careless with the country.
SPEAKER_1:  I do think that the Democrats...
SPEAKER_1:  were the instigators of the circus.
SPEAKER_1:  as a
SPEAKER_1:  It's perhaps subtle.
SPEAKER_1:  but there's a different way you talk about.
SPEAKER_1:  issues or concerns about accountability.
SPEAKER_1:  when you care about.
SPEAKER_1:  your country when you love your country when you love the ideals and when you
SPEAKER_1:  versus when you just want to
SPEAKER_0:  win. And stick it to the other side. I agree. I mean, there were people who I actually thought
SPEAKER_0:  Manage that?
SPEAKER_0:  that made it about the country rather than about themselves. And there were others who did. I took to do that.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there were a lot of others who did a lot of grandstanding.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's another problem of our political incentive structures, that the kind of sense of accountability and responsibility tends to be.
SPEAKER_0:  personal, you know, whether people decide to do it or not. It's not institutional.
SPEAKER_0:  if that makes sense. We've had a kind of a breakdown of that kind of, that sense. Until then, thank you for watching and we'll see you next time.
SPEAKER_0:  and I'm assuming that most of them did too.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I had to be sworn in.
SPEAKER_0:  when I took those positions, I took that seriously, but I already took an oath of citizenship.
SPEAKER_0:  There's, you know, presumably you did too, you know, you kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  started to become an American citizen. It's not something you take unlikely.
SPEAKER_0:  And, you know, that's why I felt this deep sense of responsibility all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  which is why I went into the administration in the first place. I got a lot of flack for it.
SPEAKER_0:  because I thought, well, look, I've been asked.
SPEAKER_0:  and there's a real issue here after the Russian
SPEAKER_0:  interference and the influence operation in the 2016 elections and I knew what was going on.
SPEAKER_0:  and I should do something.
SPEAKER_0:  If not me, then okay, someone else will go and do it, but can I live with myself just sitting on the sidelines and criticizing what people are doing?
SPEAKER_0:  you know, and kind of, you know, worrying about this, or am I actually gonna muck in there and, you know, just go and do something? It's like seeing your house on fire.
SPEAKER_0:  and you say that, you know, okay, this is pretty awful and dangerous, but I could go in there and do something.
SPEAKER_1:  To clarify the...
SPEAKER_1:  house on fire meaning.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... the cyber war going on a cyber attacks
SPEAKER_0:  Well in 2016, you know, when the Russians had interfered in the election.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, basically, this was a huge national security.
SPEAKER_0:  prices.
SPEAKER_0:  and our politics we'd gone mad as a result of it.
SPEAKER_0:  and in fact we were making the situation worse.
SPEAKER_0:  And I felt that I could, you know, kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  at the time, maybe I could do something here. I could try to clarify, I could...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, work with others who I knew in the government from previous stints in the government.
SPEAKER_0:  to push back against this and try to make sure it didn't happen again. Look, and I also didn't have this.
SPEAKER_0:  mad, crazy ideological view of Russia either. I mean, I knew the place, I knew the people had been studying it a long time and quite calm about it. I don't take it personally.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not kind of an extension of self.
SPEAKER_0:  It's something I've spent a long time trying to understand for myself, going back to that very beginning of why were the Russians trying to blow us up?
SPEAKER_0:  There must be an explanation. There was, it was a very complicated and complex explanation. It wasn't as simple as-
SPEAKER_0:  how it sounded.
SPEAKER_0:  And also there's a long tail.
SPEAKER_0:  to 2016.
SPEAKER_0:  in a Putin's perceptions, the kind of things that he thought were going on.
SPEAKER_0:  the whole way that...
SPEAKER_0:  What they did was actually...
SPEAKER_0:  fairly straightforward. They'd done this before in the Soviet period during the Cold War, classic influence operation. It just did.
SPEAKER_0:  gone beyond the bounds of anything they could have anticipated because of social media and just
SPEAKER_0:  a confluence of circumstances in the United States as well.
SPEAKER_0:  We were very fragile and vulnerable.
SPEAKER_0:  And I remember at one point having a discussion with the Russian ambassador.
SPEAKER_0:  where, you know, we were.
SPEAKER_0:  complaining about the Russian intervention, he said.
SPEAKER_0:  Are you telling me that the United States is a banana republic, that it's so vulnerable to these kinds of efforts and you're actually like genuinely mystified?
SPEAKER_0:  Although obviously it was probably part of a...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of political.
SPEAKER_0:  schtick there, but he had a point.
SPEAKER_0:  The United States had never been that vulnerable as it suddenly was in 2016.
SPEAKER_0:  and in the time that I was in government.
SPEAKER_0:  going back to what you asked about the whole impeachment and the...
SPEAKER_0:  whole exercise in Congress.
SPEAKER_0:  That vulnerability was as stark as it, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  ever could be. Our domestic politics were...
SPEAKER_0:  as much a part of the problem as anything else. They were the kindling to all of the fires. Putin didn't.
SPEAKER_0:  start any of this.
SPEAKER_0:  other kind of problems domestically just took advantage of them.
SPEAKER_0:  And, you know, basically...
SPEAKER_0:  added a bit of an accelerant here and there.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, the interference, I mean, that's a much longer discussion.
SPEAKER_1:  because it's also for me, technically fascinating.
SPEAKER_1:  I've been playing with the idea of just launching like a million bots, but they're doing just positive stuff and just being kind.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I was kind of wondering if it is possible to do something on this skill that's positive because you know a lot of people seem to be able to use all of this for pretty negative effect. I hope that you could do this use the same networks for positive.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that's actually where a lot of the war
SPEAKER_1:  I think from the original...
SPEAKER_1:  hackers to today.
SPEAKER_1:  what gives people like me and I think a lot of people that.
SPEAKER_1:  in the hacking community pleasure is to do something difficult.
SPEAKER_1:  Break through the systems.
SPEAKER_1:  and do the ethical thing.
SPEAKER_1:  So do the...
SPEAKER_1:  Because...
SPEAKER_1:  if there's something broken about the system.
SPEAKER_1:  You want to...
SPEAKER_1:  break through all the rules.
SPEAKER_1:  and do something that you know in your heart is the right thing to do.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's what Karen Schwartz did with releasing.
SPEAKER_1:  journals and publications.
SPEAKER_1:  that were behind paywalls to the public and got arrested for it and they committed. But to me it's fascinating because I.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe you can actually educate me, but...
SPEAKER_1:  I felt that the Russian interference...
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of social engineering, in terms of bots, all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like that was more used for political bickering.
SPEAKER_1:  and to actually understand the national security problem.
SPEAKER_1:  because...
SPEAKER_1:  I would like to know the actual numbers involved in the influence. I would like to, I mean, obviously, hopefully people now understand that better.
SPEAKER_1:  that are trying to defend the national security.
SPEAKER_1:  of this country, but it just, it felt like.
SPEAKER_1:  Like for example, if I launch one bot.
SPEAKER_1:  And then.
SPEAKER_1:  and then just contact somebody at the New York Times saying I launched this one bot they'll just say
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhhh...
SPEAKER_1:  MIT scientists.
SPEAKER_1:  packs, you know, and then that
SPEAKER_0:  And they'll spread. But that's exactly what happened.
SPEAKER_0:  It was, you know, kind of, I think that...
SPEAKER_0:  We're a Putin and-
SPEAKER_0:  some of the people around him.
SPEAKER_0:  Understood because
SPEAKER_0:  again, propaganda state.
SPEAKER_0:  They spend an awful lot of time thinking about how you, you know, basically put out your own content.
SPEAKER_0:  and how you get maximum effect.
SPEAKER_0:  through performance. Putin himself is a political pop performance artist.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, Trump understood exactly the same thing. So actually,
SPEAKER_0:  operating in parallel, not in collusion, but in parallel. You know, basically Trump understood how to get lots of free air time, how to get himself at the center of attention.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin did that through a less organic way. He had a lot of people working around him. I mean, that's the old Bolshevik agitprop and kind of then the whole Soviet propaganda machine.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin kind of growing up in that kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  environment and having the Kremlin press office and all the people around him, got kind of a massive machine.
SPEAKER_0:  how did that work? I mean, they haven't done what the Chinese did in Russia of like blocking everything and having a big firewall. So it's kind of putting out lots of content, getting into the sort of center of attention.
SPEAKER_0:  Trump's doing the same kind of thing.
SPEAKER_0:  And the Russians understood that, you know, if you...
SPEAKER_0:  a bit of things out there and then you call up New York Times and people are going to run with it.
SPEAKER_0:  and what they wanted was the perception.
SPEAKER_0:  that they had actually sweared the election. They loved it. This was the huge mistake of the Democrats and everything. I kept trying to push against this.
SPEAKER_0:  No, they did not elect Donald Trump.
SPEAKER_0:  Americans elected.
SPEAKER_0:  Donald Trump and the electoral college.
SPEAKER_0:  was a key part.
SPEAKER_0:  Vladimir Putin didn't make that up.
SPEAKER_0:  And basically I also remember at one point the...
SPEAKER_0:  Russian ambassador.
SPEAKER_0:  talking to me about when we were doing this standard, you know, here we are, we're lodging our complaints about the interference, you know, he basically said...
SPEAKER_0:  or we didn't kind of invent.
SPEAKER_0:  Call me.
SPEAKER_0:  and basically the decision to reopen.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, Hillary Clinton's emails.
SPEAKER_0:  or Anthony Weiner and his...
SPEAKER_0:  emails on his computer.
SPEAKER_0:  Yep.
SPEAKER_0:  He's right. I mean, you know, there were plenty of things in our own system.
SPEAKER_0:  that created chaos.
SPEAKER_0:  and tip the election.
SPEAKER_0:  not kind of what the Russians did, but it's obviously easier to blame the Russians than blame yourself when
SPEAKER_0:  you know, things are kind of all those random forces and those random factors.
SPEAKER_0:  because people couldn't understand what had happened.
SPEAKER_0:  in.
SPEAKER_0:  2016, there was no hanging chats like 2000 where there was a technical...
SPEAKER_0:  problem that actually ended up with the intervention of the Supreme Court.
SPEAKER_0:  There was, you know, pure and simple, the electoral college at work.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  a candidate that nobody expected, including the Republicans in the primaries.
SPEAKER_0:  to end up getting elected or put forward in a different 2016, suddenly becoming the president.
SPEAKER_0:  and they needed a meta explanation.
SPEAKER_0:  It was much better to say Vladimir Putin had done it and Vladimir Putin and the Kremlin guys were like, oh my god, yeah, fantastic.
SPEAKER_0:  Champagne cup.
SPEAKER_0:  Pop-Corks popping, this is great, our Chaos Agent. They knew they hadn't done it, but they'd love to take credit for it.
SPEAKER_0:  And so, you know, the very fact that other people couldn't explain these...
SPEAKER_0:  complex dynamics themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  especially dovetails beautifully.
SPEAKER_0:  with Vladimir Putin's.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  attempts to be the kind of the crumbling, grumbling in the system.
SPEAKER_0:  And he basically was taking advantage of that forevermore. And I wanted to basically try to...
SPEAKER_0:  work with us to cut through that. And the thing is then, you know, people lost faith in the integrity of the election system because people were out there, you know, suggesting that the Russians had actually to start the elections, people written books about that. who said.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, that they hacked the system when, you know, they were trying to hack our minds.
SPEAKER_0:  But again...
SPEAKER_0:  we were the fertile soul for this. I mean, we know this from Russian history, the Bolsheviks, you know, the whole.
SPEAKER_0:  1920s and 1930s with Stalin, the fellow travelers and the socialist.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, international. I mean, the Russians and the Soviets have been at this for years about kind of pulling, you know, kind of people along and into kind of a broader frame, but it didn't mean...
SPEAKER_0:  that they were influencing.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, directly the politics of...
SPEAKER_0:  of countries writ large, there's plenty of interventions. It's just that we were somehow.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a confluence of events, a perfect storm. We were somehow.
SPEAKER_0:  exquisitely vulnerable because of things.
SPEAKER_0:  that we had.
SPEAKER_0:  done to ourselves. It was what Americans were doing to themselves that was the issue.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the bigger threat.
SPEAKER_1:  than large-scale bot armies.
SPEAKER_0:  Those can be, obviously they do have an impact, but it's how people process information. It's kind of like the lack of critical thinking. I'm just not on the internet to that extent. I'd go looking for information. I'm not on social media.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm into social media, but not by myself. I don't put myself out there. I haven't got a Twitter feed. I don't have a Twitter feed.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, but there is a.
SPEAKER_0:  I have all kinds of strange things. It's Fiona Hill's cat, which I kind of like, you know, occasionally have people send things to me. You have so many fans, it's hilarious. But what I try to do is just be really critical. I mean, my mom sends me stuff and I'm like, what is this?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just, you know, your own mother can be as much of an agent of misinformation as, you know, kind of Vladimir Putin. Oh, yeah. We all, you know, kind of, we all have to really think.
SPEAKER_0:  about what it is we're reading. There's one thing from my childhood that was...
SPEAKER_0:  really important, I mean I always think every...
SPEAKER_0:  KJN schools should have this.
SPEAKER_0:  my next door neighbour.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  who were was.
SPEAKER_0:  He was actually very active in the Labour Party.
SPEAKER_0:  And he was kind of really interested in the way that opinion.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, shape people's political views. He was Welsh, he was a native Welsh speaker. So, you know, he was always trying to explore English and how, you know, there was kind of the reach of.
SPEAKER_0:  You know what I think?
SPEAKER_0:  English culture and how it was shaping the way that people thought. And he used to read every single newspaper.
SPEAKER_0:  from all the different spectrums, which was quite easy to do back in the 70s and 80s because there weren't that many in the UK context.
SPEAKER_0:  And every Sunday, he would get all the different Sunday papers from all the different kind of ideological vantage points.
SPEAKER_0:  And then when I got to be a teenager, he'd invite me to look at them with him.
SPEAKER_0:  Because he was my godfather and he was just an incredible guy.
SPEAKER_0:  And he was just super interesting and culturally an outsider, always kind of looking in.
SPEAKER_0:  And he basically ran through what the guardian looked at, the observer, the Daily Mail, the sun.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of all of these, you know, the telegraph.
SPEAKER_0:  all of these newspapers and...
SPEAKER_0:  how you could tell.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, they're different vantage points.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course, it's complicated to do that now. I mean, in this, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Fredably.
SPEAKER_0:  extensive media space.
SPEAKER_0:  I look at what it is that they're saying.
SPEAKER_0:  And then I tried to.
SPEAKER_0:  read around it and then look at what other people are saying and why they're saying it and who are they, what's their context.
SPEAKER_0:  And that was kind of basically what I was taught to look at.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think everybody should have that.
SPEAKER_1:  And certainly that's something that people in politics that are in charge of.
SPEAKER_1:  directing policy should be doing. They should be. They're not getting lost.
SPEAKER_1:  in the sort of the hysteria.
SPEAKER_1:  that can be created.
SPEAKER_1:  It does seem that the American system somehow, not the political system, just humans.
SPEAKER_1:  Love drama.
SPEAKER_1:  Very good.
SPEAKER_1:  like the Hunter Biden laptop story. There's always like.
SPEAKER_1:  One, two, three stories, somehow.
SPEAKER_1:  that we just pick that we're just gonna, this is the stuff we're gonna.
SPEAKER_1:  fight about.
SPEAKER_1:  for this election.
SPEAKER_0:  And everyone's got an opinion on it. Everybody.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's the most important like Hillary Clinton's emails.
SPEAKER_1:  Russians hacked the election.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, we had John Podesta's pasta recipes for a while.
SPEAKER_0:  that we were kind of all obsessing over. I don't know, people running out and trying them out, you know, something like that.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's fun, I mean, there's all the best.
SPEAKER_1:  conspiracy theories about Giuliani. There's I just love it. We just pick a random story. Sometimes it's ridiculous.
SPEAKER_0:  And it detracts from what the larger question should be, which is about the family members of senior officials and whether they should be anywhere near any of the issues that they're
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there's ethics, there's government ethics and things there.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of across the board. But there's a bigger story in there, but that becomes a distraction. It's a luck over there.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, the oldest trick in the book, you know, kind of idea.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, and politicians are really good at that because it detracts from the larger question because every single member of Congress and...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, government officials, their family should be nowhere near anything they're doing.
SPEAKER_1:  With that, I could-
SPEAKER_1:  push back and disagree on. i-i mean
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it depends on what they do, if they're making money out of it. You know, and kind of basically being in business is what I mean. You know, kind of this is an issue. So it's not, you know...
SPEAKER_0:  Hunter Biden.
SPEAKER_0:  on his own, it's kind of basically the kids of the Trump family, you name it.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, in general like that, I just think.
SPEAKER_1:  It's funny, like, there's a lot of families that...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, they work very closely together, do business together and it's very successful.
SPEAKER_1:  I get very weird about that.
SPEAKER_1:  It just feels like you're not.
SPEAKER_1:  In fact, I don't even like hiring.
SPEAKER_1:  or working with friends.
SPEAKER_1:  Initially you make friends with the people you work
SPEAKER_0:  That's right. No, I have the same worries as well because in the kind of clouds, you know, I would encourage, you know, my daughter to do something completely different.
SPEAKER_0:  Right. Not going to the same field. It's different if you're-
SPEAKER_0:  you know, in science or...
SPEAKER_0:  mathematics or something like this and maybe you've got a family member, you're kind of building on some of their theories and ideas. If Albert Einstein had a...
SPEAKER_0:  kind of an offspring who was in mathematics and took as far as thinking further. That would be very different.
SPEAKER_0:  But if it's kind of you're in business and other things, then it's just, you know, it's the nepotism problem.
SPEAKER_0:  that no one has there.
SPEAKER_1:  That says that too.
SPEAKER_0:  in a space of ideas. Yeah, that's what they do if they're not people aren't coming in and building on the ideas in a constructive way.
SPEAKER_1:  Right, but even for...
SPEAKER_1:  SON DAUGHTER WEINSTEIN
SPEAKER_1:  You wanna.
SPEAKER_1:  think outside the box of the previous.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what I'm meaning, but they shouldn't be sort of told, no, sorry, you can't go and study math or whatever, physics, because of...
SPEAKER_1:  But a lot of that you can't actually make it into law. Well, you could, I suppose, but honestly...
SPEAKER_1:  If you do that kind of thing, you should be transparent. There should be just an honesty.
SPEAKER_0:  It gets back to what I was talking about before, we need diversity of views and diversity of thinking and you can't have other things. It's just like being partisan or, you know, blah, blah, blah.
SPEAKER_0:  rooting just for a team.
SPEAKER_0:  if something is going to cloud your judgment.
SPEAKER_0:  or constrain the way you think about things and become.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of a barrier to...
SPEAKER_0:  moving on out. Look, that's what we see in the system around Putin.
SPEAKER_0:  It's kind of kleptocratic and it's...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it's filled with nepotism.
SPEAKER_0:  all of the kind of like the people who you kind of see out there and prominent positions that the sons or daughters of.
SPEAKER_0:  including Putin himself.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, that's when a system has degenerated.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's kind of, and I suppose in a way, this is a symbol of the degeneration of the system, but again, it's just a diversion from, kind of the bigger issues and bigger implications of.
SPEAKER_0:  things that we're discussing.
SPEAKER_1:  So critics on the left.
SPEAKER_1:  often use the straw man of TDS, charmathovenger syndrome major encephal arabic
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  Why does Donald Trump arouse so much emotion in people?
SPEAKER_0:  It's just the nature of the person. I mean, I don't feel particularly emotional about him.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, he's kind of a...
SPEAKER_0:  He's a very flawed guy, to be honest.
SPEAKER_0:  and this made me seem bizarre, I felt sorry for him.
SPEAKER_0:  Because this guy is so vulnerable.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  wrapped up in himself?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, he's just exquisitely.
SPEAKER_0:  open to manipulation. And I saw people taking advantage of him all the time. He has zero self-awareness.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I kept thinking to myself, my God, if this guy didn't have this entourage around him.
SPEAKER_0:  How would he function?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I felt sorry for us as well. I mean, that he ended up being our president because that should not have happened. I mean, in terms of character.
SPEAKER_0:  and in terms of fit for the job. Although I saw this kind of over a period of time, but I didn't feel kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  any.
SPEAKER_0:  bit of.
SPEAKER_0:  sense of derangement, you know, kind of around him. He didn't drive me nuts in that way. I just became, I was just very worried about.
SPEAKER_0:  the kind of the impact that he was having.
SPEAKER_0:  on many particular issues.
SPEAKER_1:  Here's the important
SPEAKER_1:  So what I notice is people that criticize Donald Trump
SPEAKER_1:  is.
SPEAKER_1:  they get caught up.
SPEAKER_1:  in the momentum of it.
SPEAKER_1:  and they're unable to see.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  First of all, let's start with some ground truth, which is.
SPEAKER_1:  approximately.
SPEAKER_1:  half the country.
SPEAKER_1:  voted for the guy.
SPEAKER_0:  and more voted.
SPEAKER_0:  in 2020, then voted in 2016 for it.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  I just feel like people don't load that in when they're.
SPEAKER_0:  mère
SPEAKER_0:  Didn't vote for it.
SPEAKER_0:  him and his personality and often could because I know a lot of people who voted for him.
SPEAKER_0:  first time and second time.
SPEAKER_0:  and they could disassociate.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of the...
SPEAKER_0:  all of the kind of features of Donald Trump that drives other people nuts from, you know, what they thought that an actual fact he could achieve in terms of, and it wasn't just this kind of sense about, well, I couldn't possibly vote for Democrats.
SPEAKER_0:  Sometimes it's just like.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, lucky sheik sings up.
SPEAKER_0:  and we need things to be shaken up.
SPEAKER_1:  Some people might have voted for a person out. See this one's friends
SPEAKER_0:  Some of them did as well, but I'm just saying that not all of them did either. Well, we don't know their data. That's the thing. But yeah, I can't say how much it is. I'm just saying anecdotally, I know people have voted for him because he's him, from the charisma and others who voted.
SPEAKER_0:  because he's shaking things up and he's keeping people.
SPEAKER_0:  on their toes and...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of we need that idea.
SPEAKER_1:  but the way to avoid...
SPEAKER_1:  Trump DeRangement Syndrome.
SPEAKER_1:  to me.
SPEAKER_1:  Me as a doctor, I'm sort of prescribing to the patients.
SPEAKER_1:  on this syndrome.
SPEAKER_1:  this issue.
SPEAKER_1:  is I feel like you have to empathize.
SPEAKER_1:  with the people. You have to imagine your mind all the difference.
SPEAKER_1:  like.
SPEAKER_1:  Strengths.
SPEAKER_1:  that the people who have voted for Donald Trump see.
SPEAKER_1:  and really understand it.
SPEAKER_1:  really feel it, like walk around with it.
SPEAKER_1:  and then criticize.
SPEAKER_1:  I just feel like people get lost in this bubble of criticism in their own head. I forget like the tribe you're in or whatever in their own head. They're not able to see.
SPEAKER_1:  like half this country that we're a part of.
SPEAKER_1:  Voters for the person.
SPEAKER_1:  Same with Biden.
SPEAKER_1:  Half the country voted for the guy.
SPEAKER_1:  The people that are criticizing Biden and they're doing this.
SPEAKER_1:  The way-
SPEAKER_1:  Biden is currently criticized.
SPEAKER_1:  is not based on policy.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, is based on personal stuff, similar like the Trump.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I know it is. I mean, that's what people don't look. I think part of that is...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, first of all, I want to say I completely agree with you about understanding where people are coming from. I think it's very important for people to listen.
SPEAKER_0:  to other people and their views. I try to do that all the time, try to learn from that.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, everybody's got a perspective and a context. We all live in a certain context. We're all living in history, our own personal histories.
SPEAKER_0:  matter a lot and also the larger context and environment in which we're living in.
SPEAKER_0:  and where we live.
SPEAKER_0:  and who we live with.
SPEAKER_0:  and the kinds of lives that we lead as well. Those are all extraordinarily important. I mean, I know that from myself. Everything that I've done in my life has been shaped by where I came from.
SPEAKER_0:  who I was, my family, and the way that we looked at things. You can't take yourself out of that.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, you can do it in some, you know, like a science or something else, but you know, it's still your own views and maybe some of the ideas that you have in pursuing an experiment might have been shaped by your larger context, you know, depending on what it is that you work on.
SPEAKER_0:  But the other thing is the nature of the political system.
SPEAKER_0:  The.
SPEAKER_0:  Presidential election is like...
SPEAKER_0:  a personality contest, a beauty contest.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like a kind of a referendum on one person or another.
SPEAKER_0:  It's kind of like what we see in Russia on the sea with, you know, pooping on a pooping up.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin and
SPEAKER_0:  before.
SPEAKER_0:  It's all about Putin and what do you think about Putin? It's all about—
SPEAKER_0:  what the president should be doing.
SPEAKER_0:  and you know kind of what their policies are.
SPEAKER_0:  That's kind of the bizzare-ness.
SPEAKER_0:  of the US.
SPEAKER_0:  Look, we've just seen this happening in the United Kingdom.
SPEAKER_0:  You've got this core of a couple of thousand, a couple of hundred thousand, rather, people in the Conservative Party have just voted for...
SPEAKER_0:  free.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  The lead is in a row.
SPEAKER_0:  the rest of the country isn't and they're just looking at whether they like that personality and you know what they say to them rather than what they're necessarily going to do for the country.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, which is kind of pretty absurd. And again, the presidency is a weird...
SPEAKER_0:  hybrid in the United States. You know, we were talking before about, it's the person who should be running the country, it's the chief executive or the prime minister in another setting, but we don't think of it like that.
SPEAKER_0:  We often think about whether we like the guy or not, or we'd like to hang out with him or that.
SPEAKER_0:  One of my younger relatives and I said, so why did you vote for Trump? He said, well, he was great. He was funny. I went to his rallies. I got, you know, all kind of charged up.
SPEAKER_0:  And I said, could you see yourself voting for Biden? No, he's too old. Let somebody know he's only just a little bit.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  older than Trump.
SPEAKER_0:  always.
SPEAKER_0:  the same age as your grandma. Do you think your grandma's old? Oh no, not at all. But it's just this kind of perception is boring.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, so there's people are actually sometimes, you know, basically being.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  motivated by just a feeling, you know, kind of that kind of sense, because that's the sort of nature of the
SPEAKER_0:  the presidency. It's this kind of
SPEAKER_0:  how you feel about yourself as an American, or how you feel about the country writ large, kind of the symbol of the state.
SPEAKER_0:  Look, you know, in Britain you had Queen Elizabeth II and everybody.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, seem to, for the most part.
SPEAKER_0:  I guess, but most people respected her.
SPEAKER_0:  as a person, as a personality, as a symbol of the state, even if they actually didn't really like it.
SPEAKER_0:  the institution of the monarchy.
SPEAKER_0:  There was something kind of about that.
SPEAKER_0:  particular personality.
SPEAKER_0:  that you were able to.
SPEAKER_0:  you don't kind of relate to in that context. But I mean, the United States, we've got all of that rolled into one, the head of state, the symbol of the state, the kind of queen, the king, the kind of idea.
SPEAKER_0:  the chief executive, the kind of prime ministerial role, and then the commander in chief of the military. It's all things kind of at once.
SPEAKER_0:  But ultimately for a lot of people it's just how you feel about that person. Oh I couldn't cover up for them because of this or I couldn't cover up for them because of that.
SPEAKER_0:  And in 2016...
SPEAKER_0:  I know Hillary Clinton actually did win the election in terms of the popular vote.
SPEAKER_0:  So it wasn't that people wouldn't vote for a woman. More people voted for her.
SPEAKER_0:  on the popular level, not obviously through the electoral college and the electoral college vote so
SPEAKER_0:  It wasn't just gender or something like that, but it was an awful lot of things for people.
SPEAKER_0:  Trump attractive.
SPEAKER_0:  Because he was-
SPEAKER_0:  sticking up the big middle finger to the establishment.
SPEAKER_0:  He's an anti-establishment change character. There was a lot of people voted for Barack Obama for the same reason and voted for Trump. We know that phenomenon. What was the 11, 12% of people?
SPEAKER_0:  so they could vote for some completely, totally different, radically different people because that's that sense of change and charisma.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I had people who I knew voted for Trump, but would have voted for Obama again if he'd run again.
SPEAKER_0:  because they've just...
SPEAKER_0:  the way that he spoke, the way that, you know, because they said...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, this is all my own anecdotal things, doing about one of my relatives said, I could listen to Obama all day, every day. I just love the way he sounded. I love the way he looked. You know, I just like the whole thing about him. And then say about Trump, well, he was exciting. He was interesting. You know, he was kind of like, you know, whipping it up there.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, so there's this, just this kind of feeling.
SPEAKER_0:  We always say about, could you have a beer with this person?
SPEAKER_0:  and people decide they couldn't have one with Hillary Clinton.
SPEAKER_0:  and you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe they could go off and have one with-
SPEAKER_0:  Barack Obama.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  with Donald Trump.
SPEAKER_0:  She's gonna have moment.
SPEAKER_0:  Joe Biden, you know, for example.
SPEAKER_0:  remember George W Bush didn't drink so he wouldn't have had a beer with him. He'd have gone out and got a soda or something with him.
SPEAKER_0:  But you know, there's this...
SPEAKER_0:  There's that kind of element of just that sort of personal connection in the way that the whole presidential...
SPEAKER_0:  election is set up. It's less about the parties.
SPEAKER_0:  It's less about the platform, it's more about the person.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and picking one side and like sticking with your person. I really like a sport team. Yeah, it is.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think about Vladimir Putin?
SPEAKER_1:  The man and the leader.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's actually look at the full.
SPEAKER_1:  You've written a lot about him, the recent Vladimir Putin and the full context of his life.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Let's zoom out and look at the last 20 plus years of his rule.
SPEAKER_1:  In what ways has he been good for Russia?
SPEAKER_1:  in what ways bad.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, if you look to the first...
SPEAKER_0:  couple of terms.
SPEAKER_0:  of his presidency. I think, you know, on the...
SPEAKER_0:  of.
SPEAKER_0:  overall ledger, you would have actually said that he'd
SPEAKER_0:  made a lot of achievements from Russia. Now there was of course the pretty
SPEAKER_0:  black period of the war in Chechnya, but he didn't start that. That was Boris Yeltsin.
SPEAKER_0:  That was obviously a pretty...
SPEAKER_0:  catastrophic.
SPEAKER_0:  event, but if you look at then other parts of the ledge of what Putin was doing.
SPEAKER_0:  from the 2000s onwards.
SPEAKER_0:  he stabilized the Russian economy.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  brought back confidence.
SPEAKER_0:  and the Russian economy and financial system.
SPEAKER_0:  He built up a pretty impressive.
SPEAKER_0:  team of technocrats.
SPEAKER_0:  for everything from the central bank and the economics and finance ministries.
SPEAKER_0:  who really got the country back into shape again and solvent.
SPEAKER_0:  paid off all of the debts?
SPEAKER_0:  and really started to...
SPEAKER_0:  build the country back up again domestically.
SPEAKER_0:  And the first couple of terms, again, putting Chechnya to one side, which was a little hard because I mean there was...
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of atrocities and...
SPEAKER_0:  I have to say that he was pretty involved in all of that because...
SPEAKER_0:  the FSB which you'd had previously.
SPEAKER_0:  it was in charge of wrapping up Chechnya and it created a very strange sort of system of fealty almost a feudal system.
SPEAKER_0:  and the kind of relationship between.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin at the top and Kadirov in Chechnya and there was quite a lot of distortions, you know, kind of as a result of that in the way that the Russian Federation was run.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot more of an emphasis on the
SPEAKER_0:  security services, for example, but there was a lot of pragmatism in opening up the country for business.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, basically extending relationships.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say that, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  by the end of those.
SPEAKER_0:  first couple of terms of Putin, Russians were living their best lives.
SPEAKER_0:  But there was a lot of opportunity for people.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... people's labor that was being
SPEAKER_0:  paid for, they weren't being taxed, the taxes were coming out of the extractive industries.
SPEAKER_0:  there was a sense of much more political pluralism.
SPEAKER_0:  It wasn't the chaos of the Eltsin period.
SPEAKER_0:  and then you see a shift.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's pretty much when he comes back into power again.
SPEAKER_0:  in 2011, 2012.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's when we see a kind of a different phase emerging.
SPEAKER_0:  And part of it is the larger international environment where Putin himself has become kind of convinced that the United States is out to get him.
SPEAKER_0:  A part of it goes back to...
SPEAKER_0:  the decision.
SPEAKER_0:  on the part of the United States who invaded Iraq in 2003.
SPEAKER_0:  There's also the recognition of Kosovo in 2008 and the whole kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  machinations around all kinds of other issues of native expansion and elsewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  Iraq in 2003 and this kind of whole idea after that that the United States is in the business of regime change.
SPEAKER_0:  and perhaps has him in his crosshairs as well.
SPEAKER_0:  But there's also then kind of, I think, a sense of building crisis.
SPEAKER_0:  after the financial crisis.
SPEAKER_0:  and the Great Recession.
SPEAKER_0:  2008-2009 because
SPEAKER_0:  I think Putin up until then believed in.
SPEAKER_0:  the whole idea is a global financial system and that Russia was...
SPEAKER_0:  Prospering.
SPEAKER_0:  and that Russia, part of the G8, actually could be genuinely one of the major...
SPEAKER_0:  economic and financial powers.
SPEAKER_0:  And then suddenly he realizes that...
SPEAKER_0:  in the West is incompetent.
SPEAKER_0:  that we totally mismanaged the economy of our own, the financial crash in the United States. They're kind of blowing up of the...
SPEAKER_0:  of the housing bubble.
SPEAKER_0:  and that we were feckless.
SPEAKER_0:  and that had global reverberations.
SPEAKER_0:  And he's prime minister, of course, in this kind of period.
SPEAKER_0:  But then, you know, I think that that kind of compels him to kind of come back into the presidency and try to kind of
SPEAKER_0:  take things under control again in 2007, 2012 and after that...
SPEAKER_0:  he goes into kind of a much more sort of focused role where he sees the United States as a bigger problem.
SPEAKER_0:  And he also...
SPEAKER_0:  and it starts to...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of focus on also the domestic environment because his return to the presidency is met by protests and he genuinely seems to believe, because again, this is very similar to...
SPEAKER_0:  belief here in the United States that Donald Trump couldn't possibly be elected by Americans. So somehow it was some kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  external interference because the Russians interfered and had an impact.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin himself thinks at that time.
SPEAKER_0:  one of the reasons why he interferes in our elections later, that the United States or another said interfere, because he knew that people weren't that thrilled about him coming back
SPEAKER_0:  that kind of like the Medvedev period.
SPEAKER_0:  and the protests in Moscow and St. Petersburg and other major cities.
SPEAKER_0:  he starts to believe we're instigated by the West, by the outside.
SPEAKER_0:  because of funding for...
SPEAKER_0:  transparency in elections and
SPEAKER_0:  in all of the...
SPEAKER_0:  NGOs and others, you know, they're operating, State Department, Embassy funding.
SPEAKER_0:  and the whole attitude of, God is back, kind of thing.
SPEAKER_0:  And so after that, we see Putin going on.
SPEAKER_0:  a very different footing.
SPEAKER_0:  It's also somewhere in that period.
SPEAKER_0:  2011-2012, we start to kind of obsess about Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  And he's always, I think, been kind of steeped in that whole view of Russian history. I mean, I heard at that time I was in...
SPEAKER_0:  I've written about this and many of the things that, you know, I've written about Putin.
SPEAKER_0:  that in that same timeframe, I'm going to all these conferences in Russia where Putin is and
SPEAKER_0:  Peskov, his press secretary, and they talk about him reading Russian history.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's this and this kind of period that he formulates this idea.
SPEAKER_0:  off.
SPEAKER_0:  the necessity.
SPEAKER_0:  of reconstituting.
SPEAKER_0:  the Russian world, the Russian Empire.
SPEAKER_0:  He's obviously been very interested in this. He's always said, of course, that the collapse of the Soviet Union was the great catastrophe of the 20th century, but also the collapse of the Russian Empire before it.
SPEAKER_0:  and he starts to be critical about Lenin and the Bolsheviks, and he starts to do all this talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  us.
SPEAKER_0:  same country.
SPEAKER_0:  Ukrainians and Russians being one and the same.
SPEAKER_0:  This is where the ledger flips, because the initial question you asked me is about has Putin been good for...
SPEAKER_0:  Russia or not.
SPEAKER_0:  This is where we get into the.
SPEAKER_0:  focal point of.
SPEAKER_0:  or the point where he's not focusing on the prosperity and stability.
SPEAKER_0:  and future of Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  but he starts to obsess about the past.
SPEAKER_0:  and you can start to take things in a very different direction.
SPEAKER_0:  he starts to clamp it down at home because of...
SPEAKER_0:  the rise of opposition.
SPEAKER_0:  and the fact that he knows that his.
SPEAKER_0:  Brand is not the same as it was before and his popularity is not the same as it was before because he's already gone over that.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, that period in...
SPEAKER_0:  anybody's professional and political life that if you stay around long enough, people get a bit sick of you.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, we've talked about that before, should you stay in any job for a long period of time you need refreshing.
SPEAKER_0:  And you know, kind of Putin is starting to look like he's gonna be there forever and people are not happy about that.
SPEAKER_0:  and would like another chance as well to kind of move on and move up and, you know, with him in southern place that's not going to be.
SPEAKER_0:  particularly possible.
SPEAKER_0:  And that, you know, it's around the time when he starts to make the decision of annexing Crimea. And that's when...
SPEAKER_0:  the whole thing flips in my view.
SPEAKER_0:  The annexation of Crimea in 2014.
SPEAKER_0:  is the beginning of the end.
SPEAKER_0:  of Vladimir Putin.
SPEAKER_0:  Bing.
SPEAKER_0:  positive.
SPEAKER_0:  within Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  because if you...
SPEAKER_0:  pay very close attention.
SPEAKER_0:  too.
SPEAKER_0:  his speech on the annexation.
SPEAKER_0:  of Crimea.
SPEAKER_0:  In March of 2014, you see all of the foreshadowing of where we are now.
SPEAKER_0:  It's already of kind of his view of kind of his obsessions, his historical obsessions, his view of himself has been kind of fused with the state, to kind of a modern za.
SPEAKER_0:  and his idea that the West is up to get him it becomes after that.
SPEAKER_0:  almost a kind of like a messianic mission.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, to turn things in a different direction.
SPEAKER_1:  and who are.
SPEAKER_1:  to keep people.
SPEAKER_1:  to you in this.
SPEAKER_1:  Evolution
SPEAKER_1:  of the human being of the leader is a Petrushchev.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it Shoygu, the Minister of Defense? Is it, like you mentioned, Pascal, the press secretary?
SPEAKER_1:  What role does some of the others like Lavrov play?
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's more rooted in the larger context. I mean, individuals matter in that context, so it's just kind of like this shared worldview.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you go back to the early 1990s, immediately after the dissolution of the Soviet Union, and Yeltsin, you know, and-
SPEAKER_0:  the ice...
SPEAKER_0:  come to parts of Ukraine, Belarus, pull it apart, there was an awful lot of people who...
SPEAKER_0:  wanted to maintain the Soviet Union, not just Putin.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean you remember after Gorbachev tried to have the new union treaty.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  1991 and there was the emergency committee set up the coup against Gorbachev. It was because they were worried he was going too far and unraveling the union then.
SPEAKER_0:  as well. They were opposed to his reforms.
SPEAKER_0:  There's always been a kind of a very strong.
SPEAKER_0:  nationalist contingent that become Russian nationalists over time rather than...
SPEAKER_0:  Soviet.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, hardliners.
SPEAKER_0:  who basically want to maintain the empire, the union in some form.
SPEAKER_0:  And in the very early part of the 1990s, there was a lot of pressure put on Ukraine and all the other former Soviet republics, now independent states.
SPEAKER_0:  by people around, you know, Mayor Lushkov, for example, in Moscow.
SPEAKER_0:  by other forces in the Russian Duma, not just Vladimir Zhirinovsky and others, but really serious.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of what we would call him, like right-wing, you know, nationalist forces.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, pervasive.
SPEAKER_0:  in the system.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's especially pervasive in the KGB and in the security sector.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's where Putin comes out of.
SPEAKER_0:  Remember Putin also.
SPEAKER_0:  was of the opinion that one of the biggest mistakes the Bolsheviks made was...
SPEAKER_0:  getting rid of the Orthodox Church.
SPEAKER_0:  as an instrument of the state.
SPEAKER_0:  And so there's this kind of restorationist wing within the security services and the state apparatus that want to kind of bring back.
SPEAKER_0:  Russian orthodoxy is a state instrument, an instrument of state power.
SPEAKER_0:  and who were kind of looking all the time about strengthening the state.
SPEAKER_0:  the executive, the presidency.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it's everybody who takes part in that.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's also where there's more power, honestly.
SPEAKER_0:  and they see Putin as their vehicle for power. I think for people like Sergey Karyanko, a new Karyanko back in the 90s.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, my god, that guy's all it.
SPEAKER_0:  or like Dmitri Medvedev.
SPEAKER_0:  who was a warmer, fuzzier version.
SPEAKER_0:  of Putin certainly had a totally different perspective, wasn't it, in the KGB? Did you say warmer, fuzzier version? A warmer, fuzzier version, yeah. I mean, he's kind of like, he was literally a warm personality.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if you watched him during the September 30th annexation, the guy had all kinds of facial twitches.
SPEAKER_0:  and looks so rigid and stiff that he looks like he might.
SPEAKER_0:  implode.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, that wasn't how he was earlier in his career. I mean, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  had a different view of Paris striker. We always have to remember that Putin was not in Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  during power strike he was in Dresden.
SPEAKER_0:  watching.
SPEAKER_0:  East German state fall apart.
SPEAKER_0:  and dealing with the Dastazian in a kind of place where you weren't getting a lot of information about what was happening in West Germany or even what was happening back home in Perestroika.
SPEAKER_0:  And he has that kind of group of people around him, the pat ôfsheves.
SPEAKER_0:  botany cuffs and others.
SPEAKER_0:  So he gave on off another, you know, from, you know, the different configurations of his administration.
SPEAKER_0:  who have come out of that same kind of mindset.
SPEAKER_0:  and are kind of wanting to put everything back together again. There's a lot of enablers, there's a lot of, you know,
SPEAKER_0:  power.
SPEAKER_0:  seekers.
SPEAKER_0:  And there are a lot of people who think the same as him as well. He is a man of his time, a man of his context.
SPEAKER_1:  you as a top advisor yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  and a scholar of Putin. Do you think-
SPEAKER_1:  Actually.
SPEAKER_1:  now.
SPEAKER_1:  in his inner circle, are there people he trusts?
SPEAKER_0:  But are people who trust for some things?
SPEAKER_0:  But I don't think there's people who trust for everything. I don't think he's the kind of person who tells anyone everything at all.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think he's got something deeply confined to. I think he compartmentalizes things.
SPEAKER_0:  He's often said that the only person he trusts is himself.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's probably true. He's the kind of person who keeps his own counsel.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, people talk about Kovalchuk, for example.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of some of the other people who are.
SPEAKER_0:  friends with him that got to go back to his time in St. Petersburg.
SPEAKER_0:  At various points, he seemed to spend a lot of time.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, way back when talking to people who were...
SPEAKER_0:  people think of kind of more moderating forces like Alexei Kudrin, but you know, it doesn't seem to be interacting.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, with them.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there are obviously aspects of his personal life, you know, does he...
SPEAKER_0:  speak to.
SPEAKER_0:  his daughters? Does he speak to you?
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  lovers, you know, kind of in a way people speculate about, you know, kind of who might he confide in, but I would greatly doubt that he would have.
SPEAKER_0:  deep political.
SPEAKER_0:  discussions with them. He's a very guarded.
SPEAKER_0:  very careful.
SPEAKER_0:  person.
SPEAKER_1:  What about sources of information then?
SPEAKER_1:  to trust.
SPEAKER_1:  a deep understanding about.
SPEAKER_1:  military strategies.
SPEAKER_1:  with
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  for certain conflicts.
SPEAKER_1:  like the war in Ukraine or even special.
SPEAKER_1:  subsets of the war in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  or any kind of military operations, getting clear information.
SPEAKER_0:  deeply suspicious.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, of people and of information.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think part of the.
SPEAKER_0:  problems.
SPEAKER_0:  that we see with Putin now.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I've come from isolation during COVID. I'm really convinced that, you know, like many of us.
SPEAKER_0:  Yep.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of Putin's views have hardened.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  the way that he looks at the world have been.
SPEAKER_0:  shadowed in very dark ways by
SPEAKER_0:  the experience of this pandemic.
SPEAKER_0:  obviously he was in a bubble, different kind of bubble than most of us. I mean, most of us are not in bubbles with multiple.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of policies and you know, kind of the Kremlin.
SPEAKER_0:  But we've seen so much, obviously a lot of this is stage, that isolation, they're kind of making it very clear that he's the czar, the guy who is in charge making all the decisions, one end of the table and everybody else is at the other end.
SPEAKER_0:  But you know, it's very difficult then to bring.
SPEAKER_0:  information to him.
SPEAKER_0:  in that way. He used to have a lot of information bundled for him in the old days by the presidential administration. I don't know that because it was a lot more open in the past.
SPEAKER_0:  I have a lot of meetings with people in the presidential administration who brought outside, you know, it's all source information.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, for him and, you know, kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  funneled in information from different think tanks and...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, different viewpoints and...
SPEAKER_0:  maybe a kind of more eclectic, diversified set of information. He would meet with people. You know, you've heard all the stories about where he had once called up Masha Gessen, you know, and had to come in, you know, obviously, a very different character as a journalist and a critic.
SPEAKER_0:  We've heard about Benedicta from Echo Moscovy, the radio program, the editor.
SPEAKER_0:  who Putin would talk to and consult with, he'd reach out.
SPEAKER_0:  people.
SPEAKER_0:  like Ludmila Alexeva, for example, the head of Memorial, he had some respect for her and would, you know, sometimes just...
SPEAKER_0:  Talk to her.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, for example, all of that seems to have.
SPEAKER_0:  come to a halt.
SPEAKER_0:  I think a lot of us worry.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, as to, you know, watch Putin about what kind of information is he getting?
SPEAKER_0:  You know, is it just information he's seeking and gathering himself that fits into his worldview and his framework? You're guilty of that.
SPEAKER_0:  of looking for things, gets to our social media preferences.
SPEAKER_0:  people just bring into him things that they think he wants to hear, like the algorithm, you know, kind of like the Kremlin working in that regard, or is he himself?
SPEAKER_0:  in a tapping into source of information that he absolutely wants.
SPEAKER_0:  And remember...
SPEAKER_0:  He is not a Melody Guy.
SPEAKER_0:  He's an operative and he was sort of trained in operations and contingency planning.
SPEAKER_0:  Sergei Shoigu, the defence minister, as a civil engineer, was the former minister of emergencies. It wasn't a military planet.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, somebody like Gerasimov, the head of the...
SPEAKER_0:  Sheeps of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  maybe a military guy in this case from the army, but he's also somebody who's in a different part, the chain of command. He's not somebody who would spontaneously start in a telling.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin things.
SPEAKER_0:  and Putin comes out of the FSB, out of the KGB.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Soviet era and he knows the way that intelligence gets filtered and works. He's probably somebody who wants to consume raw intelligence. He doesn't probably want to.
SPEAKER_0:  hear anybody else's analysis.
SPEAKER_0:  and he thrived in the past.
SPEAKER_0:  of picking things up from people.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I've taken part in all of these meetings with him, gone far less, because he's just collecting.
SPEAKER_0:  He's collecting information, he's sussing people out. He wants to know the questions they ask.
SPEAKER_0:  He learned something about the questions that people ask, the way that they ask them.
SPEAKER_0:  So he's soliciting information himself. And if he's cut off from that information...
SPEAKER_0:  because of circumstances.
SPEAKER_0:  then how is he formulating things in his head? And again—
SPEAKER_0:  getting into, you can't get into his head, but you can.
SPEAKER_0:  understand the context in which he's operating. And that's where you worry, because he clearly made this decision to invade Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  behind the back of most of the security establishment.
SPEAKER_0:  You think so? No, I think it's pretty apparent.
SPEAKER_1:  What?
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh
SPEAKER_1:  What would the security establishment?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, that would be the larger, you know, thinking the funneling in information from the presidential administration, from the National Security Council.
SPEAKER_0:  It looks like he made that decision with a handful of people.
SPEAKER_0:  And then, you know, having worked in these kinds of environments and it's not that dissimilar, you filter information up.
SPEAKER_0:  So think about, you and I are talking for hours here.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, if you were my...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, but basically...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, senior official and I'm your briefer, I might only get 20 minutes with you.
SPEAKER_0:  And you might be just like, you know, looking at your watch the whole time and thinking, hang on a second, I've got to go and I've got this meeting and I've got that meeting and yeah, your point, you're not going to wait there. So I give this long explanation. I've got to get to the point and then I've got to then choose for myself, what's the information I'm going to impart to you?
SPEAKER_0:  out of the 20 things that I think are important.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, okay, I've got...
SPEAKER_0:  minutes, maybe I only suddenly get two minutes, maybe you get called out.
SPEAKER_0:  And somebody, you know, kind of interrupts.
SPEAKER_0:  something happens, I'm gonna get one minute, two minutes.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. I mean, I want to remember, I had to give a presentation when I was in government, to Henry Kissinger, you know, for that defense policy board.
SPEAKER_0:  and we plump.
SPEAKER_0:  Bloody weeks on this thing.
SPEAKER_0:  PowerPoints were created, teams of people were brought together.
SPEAKER_0:  And people were practicing this, we had all these different people there. And I said, look.
SPEAKER_0:  Henry Kissinger is an academic and a former professor and, you know, I haven't, you know, I've got to watch him in action. He's gonna like.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, five seconds in if we're lucky, we get that far, ask us a question and just throw off our entire presentation.
SPEAKER_0:  What is it that we want to convey? And that's exactly what happened. And then people aren't really prepared or they wanted to convey and they're prepared.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, a nice sort of fulsome.
SPEAKER_0:  in a PowerPoint-like approach. We never even got there.
SPEAKER_0:  And so God knows what he took away from it at the end of it. And that's, you know, think about Putin.
SPEAKER_0:  He's gonna be kind of impatient.
SPEAKER_0:  He's in, we see the televised things where he, you know, kind of sits at a table a bit like.
SPEAKER_0:  people won't necessarily see us here.
SPEAKER_0:  and he puts his hands on the table and he looks across at the person and he says so.
SPEAKER_0:  Tell me.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  What's the main things I need to know? And of course the person's mind probably goes blank.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, with the kind of the thought of like, oh god, what's the main thing? Yeah. They go, well, Vladimir Vladimirovich, they start the kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  They're revving up to get to the point and then he cuts them off.
SPEAKER_0:  So you think about that and then you think about, well what information has he got?
SPEAKER_0:  And then how does he process it?
SPEAKER_0:  And is he suspicious of it? Does he not believe it?
SPEAKER_0:  And what on what inside of his own history then, you know, leads him to make one judgment over another? He clearly thought...
SPEAKER_0:  the Ukrainians would fall apart in five seconds.
SPEAKER_1:  We don't know if he clearly thought that, but that there was a.
SPEAKER_1:  High probability maybe?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, you can guess. I think he pretty much thought it, because I think he thought that, you know, kind of his answer wasn't very popular.
SPEAKER_0:  There was an awful lot of pro-Russian sentiment in whatever way he thinks that is because people are Russian speakers.
SPEAKER_0:  and that, you know, they're kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, in polling that, you know, they're
SPEAKER_0:  expressed affinity with Russia. I mean, certainly in Crimea, that worked out because a majority of the population had higher sentiments or feelings of affinity with Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  And you know, obviously.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, that kind of, they got traction there.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's more complicated. We talked about Dunbass before about being a kind of melting pot when
SPEAKER_0:  they tried the same thing in Donbus.
SPEAKER_0:  Donetsk and Luhansk as it tried in Crimea in 2014 didn't kind of pan out. In fact, you know, a whole wall broke out.
SPEAKER_0:  They tried, you know, to kind of in...
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  many of the major cities that are now under attack, including Odessa.
SPEAKER_0:  to kind of ferment pro-Russian movements.
SPEAKER_0:  they completely and utterly fell apart. So Putin was thinking...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm pretty sure based on polling and the FSB having infiltrated.
SPEAKER_0:  an awful lot of the Ukrainian hierarchies we're now seeing as quite apparent with some of the dismissals in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  It was pretty sure.
SPEAKER_0:  That's it.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of he would get traction.
SPEAKER_0:  and that it would be like 1956 in Hungary or 1968 in Czechoslovakia. Remember he comes out of the Andropov.
SPEAKER_0:  levy as it's called, a kind of cohort of people who come into the KGB under Yuri Andropov.
SPEAKER_0:  And Euron Dropov has presided over a lot of these.
SPEAKER_0:  anti-dissident.
SPEAKER_0:  movements inside of Russia itself and how you suppress.
SPEAKER_0:  opposition, but also over how you deal with.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of the uprisings and...
SPEAKER_0:  in the Czechoslovakia and Hungary.
SPEAKER_0:  there's all these lessons from this that you can put everything back in the box.
SPEAKER_0:  And yeah, there might be a bit of violence and a bit of fighting, but ultimately, you think you've got the political figures and you decapitate the opposition.
SPEAKER_0:  so they thought you'd let, Zylinski would run away.
SPEAKER_0:  Yadokovitch, run away, but...
SPEAKER_0:  That was kind of a bit, sort of a different set of circumstances.
SPEAKER_0:  And they thought that all of the local governments would kind of capitulate because they had been through broke or didn't do so much which is not enough.
SPEAKER_0:  Russians in inverted commas in there.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, mistaking language.
SPEAKER_0:  and kind of positive affinity towards Russia for identity or how people would react in the time and not understanding peoples.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, linkages and, you know, kind of importance of place, the way that people feel about who they are in a certain set of circumstances and place.
SPEAKER_1:  the invasion of Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  2022 is unlike anything.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  he was ever involved with.
SPEAKER_0:  But I don't think he thought it would be, you know, because it's kind of if he looks back into the past. You're right though, he wasn't involved in 68 or...
SPEAKER_0:  56 or what happened in the 1980s in Poland.
SPEAKER_1:  But there's a very wide front and it's the capital and I mean.
SPEAKER_1:  This isn't going.
SPEAKER_0:  This isn't Chichniel, this isn't you know kind of Syriac for example. This is a major nation.
SPEAKER_1:  It's large.
SPEAKER_0:  It was more like Afghanistan, but they didn't realize that because again, Ukrainians are us.
SPEAKER_0:  inability to think that people might think differently and might want something different.
SPEAKER_0:  and that 30 years of independence actually has an impact on people and there's like geese and...
SPEAKER_0:  If I look back to the 1990s, I mean, I remember being in seminars and...
SPEAKER_0:  at Harvard at the time and we were doing a lot of research on...
SPEAKER_0:  what was happening.
SPEAKER_0:  and the former Soviet Union at the time, because of the early 1990s, just after the bin of the hole.
SPEAKER_0:  place fall apart.
SPEAKER_0:  And there was already underyelps in this kind of idea of...
SPEAKER_0:  Russians abroad, Russians in the near abroad, Russian speakers and the need to bring them back in.
SPEAKER_0:  And I remember we had seminars at the time where we talked about at some point.
SPEAKER_0:  There'd be some people in Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  that would actually believe that...
SPEAKER_0:  those Russian speakers needed to be brought back into Russia, but that the...
SPEAKER_0:  people who spoke Russian might have moved on.
SPEAKER_0:  because they certainly had other opportunities and other windows in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, look what's happened in Scotland. You know, for example, most.
SPEAKER_0:  people in Scotland speak English.
SPEAKER_0:  The Scottish language is not.
SPEAKER_0:  The.
SPEAKER_0:  standard bearer of Scottish identity. It's almost a civic identity, a different identity than not just national identity, just like you see in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  and there's lots of English people.
SPEAKER_0:  have moved to Scotland and now think of themselves as Scottish or Brazilians or Italians and you know all kinds of people who've moved in there. It's a smaller population obviously and it's not the scale of...
SPEAKER_0:  Are you crying, but...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, people deal differently.
SPEAKER_0:  and there's been a devolution of power.
SPEAKER_0:  And when Brexit happened...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, Scotland didn't want to go along with that at all. They wanted to kind of still be, you know, a-
SPEAKER_0:  having a window on Europe.
SPEAKER_0:  That's kind of historic.
SPEAKER_0:  and lots of people in Ukraine have looked west, not east.
SPEAKER_0:  It depends on where you are, not just in...
SPEAKER_0:  Lviv, you know, or somewhere like that, but also in Kiev. And Kharkiv, you know, was kind of predominantly a Russian-speaking city. But Kharkiv was also the centre.
SPEAKER_0:  of Ukrainian culture.
SPEAKER_0:  and you're creating literature at different points.
SPEAKER_0:  People have different views. I grew up in the north of England. We don't feel like the south of England. There's been a massive divide between north and south of England.
SPEAKER_0:  For millennia, not just centuries.
SPEAKER_0:  So, you know, people feel differently.
SPEAKER_0:  depending on where they live and kind of where they grew up. And Putin just-
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't see that. I didn't see that.
SPEAKER_1:  Hold on a second, let me sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  Hush.
SPEAKER_1:  back.
SPEAKER_1:  at the fact that I don't think any of this is obvious.
SPEAKER_1:  So first of all, Zelensky before the war was unpopular. I want.
SPEAKER_0:  38%, something like that, but best in the popularity.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me sort of make the case that the calculation here.
SPEAKER_1:  is very difficult. If you were to poll...
SPEAKER_1:  every citizen of Ukraine and ask them, what do you think happens if Russia invades?
SPEAKER_1:  Just.
SPEAKER_1:  Like actually, each.
SPEAKER_1:  put each individual Ukrainian
SPEAKER_1:  in a one-on-one meeting with Putin and say, what do you think happens?
SPEAKER_1:  I honestly think most of them will say they will agree.
SPEAKER_1:  with a prediction that the government would flee, it would collapse.
SPEAKER_1:  and the country won't unite.
SPEAKER_1:  around cause.
SPEAKER_1:  because of the factions.
SPEAKER_1:  because of all the different parties involved because of that popular
SPEAKER_0:  You might have said the same thing about...
SPEAKER_0:  the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  when Hitler invaded.
SPEAKER_0:  in 1941.
SPEAKER_0:  You see, the problem is Putin always reads history from one perspective over another.
SPEAKER_0:  I think most countries.
SPEAKER_0:  basically rise to their own defense.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is actually one of the first times that Russia has been on the offensive.
SPEAKER_0:  rather than on the defensive.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, so there's kind of a bit of a flip there.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, obviously Afghanistan, but that was more complicated because it was also supposed to be an intervention right. I mean, it wasn't supposed to be to annex Afghanistan. It was to try to.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm gonna pop up.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of a reinstall of a leader there.
SPEAKER_0:  You were in there to, you know, help.
SPEAKER_0:  Your guy, Bashar al-Assad.
SPEAKER_0:  turn away the opposition.
SPEAKER_0:  Chetch now was a debacle.
SPEAKER_0:  The Chaptains.
SPEAKER_0:  Thought back.
SPEAKER_0:  Big time.
SPEAKER_0:  and it was only by dint of.
SPEAKER_0:  horrible.
SPEAKER_0:  violent persistence.
SPEAKER_0:  and ruthlessness.
SPEAKER_0:  nasty dirty tricks.
SPEAKER_0:  that動画 relieved from needs of time.
SPEAKER_0:  know, kind of Putin prevailed there, but then, you know, you wonder, did he prevail? Because what happened?
SPEAKER_0:  You know, Chechnya sometimes describes the most independent part of the Russian Federation, Ramzan Kadyrov.
SPEAKER_0:  and it plays power games in Moscow.
SPEAKER_0:  His predecessors.
SPEAKER_0:  Even his father and others wouldn't have done that.
SPEAKER_0:  and before that, Dadaev and Maskhadaev, they were willing to make a compromise, but they wouldn't have had.
SPEAKER_0:  end of the same.
SPEAKER_0:  position that Kadira facade.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that again, it's your perspective and where you stand and which bit of history you start to read. That's why I say that, you know, I kind of think Putin...
SPEAKER_0:  It's again, it's the information, the way that he processes it.
SPEAKER_0:  I think most Russians also can't believe that they've done something wrong in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, maybe at this point things are...
SPEAKER_0:  changing a bit.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's why there was so much support for this.
SPEAKER_0:  I have Russian friends again and I said, but look what was happening in Dunyets.
SPEAKER_0:  look what the Ukrainians were doing to our guys.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, look what was happening to Russian speakers.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, we were defenders.
SPEAKER_0:  We were not, we're not invaders. I think, again, the special military operation idea, now I think it's flipping, obviously, in the way that with the wall going on there.
SPEAKER_0:  But Putin wasn't, you know, kind of looking at what would happen.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, most of the kind of glory parts of Russian history when you kind of go in.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, you chase Napoleon back to Paris.
SPEAKER_0:  or you taste the Germans back to Berlin, you put the flag above the Reichstag.
SPEAKER_0:  That's very different.
SPEAKER_0:  set of affairs.
SPEAKER_0:  when you've been fighting a defensive one, you've been invaded.
SPEAKER_0:  from a world where you invade someone else.
SPEAKER_0:  And even the most fractured populations like you had in the Soviet Union at the point, can run around.
SPEAKER_0:  World War I, the...
SPEAKER_0:  fell apart. I mean, the czar didn't manage to rally everybody around.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, the whole thing fell apart.
SPEAKER_0:  and.
SPEAKER_0:  World War II?
SPEAKER_0:  Stalin had to...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, revive nationalism.
SPEAKER_0:  including in the republics in Central Asia and Elsevier to revive nationalism.
SPEAKER_0:  and you can see from nationalism you know the kind of sense
SPEAKER_1:  That's really interesting because it's not obvious, especially what Ukrainians went through in the 1930s.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not obvious that that...
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, my grandfather was Ukrainian and he was proud to...
SPEAKER_1:  Fight.
SPEAKER_1:  a Ukrainian Jew.
SPEAKER_1:  He was proud to fight and willing to die for.
SPEAKER_1:  his country.
SPEAKER_1:  It wasn't like...
SPEAKER_0:  His country then was the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_1:  of the union, right, sorry.
SPEAKER_0:  But he might fight now for his country, Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm just like...
SPEAKER_1:  um... lingering in the point you made it was not obvious
SPEAKER_1:  that that united.
SPEAKER_1:  feeling would be there.
SPEAKER_0:  No, and again, it wouldn't have been obvious for the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what, sorry. Huh.
SPEAKER_1:  That's what I'm saying. Sorry, I was referring to my grandfather, the Soviet Union. We're both saying the exact same thing. We know. Yeah, we are. You're saying it's a really powerful thing because I take it because you take history as it happened.
SPEAKER_1:  you don't realize it could have happened differently. It's kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  It's fascinating. It's that whole counterfactual, right? Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Because if you've kind of, that's why we all need in the United States to really examine our own history.
SPEAKER_0:  because.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there's a lot of lessons from that.
SPEAKER_0:  that we should.
SPEAKER_0:  treat very cautiously. It doesn't mean that, you know, history repeats or even rhymes, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  the old Axiom all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  There are a lot of things that you can.
SPEAKER_0:  take away differently from.
SPEAKER_0:  putting a different perspective and a different slant on the same set of events. I mean, I always used to wonder, like, how many books can be written on the French Revolution?
SPEAKER_0:  or even on the Russian Revolution. You know, I studied with Richard Pipes, and I remember he was really offended after he'd written his great micro-surplus on the Russian Revolution, two volumes, that other people would...
SPEAKER_0:  kind of write about the Russian revolution. He said, I've written it all. And I thought, well, actually, maybe you haven't. It's like there might be some completely different angle there that you haven't really thought of. And that's Putin. I remember Peskov saying.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin reads history all the time, Russian history, and I thought, well, maybe she should read some world history.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, maybe he should.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of read some European authors on Russian history, not just reading Lamanosa for, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Russian historians on Russian history, because you might see something from a very different perspective. Look, the United States made a massive mistake in Vietnam.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, they saw Vietnam as kind of weak, manipulated by, you know, kind of external forces, China, Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  the Vietnamese fought for their own country.
SPEAKER_0:  they suddenly became Vietnamese and Ho Chi Minh became.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, going to basically a kind of a war time.
SPEAKER_0:  fighter and leader.
SPEAKER_0:  in a way that perhaps people wouldn't have understood either.
SPEAKER_1:  You said the United States made a massive mistake.
SPEAKER_1:  in Vietnam.
SPEAKER_1:  and that for some reason sprung a thought in my head.
SPEAKER_1:  as United States.
SPEAKER_1:  since World War II.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, had anything that's not a mistake in terms of military operations.
SPEAKER_1:  abroad.
SPEAKER_1:  I suppose all the ones that are successes.
SPEAKER_1:  we don't even know about probably. So it's like very fast military operations.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, Korea is divided. I mean, I don't know what's successful, but kind of, I mean, there was a solution found that some people are promoting, in this case as well, of a sort of division in a.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, the DMZ and...
SPEAKER_0:  one side over the other and kind of perpetuating a division.
SPEAKER_0:  particularly successful but if you think about World War One and World War Two
SPEAKER_0:  The United States came in.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, under some very specific sets of circumstances. In World War I, they did kind of come in to help.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of liberate.
SPEAKER_0:  parts of Europe, France and the UK.
SPEAKER_0:  everything else, Great Britain and the war towards the end of it.
SPEAKER_0:  World War II?
SPEAKER_0:  there was that whole debate about whether the United States should even be part of the war.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, we know it wasn't thought to...
SPEAKER_0:  overturn the Holocaust and all of the kind of things you kind of wish it would have been fought for. It was because of Pearl Harbor and the Japanese pulling in.
SPEAKER_0:  But ultimately...
SPEAKER_0:  It was easy to explain.
SPEAKER_0:  while you were there, you know, particularly after Pearl Harbor and what had happened.
SPEAKER_0:  It was hard to explain Vietnam and Korea and...
SPEAKER_0:  many of them wasn't. Look, that's kind of going to be a problem for Putin. That's why there is a problem for Putin. All of his explanations of—
SPEAKER_0:  being questioned.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, Sarsavol for NATO or this or that or the other.
SPEAKER_0:  and kind of all liberating Ukraine from Nazis or...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of basically stopping the persecution of Russian speakers and.
SPEAKER_0:  All of this has now got lost in just this.
SPEAKER_0:  horrific destruction.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's what happened in Vietnam as well.
SPEAKER_0:  I became.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, a great degradation.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Russian military with atrocities and people wondering why on earth the United States was in Vietnam.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, even that kind of happened in Britain in the colonial.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of pivot as well. Why was the United Kingdom?
SPEAKER_0:  committing atrocities and basically fighting these colonial wars.
SPEAKER_0:  Northern Ireland.
SPEAKER_0:  Why was the United Kingdom still...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of militarily occupying.
SPEAKER_0:  Island.
SPEAKER_0:  There's all kinds of instances where we look at this thing. What Russia was doing now, Putin is-
SPEAKER_0:  trying to occupy.
SPEAKER_0:  another country.
SPEAKER_0:  irrespective of the historical linkages.
SPEAKER_0:  and the larger metanarratives that he's trying to put forward there.
SPEAKER_1:  What brawl?
SPEAKER_1:  Did the United States play?
SPEAKER_1:  in the lead up and the actual invasion.
SPEAKER_1:  of um...
SPEAKER_1:  of Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  by Russia.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of people say that, I mean, obviously.
SPEAKER_1:  Vladimir Putin says that
SPEAKER_1:  part of the reason.
SPEAKER_1:  The invasion had to happen because of
SPEAKER_1:  security concerns over the expansion of NATO.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  There is.
SPEAKER_1:  a lot of people that say that this was provoked.
SPEAKER_1:  by NATO.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think there's some legitimacy to that case?
SPEAKER_0:  Look, I think the whole situation here is very complicated and you have to take a much longer view than what happened in 2008 with the open door for Ukraine and Georgia, which actually by the way I thought was a strategic blunder.
SPEAKER_0:  just to be very clear.
SPEAKER_0:  because I wasn't any kind of thinking through about what the implications of that would be and what it actually would mean for Ukraine's security and also bearing in mind what Putin had already said about NATO expansion.
SPEAKER_0:  They came on the wake of the recognition by the United States pretty unilaterally of Kosovo.
SPEAKER_0:  And it also comes in the wake of, as I mentioned before, the invasion of Iraq, which...
SPEAKER_0:  Really because very
SPEAKER_0:  important for understanding Putin's psyche.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think we have to go back much further and it's not just talking about NATO and what that means.
SPEAKER_0:  NATO is part of the whole.
SPEAKER_0:  of Ukraine going in a different direction from Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  just as so as the European Union. Remember the annexation.
SPEAKER_0:  of Crimea comes after.
SPEAKER_0:  Ukraine has sought an association agreement with the European Union.
SPEAKER_0:  Not with NATO at that particular point, even though the EU on the common security defense policy...
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  all kinds of connections.
SPEAKER_0:  with NATO at various different levels in the European Security Front. It was all about Europe.
SPEAKER_0:  going on a different economic and political.
SPEAKER_0:  and ultimately legal path because if you have.
SPEAKER_0:  an association agreement eventually you get into the Aki Communitern and it just transforms the country completely and Ukraine is no longer.
SPEAKER_0:  the Ukraine of the Soviet period or the Russian Empire period, it becomes...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, on a different trajectory like...
SPEAKER_0:  Czech Republic, Slovakia.
SPEAKER_0:  Poland.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  another country becomes a different place. It moves into a different space and that's part of it.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you go back again...
SPEAKER_0:  to the period at the very beginning of the 1990s, after the...
SPEAKER_0:  dissolution.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Soviet Union. Well, there's no discussion about NATO at that point in NATO enlargement.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a lot of pressure, again, as I've said before, by nationalist elements on Ukraine and trying to bring it back in the fold.
SPEAKER_0:  and wanting to make what was then.
SPEAKER_0:  in this.
SPEAKER_0:  mechanism for divorce.
SPEAKER_0:  more of a mechanism for re-management of Commonwealth of Independent States.
SPEAKER_0:  And in the early 1990s...
SPEAKER_0:  when
SPEAKER_0:  Ukraine
SPEAKER_0:  became an independent state, it inherited that nuclear arsenal.
SPEAKER_0:  from
SPEAKER_0:  the Soviet Union, basically whatever was stationed.
SPEAKER_0:  opposition in Ukrainian territory at the time became Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  strategic and you know kind of basically intermediate and tactical nuclear weapons.
SPEAKER_0:  in the United States at the time, we had all this panic about.
SPEAKER_0:  what was going to happen with all of that. I mean, I think, you know, I was a scientist and, you know, kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  Technically, it would have been difficult for Ukraine to actually use this. I mean, the targeting was done centrally.
SPEAKER_0:  They were actually stationed there, but nonetheless.
SPEAKER_0:  Ukraine, like Belarus and Kazakhstan, suddenly become nuclear powers.
SPEAKER_0:  And Ash Carter, the former US Defense Secretary, just died tragically and Dave was talking about...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, talking together today was part of a whole team of Americans and others who
SPEAKER_0:  you know, try to work with Ukraine, Belarus and Kazakhstan.
SPEAKER_0:  got them to give up the nuclear weapons.
SPEAKER_0:  and back in the early.
SPEAKER_0:  period of that, 1980.
SPEAKER_0:  394.
SPEAKER_0:  go back and I mean I was writing about this at the time I wrote a report called Back in the USSR which is you know kind of on the website of the Kennedy School with some other colleagues.
SPEAKER_0:  And we were monitoring how there was all these accusations coming out of Moscow, the defence ministry and the Duma, the parliament and others, that Ukraine was trying to find a way of making a dirty bomb.
SPEAKER_0:  using its nuclear weapons.
SPEAKER_0:  becoming a menace and Ukraine might have to be brought to order.
SPEAKER_0:  So a lot of the dynamics we're seeing now were happening then.
SPEAKER_0:  irrespective of NATO.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically.
SPEAKER_0:  The problem was always Ukraine getting away.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeltsin himself, when he unraveled the Soviet Union, didn't really want it to unravel.
SPEAKER_0:  But he didn't have the wherewithal to bring the countries back again. Russia was weak.
SPEAKER_0:  after the collapse of the Soviet Union, its economy imploded.
SPEAKER_0:  It had to give sovereignty to all of these constituent parts of
SPEAKER_0:  the Russian Federation in terms of a sort of devolution of authority at the war in Chechnya.
SPEAKER_0:  which Yeltsin stupidly sparked off in 1994.
SPEAKER_0:  You had Tatarstan, one of the regions, the old rich regions.
SPEAKER_0:  You know basically
SPEAKER_0:  resting out a kind of a.
SPEAKER_0:  a bilateral treaty with Moscow. The whole place seemed like it was falling apart, so that you couldn't do anything on Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  because you didn't have the wherewithal to do it. And then when, you know, kind of basically Russia starts to get its act back together again.
SPEAKER_0:  all of these.
SPEAKER_0:  Security.
SPEAKER_0:  nationalists types who had never wanted Ukraine or Belarus or Moldova or anywhere else to kind of move away. They didn't worry that much about central Asia to be frank, but they know they did want.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, the core states in their view to come back.
SPEAKER_0:  And Moldova was part of that, even if it's not Slavic, but they wanted.
SPEAKER_0:  Belarus and
SPEAKER_0:  Northern Kazakhstan and probably Kazakhstan as well, which wasn't really thought about being part of Central Asia, back in the fold as close as possible.
SPEAKER_0:  So anything.
SPEAKER_0:  Look, Gabe.
SPEAKER_0:  those countries an alternative.
SPEAKER_0:  was seen as negative.
SPEAKER_0:  It could have been an association.
SPEAKER_0:  with China.
SPEAKER_0:  of them joining an association with Latin America or Africa or something else like that. But of course, NATO has all of those larger connotations of it being into the Cold War.
SPEAKER_0:  opposing entity and Putin has always seen NATO.
SPEAKER_0:  as being the direct correlation of the Warsaw Pact.
SPEAKER_0:  which is, in other words, just something dominated completely by the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  Now that of course is why getting back to Trump again, Trump was always going
SPEAKER_0:  to the Europeans, if this is really supposed to be collective security in a mutual defence pact, why are you guys not paying?
SPEAKER_0:  You know, why does the US and the States pay for everything?
SPEAKER_0:  But you know, NATO was actually conceived as collective defense.
SPEAKER_0:  in a mutual.
SPEAKER_0:  security.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was set up by the United States along with the UK and France and...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, Germany and Turkey and, you know, other countries.
SPEAKER_0:  And we see that now with the entry of Finland and Sweden. They didn't have to join NATO. They didn't want to join NATO for a long time. They wanted to partner with it, just like Israel and other countries partner with NATO.
SPEAKER_0:  But once they thought that their security was really at risk, they wanted to be part of it.
SPEAKER_0:  And so, you know, kind of, you're now really seeing, you know, that Nate was something other than just being.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, a creature.
SPEAKER_0:  or an instrument of the United States. But that's how Putin always saw it. So, you know, what-
SPEAKER_0:  This debate about murder is all about.
SPEAKER_0:  Russia being provoked.
SPEAKER_0:  is wanting to kind of return to an old superpower.
SPEAKER_0:  bipolar relationship.
SPEAKER_0:  where everything is negotiated with the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  It's to try to deny that Ukraine or Belarus, well Belarus has been absorbed by this point, by Russia or Moldova or Kazakhstan or...
SPEAKER_0:  any of the other countries have any kind of urgency.
SPEAKER_0:  not even Poland or Hungary or, you know, kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  France and Britain.
SPEAKER_0:  For years and years and years.
SPEAKER_0:  senior people like Putin and
SPEAKER_0:  people around the Kremlin have demanded a return to the kind of what they call the old concert of Europe.
SPEAKER_0:  or the concert of Vienna where.
SPEAKER_0:  big guys.
SPEAKER_0:  which now means the United States and Russia just sit down and thrash everything out.
SPEAKER_0:  And so, I mean, Putin vibe.
SPEAKER_0:  saying, look, it was provoked. It's the United States. It's NATO.
SPEAKER_0:  it's a proxy war or it's this or it's that or...
SPEAKER_0:  This is going to be a nuclear confrontation. It's like the Cuban Missile Crisis, the Euro Missile Crisis. It's basically just saying...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I want to go back to when...
SPEAKER_0:  The Soviet Union and the United States work things out. I want to go back to the whole.
SPEAKER_0:  in a period of the 1980s when Gorbachev and Reagan just kind of got together and figured things out.
SPEAKER_0:  or even better...
SPEAKER_0:  Back to...
SPEAKER_0:  Yelta Potsdam and Tehran.
SPEAKER_0:  on the big, you know, meetings.
SPEAKER_0:  at the end of World War II, where we resolved the whole future security. We've had a war, we've had the Cold War, now we've got another war, we've got a real war, a hot war, we've got a war in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  It should be the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  and Russia that sought this out.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is where we see the United States waffling about as well, trying to kind of like figure out how to handle this because...
SPEAKER_0:  It has to be handled in a way that Ukraine has agency. Because if Ukraine doesn't have agency, nobody else has agency either. Nobody else has any kind of decision making power.
SPEAKER_0:  And we have an environment in which Putin thinks that there's only really three players.
SPEAKER_0:  as the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  and Russia and China.
SPEAKER_0:  And maybe occasionally it might be India and perhaps Brazil or some other.
SPEAKER_0:  South Africa or some other country like maybe the Bricks at some point.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, ultimately, it's like the old days, big powers resolve everything. And so this war is also about.
SPEAKER_0:  Russia's right, Putin's right.
SPEAKER_0:  in order to determine things.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, strong man to strong man, big country to big country.
SPEAKER_0:  and determine.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, where things happen next. That's why he's talking about things being provoked since being the United States' fault.
SPEAKER_1:  but aren't they parts of the United States?
SPEAKER_1:  establishment.
SPEAKER_1:  that likes that kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  three-party view of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, there's always going to be people who like that.
SPEAKER_0:  pasta.
SPEAKER_0:  approach of course there is.
SPEAKER_0:  But then they don't necessarily dominate. That's the kind of thing that people kind of think about. I mean, Putin can...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, read.
SPEAKER_0:  all the various articles and he the kind of pronouncements of people. But you know, this gets back to.
SPEAKER_0:  in other words, the United States operates.
SPEAKER_0:  You're gonna poop.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin saw that Trump wanted to have a top down.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, vertical of power.
SPEAKER_0:  and other presidents have wanted to have that, but they notice that this is a pretty messy place.
SPEAKER_0:  and we have all kinds of different viewpoints.
SPEAKER_0:  Now of course we know that in Russia...
SPEAKER_0:  Everything, even criticism of the Kremlin is usually
SPEAKER_0:  fairly orchestrated, usually to kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  Flash out.
SPEAKER_0:  what people think about things. When we had these hardliners saying we needed more.
SPEAKER_0:  destruction of Ukraine not less and that the army wasn't doing enough.
SPEAKER_0:  It was in many respects kind of encouraged by the Kremlin to see how people would react to that.
SPEAKER_0:  to kind of actually create a constituency for being more ruthless.
SPEAKER_0:  than you had before because they wanted to clamp down. In the United States...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I can say whatever I want. It doesn't mean that I'm speaking on behalf of the White House.
SPEAKER_0:  And even if I have been an advisor to this president, that president, and the other, it doesn't mean I'm basically speaking on behalf.
SPEAKER_0:  of the US government. But there's kind of always an assumption from the Russians that you know, when people
SPEAKER_0:  you know, say this and people do advocate one thing over another, that they're, you know, it's operating, there's a lot of mirror imaging.
SPEAKER_0:  think that we're operating.
SPEAKER_0:  in the same kind of way. So yes.
SPEAKER_0:  There are of course constituencies who think like that and would love it. It has to be back to that and there are many people out there with their own peace plans.
SPEAKER_0:  all kinds of people, you know, have to push this.
SPEAKER_1:  There does seem to be the engine of the military industrial complex seems to give some fuel to the hawks.
SPEAKER_1:  And they...
SPEAKER_1:  seem to create momentum in government.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, but other people do too. I mean, there's always, you know, kind of checks. I mean, again.
SPEAKER_0:  You believe in the tension of ideas. I think there was a lot of tension. I mean, I've seen it. I've seen it inside of the government now, you know, and people can push back. And that's why I speak out and I try to lay it out so that everybody can.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of figure it out for themselves. I said the same to you as I say to everybody.
SPEAKER_0:  This is how I see the situation.
SPEAKER_0:  and this is how we can analyze it here.
SPEAKER_0:  Now look.
SPEAKER_0:  Do I think that we've?
SPEAKER_0:  handled the whole Russia account for years.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, no, we haven't.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, we've...
SPEAKER_0:  taken our eyes off the ball many times.
SPEAKER_0:  We fail to understand the way that people like Putin think.
SPEAKER_0:  You talked earlier about we need to have empathy for all the people who...
SPEAKER_0:  like Trump or like Biden and understand how they think. We've got to have strategic empathy about Putin as well. We've got to understand how the guy thinks and why he thinks like he does.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, he has got his own context and his own frame.
SPEAKER_0:  and his own rationale.
SPEAKER_0:  And he is rational, he is a rational actor.
SPEAKER_0:  in his own context, we've got to understand that. We've got to understand that he would take offense as something and he would take action over something.
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't mean to say that.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, we are.
SPEAKER_0:  necessary to blame by taking actions, but we are to blame when we don't understand the consequences of things that we do.
SPEAKER_0:  and act accordingly.
SPEAKER_0:  or take preventative action or...
SPEAKER_0:  recognize that something might happen as a result of something.
SPEAKER_1:  So you've been in the room with Putin.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask you for some advice.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's also just a good philosophical question.
SPEAKER_1:  for you or for me.
SPEAKER_1:  If I have a conversation with Vladimir Putin right now, can you advise on what questions, topics, ideas to talk through?
SPEAKER_1:  to him as a leader, to him as a human.
SPEAKER_1:  What would you like to understand about his mind, about his thinking?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, remember what I said before, that Putin always tries to reverse things. He wants to hear the questions that people have.
SPEAKER_0:  Because remember...
SPEAKER_0:  He himself.
SPEAKER_0:  different points has been a recruiter, which is, you know, the way that you're operating now as well, right? You're asking an awful lot of questions. Your questions also betray, you know, often the times where you're thinking about things.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, the kind of context.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  Any kind of dialogue like this reveals a lot about the other person.
SPEAKER_0:  And I've actually...
SPEAKER_0:  often noticed in these settings that Putin likes to have a lot of give and take.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think you would actually enjoy having a conversation with you.
SPEAKER_0:  But again...
SPEAKER_0:  he would always be trying to.
SPEAKER_0:  influence you.
SPEAKER_0:  Inform and influence, that's kind of, you know, part of the way that he always operates.
SPEAKER_0:  So what you would have to be trying to think about, so what is it you would want to elicit information from him? You're trying to understand the guy's worldview.
SPEAKER_0:  And what we're trying to also understand is if there's any room there...
SPEAKER_0:  where he might compromise on something.
SPEAKER_0:  So if your goal was to go in there to talk about Ukraine at this particular moment.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm in one of the...
SPEAKER_0:  problems that I've often seen in the sort of the meetings we've had with Putin which just ends up in sort of mutual recriminations.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  know, well, what about what you've done? Oh, no, you've done that about, you know, and there's always this what about-ism.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it often say, well.
SPEAKER_0:  You're saying that I've done this, but you've done that.
SPEAKER_0:  the United States invaded Iraq? What's the difference between what I'm doing and all of the things that you've been doing here?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, what you would have to try to do is kind of elicit.
SPEAKER_0:  information about why.
SPEAKER_0:  or what he is thinking about this particular moment in time and why he thinks it.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, the what about ism is a failure case. I think that shows
SPEAKER_1:  from all the interviews I've seen with him, that just shows that he doesn't trust the person on the other side. No, he doesn't.
SPEAKER_1:  Right, but I...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not cynical like people's
SPEAKER_1:  They seem to think he's some kind of KGB agent.
SPEAKER_1:  that doesn't trust anybody. I disagree. I think everybody's human.
SPEAKER_1:  And from my perspective, I'm worried about.
SPEAKER_1:  What I've seen?
SPEAKER_1:  is I think whether it's COVID, whether it's...
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  other aspects that I'm not aware of leading up to the invasion.
SPEAKER_1:  He seems to be less...
SPEAKER_1:  willing to have a
SPEAKER_1:  charismatic back and forth dialogue.
SPEAKER_0:  an open discussion. You know, actually, I mean, I said, you asked me before about, you know, that issue of trust, and he often says he only trusts himself.
SPEAKER_0:  And I said, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  He's often distrustful of people.
SPEAKER_0:  but he just trusts.
SPEAKER_0:  some people for certain things where he knows it's within their competence.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. So.
SPEAKER_0:  He has people he trusts to do things because he knows they'll do them and he knows that they'll do them well.
SPEAKER_0:  which is why, you know, he has his.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, old buddies from, you know, St. Peter's because he's known for a very long time and he knows that they want, you know, try to...
SPEAKER_0:  a fast one over him, but he also knows their strengths and their weaknesses.
SPEAKER_0:  and what they can be trusted to do. I mean, he's learning that, you know, some of the people in the military that he thought were competent.
SPEAKER_0:  or people on other things are not, right?
SPEAKER_0:  that they...
SPEAKER_0:  And he intends to actually have a lot of loyalty to people as well. Or he also kind of thinks it's best to keep him inside the tent than outside.
SPEAKER_0:  and he moves them around, you know, he kind of, okay, you know, he gives them multiple chances to redeem themselves if they don't. It's not like he...
SPEAKER_0:  has him done in? I mean, there is a lot of that in the system. But the people that he's worked with for a long time, he moves them around to something else, perhaps where they can do less harm. Although...
SPEAKER_0:  We often see that.
SPEAKER_0:  He has quite a small cadre of people that he's reliant on, and they're not up to the task, which is kind of what's happening here.
SPEAKER_0:  But also...
SPEAKER_0:  in the past has been.
SPEAKER_0:  more straightforward, just like you were saying here, more pragmatic.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think, you know, if you were engaged with him...
SPEAKER_0:  in Russian.
SPEAKER_0:  where you're actually literally speaking the same language because there's so much lost in translation.
SPEAKER_0:  I used to jump out of my skin listening to some of the phone calls.
SPEAKER_0:  because you know, the way that they're kind of relayed.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, with an interpreter.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, because you listen to the translation.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm listening to them. No, because I know I'm listening to the Russian and the translation. And the translation. I'm listening to the Russian and the translation.
SPEAKER_0:  And I haven't been at a translators institute. It's really difficult. Look, an interpreter is a trend in the moment to do something.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, the synchronicity, the synchronized or the real-time translation.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a translation.
SPEAKER_0:  is an art as well as a skill.
SPEAKER_0:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  Simultaneous translation, that's the word in English, synchronicity in Russian.
SPEAKER_0:  you're kind of focused in the moment on the fragments of the discussion, trying to render it as accurately as you possibly can.
SPEAKER_0:  And when you come out of that, you can't relay the entire conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  And often, you know, what translators do is they, you know, they take this little short hand note like journalists do.
SPEAKER_0:  Afterwards, they've just been caught up in the moment and they haven't got the big picture.
SPEAKER_0:  consecutive translation is different, you know, kind of you're trying to convey.
SPEAKER_0:  the whole mood of big chunks of dialogue that have already been there. But sometimes you might not get that right either. And it breaks up the flow of the discussion.
SPEAKER_0:  That's terrible.
SPEAKER_0:  And often it's the kind of the person who translates it's different. You know, some of our best translators are women.
SPEAKER_0:  but you know, hearing a woman's voice.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, translating a guy who has a particular guys way of speaking.
SPEAKER_0:  and a macho way of speaking and a crude way of speaking.
SPEAKER_0:  It'll be that Putin or I've seen that happen with Erdogan, the president of Turkey.
SPEAKER_0:  and it gets translated by a much more refined female speaker, you've just lost the whole thing.
SPEAKER_0:  And many of the translators on the Russian side...
SPEAKER_0:  and not.
SPEAKER_0:  competent in English in the way that you would hope they are. It's not just that they're not native speakers. They're just not trained to the same high standards they used to be in the past.
SPEAKER_0:  and you just lose the nuance, you lose the feel.
SPEAKER_0:  you almost need the interpretive actor doing the kind of the...
SPEAKER_0:  the interpretation for that, you need to match it as much as you can in the way that you do voiceovers in film.
SPEAKER_0:  Best way to talk to Putin.
SPEAKER_0:  is.
SPEAKER_0:  One on one.
SPEAKER_0:  in his own language. I have a really great friend here who is one of the best interpreters of Putin is often asked by the media.
SPEAKER_0:  to interpret farm.
SPEAKER_0:  he was at the institute that I was at, I mean I know him from that kind of period.
SPEAKER_0:  And he is just excellent, just like Pavel Palashenko was absolutely phenomenal at interpreting Gorbachev. Always good.
SPEAKER_0:  interpreting accurately because...
SPEAKER_0:  Gorbachev made lots of grammatical gaffes and...
SPEAKER_0:  sometimes was Gorbachev himself would joke that Palashenko spoke better for Gorbachev than Gorbachev could himself. But Putin is actually quite precise and careful in the way that he speaks, because there's a lot of menace sometimes to things deliberately, other times there's lots of humour.
SPEAKER_0:  and he's telling a joke for a particular reason.
SPEAKER_0:  And all of it is, I mean, he actually uses the richness of the Russian language and the crudity of language that can't be conveyed in English. Across the facial expressions that go along with it? Body language, the way that he sits back in the chair and slouches.
SPEAKER_0:  the kind of the way that he makes fun of people and he kind of uses irony.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of it is just lost and it needs to be conveyed.
SPEAKER_1:  the depth.
SPEAKER_1:  of humor and wit. I've met quite a few.
SPEAKER_1:  political leaders like that and this week only Russian when I was traveling Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  Um
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know how you translate that. I think it's almost the other person that reminds me like that a little bit as Obama.
SPEAKER_1:  There's Obama had a wit.
SPEAKER_1:  and intelligence but like a
SPEAKER_1:  He would smile as you said something.
SPEAKER_1:  that add a lot to it, like that he's trolling you or he's being sarcastic or the gather it
SPEAKER_1:  me converting into words. It's obvious that all English speakers, if they listen to Obama, but if you have to translate to a different language, I think you're going to lose a lot of time.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean when I watched the...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I watched many of Putin's speeches, you know, kind of just in Russian, not looking at any of the, you know, the subtitles or anything. And it's just watching the way that his body language is at the time when he's saying things, whether you smoke, you'll sneer.
SPEAKER_0:  He'll laugh.
SPEAKER_0:  he'll ad lib, you know, kind of from something that obviously kind of, you know, wasn't there on the prepared speech.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's really critical.
SPEAKER_0:  And you know, kind of a lot, some people speak, you know, like Trump, it just needs kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  words.
SPEAKER_0:  Puh-ah.
SPEAKER_0:  putting the words are very important.
SPEAKER_0:  Trumpets, the atmosphere, it's the kind of the way you feel about things, it's the buzz you get, you know, it's revving people up.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the kind of slogans and.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin, he's conveying a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  and what he's saying.
SPEAKER_1:  I think, I mean, of course I don't know much because I only speak Russian and English.
SPEAKER_1:  but I have in English or Russian have not met.
SPEAKER_1:  almost anyone ever.
SPEAKER_1:  as interesting in conversation as Putin.
SPEAKER_1:  the
SPEAKER_1:  I think he shines not in speeches, but in interaction.
SPEAKER_0:  with others. Yeah, when you watch those interviews and things with him, and I've been at many of these sessions, it's been hours of him.
SPEAKER_0:  Hurrying questions.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like watching a boxer sparring.
SPEAKER_0:  in a kind of training bout.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, come on, give me another one.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, and it's kind of like he prides himself in.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  He's made mistakes.
SPEAKER_0:  often.
SPEAKER_0:  the breadth of the issues that he's often covered has been fascinating. Nice buckle bite.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of really detailed notes about this because you learn a term.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's not about his world view again.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, he does live in a certain box, like we all do.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  And again, his world experience is not as extensive as you would hope it would be.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's why you have to really pay attention. That's where we've messed up.
SPEAKER_0:  That's where we haven't really paid a lot of attention to.
SPEAKER_0:  what he's been saying, he's been telegraphing.
SPEAKER_0:  this.
SPEAKER_0:  grievances, dissatisfaction.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm gonna do something for years.
SPEAKER_1:  And the thing is during war time.
SPEAKER_1:  the...
SPEAKER_1:  combined with propaganda.
SPEAKER_1:  and the narratives.
SPEAKER_1:  of resentment and grievance that you dig in.
SPEAKER_1:  on those.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe you start out not believing it, but you're sure it's all going to believe it eventually.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you convince yourself over time. Yeah. And that makes you feel calm, but sometimes when you're telling a lie, you feel kind of Whoosh, on 1970s, The Wさん K— Rule William triple Inaccuracy Of opponents
SPEAKER_0:  You're in a position like Putin. 22 years now, come at one 23 years.
SPEAKER_0:  could be out there for...
SPEAKER_0:  36 years.
SPEAKER_0:  you become more and more rigid. I mean, this is again, you know, something that you see in history.
SPEAKER_0:  You look at people through history who've moved from being left-wing in their perspectives to hard right.
SPEAKER_0:  they kind of have a sort of an ossification or a rigidity emerges in their views. And again,
SPEAKER_0:  I used to have these arguments with Professor Pace about Lenin.
SPEAKER_0:  because he would talk about it. And I said, yeah, but he didn't change his mind from being 18. Have you not thought about that? I mean, it's like, we're not formed fully formed individuals at 18.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't know anything.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, something, but not everything. I mean, obviously the younger context, you know, the kind of the way that you kind of grow up, the place you grow up, the things that happen to you, the traumas you have.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, all of these have an impact, but if you don't grow beyond all of that...
SPEAKER_0:  and Putin's been stuck in place since 2000.
SPEAKER_0:  when he became president. It's not out and about.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of being a man of the people.
SPEAKER_0:  He's not doing the kind of things that he used to do. Yeah, he gets out there and he goes to Kazakhstan and, you know, got him.
SPEAKER_0:  Tajikistan and...
SPEAKER_0:  He goes to China and he does this and that and then under Covid he didn't go anywhere.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, very few places.
SPEAKER_0:  And so he's got stuck.
SPEAKER_0:  And that worries me a lot because you could see before that he had a bit more of flexibility of thought.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's why nobody should be in place forever. You should always kind of like get out there and go out there and learn a new skill, you know, kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  He needs to sort of, you know, he needs to get out more and do something different.
SPEAKER_1:  You had an interesting point, you've made that.
SPEAKER_1:  both Vladimir Zelensky and Putin are thinking about.
SPEAKER_1:  They're just politicians.
SPEAKER_1:  They're thinking about the 2024 election.
SPEAKER_1:  which is coming up for both.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I've said that in some of the other interviews. Yeah, that's true. That's so interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I... Our election's going to be pretty much at the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  as the US election. Yeah, others will be before. I mean, because sometime in that, you know, early part of the year of the presidential election.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. And also, I don't know if you know about US elections, but they actually last way long.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, they got grown up. We're in it now, aren't we? You know, already.
SPEAKER_1:  Starting. So there's going to be a significant overlap.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, you know, you're right. That actually comes into play.
SPEAKER_1:  in their calculus.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it was one of the reasons why Putin invaded in February 2022, because it was going to be two years, I mean, he thought it'd be over by March of 2022, and he got two years to prepare for.
SPEAKER_0:  the election and you've got a big boost. You've got a boost from Crimea. I mean, I didn't mention that before. I mean, one of the reasons for inverting Crimea.
SPEAKER_0:  and annexing or invading Ukraine the first time, and I asked in Crimea, was, look what happened to his ratings?
SPEAKER_0:  They went from kind of declining, and they were still pretty good, you know, by anybody's standards, to just rocketing off into the stratosphere. I mean, I didn't really meet anybody in Russia who thought that Alex in Crimea was...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of a bad thing.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, even kind of people who were post-Putin on so many other things, Crimea was, you know, Krimnash, they kept saying. You know, this is kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, we got it back.
SPEAKER_0:  It should never have gone away. It was ours. But this is more complex.
SPEAKER_0:  And he wasn't, I don't think at the time, planning on annexing all of Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  when he went into this special military operation, he was going to try to turn it into what Belarus has become. Different numbers were written.
SPEAKER_0:  Bring back the Commonwealth of Independent States or the Union than a new Union with.
SPEAKER_0:  Belarus and Ukraine and Russia over time. But certainly.
SPEAKER_0:  Remove your cranners.
SPEAKER_0:  a major independent factor on the world stage.
SPEAKER_0:  Consolidate Crimea and
SPEAKER_0:  maybe, you know, kind of incorporate Donetsk and Luhansk.
SPEAKER_0:  that was also a possibility, but it wasn't.
SPEAKER_0:  He wasn't in his intention, in any case, to have something on this kind of scale. He only wanted to get on with then preparing for what was going to be.
SPEAKER_0:  He would think the cakewalk, the shoe in.
SPEAKER_0:  of the next presidential election.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, last time around, he had to invite a bit of competition with his...
SPEAKER_0:  person who's reputed to be his goddaughter.
SPEAKER_0:  in your subject.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, to put a bit of, you know, kind of entertainment for people.
SPEAKER_0:  the next time around, maybe he wasn't really planning on running.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, against any other.
SPEAKER_0:  serious opposition. He was just going to have the acclaim of the great leader.
SPEAKER_0:  present she.
SPEAKER_0:  in China.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin was basically, I think he also hoped that he would be able to devolve some authority away, you know, kind of so he's more like the...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, the supreme leader kind of figure.
SPEAKER_0:  the czar-like figure, the monarch.
SPEAKER_0:  and then other people get on with the...
SPEAKER_0:  Chief Executive.
SPEAKER_0:  prime ministerial run in the country and he could kind of like step back and just enjoy this. Maybe there was going to be again a new union of
SPEAKER_0:  Belarus, Russia and...
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  than Ukraine in some fashion, and he would preside over that.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of opposition, you've criticized the famed Putin critic, Alexei Navalny.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the nature of your criticism?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it hasn't really been a kind of a criticism in the way that...
SPEAKER_0:  people have implied, but more just reminding people that Navalny isn't some stooge of the West as other people have, you know, kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  depicted him in the Russian firm, but saying that this is kind of, he's pro-Western.
SPEAKER_0:  He's a Russian nationalist.
SPEAKER_0:  and a Russian patriot.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, in the past.
SPEAKER_0:  He's articulated.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, things are not sort of dissimilar from some of the people around Putin.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's more just reminding people that, you know, just because you kind of see somebody.
SPEAKER_0:  as a kind of in an opposition figure or somebody who might be more palatable from your perspective looking from the West.
SPEAKER_0:  they're not always going to be what you think they are.
SPEAKER_0:  Now Alexei Navalny is a Russian.
SPEAKER_0:  And in a particular Russian context, he's different from Putin.
SPEAKER_0:  but he wouldn't necessarily.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of run the Russian system in ways that we will like.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's not a kind of a criticism, it's more of a critique of the way that we look at things.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's a mistake to always say, well, this is pro-Western or this is a liberal. I mean, what the heck does that mean, pro-Western?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, he's a Russian.
SPEAKER_0:  is a Russian nationalist and a Russian patriot. He's often been quite critical about immigration.
SPEAKER_0:  He's had some negative views about, you know, at one point, when I said, don't feed the Caucasus.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of played upon some of the.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, the racial and ethnic.
SPEAKER_0:  tensions inside of Russia itself as well.
SPEAKER_0:  Now he is a pluralist and he wants to have...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, different.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  set of political actors there, but he also isn't promoting revolution. He's not Lenin. He's not one to bring down the state.
SPEAKER_0:  He wants to kind of, you know, change.
SPEAKER_0:  the people.
SPEAKER_0:  who are in charge, that's what he's been basically focused on and you know he might have.
SPEAKER_0:  and have things done, do things.
SPEAKER_0:  Been a wee elsewhere, might not like.
SPEAKER_1:  And I guess the bigger picture there is.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not trivial to know that if you place another human in power
SPEAKER_1:  To replace the current human and power that things are going to be better. They could be a lot worse
SPEAKER_1:  because
SPEAKER_1:  there's a momentum to a system.
SPEAKER_1:  A system is bigger than just its leader, even when that leader has
SPEAKER_1:  huge amount of power.
SPEAKER_0:  That's absolutely right. And he grew up in that same system. Now, he's younger than Putin.
SPEAKER_0:  so he's got a different generational perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  and he's not wedded to the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  or some concept of the Russian Empire. He doesn't seem to spend a lot of time, I don't know what he's doing in jail, but he's probably not sitting around reading Lomonosov and the great kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  tracks of Russian history. Could be, actually.
SPEAKER_0:  But I mean, I think Navalny has a different worldview on a different perspective, just like Medvedev.
SPEAKER_0:  was different.
SPEAKER_0:  in his time and presidency and made some.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  changes and some innovations there, but don't think that they're going to be radically different because look Gorbachev, I mean he was.
SPEAKER_0:  So different from Andropov and Cheney and Co. Now this is the person.
SPEAKER_0:  but he was also constrained by the system.
SPEAKER_0:  And he wanted to have change, but he wanted evolutionary change. He didn't know how to do it, but he didn't want to bring the whole system down. He wanted to become a fan of Chekhov.
SPEAKER_0:  when he came in after that whole period of...
SPEAKER_0:  everybody trying to figure out what to do after Stalin had died and there was all this kind of back and forth and eventually Khrushchev emerges and you know he tries to make changes to the system but he's also a creature.
SPEAKER_0:  of a very specific context. He's grown up in the same system, and it kind of brings...
SPEAKER_0:  all kinds of elements of chaos there.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's the whole thing.
SPEAKER_0:  and gets into a standoff with the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  that we know as the Cuban Missile Crisis.
SPEAKER_0:  then eventually, you know, it gets removed.
SPEAKER_0:  We're looking at what's happening in the United Kingdom right now.
SPEAKER_0:  They've just churned through.
SPEAKER_0:  Three.
SPEAKER_0:  Prime Minister's and actually
SPEAKER_0:  five prime ministers in, you know, kind of as many years, but all of those prime ministers have come out of the context of the Conservative Party in the role.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of just shades of.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, the same thing. They've all come out of the same academic and.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of privileged backgrounds, even Rishi Sunak, the new prime minister, was number one—air
SPEAKER_0:  you know, Indian or Anglo-Indian Prime Minister in British history. It was a kind of phenomenal, you know, kind of as a child of Indian immigrants, but also...
SPEAKER_0:  person of great privilege from the same academic and party background as the others.
SPEAKER_0:  So there are always differences with those human beings, but those contexts matter a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  What is the probability that Russia attacks Ukraine with a tactical nuclear weapon?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, Putin's definitely been thinking about it, right? I mean, he is the kind of person, if he's got an instrument, who wants to figure out how to use it.
SPEAKER_0:  We look at polonium, we look at Novichok, we look at all kinds of things.
SPEAKER_0:  that has also presided over in Syria.
SPEAKER_0:  He has put in charge of the war in Ukraine now.
SPEAKER_0:  General Svrkin is known as General Armageddon, the kind of person who pretty much
SPEAKER_0:  facilitated the use of chemical weapons in Syria, for example.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  don't think that Putin hasn't thought about how ruthless he can possibly be. The question is really the calculation. It's his.
SPEAKER_0:  estimation of the probability that it will get the desired effect.
SPEAKER_0:  We keep talking about this idea of escalate de-escalate. That's not what the Russians, you know, how they call it, but it's the whole idea that you do something really outrageous.
SPEAKER_0:  to get everybody else to back up.
SPEAKER_0:  Now when you talked about the precedent.
SPEAKER_0:  that the United States set.
SPEAKER_0:  of detonating.
SPEAKER_0:  the nuclear weapons in Hiroshima and Nagasaki.
SPEAKER_0:  He obviously meant the precedent of using nuclear weapons, of course, which of course
SPEAKER_0:  we would then say, well, we showed them.
SPEAKER_0:  how the imp...
SPEAKER_0:  permissibility of ever doing that again. What he's talking about is the precedent of
SPEAKER_0:  escalating to such an extent that you stop the war because he reads that saying, well,
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  US dropped the bombs on Hiroshima and Nagasaki, the war was brought to a quick conclusion.
SPEAKER_0:  Of course, there's a huge debate in America about whether it was necessary to do that, whether the war was ending anywhere. Did that really change the minds of the Japanese high command?
SPEAKER_0:  and being written about that.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course, the revulsion that people felt in the wake of that was just, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  just the shock of what actually happened and we've spent.
SPEAKER_0:  70 years, you know, basically coming to terms with the fact that we did something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  the firebombing. We've also looked at all the bombing in Vietnam and everywhere.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, all these massive bombing campaigns and realizing they actually often had the
SPEAKER_0:  opposite effect.
SPEAKER_0:  contributed and there's a lot of, you know, scholars suggesting it did to the end of the war. But all of the big bombing campaigns, the destruction actually prolonged wars because they made people fight back as we're kind of seeing in the case of Ukraine. So Putin has to calculate.
SPEAKER_0:  The probability.
SPEAKER_0:  that if he uses some.
SPEAKER_0:  tactical nuclear weapon that it will get the desired effect which is get us to capitulate.
SPEAKER_0:  and Ukraine to capitulate, us to capitulate, meaning the United States and the Europeans.
SPEAKER_0:  not supporting Ukraine anymore, pushing towards the negotiating table and negotiating Ukraine away
SPEAKER_0:  and Ukraine saying, okay, we give up.
SPEAKER_0:  like happened in.
SPEAKER_0:  Hiroshima and Nagasaki in Japan.
SPEAKER_0:  It's his calculation.
SPEAKER_0:  as much as anything else, which is really important. He said, we have to show him that he won't get that out of it. It's kind of less our probability and kind of the odds of it. It's just how he calculates that probability.
SPEAKER_0:  of getting what he wants.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I guess that's how the game of poker works. It's your probability.
SPEAKER_1:  and your estimate of their probability.
SPEAKER_1:  and your estimate of their estimate of your probability and. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So it goes on. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I think he has two tools, right? So one is the actual use of nuclear weapons and then the threat of
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, the thrust is very effective.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  the more.
SPEAKER_1:  really you make the threat. That's right.
SPEAKER_1:  This, like, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  the more you approach the actual use.
SPEAKER_1:  I get very close.
SPEAKER_0:  She's already using.
SPEAKER_0:  Chernobyl, Zaporizhzhya.
SPEAKER_0:  And then.
SPEAKER_0:  Usually, in Ukraine, they're the...
SPEAKER_0:  nuclear reactor. So he's using civilian nuclear reactors as a dirty bomb. So it's ironic that
SPEAKER_0:  He has Sergey Shoigu, his defense minister calling people up to the Ukraine to use a dirty bomb. Are you doing it?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, what is kind of more destructive than stirring up all the radioactive dust and Chernobos you send your troops through?
SPEAKER_0:  for example, or shelling the Chernobyl plant and the sarcophagus and putting it at risk.
SPEAKER_0:  and that Parisian you've got the...
SPEAKER_0:  International Atomic Energy Agency running out there in utter panic and kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  also trying to intervene in the conflict.
SPEAKER_0:  So you're putting, you know, civilian nuclear.
SPEAKER_0:  reactors at risk. I mean that also has a great added effect of cutting off.
SPEAKER_0:  Ukraine's power supply because Zaporizhzhia in particular was
SPEAKER_0:  What was it, a third of?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I'm Ukraine's.
SPEAKER_0:  power generation or some really high percentage, I'd have to go back and take a look at that. But that's a twofer. It's kind of a double effect there.
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  undermining.
SPEAKER_0:  power generation, also frightening Germans and others who've already been very worried about nuclear power and increasing your leverage on that energy front.
SPEAKER_0:  but also scaring people.
SPEAKER_0:  from the perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  of the use of.
SPEAKER_0:  nuclear weapon does.
SPEAKER_0:  reactors also become a nuclear weapon tactically deployed. And as you said,
SPEAKER_0:  the discussion of using a nuclear weapon.
SPEAKER_0:  and engendering all those fears.
SPEAKER_0:  And he's already got an effect.
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone's running around talking about the Cooper Missile Crisis and secret diplomacy.
SPEAKER_0:  and how we negotiate away Ukraine in return for Putin not blowing up a nuclear weapon.
SPEAKER_0:  So he's got a lot of people obviously talking about that.
SPEAKER_1:  Sorry for the difficult and dark question. It could be for you directly or more like.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think we have a plan for this?
SPEAKER_1:  What happens if he does?
SPEAKER_1:  Drop a nuclear.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you have a sense that the United States
SPEAKER_1:  has a good plan.
SPEAKER_0:  I know we're talking about it.
SPEAKER_0:  I think we probably have several plans because it depends on what, where.
SPEAKER_0:  When? How?
SPEAKER_1:  But don't, and also don't these things.
SPEAKER_0:  I put it very quickly.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, there's also signaling and signs of movement there. I mean, I want to be very, you know, kind of careful about this. But then the thing is, it's also very important that we do this.
SPEAKER_0:  with other nuclear powers.
SPEAKER_0:  So the other thing that's different.
SPEAKER_0:  from how it might have been in the past, and particularly different from the Cuban missile crisis and the Euro missile crisis, they're not the only nuclear players.
SPEAKER_0:  China has an emerging nuclear arsenal now.
SPEAKER_0:  Less on the strategic side, but building it up.
SPEAKER_0:  but very much on the intermediate range and tactical.
SPEAKER_0:  Kim Jong-un is firing off weapons left, right and center at the moment in North Korea. We've got other rogue states. Putin's behaving like a rogue state, just to be very clear.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is what we've got with Kim Jong-un in North Korea.
SPEAKER_0:  We've also got India.
SPEAKER_0:  and Pakistan.
SPEAKER_0:  And we've got other states we're not supposed to talk about that we know have nuclear capacities and others that would like to have nuclear capacity.
SPEAKER_0:  and the whole questioner here.
SPEAKER_0:  is about also proliferation.
SPEAKER_0:  getting back to that time when Ukraine had...
SPEAKER_0:  Nuclear weapons, at least.
SPEAKER_0:  there on its territory in southern Belarus and Kazakhstan, you've got to wonder, was it wise for them to give it up?
SPEAKER_0:  We were worried about, you know, kind of loose nukes.
SPEAKER_0:  nuclear weapons getting out of hand.
SPEAKER_0:  proliferation at the time, we wanted fewer nuclear powers.
SPEAKER_0:  Russia wanted that too.
SPEAKER_0:  Now we're going to have more.
SPEAKER_0:  We've got more.
SPEAKER_0:  And what Putin is saying is, well, that was stupid of Ukraine to give up the nuclear weapons.
SPEAKER_0:  In fact...
SPEAKER_0:  my colleagues and I back in our report back in the US, saw kind of suggest they shouldn't give him up.
SPEAKER_0:  And then that's why we had the Budapest Mamorandum. That's why the United States and the United Kingdom in particular.
SPEAKER_0:  have basically some responsibility and obligation, going back to 1994 when they promised Ukraine that gave up the nuclear weapons, that territorial integrity and sovereignty would remain intact, some obligation to actually do something to step up.
SPEAKER_0:  If we step back from that, this is the thing that people are not talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, what about nuclear proliferation? If you're South Korea, you're Japan, you know, you're any other country that's kind of worrying about your neighbors.
SPEAKER_0:  and what might happen to you.
SPEAKER_0:  Just like India and Pakistan are both like, we've got to kind of keep our strategic nuclear balance here.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything is up for question. How does the wanted nuclear weapon?
SPEAKER_0:  The Turks already want one, they've talked about one for years.
SPEAKER_0:  know, why should the Iranians be the only one with an Islamic?
SPEAKER_0:  nuclear weapon.
SPEAKER_0:  And if we know that Iran has...
SPEAKER_0:  Break up capacity now.
SPEAKER_0:  Saudis and all the other states that are in opposition to Iran will also want to have some nuclear capacity. And the United States before wanted to maintain everything under the nuclear umbrella.
SPEAKER_0:  What are the reasons why Sweden and Finland are joining there to us because of suddenly all of these nuclear threats?
SPEAKER_0:  Sweden was actually the last country on the planet to want to have nuclear weapons. They were actually pushing for a ban on nuclear weapons in the United Nations. Now that Putin's doing the nuclear saber-rattling.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, they're talking about joining.
SPEAKER_0:  and are on the verge of joining.
SPEAKER_0:  a nuclear alliance.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, see what's happening here, so...
SPEAKER_0:  We have to make it more and more difficult for Putin to even contemplate that. That's why people are saying this is reckless. This is irresponsible.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin is actually making the world less safe for himself down the line either, but he's thinking short term here.
SPEAKER_0:  He's thinking, what can I do? What do I actually have?
SPEAKER_0:  You can also destroy lots of infrastructure as he's doing.
SPEAKER_0:  You can use subversion, you know, we're worried about all of the undersea cables, all these weird things happening, you know, off Orkney or in the Mediterranean or...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, all these other things that are happening, not stream to pipelines, other infrastructure, there's all kinds of other things that you can do as well here.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not just.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, again, this is civilian nuclear threat.
SPEAKER_0:  of blowing up one of the reactors.
SPEAKER_0:  Now it's gonna be.
SPEAKER_0:  sure about where the wind turns and the wind blows.
SPEAKER_0:  and there's all kinds of things to factor in here, but Putin is definitely sitting around.
SPEAKER_0:  calculating with other people, what can I do?
SPEAKER_0:  to turn this around.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, he still thinks that he can win this.
SPEAKER_0:  or in other words, he can end it on his terms.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  Done yet, Luhansk.
SPEAKER_0:  Harrison, Zaporizhzhia.
SPEAKER_0:  and capitulation.
SPEAKER_0:  all recognized as being part of Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  or he can freeze it and then kind of figure out where it goes from there, what other pressure he can put on. I mean I'm sure he's confident he can get rid of Zelensky.
SPEAKER_0:  And it can prevail over us. I mean, the UK is going through prime ministers faster than I'm changing my socks.
SPEAKER_0:  you know so it's like a
SPEAKER_0:  He can prevail on the...
SPEAKER_0:  he can have an impact on the political.
SPEAKER_0:  seen in Europe and elsewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, everyone's talking about winter coming and...
SPEAKER_0:  I know Putin's thinking, yeah, great, I've destroyed the infrastructure.
SPEAKER_0:  of.
SPEAKER_0:  Are you worried about the winter?
SPEAKER_0:  Well yeah, but I mean look, the other thing is that we have to...
SPEAKER_0:  start preparing.
SPEAKER_0:  We have to start thinking about this. We've got a wartime economy situation.
SPEAKER_0:  That's where we are. We've got the home front to think about as well. Putin has declared war on us. He did that on September 30th, and he's done it at other points as well.
SPEAKER_0:  not paid attention.
SPEAKER_0:  But he was pretty explicit in September 30th. Let me go back and watch.
SPEAKER_0:  that speech.
SPEAKER_0:  And, you know, he...
SPEAKER_0:  is gambling that people will go back.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, to...
SPEAKER_0:  basically taking Russian gas and oil but...
SPEAKER_0:  It's not going to be that simple.
SPEAKER_0:  as well. you
SPEAKER_0:  And then the question has to be, do we really kind of think he's going to play fair after that?
SPEAKER_0:  when he's kind of also.
SPEAKER_0:  shown that he can leverage that.
SPEAKER_0:  It's such a complicated world. It is complicated. It's very complicated.
SPEAKER_1:  It's never, I mean, it feels like things are heating up.
SPEAKER_1:  and China.
SPEAKER_1:  is very quiet right now.
SPEAKER_0:  they're watching what happens. I mean for president Xi...
SPEAKER_0:  It is trying to-
SPEAKER_0:  consolidaties.
SPEAKER_0:  even further after the party congress but
SPEAKER_0:  He doesn't want to look like he made a mistake by backing Putin.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, he thought Putin was also going to be.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  Ukraine would probably be open for massive Chinese investment. China was the largest investor.
SPEAKER_0:  in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  before the war.
SPEAKER_0:  Largest single investor, I mean the EU was bigger of course.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you hope the war ends?
SPEAKER_1:  in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  Well.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I do hope.
SPEAKER_0:  it ends.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, with a ceasefire and a negotiated solution, but it has to be with Russia compromising on something.
SPEAKER_0:  and that's not where we are right now. Do you think?
SPEAKER_1:  both sides.
SPEAKER_1:  Bye.
SPEAKER_1:  be willing to compromise.
SPEAKER_0:  Most wars always end in that way.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, nobody's ever happy.
SPEAKER_1:  but they don't seem to either side.
SPEAKER_1:  like legitimately doesn't want to compromise.
SPEAKER_0:  right now.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, because the thing is that...
SPEAKER_0:  for Ukraine right now.
SPEAKER_0:  Anything is a compromise.
SPEAKER_0:  at his expense, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Fust devastation.
SPEAKER_0:  unbelievable casualty rates.
SPEAKER_0:  biggest refugee crisis since World War II.
SPEAKER_0:  Russia's just said, sorry, this is our territory, it's not just Crimea. I think there could have been a negotiation over that.
SPEAKER_0:  but you know, Donetsk and Lukács. I mean, we've got all kinds of formulas we've had all the way through history.
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  putting things under a kind of guardianship receivership of territory, the United Nations, all kinds of different ways of formulating that, we could have easily been creative.
SPEAKER_0:  for Russia's best ex-sign up. Sorry we've taken this.
SPEAKER_0:  And any other negotiations, just you recognizing this for us not doing more destruction.
SPEAKER_0:  That is not the basis for negotiation.
SPEAKER_0:  And having people come and just laying those terms down is not a starting position.
SPEAKER_0:  I think Russia...
SPEAKER_0:  is also.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, I know.
SPEAKER_0:  dilemma of its own making now because Putin has made it very difficult.
SPEAKER_0:  to compromise just by everything that he said.
SPEAKER_0:  Now for Ukraine they've already won.
SPEAKER_0:  a great moral.
SPEAKER_0:  political and military victory.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just hard to see it, right?
SPEAKER_0:  at the particular moment.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  what the Finns did in the Winter War, which the Finns were devastated by the Winter War as well but they pushed them back.
SPEAKER_0:  Now the Finns lost a lot of territory, they lost Karelia and...
SPEAKER_0:  huge spares of territory.
SPEAKER_0:  they've got to be Finland.
SPEAKER_0:  and now they're joining NATO, but they've been part of the EU.
SPEAKER_0:  The question is how to...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, get Ukraine to be.
SPEAKER_0:  Ukraine in a success.
SPEAKER_0:  But you know, it's...
SPEAKER_0:  And that's the challenge, again, they've already won.
SPEAKER_0:  psychologically, politically, militarily.
SPEAKER_0:  Because poop doesn't-
SPEAKER_0:  succeeded in what he wanted to do, but he has succeeded in completely and utterly devastating by taking advantage of heue puthite's
SPEAKER_0:  And this is the kind of the old Muscovite.
SPEAKER_0:  old Russian imperial, old Soviet mentality, you know, going all the way back to when the
SPEAKER_0:  Muscovites were the bagmen for the
SPEAKER_0:  You know, the horde, for the Mongols, it was destruction. You know, you don't play with us, we'll destroy you.
SPEAKER_0:  People talk about it as mafia, but it's old. You know, all you have to go down is go and see.
SPEAKER_0:  Tarkovsky's Andrei Rublyov.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I remember seeing that film when I was first as a student in Moscow and just being...
SPEAKER_0:  Whoa, this is so brutal.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, this is...
SPEAKER_0:  just unremittingly brutal.
SPEAKER_0:  because the whole point is...
SPEAKER_0:  you show people who's the boss.
SPEAKER_0:  The destruction is the point of things as well.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  you know you are.
SPEAKER_0:  emphasizing your.
SPEAKER_0:  Domination.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's what Putin is doing right now is saying.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, you wanna go?
SPEAKER_0:  in a different direction, so be it, but I'm going to make you suffer.
SPEAKER_0:  Remember when Hodocovsky?
SPEAKER_0:  got out of.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  penal colony when Putin let him out eventually.
SPEAKER_0:  He said he's suffered enough.
SPEAKER_0:  but he suffered for 10, 11 years.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think Putin feels that Ukraine has suffered enough at this point, or we have suffered enough.
SPEAKER_1:  apart.
SPEAKER_1:  of this invasion that's punishment for something.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's medieval.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean look, we're all capable of the same things, right? There was all that destruction in... That's what Assad was like in Syria, like his father.
SPEAKER_0:  you destroy because you teach them a lesson.
SPEAKER_0:  And look, Britain did that in the colonial era. All the history of British colonialism is exactly the same.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, all the Mao Mao, you know, and Kenya, you know, up until recent times, brutality.
SPEAKER_0:  teaching people, you know, give to...
SPEAKER_0:  teaching them a lesson.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to suffer.
SPEAKER_0:  The US did it. I mean, we did it with the Native Americans. We did it all over the place, you know, as well.
SPEAKER_0:  This is kind of what big.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, state to do.
SPEAKER_0:  different points in history. Just that Russia has not moved on from that.
SPEAKER_0:  And we've learned some lessons later. I hope we've fully internalized them of things that we've done, and kind of the past United States.
SPEAKER_0:  Ideally, you're trying to do better, and most of Europe's trying to do better as well. Think about France and Algeria, you know, again.
SPEAKER_0:  We can see this in many different settings.
SPEAKER_0:  But I think enough of Putin right now.
SPEAKER_0:  He hasn't taught all of us.
SPEAKER_0:  sufficient to lessen.
SPEAKER_1:  I just.
SPEAKER_1:  I talked to hundreds of people in Ukraine and.
SPEAKER_1:  The Tough Thing.
SPEAKER_1:  The inspiring thing is that there's a unity, the tough thing is
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of them speak.
SPEAKER_1:  intensity of hate.
SPEAKER_1:  towards not just Russia, but Russians.
SPEAKER_0:  Russians. Europeans felt about Germany and Germans.
SPEAKER_0:  at the end of World War II.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  generational heat.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, I don't think that hate.
SPEAKER_1:  is gonna pass.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it might well take a generation. I mean, I won't.
SPEAKER_0:  when I was a kid in the-
SPEAKER_0:  70s I went on exchanges to Germany.
SPEAKER_0:  And that was like 30 years.
SPEAKER_0:  more than 30 years after the end of the war. My grandfather had fought in World War I.
SPEAKER_0:  wouldn't speak to my parents when they sent me on a-
SPEAKER_0:  And we haven't fought World War II, we fought World War I, and we hated the Germans.
SPEAKER_0:  And he did not want me going to Germany as an exchange student. He refused to meet, you know, kind of the German kid who...
SPEAKER_0:  came to stay at my house.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, for example, I mean, it takes a long time to...
SPEAKER_0:  and it takes a long time to get over this.
SPEAKER_0:  But you do, and we have.
SPEAKER_0:  We have in Europe, and that was the whole point.
SPEAKER_0:  of all of that kind of exercise of European unity.
SPEAKER_0:  after World War II. Now the big challenge is-
SPEAKER_0:  What do we do with Russia? Because a lot of people are talking about we can't have European security without Russia. That's what people are saying.
SPEAKER_0:  We can't overhear.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of with Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, so how do we deal with this? We've got a-
SPEAKER_0:  basically it's going to be like Japan.
SPEAKER_0:  and Germany after World War II, after this. Just the level.
SPEAKER_0:  of the atrocities that have been carried out. As you said, the level of hatred.
SPEAKER_0:  But we found a way of doing it.
SPEAKER_0:  Now, a lot of it will require.
SPEAKER_0:  change on the part of Russia as well.
SPEAKER_0:  and Russians and really thinking about this. I mean Gorbachev before I tried to do.
SPEAKER_0:  in the late 1980s with.
SPEAKER_0:  the black spots in.
SPEAKER_0:  with glass sauce with.
SPEAKER_0:  openness and talking about Russian history just kind of never sort of withered on the vine.
SPEAKER_0:  as time went on.
SPEAKER_1:  What gives you hope?
SPEAKER_1:  about the future.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, my hope comes into the fact that we've done things before, that we've got ourselves out of tough times and we've overcome stuff, and in people, because I meet amazing people.
SPEAKER_0:  You just talked about hundreds of people that you've met within Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  and people all think differently.
SPEAKER_0:  Contexts and circumstances change and people can evolve. Some people get stuck.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin's got stuck.
SPEAKER_0:  but people can evolve.
SPEAKER_0:  And I do think that if we all pull together...
SPEAKER_0:  and we've seen this in so many contexts, we can find solutions to things.
SPEAKER_0:  just like we get back again to our discussion about scientists.
SPEAKER_0:  and just the kind of amazing breakthroughs of.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, what we did.
SPEAKER_0:  on COVID or done on, you know, kind of other.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, diseases and things.
SPEAKER_0:  there is some similarities as a pathology around war and conflict.
SPEAKER_0:  Years ago in the 1990s I worked on
SPEAKER_0:  know a lot of
SPEAKER_0:  for projects that were funded by the Carnegie Corporation.
SPEAKER_0:  of the United States under the then presidency of David Hamburg, who was a scientist.
SPEAKER_0:  and actually did see a lot of parallels between the sort of like the pathology of disease and
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of the.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  pestilence, conflict kind of idea.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course, these parallels, you have to be very careful because they're not neat. But there was kind of like an idea in there and how do you sort of treat this? How do you deal with this?
SPEAKER_0:  And we did come up with all kinds of ideas and things that are still out there.
SPEAKER_0:  We've created institutions that have helped to keep the peace. We just-
SPEAKER_0:  they got to them.
SPEAKER_0:  allowed them to.
SPEAKER_0:  degrade just like the United Nations and we've created.
SPEAKER_0:  problems inside them.
SPEAKER_0:  like the veto power of the permanent powers on the
SPEAKER_0:  UN Security Council, but we can change that.
SPEAKER_0:  You've just got to have a will. And I do think out there, there are sufficient people with a will.
SPEAKER_0:  and we've just got to get people mobilized. I mean, I'm always amazed by how people can mobilize themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  around a crisis. Remember Winston Churchill, I don't quote all the time because I can never remember all his quotes.
SPEAKER_0:  But I do remember the one about never let a good crisis go to waste.
SPEAKER_0:  And I always think that that, you know, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  We shouldn't let this crisis go to waste.
SPEAKER_0:  and something else can come out of this. Just like in Ukraine, we've worried before about...
SPEAKER_0:  corruption in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  Influence the oligarchs, we've got our own oligarchs here in the US we need to deal with as well.
SPEAKER_0:  but this is a chance to do it differently.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it really is a chance to do things differently.
SPEAKER_1:  And a part of that is young people. I have to ask.
SPEAKER_0:  And as young people, I mean, I'm feeling a bit on the older side now, but I still feel I've got a bit of youth within me yet. I'm 57, I'm not that old, but I'm not that young. But we have to work together with younger and older people. We've got to work together in coalitions of, you know, across generations.
SPEAKER_1:  You remind me of kids who just graduated college and say, I feel old.
SPEAKER_1:  So yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  No. I don't actually feel old, but it is a number, age, and you know, when you kind of think about when I was. I thought you don't like math. Yeah, yeah. I know what it's like and things like that. Yeah, but I think it's kind of interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  But you know, when I was a little kid, I kept thinking about the year 2000 and I thought, oh my God, I'll be dead, I'll be 35.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  22 years ago.
SPEAKER_1:  You've overcome.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of struggle in your life.
SPEAKER_1:  based on different reasons as you write about.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  class being one of them.
SPEAKER_1:  You're f-
SPEAKER_1:  funny sounding accent being another or just representation of class.
SPEAKER_1:  But in general...
SPEAKER_1:  through all of that.
SPEAKER_1:  to be.
SPEAKER_1:  at the White House.
SPEAKER_1:  to be one of the most powerful voices.
SPEAKER_1:  in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  What advice would you give from?
SPEAKER_1:  grounded in your life story to somebody who's young, somebody who's in high school and college.
SPEAKER_1:  thinking of how they can have a big.
SPEAKER_1:  positive impact on the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Look, we all have a voice.
SPEAKER_0:  We all have agency. We all actually have the ability to do something.
SPEAKER_0:  And you can start small in your local community or even in your own classroom, just helping somebody else out or speaking up and advocating on behalf of things.
SPEAKER_0:  When I was about 11 years old, I got involved with other kids on Save the Whales.
SPEAKER_0:  We were hardly Greta Thunberg, but we kind of got together in a kind of network writing to people and trying to raise money to...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, helped save the whales. www.Illuminati
SPEAKER_0:  of the world out.
SPEAKER_0:  doing somewhat better. I can't say that that was because of me and my network, but...
SPEAKER_0:  It was kind of a way of organizing.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of joining in at a larger movement. Everybody can be part of something bigger.
SPEAKER_0:  The thing is, it's all about working together with others and giving other people a chance as well.
SPEAKER_0:  I think in a one.
SPEAKER_0:  is that our voices...
SPEAKER_0:  have more impact when they're amplified. They don't have to be the voices of discord or the voices of hate.
SPEAKER_0:  You've been trying to do this with your podcast, kind of give people a voice, give them a kind of platform.
SPEAKER_0:  and get them to join in with other people.
SPEAKER_0:  And one of the things that I've been trying to do is kind of go and talk to just as many people as I possibly can and say, look, you know, we can all do something here.
SPEAKER_0:  We can all, you know, lend our voices to a cause that we care deeply about. We can be kind to each other.
SPEAKER_0:  We can give other people a chance. We can kind of speak out while we see that, you know, something is wrong and we can try to...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, explain things to people.
SPEAKER_0:  And what I'm trying to do at the moment is just sort of explain, you know, what I've learned about things and
SPEAKER_0:  I hope that that helps people.
SPEAKER_0:  make informed judgments of their own and that, you know, kind of maybe take things further and learn something more. That's like kind of building upon.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, the knowledge.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, that I have, you know, to try to impart, but everybody can do that different ways. You can kind of reach back.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, if you're 14, help somebody who's 7.
SPEAKER_0:  The 21 helps someone use 14.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, kind of in the kind of my age now I'm always trying to.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, reach back and...
SPEAKER_0:  work with younger people, listen to younger people, help them out, make connections for them.
SPEAKER_0:  listen to what they have to say about something, try to incorporate that in the things that I'm saying as well. The main point is that we've all got a voice, we've all got agency.
SPEAKER_0:  and it always works better when we work together with other people.
SPEAKER_1:  but sometimes it can feel pretty hopeless. It can feel...
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, there's low points. You seem to have a kind of a-
SPEAKER_1:  Restless energy, a drive to you.
SPEAKER_1:  where there are low points in the beginning when...
SPEAKER_1:  um
SPEAKER_1:  in your early days when you're trying to get the education where...
SPEAKER_1:  it may have not been clear to you that you could be at all successful.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there were always, there were lots of points where I was just despondent.
SPEAKER_0:  But then, you know, I'd meet somebody.
SPEAKER_0:  who would just suddenly turn things around. I was this look or was I out there looking for it? You know, sometimes.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, you just, if you're open and receptive to, you know, kind of, uh, hearing something from someone else, I mean, I, you know, the oftentimes I felt so despondent.
SPEAKER_0:  in such a black mood I didn't think I'd be able to go on and then I'd have a chance conversation with somebody.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I once remember, you know, I was sitting on the bench, I was probably 11 or 12, just crying my eyes out, just really upset, and an old lady just came and sat next to me.
SPEAKER_0:  put her arm around me and said, oh, it's all right pet, what's the matter?
SPEAKER_0:  know, it can't be that bad, can it? And it was just this...
SPEAKER_0:  Human.
SPEAKER_0:  embrace. It's like somebody...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, just basically reaching out to me that snapped me out of it.
SPEAKER_0:  And I thought, you know, here's somebody just, you know, she didn't know who I was. She just felt really bad that I was.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, sitting.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, crying and...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean I can't even remember what it was about anymore.
SPEAKER_0:  Now it just seems inconsequential at the time. I probably thought my life was at an end.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, sometimes people making out contact with him in the street.
SPEAKER_0:  and saying something to you can kind of pull you out of something.
SPEAKER_0:  And, you know, it's kind of a...
SPEAKER_0:  I think you would just have to open yourself up to the prospect that not everyone's bad, just like you were saying before, that there's...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, goes in everybody.
SPEAKER_0:  even during that really difficult period of impeachment.
SPEAKER_0:  I was trying to listen very carefully to people.
SPEAKER_0:  And I thought, we always, we still have something in common here.
SPEAKER_0:  We need to remember that.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, kind of when people are kind of forgetting who they are or, you know, the context in their operating.
SPEAKER_0:  There's always something that can.
SPEAKER_0:  can pull you back again, there's always that kind of thread.
SPEAKER_1:  So I'm sure you were probably attacked.
SPEAKER_1:  By Allah.
SPEAKER_1:  people.
SPEAKER_1:  and you're still able to keep that optimism that.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I kept it into kind of perspective. Like when I was a kid, I mean, things were going to mention before I got bullied, you know, kind of again, and I tried to win some, why they're doing this.
SPEAKER_0:  One of the-
SPEAKER_0:  Most amazing things.
SPEAKER_0:  that happened, you know, really almost my dad was a pretty incredible person.
SPEAKER_0:  He would always open my eyes to something. I was getting bullied really nasty by a girl at school.
SPEAKER_0:  and my dad started asking me questions about her.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  one day my dad's going to go for a walk.
SPEAKER_0:  and my town is very small. Remember it's very depressed, really you know, a deprived area.
SPEAKER_0:  and we go to this.
SPEAKER_0:  housing estate, public housing place that's not too far away from where I live. And it's really, you know, kind of one of the most rundown places and already rundown place.
SPEAKER_0:  My dad knocks on the door and I said, what are we doing dad?
SPEAKER_0:  He says, we're going to visit somebody, an old family friend.
SPEAKER_0:  I think they were even a distant relative. We're knocking the door and this old man answers the door and he's, oh Alfie. I don't know, his name is Alf Alfie.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, kind of, ah, fancy seeing you here, haven't seen you, come on in, have a cup of tea, what you doing? Said, oh, I'm just walking past my daughter, we're going for a trip.
SPEAKER_0:  There we're going for a walk and then suddenly I see that girl.
SPEAKER_0:  and she's in the kitchen.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm thinking.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh my.
SPEAKER_0:  Bloody hell, you know, British expression, what's this?
SPEAKER_0:  And it turns out that Dad had figured out who she was.
SPEAKER_0:  And he knew her grandfather and she was living with her grandfather and she'd been abandoned by her parents and she was living in pretty dire circumstances and she'd been getting raised by her grandfather and she was just miserable.
SPEAKER_0:  And the reason she was bullying me was to make herself feel better.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  And after that, she never bullied me again. She told me we didn't even talk.
SPEAKER_0:  because there was a connection mode.
SPEAKER_0:  and suddenly she realized that her grandfather was the only person she had.
SPEAKER_0:  knew my dad and there was some...
SPEAKER_0:  they were friends or they were even family, some kind of relationship there. I mean, I was raised half of North of England, I had no idea how we were related. Everybody was some relative because people have lived there for generations to get in this very small area.
SPEAKER_0:  And that turned things around. Just remember you might have.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's kind of suddenly taught to me this.
SPEAKER_0:  always a reason why somebody's doing something. A lot of the times they're really unhappy with themselves. So there's something else going on in their lives.
SPEAKER_0:  Sometimes they just don't know any better.
SPEAKER_0:  and I shouldn't take it personally.
SPEAKER_0:  Because I don't have a personal connection with half these people who are out there saying that they want this and that to happen to me.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, thank you for the kindness and empathy you still carry in your heart. I can see it through all that you must have gone through in the recent couple of years.
SPEAKER_1:  It's really inspiring to see that and.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for everything you've done, for the work you've written, for the work you continue to write and to do.
SPEAKER_1:  This seems like a really, really difficult time for human civilization on a topic that you're a world expert in.
SPEAKER_1:  So, um.
SPEAKER_1:  don't mess it up.
SPEAKER_0:  No, I know. Let's just keep it together, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly. Keep it together.
SPEAKER_1:  Your words have a lot of power right now, so it's a really, really tricky time.
SPEAKER_1:  So thank you so much.
SPEAKER_1:  given how valuable your time is to sit down with me today.
SPEAKER_0:  It was an honor. It was amazing. It's a privilege and a pleasure to talk to you as well. Thank you.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with Fiona Hill.
SPEAKER_1:  To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now, let me leave you some words from John Steinbeck.
SPEAKER_1:  Power does not corrupt.
SPEAKER_1:  Fear Corrupts.
SPEAKER_1:  Perhaps.
SPEAKER_1:  The fear of the loss of power.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for listening.
SPEAKER_1:  I hope to see you.
SPEAKER_1:  next time.