SPEAKER_0:  if you have a democratic style of governance.
SPEAKER_0:  You are interesting people.
SPEAKER_0:  with one of the most awesome and radical of responsibilities. And that's saying that you're going to pick the people that are gonna make some of the hardest decisions in all of human history. If you're gonna trust people.
SPEAKER_0:  to vote correctly, you have to be able to trust them to have open and honest dialogue with each other. Whether that's Nazis or KKK people or whoever talking, you have to believe that your people are going to be able to rise above and make the correct determinations when they hear these types of speeches. And if you're so worried...
SPEAKER_0:  that somebody is gonna hear a certain political figure and they're gonna be completely radicalized instantly, then what that tells me is that you don't have enough faith in humans for democracy to be a viable institution, which is fine. You can be anti-democratic, but I don't think you can be pro-democracy and anti-free speech.
SPEAKER_1:  Following is a conversation with Stephen Bonnell.
SPEAKER_1:  also known online as Destiny.
SPEAKER_1:  He's a video game streamer and political commentator.
SPEAKER_1:  One of the early pioneers of both livestreaming in general.
SPEAKER_1:  and live streamed political debate and discourse.
SPEAKER_1:  Politically, he is a progressive.
SPEAKER_1:  Identifying is either left or far left, depending on your perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  There are many reasons I wanted to talk to Stephen.
SPEAKER_1:  First, I just talked to Ben Shapiro.
SPEAKER_1:  and many people have told me that Stephen.
SPEAKER_1:  is the bench up here of the left.
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of political perspective and exceptional debate skills.
SPEAKER_1:  Second reason.
SPEAKER_1:  is he skillfully defends
SPEAKER_1:  some nuanced non-standard views.
SPEAKER_1:  at the same time being pro-establishment, pro-institutions and pro-Biden.
SPEAKER_1:  while also being pro-capitalism and pro-free speech.
SPEAKER_1:  Third reason.
SPEAKER_1:  is he has been there at the beginning.
SPEAKER_1:  and throughout the meteoric rise of the video game live streaming community.
SPEAKER_1:  in some mainstream circles.
SPEAKER_1:  This community is not taken seriously.
SPEAKER_1:  Perhaps.
SPEAKER_1:  because of its demographic distribution skewing young.
SPEAKER_1:  or
SPEAKER_1:  perhaps because of the sometimes hard style of communication.
SPEAKER_1:  But I think this community should be taken seriously.
SPEAKER_1:  and show them respect.
SPEAKER_1:  Millions of young minds tune in to live streams like Destiny's.
SPEAKER_1:  to question.
SPEAKER_1:  and to try to understand what is going on with the world.
SPEAKER_1:  often exploring challenging, even controversial ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  The language is sometimes harsher and the humor sometimes meter than I would prefer.
SPEAKER_1:  What?
SPEAKER_1:  I.
SPEAKER_1:  Grandpa Lex.
SPEAKER_1:  put on my rain boots, and went into the beautiful chaotic muck of online discourse.
SPEAKER_1:  and have so far survived to tell the tale.
SPEAKER_1:  with a smile.
SPEAKER_1:  and even more love in my heart than before.
SPEAKER_1:  On top of all this.
SPEAKER_1:  We were lucky to have Melina Goranson.
SPEAKER_1:  a popular streamer and world traveler.
SPEAKER_1:  Join us at the end of the conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  you can check out her channel on twitch.tv slash Molina.
SPEAKER_1:  and you can check out Steven's channel on youtube.com slash destiny.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the Lex Friedman podcast.
SPEAKER_1:  To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now, dear friends.
SPEAKER_1:  Here's Destiny.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if you watched me watching your...
SPEAKER_0:  Yay interview.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you so much.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm so curious when you're navigating a conversation like that.
SPEAKER_0:  Are you, how intentional is the thought process between like building rapport and pushing and.
SPEAKER_1:  giving a little and letting like zero, zero intention. I was watching and thank you so much. It was very kind for you to review that conversation. It meant a lot that you.
SPEAKER_1:  or complimentary parts on the technical aspects of the conversation, but no, zero. And I'm actually deliberately.
SPEAKER_1:  trying to avoid, I think you've called it debate brain.
SPEAKER_1:  which is just another flavor of
SPEAKER_1:  thinking about.
SPEAKER_1:  like the meta conversation, trying to optimize.
SPEAKER_1:  How should this conversation go?
SPEAKER_1:  because I feel like the more...
SPEAKER_1:  you do that, the better you get at that.
SPEAKER_1:  the less human connection you have.
SPEAKER_1:  Like the less genuinely you're actually sitting there in the moment and listening to the person, you're more like calculating what's the right thing to say versus like feeling what is.
SPEAKER_1:  What is that person feeling right now? What are they thinking? That's what I'm trying to do is like
SPEAKER_1:  putting myself
SPEAKER_1:  in their mind and thinking.
SPEAKER_1:  What does the world look like to them?
SPEAKER_1:  What does the world feel like to them?
SPEAKER_1:  And so from that.
SPEAKER_1:  I truly try to listen. Now I'm also learning.
SPEAKER_1:  thisgrasshoppers.com
SPEAKER_1:  Rogan and others have been giving me shit for not pushing back.
SPEAKER_1:  It's good sometimes to say.
SPEAKER_1:  from a place of
SPEAKER_1:  care for the other human being to say stop.
SPEAKER_1:  What did you just say? I don't think that's represents who you are.
SPEAKER_1:  and what you really mean.
SPEAKER_1:  or maybe
SPEAKER_1:  if it does at that time represents who they are.
SPEAKER_1:  I can see a better.
SPEAKER_1:  a better world if they grow into a different direction and try to point that direction out to them.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a really complicated dance between letting somebody share their full story.
SPEAKER_0:  versus letting somebody like.
SPEAKER_0:  essentially, I guess like proselytize your audience and it's like, okay, hold on. Let's-
SPEAKER_0:  take a minute here but
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I used to be.
SPEAKER_0:  Four or five years ago, it was attack, attack, attack, attack, attack, whatever you said. And now I'm leaning way more towards the like, okay, well, tell me how you feel about everything and then we'll go from there. Why would you feel the same?
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of people like my new approach. Some older fans will watch and they're like, why are you letting this guy just ramble on? You know, he said like five or six wrong things and you're only gonna call him out on two of them. And it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  It's different styles of conversation, but yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  due to a lot of reason.
SPEAKER_0:  search beforehand too.
SPEAKER_0:  depending on the conversation, yeah. So if we're gonna talk like vaccines and stuff, yeah, that's a ton of reading and stuff that I never thought I'd know.
SPEAKER_0:  going into it. If it's a more personal, like political philosophy conversation, there's not as much you can prepare for just it truly depends on the conversation
SPEAKER_1:  Are you actually listening to the other person?
SPEAKER_0:  I'm always listening, you have to listen, because as soon as you stop listening, the quality of everything falls apart, the connection disappears, the quality of the conversation disappears.
SPEAKER_0:  but my natural inclination is to just be way more aggressive.
SPEAKER_0:  than normal so I have to constantly remind myself. I guess you would call it a meta conversation when I'm like, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  He's probably saying this because of that, or we'll let him go here and then we'll stop later. But yeah, because my preferred style of conversation is like, I'm gonna talk, and the second I say something you disagree with, then let's.
SPEAKER_0:  iron it out, right? I got like, I think I like syllogisms like, okay, here's premise today!
SPEAKER_0:  Good, okay, premise B, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  And then conclusion, and then as long as we're both deductively sound, we're not crazy, no psychosis, then we're gonna agree on everything.
SPEAKER_0:  Whereas other people like to, most people think in stories, like narratives, like a whole, there's a whole like narrative and the individual facts don't matter as much because they'll pick and choose what they want and
SPEAKER_0:  It's really hard because everybody thinks narrative is so I have to function in that world.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's frustrating for me sometimes.
SPEAKER_1:  Why, I seen.
SPEAKER_1:  You've had a lot of excellent debates, one of them I just-
SPEAKER_1:  recently last night watch is a
SPEAKER_1:  on systemic racism.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's the first time I've seen you completely lose your shit. Oh, shoot.
SPEAKER_0:  Who was that against?
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not sure exactly, but you were just very frustrated and sorry, not lose your ship, but you're frustrated constantly because
SPEAKER_1:  Let's lay out 123.
SPEAKER_1:  and every time you try to lay it out.
SPEAKER_1:  it would falter.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it had to do with sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you use data to make an argument?
SPEAKER_1:  or do you need to use a study that does an interpretation of that data?
SPEAKER_1:  And then there's like this tension between, I think this is a behavioral economist that you were talking to in there.
SPEAKER_1:  point is you do this kind of nice layout that the whole point of behavioral economics that says
SPEAKER_1:  there's more to it than just the data. you have to give it context and
SPEAKER_1:  do the rich, rigorous interpretation in the context of the full human story.
SPEAKER_1:  And then there was the dance back and forth. Sometimes you use data, sometimes not, and you're getting really frustrated and shutting down.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that felt like a failure mode.
SPEAKER_1:  I've seen Sam Harris have similar sticking points.
SPEAKER_1:  Like if we can't agree on the terminology, we can't go on.
SPEAKER_1:  to me.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like I'm sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  the Wittgenstein perspective is like.
SPEAKER_1:  I think if you get stuck on any one thing, you're just not gonna make progress. You have to...
SPEAKER_1:  Part of the conversation has to be.
SPEAKER_1:  about.
SPEAKER_1:  doing a good dance together.
SPEAKER_1:  versus being dogmatically stuck.
SPEAKER_1:  on the path to truth.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the true challenge is identifying.
SPEAKER_0:  what of those sticking points are important.
SPEAKER_0:  versus what is.
SPEAKER_0:  NOT
SPEAKER_0:  Important. It's like if I'm having an argument with somebody about like
SPEAKER_0:  Jewish representation in media.
SPEAKER_0:  they might, it might be like a big conversation they might say a couple things
SPEAKER_0:  Like I think Jewish people, you know, they tend to help their own or whatever. And it's like, okay. But like for the purpose of the conversation, we can keep moving. But if they casually drop like, you know, yeah. I think that's why the Holocaust numbers were blown up from like 100,000 to 6 million. And that's why I was like, okay, well, hold on. Wait, wait, if you think this, we have to stop here because.
SPEAKER_0:  This is gonna be, it's not just a language game in this part, if you really believe this fact, then the whole rest of the conversation is gonna be informed by that.
SPEAKER_1:  believe you know and it has to be something that
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't bother you personally.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to step outside your own ego.
SPEAKER_1:  So Holocaust denial is somebody that would bother a lot of people. And there's some things.
SPEAKER_1:  I
SPEAKER_1:  Just observing you, I feel like when you get really good at a conversation, you can become a stickler.
SPEAKER_1:  to, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  you might have your favorite terms.
SPEAKER_1:  that really bothers you people don't agree on a star
SPEAKER_0:  Begs the question you mean raising the question. Yeah, I usually just want it people say stuff. I just let it slide Yeah, yeah, because if you fight you
SPEAKER_0:  When you're having a conversation with somebody and you're talking to their audience at the same time, because that's really what's happening, you never want to come off as over combative or over aggressive.
SPEAKER_0:  because it puts people in like, there's like a trigger in your brain.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is true of relationships, of friendships, of persuasive rhetoric or whatever. There's a trigger in the brain and as soon as that defensive trigger gets like flipped on, everything is over. You've lost the ability to persuade.
SPEAKER_0:  because everything becomes a fight at that point.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I wanted to talk to you because
SPEAKER_1:  I heard somewhere that you were referred to as the Ben Shapiro of the left. And since I'm talking with Ben.
SPEAKER_1:  as well I want it to sort of complete spiritually.
SPEAKER_1:  this platonic.
SPEAKER_1:  political philosophy puzzle in my head.
SPEAKER_1:  You are a progressive.
SPEAKER_1:  but a progressive with many non-standard progressive views.
SPEAKER_1:  And you had a heck of a fascinating journey through all of that. Like I said, I think you argue.
SPEAKER_1:  with passions sometimes with excessive amounts of passion, but almost- way of saying that.
SPEAKER_1:  Almost always.
SPEAKER_1:  with good faith and with rigor, with seriousness.
SPEAKER_1:  I asked on your subreddit, which is an excellent subreddit. Shout out to...
SPEAKER_1:  the Destiny subreddit.
SPEAKER_1:  so much at least for that particular post. What I really loved is when I asked for questions for you, they were like, holy shit, there's adults in there, let's all behave. Nobody say incest. I was like, what?
SPEAKER_1:  What was going on here, but actually the the the questions that rose to the top were really good. So
SPEAKER_1:  Somebody said that destiny was
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of your journey was a conservative in his early teens. Then he became a libertarian
SPEAKER_1:  Then he became a left-wing social justice warrior. Then he flirted with socialism.
SPEAKER_1:  And now...
SPEAKER_1:  He is a social democrat liberal. I've also heard you refer to yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  as a far left person.
SPEAKER_1:  to the degree there's truth to that journey. Can you take me through your evolution?
SPEAKER_1:  through the landscape of political ideologies.
SPEAKER_0:  that you went through. So my dad comes from Kentucky.
SPEAKER_0:  and my mom is a Cuban immigrant.
SPEAKER_0:  Cubans are notorious for being very conservative in the United States for historical reasons and for other reasons, but um.
SPEAKER_0:  My upbringing was a very Republican one.
SPEAKER_0:  I grew up listening to Rush Limbaugh.
SPEAKER_0:  Glenn Beck
SPEAKER_0:  Michael Savage.
SPEAKER_0:  on the radio, Billy Cunningham.
SPEAKER_0:  Sean Hannity a little bit later on, like, that was like my whole upbringing politically. I remember I was writing
SPEAKER_0:  I'd written articles for the school journal in favor of.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... defending the war in iraq and you know defending bush from all the criticism
SPEAKER_0:  I was like...
SPEAKER_0:  upbringing.
SPEAKER_0:  I think once I hit high school college, I had my edgy like.
SPEAKER_0:  libertarian-esque high school phase of like reading Ayn Rand.
SPEAKER_0:  of figuring out that like, oh my God, nothing in life matters except for class and money. That's actually the answer to everything.
SPEAKER_0:  I got to college, I became a Ron Paul fan, very big Ron Paul fan.
SPEAKER_0:  and then
SPEAKER_0:  From there, I kind of work, do life, life happens.
SPEAKER_0:  at the kind of the lowest point of my life in terms of where I'm working financially everything is like kind of in ruin in my life. There's a whole bunch of dumb stuff that's happened. Probably my most conservative point.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know what it is about like...
SPEAKER_0:  being poor and thinking like you can work your way out of it, you can do whatever. My upbringing is always just like, if you're not-
SPEAKER_0:  If you're not.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're not having financial success, work, work, work, work, work, work.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And then I got into streaming, very, very lucky break. Everything just lined up at the right time. And then as I've progressed through streaming, I would say through the years, I've gradually fallen more and more to the left.
SPEAKER_0:  especially once my kid turned four, five, six years old.
SPEAKER_0:  and I started to see how much different his life.
SPEAKER_0:  was.
SPEAKER_0:  just because of the financial opportunities that I was able to provide for him through no merit of his own. And that started to radically change how I viewed the world in a lot of ways.
SPEAKER_1:  So actually let's like linger on that
SPEAKER_1:  Low point.
SPEAKER_1:  You worked at McDonald's, you worked at a casino.
SPEAKER_1:  You did carpet cleaning. What was the lowest point?
SPEAKER_1:  Definitely the carpet cleaning.
SPEAKER_1:  Really? Absolutely. Why? Why was it the lowest point? That's when you were just flirting with starting streaming?
SPEAKER_0:  My whole life has been a series of lucky breaks, really, truly.
SPEAKER_0:  I grew up playing a lot of video games.
SPEAKER_0:  But back in...
SPEAKER_0:  my day, our day, you had to read. There's a lot of text on the screen.
SPEAKER_1:  Back in my day we used to play
SPEAKER_0:  They didn't all talk to you. Yeah, because nowadays everything's voice acted, back then you to read a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  I was a really good reader and a really good vocabular.
SPEAKER_1:  actually say that what games are we talking about what do you mean just reading you're talking about like our p.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, JRPG. So like Final Fantasy games, fantasy stars, like all of these, like any RPG that would have been on the SNES, Sega, PlayStation, these are the things that I'm... Pause it.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  I just talked to Todd Howard, who's...
SPEAKER_1:  of the Elder Scrolls fame and the
SPEAKER_1:  Fallout fame and beyond.
SPEAKER_1:  What's your thoughts on Elder Scrolls?
SPEAKER_1:  Why is Skyrim the greatest RPG of all time?
SPEAKER_1:  Man.
SPEAKER_0:  I really don't like Skyrim or Fallout. You don't love it? Oh really?
SPEAKER_0:  Why do you hate Scarra? Yeah, so I really like characters and like compelling stories and narratives around those characters. And I like to see them kind of like grow and change, kind of like a movie or a story. So in your like Final Fantasy games, you've got characters. There are a lot of like, um...
SPEAKER_0:  ain't like classical tropes of like a character starts off kind of like edgy angsty all on their own they develop relationships friendships they realize that the life is more about themselves and they do that and i like that that growth that's kind of what you see in all of those old role-playing games
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't like the open world ones as much because your main character is just like a blank slate, never talks, it's for you to like project onto, but there's not the same like linear narrative of like growth for the character.
SPEAKER_1:  That's fascinating. There's an actual story arc to the character that's more crafted in a beautiful way by the designers of the game.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that's better or worse. I tend towards like I want to hear a compelling story around like a set of characters that like grow and change Just again. Oh, that's beautiful.
SPEAKER_1:  put them. Yeah, I just really loved being able to leave the town.
SPEAKER_1:  You go outside the town and you look outside its nature and the world of possibilities is before you you do whatever the fuck you want.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean that immensity.
SPEAKER_1:  or just being lost in the world. It was really immersive for me. But yeah, you're right. Whatever attracts you about a world.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  You were just starting to.
SPEAKER_1:  play video games.
SPEAKER_1:  You go out play video games, that's one of your lucky breaks.
SPEAKER_0:  There's just like a lot of random skills you pick up depending on the type of game you play. I played a lot of text-based games on the computer, so I was a very fast typer. I'm still a very fast typer.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  read a lot, learned weird kind of math stuff for some of the calculations, some of the games.
SPEAKER_0:  I think I'm pretty good at...
SPEAKER_0:  getting information, figuring stuff out.
SPEAKER_0:  learning patterns, all of that.
SPEAKER_0:  And then that plus the reading and everything the games meant that I.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't want to say I excelled in school because my grades were pretty bad, but I was in all honors, all AP classes or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of dual enrollment, a lot of AP credit going into college. So I did pretty well in school, probably better than I should have, but it was because I had the game stuff that was like really powering a lot of my brain there.
SPEAKER_0:  I was trying to sleep through class.
SPEAKER_1:  So you're able to soak in information, integrate it.
SPEAKER_0:  quickly take notes. generally I think I'm pretty good at that yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  What you do this a lot when you stream your typing stuff. Is there a system in that note taking?
SPEAKER_1:  and what note, what do you use?
SPEAKER_1:  for note taking. doesn't matter.
SPEAKER_0:  I use a notepad. The original. The original. The notepad.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there genius in the madness?
SPEAKER_1:  behind that or you just don't give a shit.
SPEAKER_0:  No, I mean like...
SPEAKER_0:  It's going to depend on the style of conversation. If I'm with somebody that is very meticulously organized with their thoughts and they're a...
SPEAKER_0:  Find a better word here for Rambler. You can edit that in. Better word for Rambler. Some of the talks a lot and a lot. I'll start like.
SPEAKER_0:  taking notes, bullet points like this, this, this, this, this, this, this, because there's a style of conversation where I say seven or eight different things. And then when you go to respond to everything I said, I cut you off immediately. And we argue that point. But if somebody is going to do that, he's just like, hold on, you just said these eight things, I'm going to respond to every single one. I've written them all down and then you can go if you want to go point by point, we can. But you just said all this and I wrote it down somewhere to go.
SPEAKER_1:  So what are you actually writing down? Like a couple of words per point they left.
SPEAKER_0:  Honestly, there are very few unique conversations in politics. A lot of them are retreading old ground. So if we're having a debate on abortion, somebody might say, well, I believe this thing about viability and I believe this thing about when they're a fetus versus a human, and I'll just write down those points so that when I go to respond, I have note cards, a guiding thing there. Except minister,
SPEAKER_0:  keep me centered on my response.
SPEAKER_1:  political discourse is a kind of tree you're walking down. I got it. taken
SPEAKER_0:  Just to keep my...
SPEAKER_0:  focus guided so I'm not like running off on a weird tangent responding something I didn't say or something
SPEAKER_1:  What about like doing research? It's just, is there a system to your note taking? Because
SPEAKER_1:  Mentally, you seem to be one of the most organized people I've listened to, so...
SPEAKER_1:  Is there...
SPEAKER_1:  Is it in your mind or is there a system that's on paper?
SPEAKER_1:  A little of both.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like the human mind.
SPEAKER_0:  is a beautiful thing.
SPEAKER_0:  If you have interest in an area.
SPEAKER_0:  So like what I'll tell people is, let's say there's like a totally new topic that I'm researching, I don't know anything. And I'll do a couple of these on stream. I think they're boring, people watch it.
SPEAKER_0:  I might open a Wikipedia article and I'll read and I hit something I don't know and then I open the next Wikipedia article and I'll read it and then I might have like seven tabs open and I'll read and I'll read and I'll read.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and I'll read a ton of stuff, maybe for hour, two, three, four hours of stuff. And then by the end, you know, someone in chat will ask me like, do you even remember like this particular thing?
SPEAKER_0:  And I'll say, not really, no, not too much.
SPEAKER_0:  But what happens is, as long as you've seen it once, what'll happen is like the next day of the day after, we'll read something else and be like, oh.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember that thing from this thing. I remember like vaguely that. And then if you see it like a third time, you're like, oh, this makes sense because especially when it comes to, oh, here's like a little trick on stuff. If you're ever reading any news and there's a place that pops up, always look at it on a map.
SPEAKER_0:  because so much of history is like on a map. It's so important to like know the geography. It makes things make so much more sense.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, but yeah, once I, once I start to see stuff over and over again, just because I've like read it a few times, stuff will start to kind of connect to my mind and like, oh yeah, well, this makes sense. Of course these people believe this because of this, or of course, like this happened here, it's because you know, that happened there.
SPEAKER_0:  So yeah, it's a lot of that. If there's a topic that I'm doing specific research for, so like vaccine related stuff is a big one, the Ukrainian-Russian conflict is a big one, that I'll break out a note, I'll probably get a Google doc, and I'll just start writing an outline of kind of the rough points of everything just to organize my thoughts around different topics.
SPEAKER_1:  We're just gonna go attention upon attention upon attention. We'll return to the low point of your life at some point. Always returning from the philosophy to the psychology. So you did, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  the Ukraine topic.
SPEAKER_1:  One question is...
SPEAKER_1:  What role does US play?
SPEAKER_1:  in this war.
SPEAKER_1:  Could they have done something to avoid the war?
SPEAKER_1:  Did they have a role to play in forcing Vladimir Putin's hand?
SPEAKER_1:  Do they have a role to play in?
SPEAKER_1:  deescalating the war towards a peace agreement.
SPEAKER_1:  and the opposite if it does escalate.
SPEAKER_1:  towards something like the use of a tactical nuclear weapon.
SPEAKER_1:  Are they to blame? Are we to blame?
SPEAKER_0:  Oh man, somebody sent me an email a while ago with great words.
SPEAKER_0:  there's a specific way to navigate a conversation where you can kind of like contribute to a negative event
SPEAKER_0:  but you're not really the one responsible for it.
SPEAKER_0:  Like the classic example is a woman goes out late at night, gets a little bit too drunk and then something happens. And it's like, while there might have been steps she could have taken to mitigate the risk, it's not her fault of what happened because the responsibility rests on the agent making the choice, right? There's a chooser at some point that is choosing to do wrong or evil.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't believe in any of the arguments that say the United States has contributed to Russia's position on Ukraine or the actions they've taken on Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  There are several arguments that
SPEAKER_0:  some people.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... some even political scholars are are are putting out there to say that the united states to blame but i find them completely unconvincing
SPEAKER_0:  I think that when you ask the question of like, what is the United States role or what has our role been?
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's really important for us. I don't think we even agree as a country on what our role should be, which I think is a hard one because you've got this kind of, there's this growing populist movement in the United States. It might be the far left and the far right. I think populists tend to have this kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  isolationist view of the world, where the United States should just be our own thing, we shouldn't be telling anybody what to do, we shouldn't be the world police, and then kind of more in these like center left, center right positions, and then across a lot of Europe you've got, well okay, the United States is kind of like the big kid on the block.
SPEAKER_0:  like we're looking to them for guidance and leadership on situations like what's going on in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Insofar as the original question is like, what is the United States responsibility? I think we have a responsibility to ensure the relative freedom.
SPEAKER_0:  prosperity and stability across Europe.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that defending Ukraine's sovereignty and right to their borders is a part of that.
SPEAKER_0:  And I don't believe that prior to the invasion in 20, 22, I don't think the United States was contributing to Russia invading that country.
SPEAKER_0:  I know there are arguments given that like the expansion of NATO, you know, has something that's been threatening to Russia, but the Baltics joined and Russia didn't do anything about it. The invasion to Crimea was very clearly a response to the revolution in 2014. The invasion on the borders is clearly a response to Ukraine winning that.
SPEAKER_0:  Civil War in the southeast and the Donbass and Russia becoming more aggressive. I don't think that you can blame any of that on NATO expansion There's no NATO countries that are threatening Russia or debating Russia.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think?
SPEAKER_1:  There is a nuclear threat.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think about this? Do you worry about this? Do you think about this?
SPEAKER_0:  I think that possibility exists either way, and I think the responsibility for that is on Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  because it just can't be the case that if you have nukes, you're allowed to invade countries and take their land.
SPEAKER_0:  Because of anything, I think that that down the road also increases the potential for nuclear problems in the future, right? Because at that point, either every single country has to acquire their own nuclear weapons, because if you don't, Russia's gonna mess with you, or every single country has to join NATO, and now what, we're back at square zero, ground zero, square one, where people are like, oh, well look, all these countries joining NATO is aggressive towards Russia, what are you gonna do?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, you've mentioned that there's a...
SPEAKER_1:  complicated calculus going on with the countries that have
SPEAKER_1:  They have nuclear weapons. And what's our responsibility?
SPEAKER_1:  Are you allowed to do anything you want to countries that don't have nuclear weapons?
SPEAKER_1:  That's a really tricky discussion. For sure. Because what is US supposed to do if Russia drops the tactical nuclear weapon?
SPEAKER_1:  There's a set of options.
SPEAKER_1:  None of which are good.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  It's such a tricky moment right now.
SPEAKER_1:  Because, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  things that Biden and
SPEAKER_1:  other public figures say.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like has a significant impact on the way this game turns out because I think mutually sure destruction is partially a game of-
SPEAKER_1:  words.
SPEAKER_1:  No.
SPEAKER_1:  That's it.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I believe in the power of conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  of leaders talking to each other.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to have a balance between threat.
SPEAKER_1:  and compromise.
SPEAKER_1:  and like...
SPEAKER_1:  empathy.
SPEAKER_1:  for the needs.
SPEAKER_1:  geopolitical, the economic.
SPEAKER_1:  needs venation.
SPEAKER_1:  but also sort of respect.
SPEAKER_1:  and represent your own interest.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a tricky one, like how do you play the...
SPEAKER_1:  How do you play the hand?
SPEAKER_0:  It reminds me of...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if you've ever heard of evolutionary psychology or evolutionary biology, there are things called tit for tat strategies.
SPEAKER_0:  It kind of reminds me of that where it's like if...
SPEAKER_0:  Like there are a whole bunch of these little biological mechanisms where creatures will develop like socializing like tit for tat. If you do something bad to me, I'm going to do something bad for you. And then more complicated schemes will come out where it'll be like.
SPEAKER_0:  tit tit for tat, or it's like you can make one mistake and then I'm gonna get you if you do a second one or it could be tit tit tit for tat or there could be tit for tat tat for tat. There's like all these like back and forths where creatures kind of optimize themselves and.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think something the United States did really well in terms of that kind of conversational strategy and I
SPEAKER_0:  of this in the beginning was Biden was very clear about setting out like the exact level of US involvement for the war. We're not going to do a no-fly zone. There's not going to be US troops on the ground in Ukraine, but we are going to send a whole bunch of money and a whole bunch of arms and a whole bunch of Intel to them. And I thought he did a good job at laying out like the limitation of the US involvement while opening as much as we could in the ways that we could help.
SPEAKER_0:  but the, yeah, that looming threat of some sort of tactical nuclear weapon
SPEAKER_0:  I think on the table right now is like, it's going to be the annihilation of like Russian sea forces and everything, but.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, what happens if it continues to escalate?
SPEAKER_0:  That's like a world that nobody wants to.
SPEAKER_0:  Nobody wants to be in, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So we talked about difficult.
SPEAKER_1:  and again thank you so much for reviewing the yay conversation
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask you about Putin.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of difficult conversations, so if you sit down.
SPEAKER_1:  if I sit down with somebody like Vladimir Putin.
SPEAKER_1:  or Volodymyr Zelensky.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the right way to have that conversation? Oh man. How about that one where we could talk about...
SPEAKER_1:  somebody more.
SPEAKER_1:  well understood.
SPEAKER_1:  through history like something like Stalin or Hitler, something like that. Maybe that's an easier example.
SPEAKER_1:  to illustrate.
SPEAKER_1:  how to handle extremely difficult conversations.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, I can handle really difficult conversations between like two people.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... use of countries though your there's so much that you are representing in that conversation
SPEAKER_0:  I guess the thing that would be interesting to me...
SPEAKER_0:  would be like what his.
SPEAKER_0:  Vladimir Putin's interest.
SPEAKER_0:  Like what is the genuine?
SPEAKER_0:  interest that he has.
SPEAKER_0:  in the conflict. Because I think finding out like what is your buy-in or what is your like what is the driving force keeping here is probably the most important thing.
SPEAKER_0:  I think for Zelensky, I think it's quite a bit more simpler because he's-
SPEAKER_0:  he's on the defense, so it's defending his country and his people.
SPEAKER_0:  For Putin, I've heard all sorts of things. Dugan has his writings on the East versus the West, the collapse of the West in the face of all of the liberalism and the weird LGBT stuff that they criticize. You've got the desire to return to this former Soviet Union-esque thing. You've got Putin's quotes that the collapse of the Soviet Union was the biggest geopolitical disaster. You've got Putin's quotes that the collapse of the Soviet Union
SPEAKER_0:  20th century and...
SPEAKER_0:  I guess figuring out like what is Putin after? I'm not actually sure. I don't know the answer to that question. People write about it, but yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, there's a lot of answers to that question. There's a lot of answers that he can give you that question. So say sit down with them for three hours and talk about it.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  This is a really interesting distinction because you do do difficult conversations.
SPEAKER_1:  in the space of ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  But also in your stream you have, I mean there's a bunch of drama going on, there's human psychologies laid out.
SPEAKER_1:  in its full richness before you.
SPEAKER_1:  So to me with leaders, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  Part of the conversation has to be about the human psychology.
SPEAKER_1:  not like a meta conversation, but like.
SPEAKER_1:  really understand.
SPEAKER_1:  what they feel, what they fear, who they are as a human being.
SPEAKER_1:  make.
SPEAKER_1:  as a family man.
SPEAKER_1:  as a
SPEAKER_1:  as a person proud of their country.
SPEAKER_1:  as a person with an ego, as a person who's been...
SPEAKER_1:  affected, if not corrupted by powers, all of us.
SPEAKER_1:  can be and likely are.
SPEAKER_1:  So all of that.
SPEAKER_1:  That gives context to then
SPEAKER_1:  the answers about what do you want in this war.
SPEAKER_1:  is that the answers.
SPEAKER_1:  what you want in this
SPEAKER_1:  war will be political answers.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like a game that's being played again with words and politicians are incredibly good at playing that game.
SPEAKER_1:  I think the deeper truth.
SPEAKER_1:  comes from understanding the human being from which those words.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think that's what you do. I don't know if you do those kinds of conversations where.
SPEAKER_0:  never talked to any.
SPEAKER_0:  country leader so
SPEAKER_1:  Not a country leader, but say a controversial figure or somebody that represents a certain idea. Don't just...
SPEAKER_1:  talk in the space of ideas or challenge the ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  but understand who is this person, how did you come to those ideas?
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yeah, when I've had... there have been a couple of very controversial...
SPEAKER_0:  Riot Leaning Figures.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... so the two obviously the my streams are lauren southern and nick juntas
SPEAKER_0:  and those types of conversations initially.
SPEAKER_0:  aren't very political at all. Yeah, it's more like like
SPEAKER_0:  Obviously we believe in very, very, very different things.
SPEAKER_0:  Beliefs don't happen accidentally, so how did you get to where you are? Those are way more personal conversations, that's true.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there things you regret about those conversations where you failed? Is there things you're proud of where you succeeded?
SPEAKER_0:  for things that I'm proud of. I feel like I'm really good at attempting...
SPEAKER_0:  to understand people without judgment.
SPEAKER_0:  that I think a lot of people feel like they can have conversations with me where they can share a lot and I'm not going to jump down their throat for
SPEAKER_0:  them having a politically incorrect observation, or for them.
SPEAKER_0:  being judgmental to somebody else or having like a feeling that's maybe not something they should have, something they're embarrassed about. So I think I do a really good job at that. And then by extension of that, I've gotten the ability to hear perspectives from so many different people that I think I can understand a lot of different perspectives.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, for failures of mine...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's always going to be...
SPEAKER_0:  On stream, it'll be like I didn't push back hard enough or I didn't know a certain fact for a conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  These are usually the they're going to be on these like very technical grounds generally. I'm pretty happy with like the direction my conversations have gone recently especially over like the past six months.
SPEAKER_1:  So your goal is to...
SPEAKER_1:  and de-radicalize the audience.
SPEAKER_1:  those folks.
SPEAKER_0:  So that used to be my goal.
SPEAKER_0:  My goal was de-radicalization. Now I'm kind of hoping that that's just the byproduct.
SPEAKER_0:  So the goal I think is to talk to somebody and to show.
SPEAKER_0:  They believe this because of these reasons. And if you wanna change people's beliefs, we have to talk about the underlying reasons for why they think the things they think.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not enough to just say like that belief is bad. Cause it's like, well, they believe it for a whole bunch of things that are true and real to them at least.
SPEAKER_0:  So you have to address all of the underlying.
SPEAKER_0:  things that they believe before you can change the overlying belief.
SPEAKER_0:  So if I'm having a conversation with somebody, it'll be like, okay, why do you feel this about that, that, and that?
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, I understand that.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe like a better way to solve that would be like...
SPEAKER_0:  this or that instead of
SPEAKER_0:  this thing. This change will decide how many times a run a month.
SPEAKER_1:  To what degree do you have to empathize with the person's worldview?
SPEAKER_1:  versus pushback.
SPEAKER_0:  That's always the hard one.
SPEAKER_0:  When I'm talking to other people, it's almost always me stepping as much inside their bubble as I can. I have to like live and breathe their worldview and be able to speak their worldview in order to like navigate their thoughts. Because my worldview is um...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not even using this as an insult. I don't know if I am a little bit autistic or something, but when I break apart things, I just want to see like study, study, study, fact, fact, fact. That's how my mind works for everything. That's just how, that's what I like to see. Like personal stories don't do much for me. Narratives don't do much for me. Show me like the data and the studies or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  But for other people, I think most brains are more human than that, and they tend to see things more kind of like
SPEAKER_0:  uh... surreal pictures that kind of painted in the brush strokes are way broader and you know they don't care about the itty bitty tiny fact
SPEAKER_0:  So if I'm talking to somebody else and I'm trying to get into their head and I'm trying to change their mind on things, I'm going to be stepping into their world.
SPEAKER_0:  and I'm going to try to be working through that framework.
SPEAKER_0:  Really good example might be...
SPEAKER_0:  We'll say like when it comes to trans issues for minors, okay? 16 or 17 year old needs to get on puberty blockers. The way that I want that debate to play out is let's look at all the data, let's see what are the outcomes, let's see what are the processes for getting a medication, and then we'll evaluate all of that and then we'll go in whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  points more favorably, but that's wholly unconvincing to most people, right? So as a parent, if I'm having that conversation with another parent, the easiest way for me to have that conversation is like, hey.
SPEAKER_0:  We both have kids. Imagine how horrible it would be if we felt like our kids needed help and the government was trying to get between.
SPEAKER_0:  us and their doctor in that conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  That might be how that talk plays out, which I think that's a really good argument because I think there probably are times when the government should get in between it, but I'll have that conversation because now I'm in a world where they understand what I'm saying. I'm resonating with the way that they feel about things and then I can make progress with the way that they're kind of viewing the world because I'm talking in a language they understand.
SPEAKER_1:  So on this particular topic of trans issues, is that the reason you were banned from Twitch?
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not sure, I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  They just said hate speech, but I don't use like slurs or anything. So it's hard to know exactly so
SPEAKER_1:  I think you made the claim that trans women shouldn't compete with cis women in women's athletics. I think you made the claim that trans women shouldn't compete with cis women in women's athletics.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you...
SPEAKER_1:  Make this case and can you still man the case against it?
SPEAKER_1:  I think in your community there's a lot of
SPEAKER_1:  Trans folks who love you
SPEAKER_1:  and there's a lot who hate you. yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  And so if you can walk the tightrope.
SPEAKER_1:  of this conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  try to steel man both sides.
SPEAKER_0:  One of the argumentative strategies I say is that like any time you have a conversation, you should be able to argue both sides better than anybody else.
SPEAKER_0:  for the my side, the genuine belief side.
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  It feels like overwhelmingly.
SPEAKER_0:  All of the data is showing that.
SPEAKER_0:  trans, mostly trans women.
SPEAKER_0:  Even after I think three years on some sort of like HRT or you know estrogen
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  stuff, they're still maintaining these advantages from their male puberty over cisgender women.
SPEAKER_0:  And if that is the case, if we are gonna draw these distinctions around our sports between women and men,
SPEAKER_0:  It feels unfair to have a category inside the women's sports that are maintaining advantages that are coming from a male puberty.
SPEAKER_0:  regardless of the amount of time they've spent on
SPEAKER_0:  hormone replacement therapy.
SPEAKER_0:  So that would be my argument on that side.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's unfair from a performance enhancement.
SPEAKER_1:  So the same way we ban
SPEAKER_1:  performance.
SPEAKER_1:  performance enhancing drugs that involve increasing of testosterone.
SPEAKER_1:  in that same way would be unfair. Essentially, yeah. What's the case?
SPEAKER_1:  against.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so the case in favor of them competing together is that
SPEAKER_0:  realistically, there's not going to be a transports category.
SPEAKER_0:  realistically trans women aren't going to be competitive with cis men because they've gone through these huge
SPEAKER_0:  uh... you know like hormone changes by the medication they're taking
SPEAKER_0:  And that when we look at how sports are kind of done anyway, there's a whole bunch of biological differences between people within sports categories that are determining their placement in the professional world.
SPEAKER_0:  So for instance,
SPEAKER_0:  Somebody like me is probably never gonna go far in the NBA because I'm not tall enough.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the average height in the NBA. Don't doubt yourself. Don't doubt myself, yeah. I want to say like six, six or something there.
SPEAKER_0:  huge people.
SPEAKER_0:  Or you know, you look at like Michael Phelps as a classic example of a guy whose torso is like so long, his body is built for swimming.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think there are some trans people that will look at that or somebody advocating for this position. They'll look at that and they'll go, okay, realistically, the way that Michael Phelps body processes lactic acid, the shape physiologically of his body, it's gonna put him in a level of competition.
SPEAKER_0:  so many men are never going to reach just because of biology.
SPEAKER_0:  How is it fair that you can have these biological outliers competing in these categories, but then when we come to like sports categories with trans and cis women, you're going to take trans women and say that they can't compete against cis women. Can't you also just say that they have some level of biological difference there? Like is it really going to be that great of a difference than what Michael Phelps has versus the average swimmer or an NBA player has versus like the average height male?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think we're gonna get into some tricky ethical territory as we start to be able to, through biology and genetics, modify the human body?
SPEAKER_0:  Absolutely.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like those things are coming sooner than we wanted them to. The, oh man, do the AI, have you seen the AI art? Yes, that's so.
SPEAKER_1:  Of course, I'm an AI person.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, okay, then yeah, yeah. That's always been like, what's gonna happen when robots can do art better than humans lol.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, well, we'll see in 20 years, in 20 years, in 20 years. And now you have AI art winning competitions.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It's funny because...
SPEAKER_0:  robots are essentially
SPEAKER_0:  What's the robot behind you by the way? The robot behind me? Bro, oh nice.
SPEAKER_0:  Robots are really good. Careful what you say. Yeah, I'll be careful.
SPEAKER_0:  That's not like one of the Chinese ones with a gun on it, right? Oh, okay. Hopefully not.
SPEAKER_1:  What we'll see depending on
SPEAKER_0:  what you say.
SPEAKER_0:  Robots are really good at showing the limitations of the human mind.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Categories that we didn't believe we were limited before
SPEAKER_0:  I think that humans have this idea intrinsically.
SPEAKER_0:  we have like some type of...
SPEAKER_0:  Like.
SPEAKER_0:  innovative creative drive.
SPEAKER_0:  that is just outside of the bounds of physical understanding. And with a sophisticated enough program,
SPEAKER_0:  we see that maybe that's not actually true that's a really scary thing
SPEAKER_0:  philosophically to deal with because we feel like we're very special, right? We own the planet, we make computers, and the idea that you can start to get these robots that can do things that's like, okay, you can do math. Fine. Okay. You can do calculations, but it's fine, but you can't do art. That's the human stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  And then when I start to do that, it's like, oh shoot.
SPEAKER_1:  And that terrifies you a little bit, like a losing.
SPEAKER_1:  the human species losing control of our dominance.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think it's necessarily losing control of our dominance. I mean, I guess like a Skynet thing could come in at some point. But I think it more...
SPEAKER_0:  brings us to this really fundamental level of like
SPEAKER_0:  What does it mean to be human? What is it that we're good at?
SPEAKER_0:  What should we be doing with technology? We never really ask that question in the Western world. It's always...
SPEAKER_0:  Technology is normative in that.
SPEAKER_0:  Technology equals good and more technology equals better. That's been like the default assumption. In fact, if you ask a lot of people, how do you know if civilization has progressed over the past 100 or 200 years? They don't say we have better relationships, we have longer marriages, we blah, blah, blah. They'll say technology has improved. We've got crazy phones, we've got crazy computers. And the idea that more technology might be bad has never even crossed somebody's mind, unless it's used for a really bad thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, it's interesting. We kind of think as more and more automation is happening.
SPEAKER_1:  We're going to.
SPEAKER_1:  more and more meaning from things like being artists and doing creative pursuits. And here's like, oh shit.
SPEAKER_1:  If the art, if the creative pursuits are also being automated, then what are we going to gain meaning from? What are the activities from which you'll gain meaning? You know, my whole life had been working on artificial intelligence systems. There's been different revolutions. One of them is that.
SPEAKER_1:  is the machine learning revolution and.
SPEAKER_1:  It's interesting to build up intuition and.
SPEAKER_1:  destroy that intuition about what is and isn't solvable by machines.
SPEAKER_1:  I think, um...
SPEAKER_1:  for the longest time I grew up.
SPEAKER_1:  thinking the game of Go is not solvable.
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  because my understanding of AI systems.
SPEAKER_1:  is ultimately this.
SPEAKER_1:  is fundamentally a search mechanism.
SPEAKER_1:  that is fundamentally going to be brute force.
SPEAKER_1:  There's no shortcuts.
SPEAKER_0:  Sure. Like if it can't solve the traveling salesman problem, it's not even going to be able to give you an approximation.
SPEAKER_1:  So most interesting problems are giant travel salesman problem. And then so of course it's not going to be able to solve that.
SPEAKER_1:  then the deep learning revolution.
SPEAKER_1:  made you realize holy shit these large neural networks with a giant number of knobs
SPEAKER_1:  is able to actually
SPEAKER_1:  somehow.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  estimate.
SPEAKER_1:  functions.
SPEAKER_1:  They can.
SPEAKER_1:  do a pretty good job of understanding deep representation of a thing, whether that's a game of Go.
SPEAKER_1:  or whether it's the human.
SPEAKER_1:  Natural Language.
SPEAKER_1:  or if it's images and video or.
SPEAKER_1:  audio and even actions in different video games and actions of robotics and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  And then you realize with diffusion models and different
SPEAKER_1:  different generative models you start to realize holy shit it can actually
SPEAKER_1:  generate.
SPEAKER_1:  Not just.
SPEAKER_1:  Interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  representations.
SPEAKER_1:  or interesting manifestations of the representations of forms, but it's able to do something that impresses humans in its creativity.
SPEAKER_1:  It's beautiful in the way we think of art is beautiful. Like it surprises us and makes us chuckle and makes us.
SPEAKER_1:  a sit back and all and all those kinds of things.
SPEAKER_1:  And yet the thing that it seems to struggle with the most is the physical world currently.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's counterintuitive. We humans think that it's, um...
SPEAKER_1:  It's pretty trivial.
SPEAKER_1:  the being able to pick up a cup.
SPEAKER_1:  Being able to like write with a pen, like in the physical space, we think that's trivial.
SPEAKER_1:  We give ourselves respect for being great artists and great.
SPEAKER_1:  mathematicians and all that kind of stuff and that seems to be much easier than the physical space.
SPEAKER_0:  Her bodies are really cool. There is a, um, I don't know-
SPEAKER_0:  probably Azimov or somebody there was some science fiction writer that had a short story and it was like an alien that had landed on earth and it was describing our bodies from a totally alien perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  And when you think about all the things we can do, it's pretty cool. We can climb through a whole multitude of environments. We can exist in a multitude of temperatures. We can manipulate things.
SPEAKER_0:  just with our hands and how you know the way that we can interact with things around us and yeah We're very capable on like a physical level even though like you said we think about ourselves like oh well human beings have really big brains and we do we're really intelligent as well but our bodies are pretty cool too.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's out.
SPEAKER_1:  Fascinating hierarchical biological system.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, um...
SPEAKER_1:  that were made up of a bunch of different
SPEAKER_1:  living organisms.
SPEAKER_1:  that all don't know about the big picture.
SPEAKER_1:  of our body and it's all functioning its own little local world is doing this thing.
SPEAKER_1:  but together as of.
SPEAKER_1:  it forms a super resilient system. All of that.
SPEAKER_1:  comes from.
SPEAKER_1:  a very, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  compressed
SPEAKER_1:  encoding of what makes a human you start with the DNA and it builds up from a single cell to giant organism.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, and...
SPEAKER_1:  Because of the DNA.
SPEAKER_1:  through the evolution process you can.
SPEAKER_1:  constantly create new humans and new living organisms that adapt to the environment like that resilience to the physical world
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like running the whole earth over again.
SPEAKER_1:  the whole evolutionary process over again.
SPEAKER_1:  is might be the only way to do it.
SPEAKER_1:  So to create a robot that actually adapts.
SPEAKER_1:  is as resilient to the dynamic world.
SPEAKER_1:  might be a really difficult problem.
SPEAKER_0:  Possibly.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I was going to say like in a programming environment, you can do things on time scales that are impossible in the real world, right? Like the benefit to AI and computers is a computational they can.
SPEAKER_0:  so much data so quickly. Whereas on human timetables, we have to wait. When you talk about evolution, you know, it's...
SPEAKER_0:  Generation after generation after generation, you know, maybe in a virtual environment that could be simulated
SPEAKER_0:  and then those changes could happen a lot quicker.
SPEAKER_1:  on the human time scale, but you have to look at Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  quantum mechanical system the computation is happening super fast.
SPEAKER_1:  This is a giant computer doing a giant simulation.
SPEAKER_1:  So just because for us humans it's slow.
SPEAKER_1:  There's like trillions of organisms involved in you, your destiny being you.
SPEAKER_0:  sure, but the next iteration of like.
SPEAKER_0:  from human to human.
SPEAKER_0:  Even if on the quantum level there's a lot of stuff going on, you talk about like changes in DNA, for instance, right?
SPEAKER_0:  that's happening from a generation to generation timescale. Like in a virtual environment, that could theoretically happen.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it already is. There's like protein folding, like huge cloud computing, probably ML stuff that's like working on doing all of that stuff. And it'll run like trillions and trillions of simulations, you know, every second and stuff. Maybe not every second, but.
SPEAKER_1:  still slower than the actual protein folding, much slower.
SPEAKER_1:  The...
SPEAKER_1:  That's for the problem of solving protein folding.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... to estimate the three d structure but the actual body does that the actual portion folding way faster
SPEAKER_1:  So like, we're-
SPEAKER_1:  The question is, can we shortcut the simulation of?
SPEAKER_1:  human evolution.
SPEAKER_1:  try to figure out how to build up an organism.
SPEAKER_1:  without
SPEAKER_1:  simulating all the details because we have to simulate all the details of biology were screwed.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't have. Oh true, we'd have to put something in a pond and then watch it for a billion years.
SPEAKER_1:  way to do it. That's what the universe most likely is.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a kind of simulation created by a teenager in their basement.
SPEAKER_1:  to try to see what happens. It's a computer game.
SPEAKER_1:  That might be the most efficient way to create interesting organisms.
SPEAKER_1:  but.
SPEAKER_1:  within the system.
SPEAKER_1:  perhaps possible to create.
SPEAKER_1:  other robots that will.
SPEAKER_1:  be of use and will entertain us in the way that other humans entertain us.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a really interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  course problem but it's surprising
SPEAKER_1:  how difficult it has been.
SPEAKER_1:  to create systems that operate in the physical world.
SPEAKER_1:  and operating that physical world in a way that's safe to humans.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  interesting to humans.
SPEAKER_1:  because there's also the human factor, the human-robot interaction. To me, that's...
SPEAKER_1:  like the most interesting problem to figure out how to do that well.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  Yamask and others.
SPEAKER_1:  Boston Dynamics have worked on legged robots, so I really care about legged robots.
SPEAKER_1:  Those are super interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  how to make them such that they're.
SPEAKER_1:  able to operate successfully in a dynamic environment. Super Tricky.
SPEAKER_1:  They're like.
SPEAKER_1:  They're like the dumbest of dogs.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of which, there's a dog barking outside.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, it's really tricky to create those kinds of organisms that live in the human world.
SPEAKER_1:  Then again...
SPEAKER_1:  if more and more...
SPEAKER_1:  of us moving to the digital world.
SPEAKER_1:  So you stream a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  Like part of who you are.
SPEAKER_1:  exist in the digital space.
SPEAKER_1:  The fact that you have a physical representation also.
SPEAKER_1:  maybe more and more will become
SPEAKER_1:  Not important.
SPEAKER_0:  I hope that's the case because I bought a lot of stock in Metta and man, it's down.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot.
SPEAKER_1:  of the company. Is there some degree, like can you look at yourself?
SPEAKER_1:  Like Stephen, the physical meat vehicle and then the destiny, this digital space.
SPEAKER_1:  like digital.
SPEAKER_1:  Avatar
SPEAKER_1:  Do you sense that in a certain way you're the digital avatar?
SPEAKER_0:  I've always tried to keep my on-stream personality as genuine as possible, so they're one and the same to me. I don't really view them as two separate entities, so... But I mean, I always view myself as Steven.
SPEAKER_0:  real life person. My destiny is my online name but...
SPEAKER_1:  No, but because so many of your social network is established in the digital space, like so many people know you through the digital space.
SPEAKER_1:  Can there be, can we swap out another person that looks like you?
SPEAKER_1:  and like an AI system and then that.
SPEAKER_1:  entity known as Destiny will continue existing.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it must be like, there must be some level of sophistication that could emulate.
SPEAKER_0:  A human brain, I would imagine, right?
SPEAKER_0:  probably text not there yet but well the question
SPEAKER_1:  question is.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the level of sophistication of the audience that would recognize that something has changed?
SPEAKER_1:  like
SPEAKER_1:  It's the Turing test.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. How hard is it?
SPEAKER_1:  to trick your audience, your large.
SPEAKER_1:  audience of fans that watch your streams.
SPEAKER_1:  that when you swap out an AI that emulates you.
SPEAKER_1:  that nothing has changed.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  The question is, do you have to really simulate so much of the human brain for that?
SPEAKER_1:  I don't think so.
SPEAKER_1:  Probably not.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, like you said, a lot of.
SPEAKER_1:  political discourse is it just walking down the tree together so you can probably emulate a lot of that discussion
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it would depend on if you're doing old data sets and you're training on that and I'm having conversations about abortion and your crane and vaccines, I imagine it could do it for quite a while.
SPEAKER_0:  The only thing that would be weird is when novel issues pop up.
SPEAKER_0:  then you probably need a more sophisticated.
SPEAKER_0:  resemblance of the inner brain right now.
SPEAKER_1:  They have to keep.
SPEAKER_1:  keep training on the internet so how the language models and that's the most incredible breakthroughs is the language models you just have to keep retraining the system
SPEAKER_1:  on Reddit.
SPEAKER_1:  which is actually what a lot of it is trained on, which is hilarious.
SPEAKER_0:  I do think it's really interesting that like...
SPEAKER_0:  kind of like funny problems like the trolley problem that we can kind of work through our normative ethical systems on are now like real questions. Like if you're driving a Tesla and it's on autopilot and you're going to hit somebody but it can swerve and hit somebody else like what ought the system do?
SPEAKER_0:  We went very quickly from fun kind of like project in philosophy class to
SPEAKER_0:  We need to solve this for insurance purposes, like as quickly as possible. It's kind of interesting to think about.
SPEAKER_1:  But I actually have a, I'll bring up the trolley problem with you later.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a fascinating version of it that I find hilarious. Okay, let's return.
SPEAKER_0:  to your low point.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh...
SPEAKER_1:  You started playing video games. That was a lucky break. You, uh, you did text-based ones. That was a lucky break because you got to be pretty good at learning.
SPEAKER_1:  and then.
SPEAKER_1:  you started thinking about going to college and so on what happened next
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I went to like a prep school. So you kind of have to go to college after that's like the point, right? I was also millennial. All of us had to go to college. That's always what they told us.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, my life was kind of-
SPEAKER_0:  It's hard to describe.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't really think much of the future. I was just kind of enjoying the day-to-day because everything in my life was pretty weird.
SPEAKER_0:  Both my parents had moved to Florida by the time I was 16, 17. I was living with my grandma, I was working.
SPEAKER_0:  I had a girlfriend, moved out.
SPEAKER_0:  We got a place to college.
SPEAKER_0:  By the time I got into college, I had transitioned from working at McDonald's to, I was working at a casino restaurant basically.
SPEAKER_0:  and I was really good at that job. So hi.
SPEAKER_0:  level of patience for drunk people and sane people.
SPEAKER_0:  and I was doing music in school because I've really grown to love music. And my thought process was I can do music.
SPEAKER_0:  as a hobby, I guess, unless I get really good and maybe I can make money with that. But otherwise I love music. I'm okay going to school for music, getting good at it. And then just doing that on the side. And then my main job would kind of be this career was building at the casino.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  basically the trying to balance personal life plus graveyard shift.
SPEAKER_0:  six day or weeks at a casino and then a full-time music degree was not possible for me and eventually I had to drop school after I think it was like three years
SPEAKER_0:  And after I dropped school to maintain my casino job.
SPEAKER_0:  After a few months, I got fired from my casino job.
SPEAKER_0:  So I'd essentially just thrown away like the past like three or four years of my life.
SPEAKER_1:  Why'd you get fired from the casino job?
SPEAKER_1:  I heard there's a story behind that.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there's a story. Basically, I was just really dumb when it came to understanding corporate politics. And this is funny because the same attitude kind of followed me into the streaming world.
SPEAKER_0:  My thought process has kind of always been...
SPEAKER_0:  Um, that like, as long as I'm really good at what I do, I should be untouchable. If I'm really good, you can't do anything to me. I don't have to play any dumb games or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  At the casino, I think I was the youngest, it was originally shifly than supervisor position at the casino.
SPEAKER_0:  And when I started to get my own shifts.
SPEAKER_0:  there were problems that i would run into on graveyard shift because of
SPEAKER_0:  carry over from the swing shift.
SPEAKER_0:  Remember, one of these problems was underneath the soda machine, they weren't cleaning it properly, and fruit flies were showing up.
SPEAKER_0:  And I, my manager came in one morning and she was like.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, hey.
SPEAKER_0:  what's going on with the machine. And I told them, I was like, listen, I can't do, I can't take everything from Swing Shift and do everything in Grape Shift. I can't do this. They need to figure out their stuff better or I need more employees. It's not possible for me.
SPEAKER_0:  And she's like, what did you tell anybody else? Like, yeah, I complained to the supervisor on the swing shift all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  I should tell me.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're not getting the answer that you like, then it's your responsibility to...
SPEAKER_0:  Email the next person up.
SPEAKER_0:  I was like, oh, okay, that's interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  And some months went on and I ran into more problems because on Graveyard
SPEAKER_0:  Here's how I don't know if it's everywhere, but morning shift is the easiest. And that's when you're the most overstaffed because that's when all the VPs are in and that's when all the managers are there and everybody blah, blah, blah. Swing shift is the most challenging. That's what your highest flow of customers is. You're also decently staffed there, but there's a lot of stuff going on and graveyard, nobody cares at all about you. They don't give you any employees. You might get swamped. You might not who cares. Make sure it's clean for day shift. That's the only thing that matters.
SPEAKER_1:  question for sort of clarification.
SPEAKER_1:  This is 24 hour.
SPEAKER_1:  24 hour dinner, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  This was the dining in a casino. Oh, by the way, I had an amazing moment at a casino recently.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a special place.
SPEAKER_1:  A dining room casino is a place of magic.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a lot of, I don't know if I'd say magic, but there's a lot of otherworldly stuff going on.
SPEAKER_1:  There's
SPEAKER_1:  And I had an interaction with a waitress that was the sweetest waitress in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  I was just like...
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, made me feel less alone on this.
SPEAKER_1:  world of ours. So graveyard begins when?
SPEAKER_0:  For me, my shift was 10pm to 6am.
SPEAKER_0:  or sometimes I get called in early, so it'd be 8 p.m. to 6 a.m.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's no love for that shift.
SPEAKER_0:  No, especially not trying to do school at the same time. Absolutely not.
SPEAKER_0:  But yeah, basically long story short, I ran into a problem with my super where I didn't have enough employees on my shift VPs were coming in in the morning. There's something like hey the diners kind of dirty and I'm like you've cut all my employees past 4am Like on some nights, I'm literally cooking and doing front of house like all on my own. Like I can't do this
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  My manager Pam told me, well, you've got to figure it out. And so I remembered her advice.
SPEAKER_0:  So I emailed the VP of Food and Beverage and I cc'd her, and I said, I'm not getting the help I need for my restaurant.
SPEAKER_0:  Now I didn't know at the time that I was basically completely throwing her under the bus.
SPEAKER_0:  because of that email, but retroactively, when I look back on things.
SPEAKER_0:  retrospectively I see that was the moment that I got like marked for deletion.
SPEAKER_0:  And I didn't really understand it, even though I'd heard terminology for papering somebody out the door. But after that point, I started to get written up for like a lot of little random things. Like I'll come, like I'd missed one day of work in my three years at the casino. And I started to get written up for like showing up like one or two minutes late.
SPEAKER_0:  That's kind of weird.
SPEAKER_0:  whatever, or written up for random ways about filing paperwork. And then eventually there came a situation with another employee where they were
SPEAKER_0:  It's complicated, it has to be like call out stuff. But basically they wanted to come or they wanted to call out and I told them if they called out, they were going to get fired because.
SPEAKER_0:  They were at like 10 points. They were at nine points and 10 points is firing, blah, blah, blah. Pam told me, you can tell her that she's gonna get a point, but you can't tell her she's gonna get fired. I don't know what that meant. And then I told her that if you call out, you're gonna get, you know, you're fucked. You're gonna get fired.
SPEAKER_0:  or you're gonna be at 10 points. And then I got called in early like three days later and Pam was like, you inappropriately communicated with an employee because you said the F word in a text message. And I'm like, really? There's no shot. And she's like, well, you also tried to fire the employee. And I was like, no, I told her she was gonna get 10 points. She's like, well, you used the F word. I'm like, this is insane. And I didn't, just cause I was such a, such a high performing employee. It's like, there's no way I'm getting fired. And then I did. I was like, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  cashed out my 401k and moped for like three months.
SPEAKER_0:  because I had thrown away school.
SPEAKER_0:  for this casino job and then I got fired from this job that like, yeah, nobody believed I got fired it was just insane.
SPEAKER_1:  So if you look back, if you were allowed to not just to...
SPEAKER_1:  look back to your own memory.
SPEAKER_1:  But actually watch yourself. Like some of you recorded video that whole time.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think you would be surprised? You would notice some things that potentially.
SPEAKER_1:  of not having a self-awareness, not having like social...
SPEAKER_1:  like a civility and social etiquette that's played in the human relations. Yeah, absolutely.
SPEAKER_1:  So is that is that at the core of it essentially?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think so. I mean, that follows me even to this day. There's a lot of, um...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if you're recording or not, but when we spoke early about like meta-conversations, I have to think a lot sometimes about meta-conversations because the way that I want to drive a conversation will sometimes be way different than what is like the best way to have a conversation, whereas I just want to like-
SPEAKER_0:  go really hard on like some.
SPEAKER_0:  itty bitty like some idiosyncrasy, some factor figure, whatever, but that's not like the human conversation I need to have, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  So you got fired slash left that job.
SPEAKER_1:  And that took you to the job that would be the lowest point.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a huge downgrade in pay.
SPEAKER_0:  I went from getting like...
SPEAKER_0:  I think of the casino, because I worked so much overtime, I was doing like 22.50 an hour on all my overtime. And this was back in 2008, 2009, it's like a college.
SPEAKER_0:  Student, like, amazing pay.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I had benefits, like everything was good, and then the cocarbit cleaning was like...
SPEAKER_0:  I was probably getting my paycheck like every other week.
SPEAKER_0:  was maybe $1,500 or $1,000.
SPEAKER_0:  and I'm working like.
SPEAKER_0:  13 day stretches, like I have every other Sunday off.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's so many hours. Like I have to show up at the shop at like seven or six and then I go home at like eight or nine depending on when my jobs are throughout.
SPEAKER_1:  the day. You doing all businesses or residential or what are you doing? Everything.
SPEAKER_1:  Everything. Are you working for a company that's cooperating or are you?
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so like there's a scheduled thing, you have to go to it and so on. If you don't this
SPEAKER_0:  but still like this is why the schedule would suck is sometimes I'd show up at
SPEAKER_0:  I think we had to be in the shop at, I think it was 7am.
SPEAKER_0:  We shop at the shop at 7am.
SPEAKER_0:  First job might be at eight or nine, but that job might be like a one hour job.
SPEAKER_0:  So I might show up at 7am and have a job from 8.30 to 9.30. Then my next job might not be from...
SPEAKER_0:  until like say 11.
SPEAKER_0:  So from A39 thread I'll do one job.
SPEAKER_0:  And then I've got a drop from like 11 to 12 or something.
SPEAKER_0:  then I might have like a decent job from like five to eight.
SPEAKER_0:  But like my whole day is destroyed.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm doing like three.
SPEAKER_0:  smallest jobs, so I'm getting like 30 bucks maybe for being in the shop or, you know, my job for like 10 or 11 hours and it's just like horrible.
SPEAKER_1:  So here's somebody that seems to be extremely good at thinking and conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  have a bit of an ego perhaps.
SPEAKER_1:  in both the negative and the positive sense of that word.
SPEAKER_1:  Was there some aspect of working at McDonald's?
SPEAKER_1:  and then working at the casino and then working for the, as a carpet cleaner that was humbling.
SPEAKER_0:  No, never.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  I had a... The ego burned bright through it all.
SPEAKER_1:  See, well...
SPEAKER_1:  or not, you can push.
SPEAKER_0:  back in the ego. Yeah, no, I understand. I totally get what you mean. I had a really close friend growing up whose name was Chris.
SPEAKER_0:  and i think we probably don't use we're
SPEAKER_0:  Like four or five, I think, he lived behind me.
SPEAKER_0:  And I grew up with him and I'd always been kind of an outsider to the world that I was in once I got to high school for sure.
SPEAKER_0:  because all of those kids were incredibly wealthy. You know, Corvettes and Mustangs when they turned 16, it was a prep school. And I was doing the, they had like a work study program there where you could stay after school from 2.30 to five every day to kind of like work to pay for your tuition. So I've been working like throughout all of high school. I got another job at McDonald's when I was 18, worked at the casino. Like I had always been doing that kind of work. I never really viewed it as like beneath me or anything. It's not like I don't have like a family of doctors or lawyers or anything. And then me and my other friend, Chris guy, we'd always make fun of everybody else for being kind of like, you know, like preppy kids and everything, so.
SPEAKER_1:  So there is a...
SPEAKER_1:  There's some pride to that sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  hard work.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I guess a little bit, yeah. Because, yeah, looking especially at my dad, like the solution to every problem was to just throw more hours of work at it, basically. So that was always my...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I go too. And I never am.
SPEAKER_1:  What was psychologically the low point?
SPEAKER_0:  I think psychologically the low point was that, as I'm doing this carpet cleaning job,
SPEAKER_0:  uh, driving around my city.
SPEAKER_0:  There's like this feeling of...
SPEAKER_0:  I guess for a lot of people it's probably college, but there's a feeling when you're in high school.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything is like so exciting and the whole world is kind of in front of you and there are
SPEAKER_0:  trillion different branching paths of possibilities.
SPEAKER_0:  And you know, even through high school, you're thinking like, am I going to be a doctor or a lawyer or can I join the MBA or can I do this or that? There's all these things in front of you.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  when I especially felt it when I was doing these carpet cleaning jobs and
SPEAKER_0:  I think it was in the fall, I'd be outside some of these houses and I'd just kind of look around and I'd recognize a lot of these neighborhoods that I'd drive around with friends in or I'd be walking through, I ran cross-country, some of them I'd be running through these neighborhoods.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was just kind of like this feeling of looking around and it was like...
SPEAKER_0:  when I was here in the past.
SPEAKER_0:  This is like kind of like a transitionary phase of my life.
SPEAKER_0:  where I'm doing this and it's so fun and exciting, and then I'm gonna move on to something else and it's gonna be fun and exciting and awesome.
SPEAKER_0:  And then like, you know, two years later.
SPEAKER_0:  My whole life has collapsed.
SPEAKER_0:  Like I'm in a house that I can't afford anymore. ey reasons go trash
SPEAKER_0:  X that I hate is pregnant with my kid.
SPEAKER_0:  and I have no money, I've got no upward mobility, I failed college.
SPEAKER_0:  I, my job is horrible. Like just every single, like this is like.
SPEAKER_0:  All of those, the wave function had collapsed into one thing and that one thing was the worst thing that could have possibly been at the time for me. Yeah, like everything was gone and horrible. So yeah, that was the feeling I had at the time.
SPEAKER_1:  ever contemplate suicide.
SPEAKER_0:  thought about thinking about it.
SPEAKER_0:  But I've just never been that kind of person, so...
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, basically as a way to escape from the hardship.
SPEAKER_0:  Something that I'm so incredibly lucky, I don't know why or how, I'm just gonna chalk it up to biology. I've always had really high mental baseline.
SPEAKER_0:  I've like depression and all of that. There've been a few short stints I've dealt with it, past 30 because I did a lot of drugs.
SPEAKER_0:  But other than that, my mental baseline is just so high. And even in the carpet cleaning days...
SPEAKER_0:  Like if you man the videos might still be there I think on my old YouTube channel channel where I'll be like playing Starcraft when I first started getting a streaming and I'll be calling Up customers like this Steve from guaranteed clean. We had to move your job back one hour Is it okay if I show up instead of 230 and then I hang up? It's like alright guys. We got three more games and it's like let's go like stuff like that So my baseline has always been like really high for mental function
SPEAKER_1:  even in the low point, you had strength. Is there anything you can give by way of advice from people that-
SPEAKER_1:  for whom the wave function collapses, as it does for many of us.
SPEAKER_1:  Like holy fuck.
SPEAKER_1:  The world is not full of opportunity and you're kind of a failure.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I've been there.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I don't know. It's rough because like...
SPEAKER_0:  I usually ask for compassion from people that I have it better off.
SPEAKER_0:  Because once you're down there...
SPEAKER_0:  Like the only reason I say I got lucky, but it wasn't even really lucky.
SPEAKER_0:  or it was lucky, but it was more lucky. It wasn't just lucky that I got into streaming. It was lucky that I was into computers at an early age. It was lucky that I played video games at an early age. It was lucky that all the tech came up at exactly that right point in time. I was a pretty smart guy, but it was definitely preparation meets opportunity. And that opportunity was like at the exact precise moment of my life. If anything had gone differently, then I would just be cleaning carpets today.
SPEAKER_1:  So in the many worlds interpretation of quantum mechanics...
SPEAKER_0:  This is like one out of like, there's
SPEAKER_1:  Many, many Stevens, they're just still carpet cleaning.
SPEAKER_1:  and they're full of pain and resentment.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  The one piece of advice that I give, I hate that I have to push back against all these crypto bros and everybody online.
SPEAKER_0:  Decently intelligent people that are successful. I've never hurt anybody.
SPEAKER_0:  a contradiction to this. Maybe you will. You can tell me if you disagree.
SPEAKER_0:  I always look at kids in high school and I'm like, just try a little bit harder, like 30 minutes a night. If you don't study, just do 30 minutes, just do a little bit more.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  It is, you are laying the foundation for the rest of your life and you can't appreciate it in high school and college.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh my god, when you get out.
SPEAKER_0:  everything in your life is so much easier. you have
SPEAKER_0:  Probably more responsibility over the direction of your life when you're like 13, 14 years old than you ever will once you're like 25 and older because this is like when you're determining the foundations that everything's going to build on.
SPEAKER_1:  100%
SPEAKER_1:  First of all, it does seem that
SPEAKER_1:  the liberating aspect of being young.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like
SPEAKER_1:  Anything you learn.
SPEAKER_1:  So working hard at learning something will pay off.
SPEAKER_1:  in like nonlinear ways, like you said with video games. I feel like.
SPEAKER_1:  So like people who like I hate school. Alright, well fine, but find something.
SPEAKER_1:  where you're challenging yourself, you're growing, you're learning, you're learning a skill, you're learning about a thing.
SPEAKER_1:  course.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you could push back and say, well, there's some trajectories that might not be productive. Like if you spend the entirety of your teen years.
SPEAKER_1:  playing, I don't know, League of Legends, or a game you have.
SPEAKER_1:  love and hate relationship with
SPEAKER_0:  No, just a hate and hate.
SPEAKER_1:  relationship. Okay, well, we'll talk about
SPEAKER_1:  I think you have a love-hate relationship with hate in general. We'll just talk about it in love.
SPEAKER_1:  We'll try to decomplexify that one.
SPEAKER_1:  I think in general, just investing yourself fully with passion.
SPEAKER_1:  It really does pay off.
SPEAKER_1:  But that said also school.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like...
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't get enough credit like high school in particular middle school and high school
SPEAKER_1:  because it's general education.
SPEAKER_1:  I think if you're, especially if you're lucky you have good teachers, but honestly.
SPEAKER_1:  I haven't.
SPEAKER_1:  Mostly the textbooks themselves were good teachers. It's a one chance in life. You have to
SPEAKER_1:  really explore a subject.
SPEAKER_1:  Fuck grades, like getting good grades.
SPEAKER_1:  is attention I would say with actual learning.
SPEAKER_1:  That is true.
SPEAKER_1:  Just get a biology textbook and to explore ideas in biology and allowing yourself to be
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  inspired.
SPEAKER_1:  by the beauty of it.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I don't know. I think that really, really, really pays off and you never get a chance to do that again.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe not even.
SPEAKER_1:  Textbooks like reading, straight up reading.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  I think if you read, this is the one time in life you get a chance to read.
SPEAKER_1:  Really read. Like, read a book a day read.
SPEAKER_1:  You can...
SPEAKER_1:  really invest.
SPEAKER_1:  You can really grow by reading. I mean, you almost-
SPEAKER_1:  All those guys talk about it.
SPEAKER_0:  very rare that you meet like a dumb person who reads a lot. I don't know if that's ever happened in my life.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, dumb or not successful. And the cool thing is.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like the reading, it's like investment, the reading you do early on in high school.
SPEAKER_1:  pays off way more than the reading you do later.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... so like the the really influential
SPEAKER_1:  Reading.
SPEAKER_1:  is during those high school years, because you're basically learning from others.
SPEAKER_1:  the mistakes they've made.
SPEAKER_1:  the solutions to problems.
SPEAKER_1:  You're basically learning the shortcuts to life.
SPEAKER_1:  Like whatever the hell you want to do, music, read from the best people.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... that the music theory like learn music theory learn
SPEAKER_1:  I'll read biographies about jazz musicians, blues musicians.
SPEAKER_1:  See their like, see all the mistakes, see what they did, see the shortcuts.
SPEAKER_1:  If you want to do podcasting, read about other podcasts. If you want to...
SPEAKER_1:  Do streamer read about other streamers, physicists and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like you figure out all the mistakes and get to a shortcut through life.
SPEAKER_1:  because most people show up to college without having done that.
SPEAKER_1:  And now you get a chance to shortcut your way.
SPEAKER_1:  past them.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, 100%.
SPEAKER_1:  But nobody really teaches you that.
SPEAKER_1:  They're like, go to school.
SPEAKER_1:  this from this time to that time.
SPEAKER_1:  that you're shut up.
SPEAKER_1:  This is just what you do. Eat your broccoli.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's like there's two huge problems. One.
SPEAKER_0:  is now that I'm older, because you don't know anything as a kid, you can't really criticize adults as a kid, because you're a kid. You're ageist, if I may say so. I am, I am super ageist. As I get older, I get even more ageist. There are a lot of people where I argue, they're like, man dude, you're really 22, aren't you? I can tell every word you say, there's seeps of like 22 year oldness, but that's okay, I love that for you. You know, I could just.
SPEAKER_1:  say because you mentioned this your wife is a fellow streamer Melina you mentioned that this is a source of fights for the two of you that
SPEAKER_1:  And I could just feel that.
SPEAKER_1:  There is truth to what you're saying, which is like.
SPEAKER_1:  All right, you're saying that because you're 22.
SPEAKER_1:  Just wait until you're 25 and you won't be saying that anymore. Sure. Now that is the most annoying.
SPEAKER_0:  for people to hear. Yeah, you can't ever say that, of course. Because it's-
SPEAKER_1:  actually usually true.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  because.
SPEAKER_1:  We do go through phases in life, and you can understand that most things are phases. So just in general you can say, just wait.
SPEAKER_1:  Just wait.
SPEAKER_1:  You won't see this. You won't feel this way again. I could say that to you. You could say that to yourself
SPEAKER_1:  Just wait, whatever you're feeling like, just wait. In five, 10 years, it'll be a different person and you will laugh.
SPEAKER_1:  at the things you take seriously now.
SPEAKER_1:  that they're causing you pain now. All that kind of stuff. But people, I hate hearing that.
SPEAKER_0:  Anyway, absolutely. I think the joke that I always say is like, if I could literally step into a time machine and I could come back out and see myself as a 17 year old and I could say, hey, I am literally you from the future. You see the time machine and I would look at me and I would see the time machine and I would give myself the best advice in the world and I would be the most successful person.
SPEAKER_0:  I would ignore all of it. Even knowing it came from myself, I'd be like, this guy sold out, this dude doesn't know what the fuck he's talking about. Like, nah, I'll figure it out better. Like, he must've made some, that's what I would think is the 17, even if I knew it was myself in the future, I would just 100% never believe it.
SPEAKER_0:  And knowing that is very frustrating, but I keep that in mind when I deal with younger people. That's why I always stay on stream when I'm talking to-
SPEAKER_0:  Like there's been stuff with like Sneakos, another girl on my stream called Lab. When I see the way, I see the mistakes they're making.
SPEAKER_0:  Oftentimes because I've made all of these mistakes, sometimes in the most public and horrible fashion ever, but I'm never like a mentor. I'm not gonna sit there and like tell you like, oh, do this or that or that or that. It's like.
SPEAKER_0:  i don't know if you're gonna listen to me and i don't want to condescend to you and you know you figure stuff out i'll be here if you want to talk about it but yeah
SPEAKER_0:  There was a one of those stories, there was a company that didn't work with me because I was very adamant on defending like very radical notions about language and racial slurs and everything when I was like 22 or whatever. And there was a company and they said, well, we don't want to work with this guy for an event.
SPEAKER_0:  And after they'd said that, I'd written an article on my website.
SPEAKER_0:  called the company was Gigabyte, they make motherboards. I said, fuck Gigabyte in the ass. That was the title to my article. And it was like, well, if they don't wanna work with me, I'm gonna blow them up and never do anything ever with them again. And it was just like, looking back at it now, obviously as an older person, like, hey, you need to pump the brakes and chill. You're destroying yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  But yeah, as a young person, it's like, yeah, you're 22. Of course you think that you can say whatever and do whatever. And as long as you're good at what you're doing, you've got the whole world behind you. And yeah, cheers.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, let's go there. You have a history of using offensive language.
SPEAKER_1:  like the R word.
SPEAKER_1:  the N word including the N word with a hard R.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... calling women bitches
SPEAKER_1:  talking about rape.
SPEAKER_1:  in a nonchalant way.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  What part of that do you regret?
SPEAKER_1:  What part of that do you not?
SPEAKER_0:  Language is very complicated.
SPEAKER_0:  When it comes to stuff relating to slurs, there's been like a whole trajectory of feelings on...
SPEAKER_0:  everything related to language so my free
SPEAKER_1:  personally and for the Internet as a whole.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I don't care about the internet. For me personally.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm early twenties, I'll say like 22, 23, I think probably when I first started streaming.
SPEAKER_0:  My feeling is that
SPEAKER_0:  Any word is just a word, and if it hurts you, that's your fault. Take responsibility for yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  This probably came from my background of being a really independent person, so that's just kind of like the mind that I had for everything.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  They were basically, they were like a collection of experiences that I had.
SPEAKER_0:  And as I grew, I started to realize, like, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel differently about some of these words depending on the context and I can see how they can affect other people depending on the context.
SPEAKER_0:  So as I've kind of like grown.
SPEAKER_0:  I think I've developed a more sophisticated understanding of...
SPEAKER_0:  how different words are used and how they affect people, whether they like it or not, and more importantly, whether I like it or not. And that words can, even if I don't want it to be, they can be a vehicle for emboldening certain types of ideas that I don't want to embolden.
SPEAKER_0:  And yeah, that's kind of been the whole growth. I've been lucky that in the time that I came up on the internet, I was able to learn these lessons because if I was trying to learn those same lessons today, I would have been completely destroyed because I had insane views on language like 10 years ago.
SPEAKER_1:  We could talk about the past, we could talk about the present. Let's talk about the past first.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you deal with the fact that there's videos of you?
SPEAKER_1:  in the past saying.
SPEAKER_1:  the N word including the N word with a hard R.
SPEAKER_0:  So generally... And what's the contest? Can you give me like...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so what would be the con?
SPEAKER_0:  usually when I
SPEAKER_0:  Lay out this defense. It's not because I wouldn't have used the N-word.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, generally, whenever I said the N word, it was usually in an example of like, this is something that like a racist person would say. I don't think I've ever.
SPEAKER_0:  on the internet and I don't think I've ever called anybody like the Edward with a hard R.
SPEAKER_0:  Not because I wouldn't have but just because it wasn't in my vocabulary. I played RTS real-time strategy and we use the the f slur for gay people. That's what I use that one a ton I've called people that a ton in the past.
SPEAKER_0:  So I should actually just
SPEAKER_1:  as a small tangent. Go for it.
SPEAKER_1:  And this is what I-
SPEAKER_1:  like to explore with you.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a ruthlessness to the language.
SPEAKER_1:  in the gaming world. yen euioioioioioioioioioioioi
SPEAKER_1:  There's different communities.
SPEAKER_1:  They have different...
SPEAKER_1:  flavors.
SPEAKER_1:  of language of hate speech essentially.
SPEAKER_1:  and there's also a humor to it.
SPEAKER_1:  Witch.
SPEAKER_1:  really bothers me in a dark way that I haven't been able to really think through
SPEAKER_1:  because humor seems to be a kind of...
SPEAKER_1:  catalyst for hate. It seems to normalize hate.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, you say...
SPEAKER_1:  Basically, it's like Louis C.K. says a lot of edgy things.
SPEAKER_1:  but you take something Lucy Kay says and do it in a non-funny way and do it over and over and over and keep
SPEAKER_1:  uh, increasing.
SPEAKER_1:  The hatefulness of it.
SPEAKER_1:  vitriol
SPEAKER_1:  and somehow you.
SPEAKER_1:  Find yourself like Alice in Wonderland.
SPEAKER_1:  in a world full of hate where there is no good in.
SPEAKER_1:  evil is all the same. In fact, the good.
SPEAKER_1:  is to be mocked and the evil is to be celebrated for the humor of it.
SPEAKER_1:  basically not taking the ideas of evil seriously.
SPEAKER_1:  And I don't know what it, it reveals something about human nature that you can let go.
SPEAKER_1:  the moral relativism that
SPEAKER_1:  can happen when you do that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  at the same time.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm a fan of dark humor.
SPEAKER_1:  when done well.
SPEAKER_1:  Anyway, for people who are not familiar, I just wanted to mention...
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  some of the worst.
SPEAKER_1:  hate speech that ends in LOL.
SPEAKER_1:  happens in gaming communities. Yeah, the... And that's where you come from in certain parts.
SPEAKER_0:  So a lot of people don't remember this or don't know this because they're younger, but way back in the day.
SPEAKER_0:  in the late nineties, early mid 2000s of the internet. The way that online kind of like shit talk worked was you were just trying to ramp up to the most insanely edgy, crazy stuff you could say to like provoke a reaction.
SPEAKER_0:  Have you ever heard of something called the aristocrats?
SPEAKER_0:  That's like a joke, the joke.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah, the joke, yeah, there's a movie on it, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, basically every single like shit talk back and forth on the internet was like that. Like what is the most increasingly depraved, and back then you didn't get banned for slurs or anything on any of these chat rooms. So it was just like insane world to walk into.
SPEAKER_0:  and I was fully 100% a part of, a product of, and a contributor to.
SPEAKER_1:  that were so that probably still goes on the internet in some way and that probably still goes on the internet in maybe
SPEAKER_1:  more pacified way.
SPEAKER_0:  only in darker parts of the internet. I'd say for the most part, most.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, compared to back then, compared to 20 years ago, the internet is way cleaned up now. There are still gonna be boards you can go on or parts of the internet where you see that type of hammer, but...
SPEAKER_0:  not know when near as mainstream like back then you could open your mic on Xbox live and hear some insane stuff when that first started nowhere near what you hear today although there's still
SPEAKER_1:  those elements of escalation that happened that just seems to be part of human nature on the internet the
SPEAKER_1:  because we don't get the feedback of actually hurting people directly. So the
SPEAKER_1:  the trolling.
SPEAKER_1:  Like for the walls, you'll do like whatever, like you will still escalate.
SPEAKER_1:  within the bounds.
SPEAKER_1:  You're just saying that there's more bonds now on Reddit, there's more bounds and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  There's moderators that yell at you.
SPEAKER_1:  that ban you and so on if you cross those bounds.
SPEAKER_1:  overall that basic human instinct to escalate.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh.
SPEAKER_1:  especially under the veil of anonymity is still there.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, it's dark.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, just there's a lot of different ways to look at it and there's different ways you can break that art like for instance Like you mentioned dark humor
SPEAKER_0:  and you say that like...
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  Sometimes dark humor is funny and sometimes it's not.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that it's really important to dig into and figure out like why certain things are funny. Can I give you an example? Yeah, go. It's from your subreddit. Oh boy.
SPEAKER_1:  No, that made me laugh and I felt wrong about it. Oh no.
SPEAKER_1:  So this is a...
SPEAKER_0:  I already know what this is, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  So this is a trolley problem. To me it connects because I've-
SPEAKER_1:  Think about the, it keeps, because I worked on autonomous vehicles, the trial problem, the philosophical thought experiment keeps brought up a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, when AI is part of making the decision, do I kill?
SPEAKER_1:  three people here or five people here and they I makes that decision. How do you do that calculus? And this, this particular, there's a
SPEAKER_1:  There's a deep...
SPEAKER_1:  So it's satire that reveals some kind of flaw in society.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like that's what dark humor does.
SPEAKER_1:  Successful dark humor does.
SPEAKER_0:  And I don't know if this is law. Hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like there's a certain brand of dark humor.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think the reason...
SPEAKER_0:  I think the reason is why it's good.
SPEAKER_0:  or why it is good humor. I think it's because it, I don't think it necessarily reveals a flaw. Sometimes I feel like it reveals like a kind of virtue, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, if you look at this particular thing... Can I explain what we're... Yeah, go for it. Just listen.
SPEAKER_1:  The title of the Reddit post is, you know what to pick.
SPEAKER_1:  And it says.
SPEAKER_1:  Five people are going to die either way, but if you flip the lever the trolley will do a sick fucking loop first
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Also the top comment.
SPEAKER_1:  is.
SPEAKER_1:  A question saying, which I think is also part of the dark humor that's successful. Can I get the gender and ethnic backgrounds of the groups first?
SPEAKER_1:  And the top answer is both groups are each comprised of five.
SPEAKER_1:  White orphaned cis male.
SPEAKER_1:  Heavy meth users.
SPEAKER_1:  who are consistently in and out of drug rehab.
SPEAKER_1:  All who identifies right wing extremists.
SPEAKER_0:  Humor is so, it's such a sophisticated-
SPEAKER_0:  thing that we engage in, humor is like really complicated. But I would argue that like hopefully the humor here
SPEAKER_0:  shows the virtue of like.
SPEAKER_0:  This is obviously horrible, but that's kind of why it's funny. It's funny because it's such a horrible question to ask. Like, do we kill five people in a boring way or in a really entertaining way? And it's like, that's really, that's really, and then when you ask even more, like, what are the ethnic backgrounds? Like, that's even worse to say that, you know? So I feel like that's like the type of, there's a way that you can engage with dark humor it's like, oof, like.
SPEAKER_0:  It's funny because it's so wrong and so taboo. And we all know that it's wrong and taboo and that's kind of where the shared laugh comes from.
SPEAKER_1:  So for me, the question that asking the diversity question is a sophisticated way of revealing the absurdity of asking about diversity when it's talking about human life.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, interesting, because the way that I took that was, I think it reveals the absurdity of how people will weigh different ethnic backgrounds so differently when it comes to value of human life. Like I'm actually thinking of that in terms of like an immigration related question, where people are really keen and quick to dehumanize like black or brown people. So like the question is like, well, if five of them are brown and five are white, well, I know which one I'm gonna pull the lever for. That's how I read that. But it's satirizing that aspect. Yeah, exactly, yes, of course, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  That's what I mean. That that's the floor.
SPEAKER_1:  To me at least.
SPEAKER_1:  It showed.
SPEAKER_1:  that humanity
SPEAKER_1:  or social networks that are easy to be outraged and love the outrage and the chaos.
SPEAKER_1:  Twitter and social networks will pull that lever.
SPEAKER_1:  Like they would, they would always try to maximize the fun.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's like a, there's a sick aspect to.
SPEAKER_1:  all the atrocities, all the tragedies that happen in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  that we kind of always lean towards the outrageous narrative.
SPEAKER_1:  Weaved around it.
SPEAKER_1:  dumb
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, the one that leads to the most clicks to the most.
SPEAKER_1:  attention to the most outraged.
SPEAKER_1:  to all that kind of stuff. So that's almost like a satire of society.
SPEAKER_1:  when they are faced with tragedy.
SPEAKER_1:  they will maximize.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm trying to think of...
SPEAKER_1:  A word that's not fun.
SPEAKER_0:  entertainment.
SPEAKER_1:  Maximize the entertainment, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  This is a big criticism I give, especially to conservative crowds.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, left leaning people, everybody doesn't. I don't like when people blame the media for the state of the media today. I very much believe that everything in society is a feedback loop, and that if you're really unhappy with the state of the media, I think that the media is a good reflection for what people wanna see. Because there is a room right now in the United States where somebody could start a company where all they do is completely factual reporting, they don't have a political slant, and they're not giving you these sensationalist narratives or stories, and that media company would fail in two weeks because people don't wanna see that. Generally, people really wanna see the like, show me the guy that really believes in what I say, that calls the other guy an idiot, the guy that are screaming on TV or on the radio, like, this is what I really want. And people will engage in that, and that feedback loop will continue for generations. And then all of a sudden people are like, why is the media so biased? Why is the media driving so many narratives? And it's like, well, what do you mean? Exactly what you wanna see.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's frustrating for me. That's one of my big kind of when I defend establishments or when I talk about like the interplay between citizen and.
SPEAKER_0:  and all these institutions we have.
SPEAKER_0:  that the institutions are very much a reflection of the population, at least in democratic societies. And I think that people very much try to elude the personal responsibility or the country's responsibility to why some of them look the way that they do.
SPEAKER_1:  But that takes us back to the N word with a hard R.
SPEAKER_0:  Sure.
SPEAKER_0:  Why?
SPEAKER_0:  For the particular examples that I was giving, for the particular conversations that I was having, if you're gonna have challenging conversations around certain words, I think you should probably be able to say them, otherwise it feels really ridiculous to me.
SPEAKER_0:  That's like why- Do you still believe that?
SPEAKER_0:  Um, for com- yes, in- not like calling people those words, but in having conversations about those words, I would say that I still believe that, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  But don't you think as you said, that using those words...
SPEAKER_1:  actually gives motivation and strength to...
SPEAKER_1:  people who have hate in their hearts.
SPEAKER_0:  I think depending on the context of what's going on, I think that that's gonna be a big driver in terms of how people are going to perceive or take it. So in a conversation about the N-word, I don't think I would normally say the N-word, I would just talk about.
SPEAKER_0:  the word much the same way that like in a movie, like in Django, people use the N word. Should that be censored in that movie or in the context of that movie, is it being employed in a way where these aren't good people, you're not supposed to like them and that's what the audience walks away with.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, but that context is different than conversation. It feels like in conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  You using that word normalizes it.
SPEAKER_1:  and that.
SPEAKER_1:  Normalizing that word is going to make it easier for people who use that word
SPEAKER_1:  in a hateful way to use it.
SPEAKER_1:  Same with the F word, the F slur.
SPEAKER_1:  If you use that...
SPEAKER_1:  casually and normalize it.
SPEAKER_1:  in a way that's not hateful.
SPEAKER_1:  You're using words that's not hateful.
SPEAKER_1:  But you-
SPEAKER_1:  the side effect is that it normalizes it.
SPEAKER_1:  than people who do use it in a hateful way.
SPEAKER_1:  would be more likely to use it.
SPEAKER_1:  Therefore...
SPEAKER_1:  mathematically looking at the equation of the number of times
SPEAKER_1:  the N word or the F word is used throughout the world, it increases the number of times it's used in a hateful way.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I think that human-
SPEAKER_0:  And you're part of that problem, Stephen.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't I don't agree. I understand. I understand the thought process.
SPEAKER_0:  but I don't know if using certain words.
SPEAKER_0:  within different contexts is going to necessarily normalize like the hateful use of that word.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  that is an argument that I've heard people use, somebody will say like, okay, well, hold on, that should never be used ever, because by virtue of you normalizing it, even in an inoffensive environment, you increase the proclivity for people to use it in a potentially more offensive environment. And my argument is always like, no, I don't think that crossover exists. But if you did wanna take that argument, and maybe you do feel this way, I think that you get really problematic when you run into communities that do use certain words that people would say, well, they should be allowed to do it. So for instance, if you think that any utterance of the N word at all is highly problematic and might increase hatred, then like the entire rap industry has to dramatically change the way that they engage with the N word. And obviously a lot of people that criticize people's use of the N word aren't gonna turn to rappers and say, well, you guys can't say it either.
SPEAKER_1:  No, it's who.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, it's who uses the N word, that's what.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not, so it's not just the word. It's the...
SPEAKER_1:  It is.
SPEAKER_1:  context dependent.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  but I would say that you as a white person.
SPEAKER_1:  having conversations.
SPEAKER_1:  The context there is the kind that would lead to an increase in hate.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you think the N word should be censored in the dictionary?
SPEAKER_1:  No.
SPEAKER_1:  and I believe there's a Wikipedia page on it and it's not censored.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I don't I think it should be in the dictionary. I think the context of
SPEAKER_1:  casual conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I said, I just believe that on the internet.
SPEAKER_1:  having humor.
SPEAKER_1:  having fun conversations as you have.
SPEAKER_1:  and your streams.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  leads to the normalization of the word without any educational value.
SPEAKER_0:  I would agree with that. I think I would agree with that.
SPEAKER_1:  Sorry, so there's a difference.
SPEAKER_1:  between the
SPEAKER_1:  F's learn N-word and both I think.
SPEAKER_1:  should not be used in a fun way, but the F word was used in a fun way for a long time. For sure. I'll tell you something that bothers me about your streams.
SPEAKER_1:  What? Now you're stream-
SPEAKER_1:  your streams and basically every other stream.
SPEAKER_1:  is the casual use of the R word. Oh, the ableism, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if it's about the able. I don't even know.
SPEAKER_1:  Listen it's complicated, I'm not like virtue signaling here.
SPEAKER_0:  No, ableism isn't a virtue signal. I mean, it's a legitimate, yeah. Like I get emails from fans that say like, hey, like I deal with this particular issue. Every time you use this word, it kind of feels like you're attacking me. Like just like so it's a valid concept.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just something cuts wrong for me. Like for example, I'm not bothered by.
SPEAKER_1:  I am bothered by the excessive use of the word fuck.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  but not.
SPEAKER_1:  in the same way that moderate
SPEAKER_1:  Use of the word fuck.
SPEAKER_0:  What is it I'm curious in when somebody calls somebody in our word?
SPEAKER_0:  What is the feeling that you get that makes you feel bad about it?
SPEAKER_1:  It signals to me that you don't...
SPEAKER_1:  Give a damn about
SPEAKER_1:  people who are struggling.
SPEAKER_1:  in ways that you are not struggling.
SPEAKER_1:  Like that.
SPEAKER_1:  that signals to me.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, um...
SPEAKER_1:  about the experience of others.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you think that there are other words also that could convey like a similar feeling to your work? Because it feels like you've drawn a pretty special circle around because like I imagine I go, oh, this guy's an uneducated dumb fucker. You're a networker.
SPEAKER_0:  like
SPEAKER_0:  to those who are also that circle keep changing.
SPEAKER_0:  which you can, which is fine, it does.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think that's the whole point with the culture. I'm trying to feel my feelings kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  you know i'm a human being that exists in a social context that
SPEAKER_1:  we're all evolving that language together and just feels wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, the word...
SPEAKER_1:  bitch for example. It really bought like I've heard on your streams and in general.
SPEAKER_1:  calling.
SPEAKER_1:  a woman a stupid bitch.
SPEAKER_1:  really bothers me.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's not just the word bitch, it's context. For example,
SPEAKER_1:  Me personally, I'm speaking to me personally.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, badass bitch.
SPEAKER_1:  is different than stupid.
SPEAKER_0:  Sure, like a bad bitch or something that's different. Yeah, of course. Way different.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it speaks to a bigger sense of civility.
SPEAKER_1:  and respect for human beings.
SPEAKER_1:  They're not like you.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the feeling that I'm bothering. So..... rests.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess what I'm trying to say here is...
SPEAKER_1:  just because people speak.
SPEAKER_1:  in this kind of way.
SPEAKER_1:  in the gaming world and streams.
SPEAKER_1:  Doesn't mean that.
SPEAKER_1:  you like a lot of people look up to you.
SPEAKER_1:  It doesn't mean...
SPEAKER_1:  young people especially.
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't mean that you don't have the responsibility to sort of stand alone from the crowd.
SPEAKER_1:  Because you're somebody that values the power of
SPEAKER_1:  effective discourse.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  to be effective discourse, there's some level of civility. So you can be the sort of the beacon of civility in that world.
SPEAKER_1:  versus giving in to the...
SPEAKER_1:  the derogatory words.
SPEAKER_1:  Cause like, you have to...
SPEAKER_1:  You have to lift people out of that world.
SPEAKER_1:  Out of the muck of-
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  What I would say is like drama in ineffective discourse. It's like, I think that's one of your missions, right? It's like.
SPEAKER_1:  to inspire the world through conversation, through debate, through effective discourse.
SPEAKER_1:  So I guess I'm just calling out that I think using our word for me personally.
SPEAKER_1:  as a fan that
SPEAKER_1:  believes in your mission.
SPEAKER_1:  It just makes you look-
SPEAKER_1:  ineffective and bad and uninspiring to
SPEAKER_1:  young people that look up to you. Because those young people are going to use those words that you're using.
SPEAKER_1:  and they'll do it much less effectively.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the problem.
SPEAKER_0:  I guess the challenge is always just like finding the line.
SPEAKER_0:  Like my vocabulary shifted dramatically from, even from like two or three years ago, I think my vocabulary shifted quite a bit as we've kind of gotten rid of some words and some things are kind of coming out.
SPEAKER_0:  The R word is one that has kind of gone out and come back and gone out and come back.
SPEAKER_0:  that one we've definitely gone back and forth on. I know there are different thoughts about it in different communities on the internet.
SPEAKER_1:  This isn't sh- I mean I'm just telling you.
SPEAKER_1:  from me.
SPEAKER_1:  It cuts.
SPEAKER_1:  and I'm not a social justice warrior type.
SPEAKER_1:  it costs pretty hard.
SPEAKER_0:  What you're saying is I'm going to lose a subscriber if I'm...
SPEAKER_0:  No, it's not a subscriber.
SPEAKER_1:  I know you're in. I actually have to empathize harder because I'm like, maybe this is not a very good person. That's what I feel.
SPEAKER_1:  Like if you're so carelessly using that word.
SPEAKER_1:  that maybe you're not actually thinking deeply about.
SPEAKER_1:  the suffering in the world. Like to be a student of human nature, you really have to think about other humans and other experiences that are unlike your own. Yeah, of course. And so that's the sense I get. But at the same time.
SPEAKER_1:  You're also like the grandpa.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, ages.
SPEAKER_1:  who's trying to be cool with the young kids. A lot of the reason young kids look up to you.
SPEAKER_1:  is like you also know the language of the internet.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, but I mean it doesn't- that's not an excuse to use-
SPEAKER_0:  that we think shouldn't be used. I guess the question that I would have, because it's always a struggle, and to some extent it's kind of happened, is let's say that like three years ago,
SPEAKER_0:  I would have said I'm no longer saying the R word. That's just, I'm just gonna get rid of that in my vocabulary. Like is there a chance that today-
SPEAKER_0:  we would be having a conversation about like, why do you call people dumb fucks?
SPEAKER_0:  I think is that really appropriate? Like does this attack at the core of like somebody's like.
SPEAKER_0:  level of intelligence, education, opportunities in life? Like, is that where they- You don't think so?
SPEAKER_1:  I think that's a.
SPEAKER_1:  As the kids say, cope.
SPEAKER_0:  You really think so? I think that's a cope. Because the words have definitely moved in a way where it's like, this was okay, now it's not. This is okay, now it's not. And I think that you're still gets to listen to it more.
SPEAKER_1:  and your ground by using, listen, you could, you could.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's better to use those words if you want to defend the ground.
SPEAKER_1:  Word stand on.
SPEAKER_1:  to use them rarely and deliberately.
SPEAKER_1:  versus how you currently use them.
SPEAKER_1:  which is...
SPEAKER_1:  to express an emotion like you, I'm going to be honest, you use the R word.
SPEAKER_1:  Not when you're at your best.
SPEAKER_1:  True.
SPEAKER_0:  And so that's not that's generally that could be true for a lot of swearing to that. But yeah, I know.
SPEAKER_1:  No, but like, you know that our word is offensive, you know, and there's part of it is like.
SPEAKER_1:  D-duh.
SPEAKER_1:  You
SPEAKER_1:  Tell yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  that you're still kind of fighting political correctness by using it a little bit when you say it.
SPEAKER_0:  No, I don't think so. I think I'm trying to think in terms of like, where is the virtue where like there's a whole bunch of arguments for why some words are okay, some words aren't okay or whatever. And I try to like think more along those lines rather than
SPEAKER_0:  But there's going to be a lot of phrases where, like if the R word has come out,
SPEAKER_0:  conversation is over. I know that like things my brain is shut down the person thanks is but there's like a there's a lot of words also in terms of like
SPEAKER_0:  it like if you ever hear me so like fucking moron in a debate it's like it's done like this conversation is over there's no way that anything productive is happening past that point
SPEAKER_1:  I think fucking moron is not.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's ineffective, it's not civil, but it's not.
SPEAKER_1:  It doesn't bother me in the way.
SPEAKER_1:  is basically when you...
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking away that I know there's a group that's going to be hurt by that.
SPEAKER_1:  not only do I think about the hurt that group experiences, I think of you.
SPEAKER_1:  as the lesser.
SPEAKER_1:  intellectual.
SPEAKER_1:  Like there's a lesser person who's thinking about the world.
SPEAKER_1:  What bothers me the most is
SPEAKER_1:  just what kind of...
SPEAKER_1:  mindset that inspires in young people, especially when you're a public figure and a lot of people look up to you. So I definitely don't think. bringtblatt.com
SPEAKER_1:  So this idea.
SPEAKER_1:  The R word is not the battleground of expanding.
SPEAKER_1:  the Orton window of discourse.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, like I don't think.
SPEAKER_1:  It'll lead to
SPEAKER_1:  DUMB FUCK
SPEAKER_1:  being cancelled.
SPEAKER_1:  of the two years later
SPEAKER_1:  Unless that word is hurting.
SPEAKER_1:  people's experience, which.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't foresee that happening. I think legitimately.
SPEAKER_1:  Our word and
SPEAKER_1:  F slur and
SPEAKER_1:  calling women bitches.
SPEAKER_1:  It context matters here too, like of course, but just the way I've heard you use it.
SPEAKER_1:  It is not, it's from emotion.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's from frustration and it ultimately is rooted in disrespect.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't, I think it's ineffective. And of course, like who gets to say
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  But I'm saying...
SPEAKER_1:  somebody who would like I admire.
SPEAKER_1:  effective conversations.
SPEAKER_1:  and I admire great humor.
SPEAKER_1:  Dark humor.
SPEAKER_1:  Wit.
SPEAKER_1:  To me, oftentimes...
SPEAKER_1:  the use of the R word.
SPEAKER_1:  In the way you've used it in the way I see the community use it.
SPEAKER_1:  is none of those things. It contributes not at all to the humor and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  Now I can see it might contribute to the
SPEAKER_1:  to the camaraderie of that particular group.
SPEAKER_1:  especially when they normalize the use of that word.
SPEAKER_1:  You kind of take some of the edge off.
SPEAKER_1:  But you forget.
SPEAKER_1:  that there's a...
SPEAKER_1:  A large number of other people that
SPEAKER_1:  have the chemistry, don't hear the music of the friendship that you have, the relationship you have.
SPEAKER_1:  Instead they hear
SPEAKER_1:  The normalization of a hateful word.
SPEAKER_1:  and it ultimately has an impact that's hateful. and then people like me show up.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I haven't watched much of your stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  It turns me off from like a couple of times your content came.
SPEAKER_1:  came before me and I listened to it a little bit, turned me off completely. I didn't understand.
SPEAKER_1:  how good your heart is. i didn't understand.
SPEAKER_1:  How?
SPEAKER_1:  your mission of actually
SPEAKER_1:  do you write do you radicalize people help people like your
SPEAKER_1:  uh... and increase the level of
SPEAKER_1:  good faith discourse in the world. I didn't understand any of that cause like what I was hearing is pretty rough.
SPEAKER_1:  the R award type of stuff. And I just feel like the benefit cost analysis is heavy on the cost.
SPEAKER_1:  Gotcha.
SPEAKER_1:  That's why I just have to sort of call this out.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay. I think it, and I straight up think it's wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's my own, that's my idea. Why do you think it's wrong?
SPEAKER_1:  because it's hurting people without any benefit to you whatsoever.
SPEAKER_0:  When you say hurting people, do you mean the person I'm using it at or do you think there's like the... No, no, no, no, no. You're talking about the affected third group. The third group.
SPEAKER_0:  It's good feedback, right? I always consider everything, especially I respect you a lot. You're a really smart guy.
SPEAKER_0:  something that I always kind of like.
SPEAKER_0:  fight over in terms of like language or like who to attack or what to attack or what to do.
SPEAKER_0:  is that um...
SPEAKER_0:  It's very hard to draw, like what boxes.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... are ok insult to wonders what are
SPEAKER_0:  So for instance, if I call somebody like a Nazi with a lot of vitriol.
SPEAKER_0:  I am okay with every single
SPEAKER_0:  Nazi being negatively affected by that.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  No
SPEAKER_0:  Category intrinsically calls upon at some level of moral condemnation for me, right? Whereas like if I'm out there I try not to do like image related jokes, right? I don't want to call you like oh, you're a fat fucking loser because there's a lot of people that are fat that are overweight Where I don't want them to feel bad. I don't want them I'm not trying to call you out or like insult you so there's like a lot of you say cost-benefit I like I like a lot of collateral damage from a word like that where there's no purpose in doing
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So certain words are easy to get rid of. They're off the table, right? Epsler, N word, like these are not words you call people because there's so much collateral it's not worth it.
SPEAKER_0:  We've got.
SPEAKER_0:  some words where it's like if you have some form of like mental thing, it is a bad thing, you're not a bad person, but just using that word could feel like a collateral damage to those people. And then there's other categories of words, so like if I say that like...
SPEAKER_0:  This person is like, they're a stupid fucking Republican.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? There's probably some Republicans that-
SPEAKER_0:  aren't dumb that I don't want to feel called out by that.
SPEAKER_0:  Like are those types of phrases that you think should be completely removed as well? Or I'm kind of curious now.
SPEAKER_1:  This completely removed.
SPEAKER_1:  Just so we're clear.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not referring to censorship.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh no, I'm not even talking about this, I'm just a person like emotionally like Remove this
SPEAKER_1:  wrong word though like I
SPEAKER_1:  care about.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not trying to listen to people on the internet saying that you shouldn't say that word that's not good I mean
SPEAKER_1:  I'm trying to look.
SPEAKER_1:  your mind and heart.
SPEAKER_1:  And the reason we're talking today.
SPEAKER_1:  is you're betraying your gift.
SPEAKER_1:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  You're better than this.
SPEAKER_0:  You think it's indicative of like a more flippant thought process where it's like, the only way you can say that word is if you're ignoring the hurt and suffering of those people. And if you're somebody that says- Even those people-
SPEAKER_1:  You're ignoring.
SPEAKER_1:  the
SPEAKER_1:  state of language.
SPEAKER_1:  Cause I think you're getting to the point. Cause it's not about a single word. It's about like a
SPEAKER_1:  It's music.
SPEAKER_1:  And I just feel like there is a...
SPEAKER_1:  All right, so I know.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a strong note that ruins the melody.
SPEAKER_1:  Gotcha. And I don't think I can say, you know, you shouldn't use the R word or whatever. I'm just speaking to, I'm just listening to music and reviewing the final result.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not necessarily-
SPEAKER_1:  is maybe one use of the word the r word.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... strategically a part of the actual
SPEAKER_1:  Like.
SPEAKER_1:  or when you've built up a camaraderie.
SPEAKER_1:  that's sandwiched in in
SPEAKER_1:  Like.
SPEAKER_1:  some love but then you try to reveal their because you're talking about a lot of is a bunch of drama you have a but you have friends with whom you're worrying and stuff
SPEAKER_1:  And there are.
SPEAKER_1:  all a little bit beautifully insane.
SPEAKER_1:  And you've said that you are becoming more and more insane. It's beautiful to watch. It's just the human condition laid before us.
SPEAKER_1:  Wonderful. And some of that is swearing and so on. So it's a tricky thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  the whole skill of-
SPEAKER_1:  discourse just like it is with dark humor is walking that line. I just feel like
SPEAKER_1:  It's a...
SPEAKER_1:  Overuse of the R word and I don't want to die in that ground because I don't think it's that that represent There's certain things like that.
SPEAKER_1:  It feels like it ruins the music.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's the same like a dumb Republican or dumb Democrat. I don't.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, that ruins it too a little bit.
SPEAKER_1:  Depends on how you use it.
SPEAKER_1:  You can be lazy with that.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, like even overuse of the word, I think, bots is what's used for people who don't think or something. I don't actually know the definition.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm offended on behalf of robots.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, but...
SPEAKER_0:  That might be a compliment soon.
SPEAKER_1:  Exactly. But I guess bot means you don't think.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, you're like an NPC you just copy paste.
SPEAKER_1:  Again, I'm a fan on behalf of NPCs. I count myself as one. There's a sense if you say bots too much.
SPEAKER_1:  that you're just dismissing people.
SPEAKER_1:  Everything I say is right.
SPEAKER_1:  Anyone that disagrees with me is a bot.
SPEAKER_1:  That's lazy too. Sometimes it's funny, sometimes it's effective.
SPEAKER_1:  Basically saying a lot of people in the mainstream media or something that are bots. Okay, that's
SPEAKER_1:  a little bit of that is affected
SPEAKER_1:  Too much, it becomes ineffective.
SPEAKER_1:  And I'm trying to speak to that. Yeah, and I'm just the reason we're highlighting clear examples.
SPEAKER_1:  like the N-word.
SPEAKER_1:  Joe Rogan had to contend with that.
SPEAKER_1:  Hi, other, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's ineffective. It makes you less effective at discourse.
SPEAKER_1:  Like like you've talked about many times language is a tricky one
SPEAKER_0:  It's always hard because you talk about like constructing a melody.
SPEAKER_0:  There's not one melody that sounds good to everyone.
SPEAKER_0:  but there are probably certain notes that like, if you got rid of them.
SPEAKER_0:  everybody's talking like it about as much and you don't really lose anything as a whole other part of an audience that might be more willing to listen and of
SPEAKER_1:  And it's not about losing the magic of that melody. Like you don't want to be vanilla. Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_1:  I just feel like there's stuff that doesn't need to be there. Yeah, for sure. It's fat.
SPEAKER_1:  But then again, you're...
SPEAKER_1:  The other thing that people should understand.
SPEAKER_1:  that might be listening to this, you're streaming many hours a day.
SPEAKER_1:  for many years. I don't know what's up.
SPEAKER_0:  11 or 12 I think, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Started in 2010.
SPEAKER_1:  And so one of the things that people can do is just clip out anything.
SPEAKER_1:  You're going through the full...
SPEAKER_1:  human experience of emotion.
SPEAKER_1:  Anger.
SPEAKER_1:  Fear.
SPEAKER_1:  frustration all of it.
SPEAKER_1:  So of course, it's going to be...
SPEAKER_1:  moments when you're not the best version of yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  Anything else to say about the language?
SPEAKER_0:  complicated. I'm still always trying to figure it out, you know. There are opinions that I have that have changed throughout the years.
SPEAKER_0:  possible that the R word has always been the next one on the chopping block that we're all kind of looking at but people always worried about that treadmill.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's possible in a year or two I'll have a different view on it or all have changed away some of the words I use. It's always like a work in progress. There's always like different communities that feel different ways about different words.
SPEAKER_1:  Yep, but do you acknowledge that there's people out there?
SPEAKER_1:  they're never gonna talk to you.
SPEAKER_1:  They're never gonna.
SPEAKER_1:  think of you as a good man because you use the N word with the hard R.
SPEAKER_0:  In the past? I mean, yeah, those people exist, but...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, there are some people that are beyond.
SPEAKER_0:  My reach.
SPEAKER_0:  which I'm okay with.
SPEAKER_0:  Like there's going to be some people because of things that have been involved or even ideas that I have now.
SPEAKER_0:  that might make them beyond my reach.
SPEAKER_0:  um... some of the said earlier is right here i think the goal is to like identify what are the elements that you can cut out
SPEAKER_0:  that aren't integral to your message.
SPEAKER_0:  but it could be alienating too.
SPEAKER_0:  more people and those are probably the things that you identify but I think that you can get lost in yourself or lost in the internet or lost in a you know
SPEAKER_0:  the outside of yourself if you're trying to appeal to every single person. That's just never going to be the case.
SPEAKER_0:  And for, I actually, I like that I've had the journey that I've had on the internet that you can find me saying and defending a lot of insane stuff 10 years ago, because I think it shows like a level of progress. And I think I do get a lot of respect and buy into certain communities where it's like, I'm not just some random dude telling you that like, oh, you shouldn't say, you know, the F word or the N word. Like I'm a guy that's been there, that's done it, that's defended it. And you can see my whole past, my whole history is laid bare for you to watch every of, you know, thousands of hours of it. But I can show that like there's growth and evolution and change that can happen in a person. So.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and you're honest about that growth.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a tricky thing because people just call it.
SPEAKER_1:  bring up.
SPEAKER_1:  stuff from your past. For sure.
SPEAKER_1:  I hope we figure out as a civilization a mechanism.
SPEAKER_1:  clearly say this was...
SPEAKER_1:  This is me two years ago. This is me five years ago.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm a different person and like
SPEAKER_1:  Because Twitter doesn't care about that. These social mechanisms that bring stuff up doesn't care about that.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like one stupid thing you say.
SPEAKER_1:  It becomes like a scarlet letter.
SPEAKER_1:  And I don't know how to fight that. It's tricky to fight that.
SPEAKER_1:  Have you ever seen Men in Black?
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  When K and J are on the bench and he says, person is smart, but people are stupid, dumb, finicky animals or whatever, there's something that changes for human dynamics when there is a group of people that make it so hard to control. Like I think one-on-one, anybody can sit across on somebody and admit to some horrible stuff. I used to be, I abused my husband when I was 20 and now I'm 35 and I see what's wrong or I did this, I was addicted to whatever and I made these mistakes. So one-on-one, it's always easy.
SPEAKER_0:  but in group environments that in-group, out-group, tribalistic thing of identifying one thing and then coming to destroy a person's life is like, it's such a huge-
SPEAKER_0:  like impulse we have.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably when we were like hunter-gatherers in the forest. Probably good.
SPEAKER_0:  because you really want to.
SPEAKER_0:  push weird people out or anything like that. But now on the internet, when we can hunt for any dissenting opinion and just with ruthless precision destroy somebody's life over it is a pretty scary dynamic.
SPEAKER_1:  I think one of the mechanisms that could fix it...
SPEAKER_1:  is make it super easy.
SPEAKER_1:  for each individual person to analyze all the stupid shit they themselves have said in the past
SPEAKER_1:  Like a full recording.
SPEAKER_1:  because I think people are just honestly.
SPEAKER_1:  paint a very rosy picture to their own brain of
SPEAKER_1:  of who they-
SPEAKER_1:  have been in the past. Yeah, of course. If we can have empathy for the fact that we've said stupid shit.
SPEAKER_1:  or we're drunk.
SPEAKER_1:  the ridiculous things you say, the offensive things you might have said.
SPEAKER_1:  they found some things you might have done. I just feel like-
SPEAKER_1:  that would give us.
SPEAKER_1:  the ammunition.
SPEAKER_1:  to have empathy for others that are like, okay, yeah, this guy five years ago said this, maybe that doesn't represent them.
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't represent who they are anymore than
SPEAKER_1:  Stuff I said five years ago represents.
SPEAKER_1:  who I am today.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like technology can actually enable that.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe, although you're talking about more recording and more stuff which people are already wary of, but um...
SPEAKER_1:  It's a...
SPEAKER_1:  Double-edged sword.
SPEAKER_1:  I think there is going to be more and more recording. We have to figure out how to do that in the way that respects.
SPEAKER_1:  people privacy and gives them ownership of their data and so on. I've looked at the search history I've done on Google, which for most people is available.
SPEAKER_1:  like your Google search history.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's fascinating to watch the evolution of a human being.
SPEAKER_1:  It doesn't seem like the same person.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like a different person, for sure.
SPEAKER_0:  It's weird. It's also hard too with the internet today. I'm going to be a just again.
SPEAKER_0:  but now all of the people are thrown together, you know? where it's like
SPEAKER_0:  Like I don't want a 27 year old judging.
SPEAKER_0:  There you go again. Like a 15 or 16 year old. Like obviously he's in high school. There was that story that came out of the, there was a kid that saved the recording of.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it was like some white girl. I think that she like got her driver's license and she was like, I can drive now, N words with the A or whatever, it was dumb, she shouldn't have said it. But I think she was like 15 or 16 when she TikTok this or whatever. And he held on to that recording until she applied and got accepted to college.
SPEAKER_0:  three years later and then he released it to get her kicked out of college.
SPEAKER_0:  Damn.
SPEAKER_0:  If everything that I had ever said as like a 15, 16 year old was like immortalized on the internet, my life wouldn't have even begun.
SPEAKER_0:  And those are insanely high standards to hold people to.
SPEAKER_0:  Not that like obviously you shouldn't be saying those, you shouldn't be saying certain words or whatever, but you have to be able to make mistakes in adolescence. Like everybody does, we all did. Everybody did it growing up, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Why do you think there is so much misogyny in the streaming community?
SPEAKER_1:  and how can you fight it? cause you've shown
SPEAKER_1:  a lot of interest in fighting it, trying to decrease or eliminate misogyny from your community.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's really difficult.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that eliminating racism is easier than eliminating...
SPEAKER_0:  Misogyny.
SPEAKER_0:  Because I don't on anywhere.
SPEAKER_0:  Because I think fundamentally, I don't think there's that much difference between like white people and black people and brown people and Asian people or whatever. You know, we have different cultures and stuff, but at the end of the day, we're all people.
SPEAKER_0:  But I think they're.
SPEAKER_0:  Are differences between men and women?
SPEAKER_0:  like throughout all of history and time, and then even today in every culture.
SPEAKER_0:  And when real differences do exist, it's harder to account for them in a way that can we have conversations with each other without it becoming very gendered in a negative way, right? Negative way of gendering something, maybe like a misogynistic way of doing it.
SPEAKER_1:  Of course.
SPEAKER_1:  It's unclear to me that.
SPEAKER_1:  It's so difficult to, um...
SPEAKER_1:  to avoid the negative gendering versus the positive because there's a lot of positive to the...
SPEAKER_1:  the tension, the dance between the different genders and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe in this particular moment in history, it's not.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's not trivial to me that racism is easier to eliminate. It's an interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  hypothesis just because there's more biological difference.
SPEAKER_1:  two-man women.
SPEAKER_1:  That means it's harder to eliminate.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if this is true, I hear this a lot, I feel like I read this somewhere, but I need to get a better source for it repeated everywhere, but I've heard that like in the US military, for instance, they've gotten exceedingly.
SPEAKER_0:  well, they do an exceedingly good job at getting different people of different races to integrate. And it's like not a huge problem once you're through basic training, all the training, everything.
SPEAKER_0:  but for different sexes, it still represents a significant problem that the military hasn't figured out. And I actually looked at like, well, what's the military doing? Because if something was solvable, like can we sleep for four hours a night and be healthy? If we could, I bet the military would know. So I kind of look sometimes to them to see their integration, but it might be that there are other issues there that make it- Yeah, it feels like the military is a very particular kind of- For sure. Yeah, it could be.
SPEAKER_1:  the actual task at hand might.
SPEAKER_1:  bias.
SPEAKER_1:  the difficulty of the process.
SPEAKER_0:  Potentially, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  There's been a lot of interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  talk about like...
SPEAKER_0:  women integrating into male groups.
SPEAKER_0:  And how do you do this in a way where everybody is happy with the outcome?
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  There's not like issues.
SPEAKER_0:  I think Jordan Peterson spoke about this a little bit. And then workplace culture speaks about this a bit.
SPEAKER_0:  Would you happen to remember?
SPEAKER_0:  I want to say it was like five or 10 years ago. There was a big tech conference.
SPEAKER_0:  and there were two guys behind a woman and they made a joke about like a USB dongle, or like dongle was a dick.
SPEAKER_0:  And this woman turned around, she tweeted pictures of them, spoke about misogyny, and then that blew up into a huge ordeal that like, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  There was this interesting phenomenon that...
SPEAKER_0:  N A
SPEAKER_0:  less misogynistic and more inclusive workplace environment.
SPEAKER_0:  some women might end up feeling...
SPEAKER_0:  Worse.
SPEAKER_0:  because in a more misogynistic environment, you're thinking like, okay, that's a woman, she doesn't get our humor, I'm gonna treat her in a very indifferent, very dispassionate, cold way and whatever, and then I'm gonna have my boys over here. And then you've got these environments where they're a little bit more warmer, and it's like, oh cool, we're gonna bring this woman into our environment, and we're gonna make all the same types of crass jokes we did before, and it's actually worse now. Another woman feels even more otherized, it's like, oh my God, why do you talk like this?
SPEAKER_0:  I think that internet communities, especially online ones that do like political debate and video games, are very much like big boys clubs.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's not enough to just say, you can't be misogynistic to get rid of misogyny. There's always gonna be an othering effect on women. There's a lot of like behaviors that are unintuitive that you have to account for and you've got to try to like push that back.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's just a very, very, very challenging thing to do.
SPEAKER_0:  I like to deal with concrete examples more. So here's a concrete example. And this is like a recent initiative in my community because I'm trying to like be, because misogyny hasn't been fixed anywhere on the internet and I'm curious about other ways that I can push my community to do this.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think you should almost ever make a comment on a woman's appearance ever, if they're appearing in like some political or professional manner. Even if it's a positive comment, I think it's equally bad to a negative comment. It's just never good to do. And that's kind of an unintuitive thing. Cause it's like, well, a woman appears, wow, she's really cute. It seems like a nice comment. You're being nice, you know, she looks cute, but it's like, it's not at all the point of why she's there. And just by saying that, you're kind of like otherizing her as like a person to like.
SPEAKER_0:  think she looks good rather than listening to anything she has to say.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, there's a lot of stuff that you're saying and.
SPEAKER_1:  that is a part of massaging, it's almost like.
SPEAKER_1:  obvious.
SPEAKER_1:  Like any woman will tell you that.
SPEAKER_0:  A woman will, yeah, but they're not in these spaces and a lot of the guys don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  I think what that requires.
SPEAKER_1:  is just empathy.
SPEAKER_1:  You don't need, you don't need, you need to consider the female experience.
SPEAKER_1:  That's it. Like you have to either read about or talk with women. You learn, like the low hanging fruit is very easy to learn.
SPEAKER_1:  It feels like just a level of social skill.
SPEAKER_1:  often times in internet communities is quite low.
SPEAKER_0:  I disagree, I don't like to say.
SPEAKER_0:  And here's the problem with empathy is it's very hard to have empathy for experiences that are so outside of your own.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, maybe some people. There might be some people that can do it. I can't.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a lot of stuff that I had to learn.
SPEAKER_1:  women are half the population.
SPEAKER_0:  but they're women.
SPEAKER_0:  They're different.
SPEAKER_1:  t
SPEAKER_1:  different. awesome fighter.
SPEAKER_0:  We'll talk about it. We'll write it down. They're not totally different. They're totally different. So here's an example, okay? So here's an example.
SPEAKER_0:  Especially for me, my archetype makes up a lot of the internet.
SPEAKER_0:  Wait.
SPEAKER_0:  man.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  There's never been a point. The name of a beautiful woman.
SPEAKER_1:  who might be a dancer. What's the backstory? From New Orleans or from...
SPEAKER_0:  I haven't thought that through yet. It's ambiguous, okay. Like an open world. An open world, I want you to project wherever you want Destiny the Dancer to be from. That's in your mind, okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Alright, I'll save that for later tonight. Yeah, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  as a white guy.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if there's ever been a spot that I've been in where I've been made to feel like I don't belong there just by virtue of who I am.
SPEAKER_0:  I actually don't, it's impossible for me to empathize that because I don't even have that experience.
SPEAKER_0:  If you go back eight, nine years.
SPEAKER_0:  One of the big issues that came up was harassment in gaming against women.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was one of the big debaters against that saying that like
SPEAKER_0:  Sure, women might get harassment, but everybody gets harassment. If you're a woman and you're in gaming and you get harassed, congratulations, you're being treated like a man. What you're actually asking for is for us to actually treat you differently. You don't wanna be insulted. You don't wanna be treated like a man. And that's actually misogyny, is women making that argument.
SPEAKER_1:  stand by that.
SPEAKER_0:  Is that a problem if I do?
SPEAKER_0:  No, I'm just kidding.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, hold on. It's a little while after. I disagree with it. Sure, okay. That's good, you should.
SPEAKER_0:  A little while later, I had a friend, Jessica, super cool girl.
SPEAKER_0:  We go to play games, she was between jobs, and she's like, I've got like two months, and we're going to grind CSGO.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm like, okay, this is awesome. Let's do it. CSGO Counter-Strike, Global Offensive, shooter game, FPS, microphones.
SPEAKER_0:  First day we start playing, okay? Hop into our first game.
SPEAKER_0:  Obviously she talks everybody's making that is that a 12 year old boy? Why aren't you making sandwiches blah blah blah? Yeah, okay, whatever play our first game play our second game same jokes third game fourth game by like the fourth or fifth game
SPEAKER_0:  I was actually starting to feel triggered. Like every time the game started, I was like, can you just like talk so we can get over like the stupid fucking jokes? It's so fucking stupid. And you hear the same fucking joke every single time.
SPEAKER_0:  and it took.
SPEAKER_0:  one day of that experience for me to realize.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not about being insulted. It's like this othering feeling that you don't belong. And I've never felt that because I'm a white guy. Like it's not to be like virtue singular. So, but like there's just, there's no places where it's like, you're white, you don't belong here. You're a guy, you don't belong here. Like I've never felt that, not inclusion. And playing with her.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a different feeling.
SPEAKER_0:  when it's the same types of jokes coming from a group of people to make you feel like you don't belong there.
SPEAKER_0:  Where I was like.
SPEAKER_0:  Damn, this actually feels really bad.
SPEAKER_0:  And it feels bad in a different way where it's like, if you call me like an F slur or any other type of swear word or insult, like, yeah, you can call me that. But at the end of the day, like, we're all kind of the same. We're all white dudes and we call each other names, but like, this is a woman and this is not her place and she doesn't belong here.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of the analogy that I would make, because after getting these experiences, I would learn this afterwards.
SPEAKER_0:  If I tell you that there's another guy in a room.
SPEAKER_0:  And you need to think of the worst insults ever for that person without ever knowing anything about them or meeting them.
SPEAKER_0:  If I tell you that it's like a white straight guy and you have to write insults, you're fucked.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe you can do like, School Shooter?
SPEAKER_0:  There's not really much you can say at the end of the day.
SPEAKER_0:  But if I tell you it's a woman, whoo, we could, there are so many different jokes you can write. If it's a black person, so many different racist things we can say. For sure.
SPEAKER_1:  I can come up with a lot of stuff for a white guy.
SPEAKER_0:  In terms of stuff that is just intrinsic to him being a white guy
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, like there's...
SPEAKER_1:  Really? What are you talking about?
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot, the internet has sharpened that sword.
SPEAKER_0:  In terms of like jokes that are targeted at his sex or-
SPEAKER_1:  cells.
SPEAKER_1:  virgin.
SPEAKER_0:  Weak. Some of the incel version, maybe, yeah, that's getting there, sure. That's for sure. That's recent though, sorry, I'm older on the internet. We didn't have those words way back then. That wasn't the best thing. When I was making these analogies, that incel and virgin wasn't- Back in my day, we didn't have general relativity. There were no incels back then. None of us had sex, we just accepted it. We were all computer gamers. Nobody had sex and played video games back then, okay? People don't remember that. There wasn't the Big Bang Theory. You were just a loser that was stuck in a room. You guys didn't even know sex existed. Exactly. So you can use it as an incel. We had to download sexual pictures, and it was like two minutes and you didn't even know if you were gonna get the right thing by the time it finished loading. But what I'm saying is like, okay, I think you agree that if somebody gives you a race, like a black person who's a woman, we can write very cutting, scathing insults for that person that are very authorizing. Or words that would really hurt if they're spoken to. Yeah, that are very cutting to the person. But for a white guy, it's kind of hard because that's the default. There's not as much authorizing of those people. Yeah, that's kind of the point. For a white guy, just like black people, is it kind of a normal stuff? Yeah, I don't think it is. And I think it's something that often reminds me of myself too. When I was four, I think it was the aim of kind of the whole series. So I already have friends that I, and I think I respect my friends because I have my friends around. So, many people then roots to that compared to my brother, and I think he looks at it like that. But also, yeah, so that's another challenge, the large political complexity of people and also in real terms what is your background.
SPEAKER_1:  insults you have.
SPEAKER_1:  from Y guy to Y guy, the insults are much harsher.
SPEAKER_1:  So when you start to apply the same kind of harshness to other groups.
SPEAKER_0:  you can make them feel like they really don't belong. And that other rising effect is something that's very hard for me. I can't really empathize with it, because I've never felt it. So I have to intellectualize it and then sympathize with it. It's like a whole process I have to go through. And then I try to walk other people through that.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're a white guy on the internet, which is a lot of the internet, you really don't know what that feels like. You've never felt like that before.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, so you're now in a leadership position.
SPEAKER_1:  Grandpa Destiny. So that's a lot of people look up to you for that
SPEAKER_1:  for that sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  Pathway to empathy. Apartments center.
SPEAKER_1:  how not to otherize. I mean, you have felt otherizing. You mentioned high school people like not being.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, but those are always for things that like, it's different to insult somebody for a non-immutable characteristic. Like, okay, you think poorly about me because I'm like not enough money, or I don't have money, but I could get more money, and I could change that. But it's different for somebody to really attack you for like your gender or attack you for like your race.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of the attacks that hit the hardest is not about gender.
SPEAKER_1:  It's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's, I do think that they're like.
SPEAKER_1:  the way women are attacked on the internet.
SPEAKER_1:  It's the same kind of attacks you would
SPEAKER_1:  towards other guys, but you go harsher.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like they're fundamentally different.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like when we're attacking guys.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not usually attacking you.
SPEAKER_0:  on like.
SPEAKER_0:  the virtue of you.
SPEAKER_0:  being a guy.
SPEAKER_0:  But like if it's a woman and she's typing something like, oh, did your boyfriend type that for you? Or like, what are you even doing here? Like, don't you, shouldn't you be trying to find a husband or like, oh, you're like a stupid kind of, like go start an OnlyFans?
SPEAKER_1:  But the stupidity, the intelligence aspect is what's the tech.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, but it's so much different. Like you can call a guy stupid, but that's because he's a guy that's being stupid. But when you call a woman stupid, she's stupid because she's a woman.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, but I honestly think that women are called stupid more than men.
SPEAKER_1:  internet.
SPEAKER_1:  There's nothing to do like the attack.
SPEAKER_1:  is not gendered.
SPEAKER_1:  It's.
SPEAKER_1:  the gender inspires an increased level of attack.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like it is gendered.
SPEAKER_0:  I wish we had data.
SPEAKER_0:  Have you ever heard of the XKCD comics?
SPEAKER_0:  It's a really good comic where, and this is something that I've dealt with a lot in my community, okay?
SPEAKER_0:  There's a guy at a board.
SPEAKER_0:  fucks up a math equation.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like, wow, you suck at math.
SPEAKER_0:  And then the next panelist is a girl that does it.
SPEAKER_0:  And she fucks it up and it's like, wow, women suck at math.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's like that feeling that happens where when I bring on.
SPEAKER_0:  I want us names, but they're like YouTube people that I've brought on that have crazy opinions. And when they're men,
SPEAKER_0:  That person is crazy. Oh my God, he said the crazy stuff. He's so dumb, he's so crazy, so stupid. But when it's a woman,
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, oh my God, why do you always bring dumb women here? Why do so many women on the internet have crazy opinions? There's a different like minority character that has to like stand it.
SPEAKER_0:  and like represent like their whole group.
SPEAKER_0:  where like white men don't typically have to.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of groups versus individuals, yes. But then what I feel happens.
SPEAKER_1:  is then another.
SPEAKER_1:  person from that group comes another woman comes and people before she says anything.
SPEAKER_1:  will already feel like.
SPEAKER_1:  They're ready without a time.
SPEAKER_0:  For sure.
SPEAKER_0:  but they're ready for the attack because she's a woman.
SPEAKER_0:  They're gonna call her, she's stupid because she's a woman, not because she says something, but just because she's a woman.
SPEAKER_1:  So like, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  The group.
SPEAKER_1:  in their brain accumulates all the negative characteristics of the individuals they've met. Not the positive, the negative. And it becomes like this ball of stickiness. And then that becomes the bias for their...
SPEAKER_1:  judgment of a new person that comes with white men.
SPEAKER_1:  There's more of a blank slate in terms of bias of how they analyze the person.
SPEAKER_1:  with any of the minority group there basically make a judgment.
SPEAKER_1:  based on the negative characteristics of the individuals that met in the past. I just, that leads to a system.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, you're just harsher.
SPEAKER_1:  or minority groups.
SPEAKER_1:  and towards women.
SPEAKER_0:  How do you solve that?
SPEAKER_0:  The most important thing for any problem ever is step one is to be aware of it. If you're not aware of it.
SPEAKER_0:  then you're
SPEAKER_0:  hopelessly lost at sea.
SPEAKER_0:  But yeah, the first thing I like to say is just like, be aware of it. Like I've had, there's a girl that I've had on recently and she says a lot of, in my opinion, kind of crazy things, but people will use her as like, this is why women shouldn't be here. This is like, she's crazy and she's a woman and blah, blah, blah. But I can bring in a guy who says similarly dumb things and he's evaluated on his own merits, cause it's a guy, you know? There's never ever, ever been a case where I brought a stupid guy on stream and everybody's like, this guy makes me hate men. This guy makes me hate white people. That has never happened. But then there's like other women that come on and it's like, now I know why incels exist. Or I totally understand where Red Pill ideology comes from, you know? The kinds of statements are kind of true.
SPEAKER_0:  When you're making these observations over and over and over and over again, it-
SPEAKER_0:  It damages your ability to individually perceive somebody. And then two people that make the same statements, one can be perceived more harshly just because of that like group bias you've got built up.
SPEAKER_1:  I think there's something about streaming that just brings that out of people. Like, because you have to talk for like seven hours.
SPEAKER_1:  So you're like, all right, well, whatever psychological issues and complexities I have, I'm going to explore them for some magnified magnified work. And then it's the Gerard easy talked about the mimetic
SPEAKER_1:  uh... theories of gerardian
SPEAKER_1:  Like whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  the things that are very similar and you're going to magnify the conflicts that you have and you're going to explore the
SPEAKER_1:  all the different perspectives on those different conflicts.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I don't know if it's just anecdotal, but.
SPEAKER_1:  It's nice to have women on stream. I think the dynamic.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you guys have as wonderful as this really interesting. So it's just a female voice in general. I love having women on the podcast.
SPEAKER_1:  the female voice I feel like is under heard on the internet. Thanks for all the support on Patreon!
SPEAKER_1:  And I would love the internet to be a place where women feel safe to speak.
SPEAKER_1:  Alright.
SPEAKER_1:  Given that you're...
SPEAKER_1:  Like we talked about a progressive with.
SPEAKER_1:  non-standard progressive use.
SPEAKER_1:  See, you're very pro-free speech.
SPEAKER_1:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_1:  Procapitalism.
SPEAKER_1:  So given that, it's very interesting that you're also...
SPEAKER_1:  pro-establishment and pro-institutions.
SPEAKER_1:  Mhm.
SPEAKER_1:  So right now if you look at the world, there's a significant distrust of institutions.
SPEAKER_1:  at least in sort of public intellectual discourse.
SPEAKER_1:  What is the nature of your support for government and institutions? Can you make the case for and against them?
SPEAKER_0:  Broadly speaking.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a...
SPEAKER_0:  synergistic effect.
SPEAKER_0:  when two humans come together.
SPEAKER_0:  If I can speak.
SPEAKER_0:  very
SPEAKER_0:  broadly in terms of, we'll say, utility, okay? my happiness with one person might be ten.
SPEAKER_0:  The happiness of the other person might be 10.
SPEAKER_0:  When they come together, it's like 50 between the two of them. There's like this synergistic effect when humans work together that the sum is
SPEAKER_0:  greater than all the individual parts or whatever. There's like an emergent thing that happens there. There's a-
SPEAKER_1:  Passes a possibility
SPEAKER_0:  of that. Yeah, a possibility. Sure. Things could go really wrong. There could be a cannibalistic tribe that all hates each other. Sure.
SPEAKER_0:  For the purpose of this, there's a-
SPEAKER_1:  their failure.
SPEAKER_0:  modes but yes. Okay sure yeah. Well I think broadly speaking...
SPEAKER_0:  Are you gonna be the well actually guy? Okay, if you wanna well, okay. Well, actually, sometimes cannibalism is actually good for both. True, yeah, sometimes things do go wrong. But I think broadly speaking, the fact that you're sitting here in clothing that you didn't make, and I'm sitting here on an airplane that I don't know how to fly, or Bill, like right, there's a lot of cool stuff that happens when people come together and they make civilizations.
SPEAKER_0:  and part of that civilization building.
SPEAKER_0:  is the fact that we can specialize and it's the fact that we can offload a bunch of trust onto third parties that we delegate the power to make important decisions about our lives, right? I don't know anything about how to like build like a combustion engine, but I know that when I push the button on my car, it's gonna drive around and the fumes aren't gonna kill me and I can park it in garages and the building is not gonna collapse. And the only reason all of this works is because I've offloaded a lot of trust onto these third party things. And I would say that the pillars of these third party things that society has built on are roughly speaking institutions.
SPEAKER_0:  So that might be the institution of.
SPEAKER_0:  peer review for scientific articles. It might be the institution of voting for government, right? Or the ability for us to vote in that whole process. It might be, yeah, the FDA, like all of these institutions are things that they need to exist because we don't have the time or the capability to individually sort through all of these things individually. We have to rely on some third party to do it.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  So you believe.
SPEAKER_1:  At scale, the-
SPEAKER_1:  We're together.
SPEAKER_1:  We're greater than the sum of our parts. That's the case for institutions.
SPEAKER_0:  Absolutely.
SPEAKER_1:  What about the inefficiencies of bureaucracy?
SPEAKER_1:  Is there some aspect when, at scale,
SPEAKER_1:  different dynamics come into play than they do when there's two people together.
SPEAKER_1:  Two people that love each other, the birds and the bees.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there some aspect that leads more to cannibalism at scale?
SPEAKER_1:  So like corruption, inefficiencies that do to bureaucracy and so on.
SPEAKER_0:  Bureaucracy.
SPEAKER_0:  which is not.
SPEAKER_0:  I hate it when people try to say bureaucracy is government because bureaucracy exists a ton in private environments as well, right? In businesses and everything. Bureaucracy introduces its own set of problems, but I mean, a bureaucracy is necessary because it's coordinating all of the underlying things in order to create something that's greater than the sum of its parts, right? Like all of the software developers in the world are useless without being paired with good designers in order to make their products usable by a person. And the coordination of those people and the coordination of increasingly more and more things necessitates some level of bureaucracy. I think we always say bureaucracy when it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  a bad, it's like a slur on us. Like you're a bureaucrat, you're bureaucratic. The bureaucracy is slowing everything down. It's like, sure, the bureaucracy slows things down, but bureaucracy also gives us things like, you know, safe medicine and safe water to drink for most of the US or safe buildings to live in or safe cars to drive.
SPEAKER_1:  So the managers in institution versus like the software developers and designers the managers is the bureaucracy.
SPEAKER_1:  the reason bureaucracy is used as a slur.
SPEAKER_1:  is that.
SPEAKER_1:  something about human nature.
SPEAKER_1:  leads to bureaucracy often growing.
SPEAKER_1:  growing indefinitely.
SPEAKER_1:  sometimes coming less and less efficient without a foot me this is what capitalism can come in
SPEAKER_1:  that capitalism puts a
SPEAKER_1:  pressure on the bureaucracy not to grow too much because
SPEAKER_1:  You want the bureaucracy to be useful.
SPEAKER_1:  but
SPEAKER_1:  NOT
SPEAKER_1:  large.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  And to be a certain size, of course.
SPEAKER_1:  the minimum size.
SPEAKER_1:  to get the job done. And so capitalism provides that mechanism.
SPEAKER_1:  Government.
SPEAKER_1:  does not always.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that's the criticism of government, of institutions, where it can grow without a significant mechanism that says.
SPEAKER_1:  there's a cost to bureaucracy that's not being accounted for here.
SPEAKER_1:  We're just paying.
SPEAKER_1:  for the increasing.
SPEAKER_1:  size of government without the benefit.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, government is a special institution because it doesn't have to show itself to be financially viable. And we kind of live in a capitalist economy where that's generally the case. So government gets its powers from votes from the people, which introduces a whole new set of
SPEAKER_0:  possible positives and possible negatives, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Having something, for instance, that gives food or shelter to homeless people, maybe you don't want that to have to run at a profit. But giving an organization that can self-justify its budgets perpetually and indefinitely growing, maybe that's not the best thing. Yeah, we always have to figure out how to do the constraints there.
SPEAKER_1:  What about the corrupting nature of power?
SPEAKER_1:  That comes with institutions as well.
SPEAKER_0:  Absolutely. So then you better pick your style of institution very carefully.
SPEAKER_0:  The democratic institution we have in the United States today, I think works very well.
SPEAKER_0:  But I mean, there are other styles of government that have been tried in the past that I think lend themselves more to corruption. Not to say that, by the way, there's not corruption in the United States. Of course, there's gonna be varying levels of corruption not like all.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  at all levels, but you run into this interesting problem where...
SPEAKER_0:  Authoritarian regimes can act with ruthless precision and swiftness.
SPEAKER_0:  because they don't have to ask any questions. They just do, do, do, do, do, and that's it.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  The problem is, it's an authoritarian regime. They're prone to missteps. They're slow to respond to changing or evolving needs. There was an interesting study that was put out a while ago that showed that every single famine that happened around the world, almost 98% of them, happened under authoritarian regimes where freedom of speech is very limited. It's very rare for a famine to happen under democracy because press and everything makes the government more responsive to the needs of the people.
SPEAKER_0:  Power can corrupt, there are levels of corruption, but you have to have like a system of checks and balances on all of those different levels to make sure it doesn't run off the rails, I guess.
SPEAKER_0:  and do a sick loop-de-looping, you know, half the population gets.
SPEAKER_1:  Nice callback. There's a lot of people that will listen to you say that.
SPEAKER_1:  The democracy in the United States is working pretty damn well and they will spit out the drink if they're drinking a drink.
SPEAKER_1:  and be very upset. Can you make the case that they're right and you're wrong?
SPEAKER_0:  When I make the case that- He's the steel man. They're right, yeah. Well, the steel man for them is that people have a lot of problems on the day to day. And when they look and they see what government is doing they might see potholes.
SPEAKER_0:  outside their house.
SPEAKER_0:  homeless people all over their downtown. And the United States just approved another X billion amount of dollars for Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  or they might be living in a city where half the factories are shut down, a lot of their people out of work.
SPEAKER_0:  but the president is on the TV talking about how to find jobs for immigrants coming in from Mexico. And for these people, they have problems that exist in their lives. Some of them are paying taxes to alleviate these problems. And then when they listen to the government talk, they're like, oh, you're a
SPEAKER_0:  It feels like the government is not responding to the needs that they have.
SPEAKER_0:  And then that's one problem. Then on top of that, you've got all of these people working in alternative media that can show you, well, look at this politician wasting this much money, or look at him double speaking here or there. Look at Hillary Clinton saying she's got a private position and a public position. Look at how all of these politicians have family members that are getting rich because of their relationships with people in Congress. Look at the revolving door between capitalist companies and the government. How can you look at all of that?
SPEAKER_0:  take into account that the government's not responding to your needs and then really feel like it's a government by the people and for the people.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, this was very good.
SPEAKER_1:  Good steel man and good question.
SPEAKER_1:  How can you, how can you?
SPEAKER_1:  How can you tell that they're not just politicians that care more about
SPEAKER_1:  continuously winning the elections versus
SPEAKER_1:  being running government.
SPEAKER_0:  Effectively. They should care about winning the elections. That's the first misconception. A lot of people say this guy only cares about getting voted in. This guy, like he doesn't even believe about in fracking or abortion. He just changed his opinion to get voted in.
SPEAKER_0:  Anytime somebody says that, you just say, that's really good. You want them to change their opinions so they get voted in. That's the whole point of a democracy. You don't want them to be made obstinate. You don't want them to say, I'm not changing my opinion no matter what the people want. You want them to evolve and adopt new opinions based on what the population, their constituents are voting for. Yeah, but the cynical...
SPEAKER_1:  take is that they're.
SPEAKER_1:  the surface they're changing their opinion, but that there's a boys club or boys means the elite.
SPEAKER_1:  UNDER
SPEAKER_1:  in the smoke-filled rooms.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... in secret there actually have their own agenda and they're following that agenda and they're just saying
SPEAKER_1:  anything publicly to placate the public.
SPEAKER_1:  based on whatever the...
SPEAKER_1:  the new trends are.
SPEAKER_0:  So
SPEAKER_0:  Here is... Yeah, I understand.
SPEAKER_0:  Somebody asked me this question and it-
SPEAKER_0:  I 180'd completely. Um, I was a Bernie Sanders supporter in 2016 and my, my single issue voting.
SPEAKER_0:  thing was lobbying.
SPEAKER_0:  I thought that lobbying, the government was corrupt, they weren't responding to these people. It was completely destroyed my faith and the government everything.
SPEAKER_0:  And I had one question posed to me by a conservative that used to come on my stream and shout at me and he said
SPEAKER_0:  And then he asked me, can you think of any?
SPEAKER_0:  Any-
SPEAKER_0:  popular opinion that the American public has.
SPEAKER_0:  the government is unresponsive to. Is there some big piece of legislation or policy or whatever that people want that the government isn't doing?
SPEAKER_0:  When they asked me that, I couldn't think of a single good answer.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm like, oh jeez.
SPEAKER_1:  There's drugs.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not. And that's,
SPEAKER_1:  Legalization of drug. Hold on a sec. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Go for it. Oh shoot, you're doing the Joe Rogan thing. You're pushing back because I brought up weed. Go ahead.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm sorry. I have become-
SPEAKER_1:  meme.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't even...
SPEAKER_1:  I don't want to interrupt your, your, cause there's means upon means upon means I can go with here. But no, cause people bring up, okay, there's no issues. There's no issues that the government is not representing of the public.
SPEAKER_0:  So here's the issue. So somebody will bring up like, well, what about the legalization of drugs? Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  The first issue people have is one, they look at national polling.
SPEAKER_0:  Very few things are decided on a national level. So that's the first huge mistake. Arguably a lot of BLM made mistakes in this arena where they're saying like, why isn't the government doing anything about policing?
SPEAKER_0:  Federal government can't do anything about policing. That's gonna be your, sometimes that's gonna be your state government, sometimes your local city government.
SPEAKER_0:  the people that like elect like your chief of police, your police commissioner, that's coming from your mayor. So you've got people looking one, at the wrong parts of the government to even figure out the solutions to the problem. Two.
SPEAKER_0:  oftentimes for pulling.
SPEAKER_0:  Questions are vague enough that you can pull very high, but when you get into the weeds on things, no pun intended, you start to realize like, oh shoot, this is more complicated than I thought.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know the numbers in particular for legalization of marijuana, but this is what I'm going to guess is the case. If you poll and you say, should we legalize marijuana, that number might poll at like 65-70%.
SPEAKER_0:  but that's including people that are in favor of medical marijuana. If you were to pull like, should we legalize?
SPEAKER_0:  should we decriminalize recreational use of marijuana?
SPEAKER_0:  that number might drop to like 52%. And then if you pull like, should we completely legalize, not just keep criminalized, but completely legalize recreationalism or whatever, that number might drop to like 40%.
SPEAKER_0:  There's like all these different ways you can pull around issues where people are like, oh no, we broadly agree on this topic. But when you really figure out, well, do you, do we really agree or is it just like broad consensus around a thing that's never gonna show up like in a piece of legislation?
SPEAKER_0:  A really good example, one example I do know is...
SPEAKER_0:  Socialized healthcare. I think if you pulled there was a time
SPEAKER_0:  a few years ago where if you poll America, do you think every American citizen should have access to free healthcare?
SPEAKER_0:  answer that poll at like 74% yes.
SPEAKER_0:  But when you asked...
SPEAKER_0:  should the government be the sole provider of healthcare, it dropped to like 26%.
SPEAKER_0:  dropped 50 points.
SPEAKER_0:  And you could see it was both asking questions about single payer, but the way that it was asked was so different that even if you all, it looks like there's consensus, there's not nearly as much consensus as people think around certain ideas.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, we are gonna...
SPEAKER_1:  You're right, you're right, you're right, you're right.
SPEAKER_1:  that polls, the way you ask the polls really matters. When you ask, should the government be in charge of a thing, that also biases the answer.
SPEAKER_1:  Right? Like because there's such a negative.
SPEAKER_1:  experience with government creating a dot gov site that runs the thing.
SPEAKER_1:  But sometimes.
SPEAKER_1:  Sometimes I think if you dig in, if you have a.
SPEAKER_1:  One hour conversation with each individual citizen.
SPEAKER_1:  I think you will understand that yes, there is support for socialized medicine.
SPEAKER_1:  Like it's not.
SPEAKER_0:  The argument has to be made though.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you mean? Like if you just ask a conservative like what about single payer? They're gonna tell you no. You might be able to build up to an argument for it, but you're gonna have to make the case for it. No, but I thought we're
SPEAKER_1:  talking about.
SPEAKER_1:  the feeling deep inside your mind and heart.
SPEAKER_1:  Does the government represent that?
SPEAKER_1:  Oh.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's not like some shallow.
SPEAKER_1:  surface layer.
SPEAKER_1:  public opinion.
SPEAKER_1:  does the government effectively represent what the people want?
SPEAKER_1:  not a shallow survey but a deeply what they want.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not actually that familiar with the debates over healthcare, but let's maybe look at an easier one. Maybe you'll say it's harder.
SPEAKER_1:  War.
SPEAKER_0:  war is a really good example where the government was very responsive i think to the
SPEAKER_0:  people.
SPEAKER_1:  You think so.
SPEAKER_1:  Iraq, Afghanistan.
SPEAKER_1:  The government didn't manipulate.
SPEAKER_1:  public opinion.
SPEAKER_0:  There's an argument to be made that they did in terms of like WMD and everything, but after 9-11, were you in the United States after 9-11?
SPEAKER_0:  After 9-11, I legit-
SPEAKER_1:  accusatory.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, where were you on 9-11?
SPEAKER_1:  Oh
SPEAKER_0:  Checking, okay. All right.
SPEAKER_1:  I have evidence and witnesses. No, okay. I'm very defensive right now. It's very strange.
SPEAKER_0:  Look into it.
SPEAKER_0:  Alex Jones. I think after 9-11, we could have gone to country, we could have gone to war with any country in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  we were ready because all of America was like, oh my God, and they pointed to Iraq and the reasons for the WMDs was kind of dumb, but I don't think we even needed WMDs to go to Iraq. We could have just said, you know, Saddam Hussein was giving medical aid to Taliban, Al-Qaeda, Iraq, let's go, and we would have gone for it.
SPEAKER_0:  But um...
SPEAKER_0:  post-Iraq, Iraq was for a while popular and then became obviously deeply unpopular, Iraq and Afghanistan. And I think you could see that influence other foreign policy that the United States had. For instance, we opted more towards drone warfare than troops on the ground for places like Yemen. We opted more towards sending money and help instead of boots on the ground for places like Syria. And I think that a lot of that was in response to how unpopular...
SPEAKER_0:  the Iraq stuff had became. And when you looked at a lot of elections afterwards, even for Obama, like one of the defining characteristics of a lot of campaigns were like, I'm gonna close Guantanamo Bay, I'm gonna get us out of foreign wars, even up to Trump, I'm going into, I'm not gonna stop doing all this weird stuff in the Middle East.
SPEAKER_1:  but they didn't still withdraw.
SPEAKER_0:  from a gas then they didn't withdraw but they definitely like tapered off and weren't like as aggressively pushing those types of conflicts because they knew it was unpopular
SPEAKER_1:  but I think.
SPEAKER_1:  If you also consider perfect information or good information, if you ask a lot of people
SPEAKER_1:  Are you okay spending this amount of money?
SPEAKER_1:  for this purpose, so military conflict in Iraq and Afghanistan.
SPEAKER_1:  I think almost from the very beginning.
SPEAKER_1:  It was a no.
SPEAKER_1:  After 9-11, I feel like maybe like a few days after 9-11.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, what was the name?
SPEAKER_1:  There's some memes and so on, yes, but...
SPEAKER_1:  The nature of the public support for the war.
SPEAKER_1:  Was there public support in 2003, which is when the invasion happened?
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like initially there was a lot I remember seeing it on, but then I also lived in a Republican household and I was not very like media savvy at that time. And I don't know if the name
SPEAKER_1:  sure that public support had to do with WMDs or with 911.
SPEAKER_0:  because the weird. Came about WMD.
SPEAKER_1:  But I wonder what is the name if you were to poll people and let's say hypothetically there was above 50% support
SPEAKER_1:  for the war, what would be the nature of that support?
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  to what degrees the government actually representing.
SPEAKER_1:  the will of the people versus
SPEAKER_1:  some.
SPEAKER_1:  complex mechanism like the military industrial complex.
SPEAKER_1:  is manipulating the narrative that's controlling public opinion.
SPEAKER_1:  And then there's the media that
SPEAKER_1:  uh, gets.
SPEAKER_1:  a lot of attention by being divided.
SPEAKER_1:  and how they're shaping the narrative.
SPEAKER_1:  through the mechanism of division.
SPEAKER_1:  So what.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a lot of complicated things out there. It's not just like the people and then the government and that's, yeah, for sure I agree that there are gonna be different elements at play. and I will be very proud.
SPEAKER_1:  much.
SPEAKER_1:  of those.
SPEAKER_1:  elements that lead us astray can be attributed to the largeness of the different systems.
SPEAKER_1:  and the different institutions.
SPEAKER_1:  like
SPEAKER_1:  the media institutions and government.
SPEAKER_1:  the institutions that have a monopoly on violence.
SPEAKER_1:  put it this way. Put it this way.
SPEAKER_1:  One way to define government.
SPEAKER_0:  It's complicated.
SPEAKER_0:  There's definitely going to be different institutions at play. But I think that like-
SPEAKER_0:  All I would say is, in reference to my original point, when there becomes broad consensus around a thing, I think the government will usually follow. It's not gonna fight. It's gonna follow more often than not.
SPEAKER_0:  But I think that a lot of times I think Americans think that there's more consensus around certain issues
SPEAKER_0:  there actually are. So like a really good example we're on that war point too.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  What caused like the lowest dip?
SPEAKER_0:  in Biden's approval rating.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm pretty sure it was right after we pulled out of Afghanistan.
SPEAKER_0:  which
SPEAKER_0:  I think if I would have asked people like a year before, like let's assume that we could pull out of Afghanistan.
SPEAKER_0:  The government's probably gonna collapse after we leave because they just don't have the will to fight, they don't have the support, they don't whatever, it's just not gonna work. But like no Americans are gonna die.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe a couple other people will go, but like, no, America's gonna die, we're gonna get out of here this time. Would you support that? I think broadly speaking.
SPEAKER_0:  I think more than 60 or 70% of Americans are like, yeah, that would be fine.
SPEAKER_0:  But then when it actually plays on TV, when we see the people hanging onto the planes, when we see like helicopter embassies, some of the courts and politicians, well now it's like, oh my God, this was horrible and I was so botched.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was so like, it could have gone so much better. It's like, well, could it have gone better? Like maybe, maybe not, but I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  It seems like you can have consensus around a certain opinion.
SPEAKER_0:  The way that things play out and the way that people actually feel, it's actually way, way, more complicated and there's not usually this broad consensus opinion.
SPEAKER_0:  Alright, yeah, go ahead. Sauce
SPEAKER_1:  to believe that I mean
SPEAKER_1:  just to lay my cards out.
SPEAKER_1:  on the table.
SPEAKER_1:  I have a-
SPEAKER_1:  faith.
SPEAKER_1:  in the power of effective government.
SPEAKER_1:  I just.
SPEAKER_1:  have, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  a lot of concern about what happens.
SPEAKER_1:  as institutions grow in size. For sure.
SPEAKER_1:  and I just have a lot of worry about the natural.
SPEAKER_1:  corrupting influence on the individuals and
SPEAKER_1:  on the system as a whole. Like the boys club nature of it. I don't know, there must be a better term.
SPEAKER_1:  But basically they...
SPEAKER_1:  They agree to the game and they play the game and there's a
SPEAKER_1:  generational aspect momentum to the game.
SPEAKER_1:  and they more and more stop being responsive to.
SPEAKER_1:  the people that they represent. I just feel like there is that mechanism.
SPEAKER_1:  and...
SPEAKER_1:  I think the nice thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Democracy, elections are resistance to that natural human mechanism.
SPEAKER_1:  Also, the balances of power is a resistance to that mechanism.
SPEAKER_1:  In some ways, the media that reveals the bullshit of politicians is also a resistance to that labor
SPEAKER_1:  It's hard to be full of shit as a politician.
SPEAKER_1:  because people will try to catch you on it.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's a...
SPEAKER_1:  honesty.
SPEAKER_1:  method there that keeps you honest. It's the sun degree, but.
SPEAKER_1:  It still feels like...
SPEAKER_1:  It still feels like politicians are gonna politician.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, they definitely play their games, that is true.
SPEAKER_0:  There's probably always gonna be that meta-narrative over like, governance.
SPEAKER_0:  that just develops as like you have to form relationships and play games to get legislation passed and everything. The only reason why I don't like it when people attack institutions is because one, institutions are incredibly important, arguably paramount, no, they are, to keeping society running. And two, I think sometimes when we shift the blame on the institutions too much,
SPEAKER_0:  I think that we lose sight of what the real problems are. So for instance, in the United States today.
SPEAKER_0:  People might be very critical of the government not getting much done.
SPEAKER_0:  but then everybody turns their eyes to the government for being ineffective.
SPEAKER_0:  But what I would argue is I would say the government is actually incredibly effective and it's showcasing the will of the American people really well right now, which is we are historically more divided than we have ever been.
SPEAKER_0:  And if I were to just look at the people and I were to say, we have a historic divide that is getting rapidly blown apart by things like the internet and the media, right? If that exists, well, what would I expect that government to look like? I wouldn't expect that government to be governing very effectively. I would expect that government to show that legitimate divide in people.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think that divide, we have a perception of a large divide?
SPEAKER_1:  between left and right.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think that's a real divide that's in this country?
SPEAKER_0:  Narrow the language. What do you mean by real divide?
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think there is that divide in ideology that there's a large number of people that believe a certain set of policies and the different set of policies? Or is it just the perception on Twitter?
SPEAKER_0:  No, I think there is a large divide in terms of belief. I don't think there's very much divide between any people in terms of like what they, like on the most fundamental levels want in terms of like human beings. But in terms of like Democrat versus Republican right now, I think there is a huge divide in terms of the direction they want to see the country go and what they believe.
SPEAKER_0:  really in what they even believe is reality, right? Unfortunately, that's what we've gotten to.
SPEAKER_1:  Can I just speak about the mechanism of the left and right here?
SPEAKER_1:  maybe on the mimetic rivalry aspect.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there some aspect to the left on which you're a part of that attacks their own?
SPEAKER_1:  for ideological impurity more than the right does.
SPEAKER_0:  Is it the bigotry of small differences?
SPEAKER_0:  There's a concept where...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  When you're near somebody who is very slightly different than you, you want to destroy it, but when you're with somebody that's way different than you, you don't.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the left does it, but I think the right does it too. I didn't realize it until I started dipping more into conservative communities, but oh my God, the people from the Daily Wire and the people from Turning Point and-
SPEAKER_0:  the America first, but all these different groups of people hate each other and they fight each other so much they hire and fire sometimes employees they talk
SPEAKER_0:  smack about each other. I think there's a lot of political division between both sides. I think that the left just kind of gets highlighted more because it's like the internet and a lot of the internet spaces have a lot of left leaning people. So you see like the crazy communists and the crazy progressives and the crazy center left liberals and the crazy blah, blah, blah. Whereas like a lot of the right leaning people have kind of been.
SPEAKER_0:  pushed off of the main areas of the internet now.
SPEAKER_1:  Interesting. My sense was that it's hard to exist on the center left.
SPEAKER_1:  but maybe because I just don't have the full spectrum view.
SPEAKER_1:  of the political divide. It felt like central art is a difficult position to occupy.
SPEAKER_0:  definitely say so.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if it's that difficult to be said, right?
SPEAKER_0:  it's very difficult to be center right. I think actually maybe even more difficult because a center right person might be somebody who's like conservative.
SPEAKER_0:  but not a fan of Trump and you're like over.
SPEAKER_0:  like looking like Liz Cheney, right? You've had politicians that are just like, they didn't back the Trump stuff and now they're gone. Or you might be like Senator Wright, but like you don't think the election was stolen.
SPEAKER_0:  And now you're like, half the Republican Party's looking at you like you're crazy, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  That's true. Yeah, that's true. I think, uh,
SPEAKER_1:  Ben Shapiro or who I'm talking with.
SPEAKER_1:  I think he publicly spoke against Trump.
SPEAKER_0:  He did initially, but I felt like he softened his language upon him pretty significantly, but...
SPEAKER_1:  So there's a significant pressure to kinda...
SPEAKER_1:  out a certain kind of messaging.
SPEAKER_0:  which the whole Republican Party is feeling right now. Geez, that two years from now, that election is gonna be insane.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just hard. Okay, so to generalize, it's hard to be in the center. It feels like for sure this center and then like.
SPEAKER_1:  do like a random walk.
SPEAKER_1:  among the policies around that.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know what that mechanism is. I mean, it makes people like me.
SPEAKER_1:  not feel good.
SPEAKER_1:  being in the center.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like people are just not nice.
SPEAKER_1:  to people in the center.
SPEAKER_1:  the public.
SPEAKER_1:  The Twitter Machine.
SPEAKER_1:  is not nice to the people who are open-minded in the center.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that, there's some truth to that.
SPEAKER_0:  Two reasons for that.
SPEAKER_0:  One is because I think a lot of people that market themselves as center are legitimately spineless cowards.
SPEAKER_0:  and deserved to be called out.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm like.
SPEAKER_1:  I've never killed a man, but today might be my first. Oh no.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  There I take over like I told you I'll take over your stream.
SPEAKER_0:  With the AI, we'll see. Is that guy gonna be streaming in the background? Hey, fellas.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, gotcha, gotcha, gotcha.
SPEAKER_0:  Gotcha. Lots of gotchas. Lots of gotchas. Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  and decrease the amount, which already is a pretty low level of emotion. Just decrease it completely. When people are screaming at you and it's like,
SPEAKER_1:  accusing stuff just remain calm. Absolutely. Most of our sharing about Madonna rumours outs the
SPEAKER_0:  the gas lighter strategy.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, so what were we talking about?
SPEAKER_1:  I don't.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  I don't even, I don't ever identify a center anything because it's got such a bad reputation because so- Fuck that, I sta-
SPEAKER_1:  center.
SPEAKER_1:  with a spine.
SPEAKER_1:  It's called being open-minded and it's not center left and right. Those are just labels.
SPEAKER_0:  Here's a really good quote my mom said to me when I was really young. She said Stevie.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't ever let your mind be so open that your brain falls out.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's what I find that a lot of center people do.
SPEAKER_1:  That's not what she told me last night.
SPEAKER_1:  Why are you like this?
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_0:  Sorry. Okay, I'm glad I can bring that. I'm glad you feel like this is a safe space. Like I said, people are not judgmental. If you wanna talk about fucking my mom, you know what, you're totally within your rights. I didn't say that, you said that. That's totally great, I support that. She's a beautiful woman. Her husband probably wouldn't be too happy about it, but you know.
SPEAKER_1:  I didn't say there was any sexual relations. It was just that.
SPEAKER_1:  having a conversation with her. You projected that, that says more by you than me. Anyway, go ahead about Spinalis Center. Spinalis Center. There is some aspects to that, which is.
SPEAKER_1:  like amorphous. To me center means you.
SPEAKER_1:  Youth.
SPEAKER_1:  think freely about each individual policy without being st-
SPEAKER_0:  Some ideal, yeah, but a lot of people don't do that. They call themselves centrist, but then they just, they're anti-establishment essentially on everything. I don't know your position on like the vaccines or anything.
SPEAKER_0:  But like I met a lot of like free and open thinkers who are like, you know what? I'm open to everything and it's an experimental vaccine and I'm going to eat hydroxy, Clark, when an Ivermectin, because that's what the institutions are telling me not to take. And I think Fauci got too much money from that company and these are, but I'm an open thinker and I'm and they would open thinker.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm at MIT, what do you think my position on vaccines is exactly?
SPEAKER_0:  I hear a lot of crazy things from a lot of people. You might be from MIT, but I know you're from the internet. People from the internet are weird and crazy.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I, uh, who knows.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't like arrogance and I have criticized.
SPEAKER_1:  scientists during COVID, a lot of people, scientists included, have
SPEAKER_0:  arrogance. Which is fair.
SPEAKER_0:  But, and I think there's a lot of good criticism to be made of different.
SPEAKER_0:  scientific and medical establishments over a lot of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  Nobody can make those good criticisms because they're too like obsessed over like just trying to have the anti-establishment answer. And that is what is upsetting me the most. Like I think there are good conversations to be had.
SPEAKER_0:  about.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of stuff related to how we handle the coronavirus. You know, were lockdowns effective? Was there enough data to support the huge measures we took? You know, why didn't we have the option to show I was infected a month ago? Why do I need to be vaccinated? Why wasn't that option everything in the United States? I don't think it was. There are really good questions to be asked there.
SPEAKER_0:  but all the people asking the questions are also trying to tell you that ivermectin and monoclonal antibodies are the way to go for everything. And the vaccine is evil and they're just gonna turn you gay like the frogs. And it's like, Jesus, like you can't, there's like no place to reasonably criticize from because all of the people that are criticizing aren't doing it with an open mind or, you know, they're not reading studies or doing anything. They're saying like, I do my own research, which means they listen to whatever the last guy on Joe Rogan said, and now they're parroting that opinion. Easy now, easy now, bro. Last guy on Joe Rogan, not Joe Rogan.
SPEAKER_0:  That Robert Malone guy on Joe Rogan got me real fired up. That's one guest. People see him as like the father of mRNA technology. He published one paper, okay? What do you mean people?
SPEAKER_1:  which people.
SPEAKER_0:  think that. Dope broken fans. I get like I run into these people. I start arguing with people and they start setting me. Well, what about-
SPEAKER_1:  I'm your Rogan fan.
SPEAKER_1:  and I appreciate the vaccine.
SPEAKER_0:  That's good. I'm glad you do. But there's definitely- Sorry.
SPEAKER_1:  But you said there's a type, what's the type? What's the type of Joe Rogan fan? Anti-establishment.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that's not Joe Rogan, that's a general public discourse, it's a default.
SPEAKER_1:  and his establishment on the right and the left.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the default easy thing to go to.
SPEAKER_0:  I think Joe Rogan fans are definitely a certain type of anti-establishment though. Like I could guess to Joe Rogan fan. Like if I were to do general population versus Joe Rogan fan who do you think is more likely to be anti-vaccine?
SPEAKER_1:  Do you have data on this?
SPEAKER_1:  Are you just guessing? Just guessing. Yeah, I think you are actually judging.
SPEAKER_1:  I am. Calendar
SPEAKER_1:  Because I think you're also.
SPEAKER_1:  The beautiful thing about podcasting this could be similar streaming is there's a large number of people that just listen.
SPEAKER_1:  Like what does it mean to be a Joe Rogan fan?
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think you just listen. I think people listen and absorb.
SPEAKER_0:  the information.
SPEAKER_1:  I would say that Joe Rogan fan base is as divided than the vaccine is the general public.
SPEAKER_1:  Gotcha.
SPEAKER_0:  Man, I'm gonna look for polling data on that. I'm sure somebody's gotta have done it out there, but-
SPEAKER_1:  No, but you're basically revealing the fact they have no data, you're using your own judgment for sure.
SPEAKER_0:  Based on how he's had conversations about his experience with the coronavirus and then based on the guests that have come on that have talked and echoed a lot of like anti-vax talking points and been completely unchallenged and then based on statements he's made about like myocarditis and the vaccine and everything as well. So it's the level of GTA.
SPEAKER_1:  challenge or not that he's doing.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, yeah, and then what his true positions are and then the types of guests he typically chooses to bring on to talk about the vaccines. Yeah
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, but that represents somehow a deep anti-establishment.
SPEAKER_1:  feeling.
SPEAKER_1:  Versus just the vaccine. I mean, I've seen the vaccine and other things being.
SPEAKER_1:  A thing that broke people.
SPEAKER_0:  I think all the coronavirus, that whole one or two years broke.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of people.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot of emotion and emotion quickly.
SPEAKER_1:  solidified into an opinion.
SPEAKER_1:  that almost had nothing to do with like...
SPEAKER_1:  like thinking through and updating your knowledge that's all you just need to know.
SPEAKER_0:  made up your mind. Yeah, but I think a lot of it comes from that anti-establishment place. Like what the vaccine represents, the ultimate.
SPEAKER_0:  of establishment. It was a huge
SPEAKER_0:  private company backed by a huge
SPEAKER_0:  uh... public government
SPEAKER_0:  and there's Fauci and there's Biden and there's Pfizer and there's all these countries locking us up in our homes telling us to do a thing. Like the vaccine was like the ultimate like.
SPEAKER_0:  submission tool to like show you that the government owns you. Not only do you have to get injected once, it's a series. And then you gotta get boosters and it's like, they're trying to keep you under their thumb and it's, that's the control. I feel like that vaccine became like the ultimate rallying cry between like, do you support, are you a sellout that is gonna believe whatever the government tells the sheep to take, or are you gonna be like the guy that stands against the crowd and gets fired from his job and pulls his kids from school because they're not gonna let the evil Fauci medicine, you know, jab them in the arm.
SPEAKER_1:  And the funny thing is the crowd that stands against.
SPEAKER_1:  the institution is not larger than the crowd of sheep.
SPEAKER_1:  There's like one sheep stand.
SPEAKER_0:  Sure. Yeah. Or it feels that way sometimes. One vaccine.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, okay, what's the defense of institutions? How do you regain the trust of institutions?
SPEAKER_1:  First of all, do you think that there's ways in which?
SPEAKER_1:  WHL CDC failed.
SPEAKER_1:  And do you think there's criticism towards Pfizer and the big pharma companies that deserve it?
SPEAKER_1:  Damn, dude, it's the pharmac-
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not sure for CDC and WHO. So here's a criticism that I have of all of academia and I feel it stronger stronger every day
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think it's enough.
SPEAKER_0:  to be a researcher or to be correct about issues, academia needs to increase its ability to communicate.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, it is just an, uh, an unbelievable, unmitigated failure that academics are unwilling to wade into the complicated topics, uh, that exists today because other people are, you know, first you call.
SPEAKER_1:  me spineless and then you call me a bad communicator.
SPEAKER_0:  But no, look, you're here, you're doing it, so you get props from me, okay? Good job.
SPEAKER_0:  That mother- Like so many but I'm sure you've I'm sure
SPEAKER_0:  that you must have.
SPEAKER_0:  heard another.
SPEAKER_0:  a fellow academic, a fellow colleague, expressed some amount of frustration about, like, in their specific discipline.
SPEAKER_0:  They know something to be true and they know that like a lot of the messaging is like wrong or bad in the public about it, but they're never gonna step out and say anything because either one, they're very measured and careful with their tech, which they feel is incompatible with what people wanna hear or two.
SPEAKER_0:  they're really worried that they might be incorrect. So they're gonna be cautious while everybody else is going out in like hardcore.
SPEAKER_1:  And they also don't have the support of institutions for them to go out on a limb. Yeah, that too. So like to take risks. For example, I've heard that with.
SPEAKER_1:  Lab leak theory.
SPEAKER_1:  I've had a lot of biologists, viologists, friends that are like...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's obviously leaked from the lab.
SPEAKER_1:  Like early on.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, maybe, okay. We can fight over this one, but sorry. Let's go.
SPEAKER_1:  We can fight over this. Like they.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, I should sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  backstep and say like that's like you talk about shooting the shit you haven't really investigated but your gut
SPEAKER_1:  Like this doesn't make any sense.
SPEAKER_1:  They would never say that publicly. Of course.
SPEAKER_1:  Mostly because you're saying like, what they would all say is like, we want to see data. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Which would be good, which is fine.
SPEAKER_1:  So they're going with like, like this is too many coincidence in the same place. That's the, the logic, but they don't want to say anything because there's no data you need to have evidence. You need to have actual evidence to say one way or the other.
SPEAKER_1:  There's that.
SPEAKER_1:  But there's also just like you said, I mean, effective communication. You're a fan of Sean Carroll. Oh, yes.
SPEAKER_0:  He's like one of the only people in this whole planet.
SPEAKER_0:  that I like besides you. I love dsoc now.
SPEAKER_1:  Any time Sean Carroll's brought up.
SPEAKER_1:  as evidence.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a smile that comes over your face. I love it. Of like joy. Of like a little kid thinking about Santa Claus. Okay, I love Sean Carroll too.
SPEAKER_0:  I love Sean Carroll because I hate this divide between like you're either STEM or you're like philosophy, arts and all that other stuff. And the two worlds can never cross. And I love that it was so good at physics, but like explores and pays attention to all of the like sociological stuff too. It's so rare to find that quality in a person. He's legit.
SPEAKER_1:  one of the really, really, really specialized, but you don't have to be a chancre. You can be just a little.
SPEAKER_1:  better at educating another person in the.
SPEAKER_1:  in the medical and the health space is somebody named Andrew Huberman, a friend of mine.
SPEAKER_1:  from Stanford, he's an incredible educator.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a kind of process in science.
SPEAKER_1:  they usually call it review or survey papers where you basically
SPEAKER_1:  summarize all that's going on.
SPEAKER_1:  integrate it and like draw wisdom from it and also project like where's the discipline heading and Andrew does that basically on all these sub components of the different stuff going on in
SPEAKER_1:  in neuroscience and biology, neurobiology, all that. He's able to, he does a.
SPEAKER_1:  podcast called Huberman Lab.
SPEAKER_1:  where he just summarizes on and is able to explain what does that actually mean for your
SPEAKER_1:  for your life in terms of protocols of how to make your life better. I feel like people should be able to do that more and more. But with viral, virology and.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh boy, that's a tricky one.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a really tricky one.
SPEAKER_0:  I wish that people could have...
SPEAKER_0:  honest conversations like I attack a lot of people that do the lab leak theory stuff, but truly...
SPEAKER_0:  we should be able to have that conversation publicly. It just, it always feels like the people that are having the conversation don't ever really wanna have the conversation. They're not being honest. Like, every, like.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm a guy that like does his own research and it's so boring reading studies and a lot of it I can only do abstracts and like I like it's so much work.
SPEAKER_0:  But I'll never ever say that about myself. I'm a guy that does his own research because every time I hear somebody say that, they don't do any research. When they say they do their own research, what they mean is they've seen one podcast and their opinion on this- What podcast is that? Definitely not mine, because if it was mine, I'm criticizing anything they say.
SPEAKER_0:  But yeah, so like LabLeak is another one where it's like, well how do you know it's LabLeak?
SPEAKER_0:  how do I know it's lab leak? Because Fauci lied and Hunter Biden, and it's like, okay, come on, you haven't engaged with it at all. There's really interesting research that shows there's a really strong study that shows that there's like a high degree of certainty that it came from the wet markets.
SPEAKER_0:  very, very high degree of certainty. And there was an article that came out recently where it's like Senate concludes that virus actually came from the Wuhan Virology Lab or whatever. And that whole article, if you actually read it, it never says that in the article. I don't know why they tweeted it with that headline.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  But yeah, it's.
SPEAKER_0:  to back up, I'm sorry.
SPEAKER_0:  I think we should have.
SPEAKER_0:  Good, you should be sorry. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not sorry actually. I get to ramble here. Okay. I'm here for a long time. I rescind my apology. Okay. I actually rescind my apology.
SPEAKER_0:  We should be able to have challenging conversations about things, but you gotta, man, be well-read on both sides. Not this like, I do my own research, so I don't believe anything that Fauci says. Like, come on, dude, you can do better than that. Not you personally, but...
SPEAKER_1:  Gotcha.
SPEAKER_1:  So for you who don't know, that's the catch phrase.
SPEAKER_1:  Gotcha. Through all tragedy.
SPEAKER_1:  and triumph through all the roller coaster of life.
SPEAKER_1:  Your response to it is gotcha.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a election. Let me jump to that before I continue to with political discourse.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, psychologically you are in a lot of heated debates and you're usually super calm under fire until you're not. Sometimes you lose your temper.
SPEAKER_1:  completely. We're saying the same thing about, L A B H R Y a
SPEAKER_1:  That's like your opinion, man.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask you about your psychology. What are psychologically your strengths and weaknesses?
SPEAKER_0:  or self aware about.
SPEAKER_0:  I think I'm very non-judgmental, so I can entertain a lot of different thoughts without agreeing with them or condoning them.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's a really big benefit to me.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, for whatever reason, I seem to be.
SPEAKER_0:  like pretty calm and dealing with.
SPEAKER_0:  annoying people. It's why I got promoted at the casino so fast. I could deal with like drunks or whatever. Like it just didn't affect me that much.
SPEAKER_1:  What percent of the population is annoying?
SPEAKER_0:  depends on how you're engaging with them. Most people aren't really annoying ever. But if you're doing like a political debate, what percentage is annoying? I guess it depends on who I'm debating and what the topic is.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess I'm trying to point out the fact that sometimes.
SPEAKER_1:  You can say...
SPEAKER_1:  that reveals something about you if you think a large percent of people are annoying.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I would say working graveyard shift when alcohol is involved, that percentage of people goes very, very, very high. Or to be more fair, actually, it's not a high percentage, truly. But if you're a server, one bad customer can ruin the rest of your shift.
SPEAKER_0:  So you only need like one or two people acting in that manner to just like totally throw you off
SPEAKER_1:  and you're able to.
SPEAKER_1:  At least these days, not.
SPEAKER_1:  allow that one customer to throw you off.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I'm very much like a I noticed especially after having a son
SPEAKER_0:  There's something about like six year old kids or whatever where it's like...
SPEAKER_0:  If they get mad, they're never gonna be mad for that long. Like they'll move on. Like that's my mentality. I'm like a six year old kid. Like I might be mad about something, but I'll get over it in like 30 minutes or an hour.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm pretty good about not carrying that through. It was very rare that I'll hold a grudge against anybody or be angry about something or really disaffected by something over the long term. That almost never happens to me.
SPEAKER_1:  What are your weaknesses psychologically?
SPEAKER_0:  I still have a problem with projecting.
SPEAKER_0:  I think we all probably do, but like my mind onto others, it's like, if I understand this and I've said this, you should understand it and if you're not, you're dumb. That's like an issue that I-
SPEAKER_0:  I still have that where I project too much.
SPEAKER_1:  What about like holding grudges and stuff like that?
SPEAKER_0:  I never hold grudges. I'm like the least grudgy person ever. It's kind of a meme on my community because anybody can always like come back
SPEAKER_0:  Um, as long as they're acting different. Yeah. What about this?
SPEAKER_1:  As long as they're acting.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, all right. The reason why I say that is because, so for instance, nobody likes this, but I have a strong stance on apologies, and then I hate them. I don't ever want to hear an apology. I don't care about them ever. They don't mean anything to me. If you did something bad, as long as you've like fixed the behavior and you're not doing that thing, then we're generally chill. So like, there's been a lot of people that have been involved in weird stuff with me, but then like they go off, they do their thing and they come back and it's like, okay, cool. As long as you don't do it again, like we're fine. Like it's all good.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm sorry you feel that way.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not your fault, Stephen. It's not your fault.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, gotcha.
SPEAKER_1:  You've said plenty of negative stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  Positive stuff, negative stuff about Hassan.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, this is my podcast. I get to get you to force you to say positive things. What do you love?
SPEAKER_1:  Oh no. I'm all about you.
SPEAKER_0:  Love.
SPEAKER_0:  go back to grill me on the our word stuff we can make me compliment us on this is gonna be a harder conversation
SPEAKER_1:  All right. Hey, we're justoshowing obten happier.
SPEAKER_1:  We're going to get you to feel emotions. Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  So for people who don't know, he's another popular political streamer.
SPEAKER_1:  I think you had a...
SPEAKER_1:  as the kids call it, a bridge burning over Bernie Sanders. I don't know, my research is very limited on this. But what do you respect and love most about Hassan?
SPEAKER_0:  He puts in a lot of work.
SPEAKER_0:  when he was like growing his stream from 2000 concurrent viewers to 15,000, he was streaming like
SPEAKER_0:  was like 12 hours a day, like every single day.
SPEAKER_0:  So that was that. I'm gonna get a lot of work.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, he does seem to be pretty good at networking and like socializing and making the correct friends and connections to continue to build his business.
SPEAKER_1:  What about him as a political thinker? I know you don't think I leave him on that.
SPEAKER_1:  And in that regard, what I think that's-
SPEAKER_0:  Thanks for watching!
SPEAKER_1:  Oh man.
SPEAKER_1:  I honestly want to push back on that.
SPEAKER_0:  Because... Show your face...
SPEAKER_0:  I have zero respect for him as a political thinker.
SPEAKER_0:  There's not going to be almost anything. So you can't- I admire the fact that-
SPEAKER_0:  through no.
SPEAKER_0:  actual capability or ability of his own, he manages to wind up at some of the correct answers just because he's towing the line. So that is good job for him on that. He's got a lot of correct opinions, just he has no idea why. So I think that's undeserved.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that's too harsh, man. The reason I bring that up is I feel like there is-
SPEAKER_1:  A deep grudge in there, somehow.
SPEAKER_1:  So you're.
SPEAKER_1:  the father and also since you're so old, the grandfather.
SPEAKER_1:  of the uh...
SPEAKER_1:  political debate on stream, on livestream.
SPEAKER_1:  political debater. So
SPEAKER_1:  There could be some grudge about that.
SPEAKER_1:  Split that happened or not enough credit given or all that kind of stuff. I just I just think he's somebody that
SPEAKER_1:  has a
SPEAKER_1:  a left-leaning ideology that's different than yours. He was a Bernie supporter, right? And I guess you were not.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you explain to me where the division is?
SPEAKER_0:  He exemplifies everything that I absolutely hate about politics.
SPEAKER_0:  Which is shallow engagement.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, heavily ideologically driven.
SPEAKER_0:  and you're not ideological.
SPEAKER_1:  We're different
SPEAKER_0:  Absolutely.
SPEAKER_1:  That's what we're talking about like the free thinker in the real
SPEAKER_0:  meaning of that word. Yeah, so the way, let me qualify it. Issue by issue thinking. Let me qualify what I mean when I say that.
SPEAKER_0:  I spent a lot of time, unfortunate time.
SPEAKER_0:  delving into the boring world of philosophy. I spent a lot of time thinking about like.
SPEAKER_0:  What are my ethical positions? How do I feel about myself?
SPEAKER_0:  the people around me and how that relates to the world around me. And then from all of these positions, I think you might've used the phrase first principles earlier.
SPEAKER_0:  From these kind of like first principles, out of that is where all of my political positions are built out of.
SPEAKER_0:  like full stop. So if you ask me a question like, how do you feel about like the right to own a firearm or how do you feel about social healthcare? Like we can walk through, well, this is how I feel about it as like a thing from the government. This is where the government gets its power. This is ethically how groups of people are supposed to function. This is morally how we relate to each other. And personally, this is how I feel like, like I'll be able to do every single political belief back there. It's not like I'm telling you, like if I were to ask Hassan, what do you feel about this political topic? He's gonna tell me what progressives are supposed to say. I don't know what he thinks about it. I don't know if he-
SPEAKER_1:  Don't you think that's a cynical take? Why is he just because his views coincide with the mainstream narrative?
SPEAKER_1:  mainstream viewpoints of progressive thinkers.
SPEAKER_1:  Why does that mean he's not thinking?
SPEAKER_0:  Because this engagement with every subject is incredibly shallow, 100% predictable. Like I could write like a-
SPEAKER_0:  I could probably program a script to like give you every single potential answer you could have to any single question you could give.
SPEAKER_1:  and I think that's a pretty cynical take.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, it could be the case that his brain perfectly aligns with every single mainstream
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if you know it is perfectly aligned.
SPEAKER_1:  Because I think you're just taking a very select, just like streamers do of each other.
SPEAKER_1:  a very select slice.
SPEAKER_1:  that represents.
SPEAKER_1:  the perfect alignment.
SPEAKER_1:  as opposed to looking at a person struggling with ideas and thinking through ideas and then giving them a pass like a lot of people.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I give you a pass on.
SPEAKER_1:  just the fact that you say a lot of crazy shit on stream for drama.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, which is- I don't say things for drama. It might be dramatic, but-
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, you've evolved as a fish evolves.
SPEAKER_1:  legs.
SPEAKER_1:  You've evolved a mechanism boat which creates controversy.
SPEAKER_1:  that you could say it's not intentioned, but it happens. I think the extremists kind of learn that kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  So I'm sure Hassan does the same kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  And so like underneath it, there's still thinking being this.
SPEAKER_1:  that's contending with political ideas.
SPEAKER_0:  you know it's not a really good job of hiding it
SPEAKER_0:  There are other political figures that I really don't like that I wouldn't say the same thing about. So like, I don't know if you have Vosh written in there. I'm like, okay, that's a person that he also split out of my community and grew up to something. And now he hates me and he's an anti-fan community. And they all hate me. Okay, tell me something you love about what my shit is. I can tell you a lot of things about Vosh. I think Vosh legitimately thinks through a lot of his political positions. I admire or did admire that he has like his own like positions he would take someone's country to people further left than him. He's got some positions that don't fit his ideology kind of at all. Like he's his own independent thinker, rhetorically he's very effective. He was willing to sit down and do research for like his debates and everything. He would spend a lot of time practicing like his rhetorical effectiveness and navigating conversations. He intentionally and purposefully built like a community that exemplified his values. Yeah, I've got a lot. I don't.
SPEAKER_0:  we are completely split and hate each other now. but like I had loss like 2 years ago with most people. for witnesses she says... She says
SPEAKER_1:  Why why why first of all hate is a strong what why?
SPEAKER_0:  the heat.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, I don't hate him, but he hates me because we had a couple of really big debates. What happened?
SPEAKER_0:  Well one had to do with whether or not you should live your values and
SPEAKER_1:  Can you give me the story that's a charitable interpretation? I always give charitable interpretation. You don't. I absolutely do.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't. Wait, name one time a-
SPEAKER_0:  five minutes ago, you talking about Hassan. Everything I said about Hassan is true. There is no steel man there, okay? That's not charitable. That's, I'm sorry. If you can prove me wrong, I would love for you to do it. Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  my gut instinct. Usually when somebody feels strongly about another person in that way, it's not coming from a place of data and reason. It's coming from a place of reason.
SPEAKER_1:  from a place of emotion.
SPEAKER_1:  It's coming from a place of resentment and grudge and all that kind of stuff. Yeah, I understand. There's emotions deep in there. So the gacha is hiding.
SPEAKER_1:  The got you is the surface of an iceberg.
SPEAKER_1:  and there's a deep ocean underneath that you yourself have not seen
SPEAKER_0:  explored I disagree but I understand why
SPEAKER_1:  is actually a doorway the young
SPEAKER_1:  Laugh as a dory.
SPEAKER_1:  for you to explore the
SPEAKER_0:  I understand why you think the way you do and you should you shouldn't believe me and I understand that because if somebody told me the same thing I think you probably just really don't like this person for a reason or two.
SPEAKER_0:  I understand why you think that way, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  The reality is though, for any political person that I disagree with, like I can give them a fair shake. It's one of the few things I think I do exceedingly well on my stream. Even with Hassan, there's been drama that he's been involved in. And I've like very, when I'm involved in drama, he'll always throw me under the bus. But when he's involved in stuff, I'll always say like, oh, like I think Hassan was right here. Or I think that he meant this.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a thing that came up once we're on a live stream fail. He was getting roasted because he referred to somebody.
SPEAKER_0:  He used the expression shitskin.
SPEAKER_0:  to refer to somebody's.
SPEAKER_0:  like the way they look.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I have only ever heard that in the context of 4chan people talking about like Indians or like black people.
SPEAKER_0:  like it's a racial thing.
SPEAKER_0:  but I could tell.
SPEAKER_0:  Context and everything that he was saying he was insulting some guy. I think it was kind of like in cell virgin ever He was going for like acne skin.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's what he meant when he said it. And there were a whole bunch of people that were insulting, like, oh my God, did he just say racist term? I was like, no, I don't think he was racist. I think he was like, he was just reaching for words, and that's what came out.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, so like that's an example of me being.
SPEAKER_1:  But didn't you criticize them for something? I was trying to like Google why the hell you guys split up because I thought your friends you should be like
SPEAKER_0:  We slid up over our Kamala Harris video, but go ahead. What were you?...
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like you criticized them over something.
SPEAKER_1:  And I'm, okay, this is very vague memory, but you criticize them over something and I felt that criticism wasn't.
SPEAKER_0:  charitable.
SPEAKER_0:  Was it Pete Buttigieg stuff?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, Peter Buttigieg, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes. Yeah, so.
SPEAKER_0:  I've said this a million times, but no amount of context or no amount of nuances is ever acceptable to people. I don't-
SPEAKER_0:  Think Hasan is homophobic.
SPEAKER_0:  But I think the comments made about Pete, booty judge were really homophobic. That's what he said. Yeah, and there were a lot of people making a lot of comments that made me really uncomfortable.
SPEAKER_0:  about Pete Buttigieg that was insane to me.
SPEAKER_1:  by
SPEAKER_1:  Come to the faade.
SPEAKER_0:  No, but it was an environment of progressives, all the progressives were attacking Pete, and I felt like his gayness became-
SPEAKER_0:  Like the subject.
SPEAKER_1:  Why throw Hassan under the bus?
SPEAKER_0:  He was jumping along with all of those types of like insults
SPEAKER_1:  You don't think you've done the same kind of stuff?
SPEAKER_0:  If I do, call me out at it and I'll probably say I shouldn't have done that.
SPEAKER_1:  what the R-word was about. That's a good call out. No, but like your friend, like you should privately tell him, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  Well no, by then we were sworn enemies, so...
SPEAKER_0:  So that wasn't the reason you- No, no, no. It was over a Kamala Harris video. It's war on enemies.
SPEAKER_0:  He hates me. What am I supposed to... Listen, for all of these people, I will accept them back into my life if they ever want to come back in at any point in time, but usually they're the ones that are saying like... If they correct themselves, right?
SPEAKER_0:  No, I'm not expecting anybody to do it. So here's the deal with Vashana-san. These are like the three, we're the three.
SPEAKER_0:  Guys, none of us will talk to each other. Hassan because he won't give clout to anybody and Vash because he thinks I'm bad faith. And then neither of them will talk to me because they both hate me.  anxious
SPEAKER_1:  I should go on a camping trip together. It's like brokeback mountain but three way.
SPEAKER_1:  and just like rejoin, refine, refine the patient for each other. Honestly, just from the internet perspective, for me as a just stepping into this world.
SPEAKER_1:  Um,
SPEAKER_1:  There's some aspect to which you have a responsibility. I hate that word. You have an opportunity. I wish you guys a d-
SPEAKER_1:  kind of be the beacon of like.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... forgiveness and friendship and my camaraderie
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I agree. And even if we disagree, it would be really good content for us to argue.
SPEAKER_1:  Shit talk, like friends shit talk. Sure. There's a guy in there like I knew he hired me.
SPEAKER_1:  Like the fact that you guys don't-
SPEAKER_1:  talk to each other.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I would love for you to shit talk publicly.
SPEAKER_1:  with the camaraderie always there. Like there's love in the beginning, love in the end, but you beat the shit out of each other in the middle. And that's what live streaming is for, with political discourses, that's...
SPEAKER_1:  That's great political discourse. Versus, I think what underlies it is some jealousy and so on. You get this many followers. bye
SPEAKER_0:  I just want to make sure you're clear to your eyes. Everybody has
SPEAKER_1:  to your audience.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm sure you have flaws and I'm just not in this.
SPEAKER_0:  It's hard to find, you know, because I'm-
SPEAKER_1:  You're only flies, you're too modest. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  So why did you guys split up? Because I would love it, honestly. Just let me just put that idea out there for you guys to.
SPEAKER_0:  to make up and so yeah it's out there of course as everybody talks me Vashana son it's crazy that like the three largest like political debate left-leaning people online like can't do any type of content or collaboration at all it's so stupid
SPEAKER_1:  What was the reason you guys split up? The Kamala Harris?
SPEAKER_0:  So Hassan's entry into kind of like the Twitch political debate world was in, I think 2018, I think he did a debate with Charlie Kirk.
SPEAKER_0:  And he reached out to me to kind of like review that debate to like go on to go over it on stream. And he came on, we went over it and then we kind of friendship developed. We hung out in real life. I think when I came to LA, I think I slept on his couch. We played with his dog. We were like kind of friends.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And as time went on...
SPEAKER_0:  I think he was a little bit more...
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  He was farther left than he led on. So like I was a social Democrat, he was a social Democrat. But back in those days, like 2018, when people said they were a social Democrat, they really meant socialist, but they just didn't wanna say it. So he was farther left than me and we had a lot of-
SPEAKER_0:  deep divides in our approach to politics. Whereas like I was very much like a first principles, this is my whole political position. And he was very much kind of like a, this is like the political ideology I'm involved in. And this is kind of like the field that I kind of like navigate in.
SPEAKER_0:  So there were a couple instances where these divides would be laid very bare. One was when it was either him or the young Turks.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it was him.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a shooting in a neighborhood.
SPEAKER_0:  where a very young black child gets killed by a white shooter.
SPEAKER_0:  and they did a video about like hate crimes and how hate crimes are on the rise between races and white people are evil and blah blah blah. Not that, but like white people committing hate crimes against black people.
SPEAKER_0:  And I remember saying to him, I was like...
SPEAKER_0:  Hey.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't have all the data yet for this. It feels really bad to make videos about this beforehand because it's the same type of shit that happens at airports. You know, is there a thing going on? Was it a brown person? Are they Muslim? It's Islamic extremism. We see this played out so many times in recent history, probably not a good idea to jump to conclusions. And he's like, well, no, you don't understand. Like it's not that big a deal, whatever. And obviously as the story goes, tale as old as time, the data comes out, it was just an errant.
SPEAKER_0:  shot there was like gang violence shot goes out of nowhere hits a kid in the car it wasn't like a hate crime the guy was trying to kill a kid
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, we basically we bump up against a few kind of political disagreements like this.
SPEAKER_0:  and an annoying thing is happening in my community where Hasan is like the serious political figure because he's from the Young Turks and I'm just kind of like I do politics but I also game and anytime I criticize the sun people like destiny
SPEAKER_0:  you need to be more respectful he does this full-time if you're gonna bring criticisms you need to be like really well read and researched because he's got a you know more serious whatever which I thought was ridiculous
SPEAKER_1:  Otherwise, if people don't know, he worked at
SPEAKER_1:  the young Turks.
SPEAKER_0:  which is like the largest left leaning YouTube channel probably or at least at the time.
SPEAKER_0:  So finally, he did a video on... Skip ahead to some more minor discriminations. He does a video on Kamala Harris. He calls it Kamala Harris.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's like seven or eight horrible things about Kamala Harris. And I'm like, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  I know at least one or two of these things are not fully accurate, so I'm going to do all the research.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm gonna have all the sources and we're gonna have a long conversation about it so that now when I provide criticism to him, it's not gonna be like this horrible, like just me saying something flippantly or whatever, it's gonna be like substantial criticism.
SPEAKER_0:  So I was on a f-
SPEAKER_0:  Plane ride.
SPEAKER_0:  JFK to Orlando, whatever, flying to Sweden, is my wife.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  On the plane, I review all of the video, all the data, do all the research and I write everything. It's like, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  I get.
SPEAKER_0:  to my arm.
SPEAKER_0:  my wipes.
SPEAKER_0:  Dad's house, and I'm-
SPEAKER_0:  at the table, we're having a conversation like, hey, we should talk about the Kamala Harris stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  And he's like, okay, well, let's do it. And we go over it.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I'll leave to the audience to watch the video. Enough people will say this, I feel pretty confident in saying this. I was pretty reasonable, pretty measured, pretty calm the whole time, and I think he started to get increasingly irritated that I was levying more and more serious criticisms at the quality of work that he did.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably because he felt a little bit intimidated, I think, by my willingness to dive through political stuff. There have been a couple of awkward blubs where, like, on, um...
SPEAKER_0:  there's like a show called the Raj Royale where sometimes politics would come up and Hassan would kind of try to explain something and there was another person one time in the show that made the joke it's like instead of Hassan taking 10 minutes to explain this, can Destiny just come here and explain it in 30 seconds and he like exploded that he got so
SPEAKER_0:  fucking mad at that.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, so yeah, I think that when I made that kind of call out or critique of him over the Kamala Harris stuff, he's probably feeling like increasingly irritated, threatened, agitated. And then that's kind of what began the huge.
SPEAKER_1:  split from ours.
SPEAKER_0:  think you were a dick at all.
SPEAKER_0:  i don't think so that conversation
SPEAKER_0:  especially given that like.
SPEAKER_0:  at that point because this is still 20.
SPEAKER_0:  18 or 20, this might be 2019.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm still known at that point as being very aggressive.
SPEAKER_0:  towards conservatives or all writers. Oh, I gotcha. Yeah, so, and with lefties is what I call them. I think I'm being like very gentle. Like my conversation starts with conservatives, like you're a fucking idiot, you're so dumb. Like that's how I'm like doing. So like with him, I'm like, well, don't you think that like, this is like a little bit of like an inconsistent presentation of how like, I feel like I'm being nice. But I always leave to the audience so they can go and watch.
SPEAKER_0:  that Kamala Harris video Destiny of Sun if they think that I was being a dickhead. But a lot of people watching said I was being pretty gentle. Wow let me see.
SPEAKER_1:  As a new fan of this space, I hope you guys make up and I hope.
SPEAKER_1:  You guys fight it out in the space of discourse and ideas. Me too. And also with empathy, understanding what the strength of the other person is, what their buttons are and.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there's like...
SPEAKER_1:  an unspoken rule that you don't press the button.
SPEAKER_1:  You sure need to.
SPEAKER_1:  unless you're doing it mutually and it's fun.
SPEAKER_1:  because you know you just want to piss each other off so yeah that's kind of like what friends do you don't cross a certain line
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  but then other than that, you fight it out.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, let's step back.
SPEAKER_1:  One other super interesting aspect.
SPEAKER_1:  of your world view is your big supporter.
SPEAKER_1:  of Biden.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you explain what you love about Biden? Do you love Biden more than Sean Carroll?
SPEAKER_0:  Sean Carroll's just like in another world of...
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like I'm...
SPEAKER_1:  Culturally appropriating you by saying gotcha now.
SPEAKER_1:  It's so convenient.
SPEAKER_0:  It's an easy word. You just I know I we're on the same wavelength. Okay, we're synchronizing. That's good I mean it is really interesting
SPEAKER_1:  because even the people that support Biden usually don't say they love.
SPEAKER_1:  sort of they don't support it strongly you know.
SPEAKER_0:  ideologically.
SPEAKER_0:  Philosophically, the reason why I like Biden is because he's really committed to this bringing the left and right together, which is something we so desperately need in the country. And his statements over and over again of like, I'm not the Democrat president or the Republican president, I'm the president of the United States. His desire to bring Republicans together to work on things like the infrastructure bill, that's...
SPEAKER_0:  so incredibly needed and I have a huge amount of respect and admiration for him for trying to push through on that message.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think then it's unfortunate that he made that comment about MAGA? MAGA Republicans? Yeah, I mean I forget what the comment was but MAGA Republicans are-
SPEAKER_1:  not good people kind of Anna IC
SPEAKER_0:  I watched the full video and
SPEAKER_0:  He's right, there is this.
SPEAKER_0:  toxic aspect and it's hard to call out because they're always going to spend like, oh, he hates our Republicans. He's not. If you watch the quote, he's very specifically calling out like this, this group of people that think that the election was fraudulent.
SPEAKER_0:  Is it clear?
SPEAKER_0:  It is what he meant by we bring it up.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh oh.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember watching our stream, he was like, if you said it, yeah, that's bad. You can probably like YouTube, MAGA, Republicans, Biden. But like, it feels like it's pretty clear he's talking about the people that are like election denying.
SPEAKER_0:  Too much of what's happening.
SPEAKER_1:  in our country today is not.
SPEAKER_0:  normal.
SPEAKER_0:  Donald Trump and the migrant Republicans.
SPEAKER_0:  representing extremism.
SPEAKER_0:  that threatens the very foundations.
SPEAKER_0:  of our republic.
SPEAKER_0:  Now I want to be very clear.
SPEAKER_1:  whatever
SPEAKER_1:  Listen to this part.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_1:  Not every public.
SPEAKER_0:  and not even the majority of Republicans are mega Republicans.
SPEAKER_0:  Not every Republican embraces their exp...
SPEAKER_1:  ideology.
SPEAKER_1:  I know.
SPEAKER_1:  because I've been able to work with these mainstream Republicans.
SPEAKER_1:  But there's no question.
SPEAKER_1:  that the Republican Party today is dominated, driven, and intimidated.
SPEAKER_1:  by Donald Trump and the MAGA Republicans.
SPEAKER_1:  And that is a threat to this country.
SPEAKER_1:  I disagree with that man, he didn't clearly say...
SPEAKER_1:  Extremist ideology. He didn't say the
SPEAKER_1:  people that doubt the validity of the election. I mean, that's.
SPEAKER_0:  Donald Trump.
SPEAKER_1:  No, but-
SPEAKER_1:  this.
SPEAKER_0:  That's all the candidates that Donald Trump is supporting. How many, what is it like 40, 50, how many candidates right now that are mega candidates are election- NO BLESS.
SPEAKER_1:  There's, you know, 80 million or whatever people voted for Donald Trump.
SPEAKER_1:  You could say that's the MAGA Republicans.
SPEAKER_1:  So to me, it sounded like he.
SPEAKER_1:  was referring to
SPEAKER_1:  Not even the majority. I mean, that's one nice, helpful clarifying.
SPEAKER_1:  statement. But it's basically there's the mainstream Republicans and then there's those that voted for Donald Trump.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the way I heard it.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay. And it's like, so maybe you should have done a better job at clarifying, but.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like there's a clear, there is a huge problem.
SPEAKER_0:  with this group of Americans that think that like the election is stolen. It feels like that's what he's trying to call.
SPEAKER_1:  No matter.
SPEAKER_1:  If that's what he meant.
SPEAKER_1:  Even flirting with that line?
SPEAKER_1:  is not a person who's bringing people together.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like extending a hand to the like, most, I've worked with Republicans in Congress, not even a majority of Republicans are like this.
SPEAKER_0:  No, but why say not-
SPEAKER_1:  the majority of Republicans that like this say.
SPEAKER_1:  like weird like a
SPEAKER_1:  one country.
SPEAKER_1:  We believe the same thing. So like.
SPEAKER_1:  Focus on the uniting part versus.
SPEAKER_0:  He does before and after, that was 50 seconds, okay?
SPEAKER_1:  You never, the point is you never say something like that. Listen, like that, you've spoken about the Bosnia speech, which is your favorite of his. I want back to it and listen to it.
SPEAKER_0:  Before I move to that, just on this, it's really hard for him to call out that group of election deniers, I think, without it always feeling like. Why call them out?
SPEAKER_0:  because it's
SPEAKER_0:  arguably one of the most destructive forces that exist in this country today.
SPEAKER_0:  Did it destroy anything?
SPEAKER_1:  They're trying to.
SPEAKER_1:  Did it?
SPEAKER_0:  It didn't, did it?
SPEAKER_0:  So does that mean we don't call it out? We wait till next time? Because calling it out is-
SPEAKER_1:  is giving fuel to the division.
SPEAKER_1:  Like.
SPEAKER_1:  the people that doubted the validity of the election.
SPEAKER_1:  That's anger, that's frustration with the other side.
SPEAKER_1:  You heal that.
SPEAKER_1:  as opposed to saying all those people that believed that at any time are idiots.
SPEAKER_1:  They're un-American.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, they don't think the election was real. I don't know if Biden has the ears of these people at all. I don't know what he can do for.
SPEAKER_1:  There's people that believe the same thing on the in 2016 with the Russian hacking, right? There's this, hold on.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  That is a super not fair comparison.
SPEAKER_0:  They were definitely the mainstream.
SPEAKER_0:  Democrat opinion.
SPEAKER_0:  was that.
SPEAKER_0:  Russian
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  intrusion in terms of like social media and stuff happen.
SPEAKER_0:  But there was never a claim that like the election was stolen. No, or at least I don't know of any mainstream Democrat that supported that.
SPEAKER_0:  Donald Trump is not just saying there was interference and blah, blah, blah. Donald Trump is literally saying the election was literally stolen, that vote boxes were, ballot boxes were hidden, that vote tallies were manipulated, that I think the claim is there's a huge gulf difference between the two.
SPEAKER_1:  So you can attack Donald Trump.
SPEAKER_1:  I believe it's not the words of a uniter to attack.
SPEAKER_1:  people that believe that.
SPEAKER_1:  You could argue maybe it's okay.
SPEAKER_1:  but especially not being super clear about that.
SPEAKER_1:  about who you're referring to as the MAGA Republicans.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, because MAGA
SPEAKER_1:  is a hat.
SPEAKER_1:  and a slogan.
SPEAKER_1:  that refers to...
SPEAKER_1:  Whatever the number is, 70 million people, however, that voted for Donald Trump.
SPEAKER_1:  Like.
SPEAKER_0:  all the Republicans that consider themselves mega Republicans, what percentage of them do you think believe the election was stolen?
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like that number is, I don't have the pump, I feel like the number is like probably more than 70%.
SPEAKER_1:  What's a mega Republican? Maybe-
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe I'm not from the- Like a Trump-supporting Republican, a MAGA Republican, they're there for Trump.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the difference between somebody that voted for Trump and a MAGA Republican and a MAGA Republican?
SPEAKER_0:  So my mom is a MAGA Republican.
SPEAKER_0:  If Trump ran independently and DeSantis ran under the Republican ticket, my mom would vote for Trump. She'll follow him to the end of the earth. That's like a MAGA Republican.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's easy to mistake that distinction.
SPEAKER_1:  in these kinds of political speeches.
SPEAKER_1:  As to me, anybody who voted for Trump.
SPEAKER_1:  can easily in the context of the speech be interpreted as a republicn
SPEAKER_0:  Gotcha.
SPEAKER_0:  I understand what you're saying. Maybe you could have been more clear, but I think in listening to that...
SPEAKER_0:  like
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's pretty obvious who he's talking about, but I guess if you have an emotional response to it, I can understand the emotional response, but there's a lot of people- I don't have a-
SPEAKER_1:  I just don't like.
SPEAKER_1:  I think I'm with, what is it, Michelle Obama. They go low, we go high.
SPEAKER_1:  Meaning like...
SPEAKER_1:  To me, a uniter doesn't participate in derision.
SPEAKER_0:  Sure, a uniter might not, but a leader has to be able to accurately assess the situation before him and make people aware of what's going on. You mean all
SPEAKER_1:  the impeachment trials, all the censoring from social media, all of that didn't do the job.
SPEAKER_0:  That's not his job. I don't know about censoring any of that. Maybe.
SPEAKER_1:  His job is to inspire a nation to unite a nation.
SPEAKER_0:  How can he do that when half the people don't believe that he was even legitimately elected?
SPEAKER_0:  Like I think he's done a good job at working on legislation and doing stuff that hopefully benefits all Americans, but I think it's important to recognize that like there is a contingent of Americans that
SPEAKER_0:  Don't even believe it. Like this is really crazy.
SPEAKER_1:  I find you have people that recognize that and are fighting that and are constantly screaming that from the rooftops.
SPEAKER_1:  His job.
SPEAKER_1:  is to be the inspiring figure.
SPEAKER_1:  that makes the majority of Americans be proud for him to be a president.
SPEAKER_1:  of the nation they love.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's what the uniting aspect is.
SPEAKER_1:  is you remind people.
SPEAKER_1:  that we are one and we love this country. I love the ideas that it represents.
SPEAKER_0:  Should be does that another press that speech like a 20 minute speech, isn't it?
SPEAKER_1:  But that's a fuck up.
SPEAKER_1:  You just don't participate in that division. Anyway, I understand. I understand. I just wanted to push back on the saying one of his strengths is that he's a...
SPEAKER_1:  He's uniting, but yes.
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  That is an ideal, that is a goal, is a great one, and he is one that espouse that goal.
SPEAKER_1:  for a long time. Do you think...
SPEAKER_1:  What else? From policy perspective and so on.
SPEAKER_0:  I thought the way he's handled Ukraine and everything thus far has been almost perfect. I think he did a really good job.
SPEAKER_0:  and at the political maneuvering of bringing other countries into the fold, at establishing clearly like what our mission was in relation to Ukraine. I thought you did a good job there.
SPEAKER_0:  I admire him for pulling out of Afghanistan. Even it was a little bit rough around the edges, like we got out and we're gone. No American loss or lost.
SPEAKER_0:  the domestic policies passed more major legislation than I think anybody thought possible.
SPEAKER_0:  the green energy stuff for the last bill, the infrastructure bill.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of the coronavirus relief I thought was really good, especially the expansion of the child tax credit.
SPEAKER_0:  So from a policy perspective, foreign and domestic, I think he's been successful. Rhetorically, I think he's been successful.
SPEAKER_0:  generally been above board in terms of like not attacking people being too divisive.
SPEAKER_0:  He's trying to bring people together and work on them.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think about the sort of?
SPEAKER_1:  popular in the media.
SPEAKER_1:  criticism of his mental decline.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think he's experiencing much of his life?
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think? Spellingcheese
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, maybe a little bit.
SPEAKER_0:  But he's still doing a good job, so, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  not from a speech perspective, you mean from a...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I'm analyzing it as a job. Yeah, from a speech perspective, maybe not the greatest, but yeah, I mean, he's definitely what is he like 8081? How old is he?
SPEAKER_1:  I lose track after so many years. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  But you did say that he's probably going to run in 2024.
SPEAKER_0:  he's probably going to win.
SPEAKER_0:  Did I say that? That he's probably going to win? No way. Did I say that? He's probably going to run.
SPEAKER_0:  who knows who will win. But I think, I feel like the incumbent advantage is so strong. You really gonna throw that away? Like, there's been like one or two times in history in the US, right, where like the non-incumbent, the parties put somebody else up.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, the concern is like the, just the age and the.
SPEAKER_1:  the metal decline, just the...
SPEAKER_1:  the wear and tear of the campaign.
SPEAKER_1:  All of that kind of stuff. All of the speech you have to make, the debates and all that kind of stuff. Yeah, I guess we'll see what happens.
SPEAKER_0:  What?
SPEAKER_0:  the least excited uh i mean two years when i was a long time and his current mental state yeah he could run and
SPEAKER_0:  You could do a possible job in two years.
SPEAKER_0:  Man, I don't know. I've seen videos of Bill Clinton recently. He's looking pretty rough.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, you know, if Biden is looking a lot more rough.
SPEAKER_0:  worse for wear in two years then maybe they actually do have to dig out another person.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... for running out
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think about?
SPEAKER_1:  Trump.
SPEAKER_1:  When
SPEAKER_1:  He won in 2016, I think is when you...
SPEAKER_1:  came to fruition politically speaking. So what do you think is winning the 2016 election?
SPEAKER_1:  represents.
SPEAKER_0:  So for me.
SPEAKER_0:  Trump, the reason why I got into politics was Trump was like this new.
SPEAKER_0:  epistemic force in American politics that like
SPEAKER_0:  You kind of have to like flirt with facts before, even if you wanted to be non-factual.
SPEAKER_0:  Super didn't care.
SPEAKER_0:  Lying was like a first language to him, just like in speaking in terms of like...
SPEAKER_0:  the the way that he used language to just say to you what he felt like you needed to hear to support him and not care at all about what is going on about.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that's what Trump represented to me in terms of like
SPEAKER_0:  things that I cared about. He also represents a lot more, obviously, that there was this undercurrent of American opinion that a lot of people didn't know still existed, and it did, he got elected.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... that the overton window was misidentified by even a large amount of the republican party
SPEAKER_0:  that populism was a lot more popular than a lot of people figured, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there's a lot that I guess you represent on you.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think Trump should have been banned from Twitter?
SPEAKER_1:  Can you make the case for and against it? So you're a big supporter of free speech. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  The case in favor of it.
SPEAKER_1:  should be brought back.
SPEAKER_0:  der
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, because if he gets brought back, there's a higher chance that I'll be brought back, so.
SPEAKER_0:  supporting that all the way. Thank you, Elon.
SPEAKER_0:  unban my account.
SPEAKER_1:  Hahaha
SPEAKER_1:  because he called me.
SPEAKER_1:  weak spine I'm gonna have to message you
SPEAKER_0:  on. Okay, at Omnidestiny, it was a verified Twitter account. Omnidestiny. No, no, I'm just kidding.
SPEAKER_1:  Why'd you get banned from Twitter, Destiny? I don't know. I'll add that to Elon.
SPEAKER_1:  I saw that there was a screenshot.
SPEAKER_1:  of you.
SPEAKER_1:  referring to the rape of somebody
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, that was on an older Twitter account and that was a bad tweet.
SPEAKER_1:  multiple Twitter accounts.
SPEAKER_1:  go around the bands that you keep getting.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, hold on.
SPEAKER_0:  You're slandering me a lot right now. Let's get the facts straight. I don't even remember why my first time I got banned, but it was a wild account. I tweeted some wildly inappropriate things. Do you regret?
SPEAKER_0:  I don't like that word. I'm gonna give the answer that most people give. It's like, I don't regret it, because I learned a lot. So I'm glad I had the bad experiences that I did. Why don't you like the word regret?
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  If we look at where we are.
SPEAKER_0:  How do you feel about determinism?
SPEAKER_0:  I believe in the hardest of determinism. That's who I am, okay? So who I am today is the culmination of everything that's occurred in the past. I believe-
SPEAKER_1:  I believe you speaking out, sorry, it's an inter...
SPEAKER_1:  I believe in you.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking about regret is a nice way to communicate.
SPEAKER_1:  in this deterministic world, you've analyzed the acts of the past.
SPEAKER_1:  and you're no longer that person. Yeah, of course, for sure. That's what regret you.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, thanks for giving me the human explanation. Okay, true. So in that sense, there's a lot of things I've done that I regret.
SPEAKER_1:  What are you? You're not human, you're a bot?
SPEAKER_0:  NPC is my preferred. Game is a cod Yumother.
SPEAKER_0:  I wish I would have been smart enough at the time to not have to have made those mistakes.
SPEAKER_0:  There we go. Good job. But yeah, obviously really dumb, really crazy off the wall tweets.
SPEAKER_0:  But that account got banned, but then I made another account.
SPEAKER_0:  I can't believe I'm giving you a history of my Twitter accounts. But another account called Omnidestiny. It's an honor. And that was my, I got verified. I was cool. They let me have that account because originally they banned it. And I said, appeal. And I was like, oh, let me have one more. And back then, Twitter was cool. And they're like, OK, go for it.
SPEAKER_0:  And that account lasted for a long time. And I don't actually know 100% why that account got banned.
SPEAKER_0:  I believe that the tweet that showed up in the final, I got banned for hate speech.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was because I was
SPEAKER_0:  There was a picture that I tweeted.
SPEAKER_0:  with three different alt-righters that are kind of like neo-Nazi people, and they were all like mixed race people. And I said like, alt-right looks like a Disney Channel original movie.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of racial composition. And somehow they got flagged for...
SPEAKER_0:  instigating violence against minorities, I think. And I think that's the tweet that got me banned, because I think that's what showed up in the final report. But I don't know, maybe there were other reasons because nobody ever communicates, but.
SPEAKER_0:  Ever since that account went under.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just been renovating ever since, so.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll ban evading ever since. So all my new accounts that I'm gonna ban just get banned because they finally figure out it's me and then they ban evade. There's like one dude at Twitter HQ who's like constantly looking for my new accounts and then they get me.
SPEAKER_0:  Anyway, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So post...
SPEAKER_0:  Post Trump world. Do you think, okay, I mean this- Oh, should he be banned? Oh, you asked me to make both cases.
SPEAKER_0:  um...
SPEAKER_0:  Should he be banned?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean damn dude, when you're tweeting out shit that's arguably leading to stuff like January 6th, I can understand why, because it's like, what else is this wild dude going to tweet out? Like is he going to start instigating other violent events? So I'm sympathetic towards the like, okay, well he can't just be here saying stuff like this, that's insane, we're going to ban him.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm some of those instigating. Yeah, you're instigating.
SPEAKER_1:  violence in the
SPEAKER_0:  physical world. Yeah, like if I were to tweet stuff like that, I would get banned probably.
SPEAKER_0:  On the flip side.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the president of the United States. It seems like he's like doing presidential decree by social media sometimes. Like is it really right that one public.
SPEAKER_0:  or private, I should say, one private company can...
SPEAKER_0:  like erase the president of the United States words from the eyes of a lot of Americans that are using these social media feeds.
SPEAKER_0:  And one big one.
SPEAKER_1:  which I for sure am against.
SPEAKER_1:  is the permanent ban.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I don't like that. I hate that. Even in my community, if somebody comes back over like a year...
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, did you just compare yourself to the president?
SPEAKER_0:  No, I can find myself to Twitter banning the president of the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  Let me put it this way, if I ban Donald Trump in my chat room, I don't ban him in a year.
SPEAKER_1:  A year.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the process for unbanning Donald Trump? What would he have to do?
SPEAKER_0:  Usually people send me an email and they're like, listen, I did this stuff, I'm sorry I was dumb. I'll give them another chance.
SPEAKER_1:  But a year, what if they send an email a month later?
SPEAKER_0:  Use the Alabana.
SPEAKER_0:  That's actually my problem. I ban pretty quickly in my community, but if you ever ask me to come back. You're a big softy. Yeah, I usually let them back, yeah. Well, because I used to be the worst type internet person and I think I'm.
SPEAKER_0:  a little bit better than I used to be. Now that you're older. Yeah, now that I've matured, yeah, of course. Age bestows a wisdom that just can't be gotten any other way. What's your?
SPEAKER_1:  sense in general is there something interesting you could say about your view on free speech?
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like one of those terms it's also over.
SPEAKER_1:  Overused to mean a lot of different things. What does it mean to you?
SPEAKER_0:  if you have a democratic style of governance.
SPEAKER_0:  You are interesting people.
SPEAKER_0:  with one of the most awesome and radical of responsibilities. And that's saying that you're going to pick the people that are gonna make some of the hardest decisions in all of human history. If you're gonna trust people.
SPEAKER_0:  vote correctly, you have to be able to trust them to have open and honest dialogue with each other.
SPEAKER_0:  whether that's Nazis or KKK people or whoever talking, you have to believe that your people are going to be able to rise above and make the correct determinations when they hear these types of speeches. And if you're so worried that somebody is gonna hear a certain political figure and they're gonna be completely radicalized instantly, then what that tells me is that you don't have enough faith in humans for democracy to be a viable institution, which is fine.
SPEAKER_0:  You can be anti-democratic, but I don't think you can be pro-democracy and anti-free speech.
SPEAKER_0:  within reason.
SPEAKER_1:  So what's the within reason? Hi I'm
SPEAKER_0:  You can't post like child porn or something on Twitter, where people try to get you on that stuff. Or like direct calls to violence are probably not, you shouldn't be tweeting out like, meet up tomorrow and go bomb, blah, blah, blah.
SPEAKER_1:  So do you think it's okay to allow racism and anti-semitism and...
SPEAKER_1:  I hate speech.
SPEAKER_0:  Hate speech, yes, because that's.
SPEAKER_0:  can be very broadly defined.
SPEAKER_0:  I can understand there being some basic rules of like no slurs on like a platform.
SPEAKER_0:  that gets into like acceptable forms of moderation or like excessive harassment and bullying I can understand.
SPEAKER_0:  But past that...
SPEAKER_0:  when the moderation becomes ideological, I get a little bit nervous because there's a whole other-
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, of course it's all a gray area, but...
SPEAKER_1:  when it feels like ideology has seeped into the censorship.
SPEAKER_1:  Not good. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  which it's so fascinating to think, especially now that Elon bought Twitter, how do you-
SPEAKER_1:  Engineer a system.
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  prevents ideology from seeping in.
SPEAKER_1:  and nevertheless is able to.
SPEAKER_1:  Create a platform that has healthy conversations because if you have one guy who's just screaming nonsense non-stop
SPEAKER_1:  It has this effect.
SPEAKER_1:  where the quiet voices at the back of the room are silenced. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  like.
SPEAKER_1:  That's what you usually don't talk about. Like if you let-
SPEAKER_1:  one annoying, loud person in, that's actually censoring the voice of a lot of people that would like to speak, but they don't get a chance.
SPEAKER_0:  That's one of the things, especially around trans discourse, I have to constantly do that reminder for my audience. So when I'm dealing with these types of people on the internet, a lot of them might seem really crazy, a lot of these types of people might seem insane, but in the real world, outside of the crazy Twitter activist world, the vast majority of people you're meeting from LGBT communities are the coolest, normalist people. All they want is the right to live their life in the way they want to and to be unobstructed. And like, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  but people will get this impression of like an online activist, like a vegan or LGBT person or whatever. And then they think that every single person in real life is like that. And it's a really negative.
SPEAKER_0:  stereotype and then even the other people in that group.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, is Maria coming over?
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah, I don't know if that's her.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, Malina just joined us. What were we talking about?
SPEAKER_0:  Was it interesting? You were saying that-
SPEAKER_0:  You were going to talk to Elon about getting at Omni destiny, the verified Twitter account on ban. I said that so it sounds like a lot. That's so gracious of you. I can't even believe you would do that for me.
SPEAKER_1:  And then you admitted that you tried to evade the band multiple times, which I'm sure would be very looked up.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I heard that in Norway, in their prison system, they don't actually punish you for trying to escape jail because that's like the natural human thing to do. They hug you?
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if they but they don't punish you because of course you're trying to be free That's all I'm trying to be on Twitter. I'm just trying to be free. Well, that's the natural human Yeah, that's the natural human of course, it's the Banyan Man
SPEAKER_1:  destructive force.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I'm a positive a force for good. That's right. Oh my console to get banned for bad new vanishing I don't get banned for doing bad things. And I'm progressive show. I'm like far left.
SPEAKER_0:  I love.
SPEAKER_1:  progressive process that this is what you criticize us on for being.
SPEAKER_0:  I show them from a place of first principles, not from a mindless AI echoing kind of thing, you know? Okay. So you're a free thinking bot. Yeah, exactly.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I'm sure we'll return to some politics. That was beautiful.
SPEAKER_1:  Heh.
SPEAKER_1:  Malia, can you tell us about...
SPEAKER_1:  yourself you're also a fellow streamer.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes. I stream and I started streaming because I met him basically.
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of, but I don't do the politics.
SPEAKER_0:  I do like travels.
SPEAKER_0:  or talk about relationships.
SPEAKER_0:  to my audience basically.
SPEAKER_1:  You're from that part of the world, right? Sweden. Yeah. So did you escape from prison and they didn't?
SPEAKER_0:  That was Norway. That was different.
SPEAKER_1:  really I've been to Sweden a bunch of times. I love it. There's a tech sector that that's really
SPEAKER_1:  Like flourishing. Where did you go?
SPEAKER_1:  Which city? Stop.
SPEAKER_1:  I think I gave a few lectures there. There's a vibrant tech sector, it was cool. And people are super nice.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  We're friendly. We're not like very deep. Like we're not really how much deep conversation is like a meadow.
SPEAKER_1:  There's not many intellectuals that come from Sweden.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't really speak very highly of ourselves, we kind of like just chill all the time. We don't make a scene, we don't, we're just like...
SPEAKER_0:  You know
SPEAKER_0:  Do you know what the name for that is? There's a specific name for it. Jan Delagen. Yeah, Delagen. Yeah, Jan Delagen, yeah. Oh, there's a philosophy behind it. When you're part of Sweden or Norway, you don't talk too highly of yourself because it's seen as kind of rude. Think of America except the exact opposite. You don't even really wanna make yourself into a victim too much. You don't wanna be too much of anything. You're just sticking to the group. So make big scene about yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  But that said, you came.
SPEAKER_1:  here.
SPEAKER_1:  and you were you put yourself in front of the camera and
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, do you understand how weird that is for my friends in Sweden?
SPEAKER_0:  I just didn't talk about myself and just like make a big deal about myself for hours every day. Was that like terrifying?
SPEAKER_1:  And did you have anxiety about that? No.
SPEAKER_0:  because I don't see them but then I come back and I'm like ooh.
SPEAKER_1:  Also, what do you feel like when you're actually streaming? Do you feel like you're just alone in a room?
SPEAKER_1:  and one and one two
SPEAKER_0:  No, I see I see Chad I'm thinking other like a little fairies. They're not really real. They're just like out there I don't know what they look like. I just see little names and they're just cute just colors, you know
SPEAKER_1:  talking a little fairies and
SPEAKER_0:  That's what I do. Is that how you feel, Boy Chat? They're demons for me. They're demons? My Anna Farries.
SPEAKER_1:  Are they so as chat a source of stress or happiness like.
SPEAKER_0:  Is there a community? No, for me, that's a source of happiness. I've been very intentional with the construction of my community, so I'm really happy with where it's at.
SPEAKER_0:  How are you able to actually have-
SPEAKER_1:  of deep political discourse while playing a video.
SPEAKER_0:  game at the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  I have a really good chat room.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of like the way that people engage in conversations. Like I was one of the earliest people to embrace the philosophy of like, I am in total control of what.
SPEAKER_0:  people watch me think?
SPEAKER_0:  that I have a high level of responsibility for how they conduct themselves, and that if I conduct myself in a certain way, I can expect a certain level of conduct from them. And for the most part, it's worked pretty well for the past.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, nine or 10 years, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  What about the actual playing of the game? Like you're able to parallelize the brain like.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess seems like Factorio seems like a super complex game.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I don't actually think that's possible. I don't think multitasking for a human brain is possible.
SPEAKER_0:  If you see me playing a game, usually what's happening is the conversation is like, I've had it a million times, so I'm not thinking about it, I've automated that. Or if the conversation is very challenging, then if you really watch what's happening again, I'm probably just running around in circles, because I have to think about the conversation. Okay, because with...
SPEAKER_1:  It looks like a lot of stuff is going on. Sometimes, yeah. So it's hard for.
SPEAKER_1:  a person who hasn't played the game to detect that you're not actually...
SPEAKER_0:  like you're super intelligent and multitask or does it come off as like he's not interested in this conversation at all.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Yeah, there's a coolness.
SPEAKER_1:  like when you're not paying attention.
SPEAKER_1:  like.
SPEAKER_1:  If you're looking elsewhere, like you're checking your phone, you're too cool for this conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, the reality is though, is if you watch, it was easier to see in Minecraft, because in Minecraft when there was a challenging conversation, if you watch me play, I'm literally just running around and jumping in circles, because I have to think about the conversation 100%. I can't do a complicated task and think about the conversation. Or like the people always joke in my chat like, oh no, the notepad came out. If it's a really challenging conversation, I'll get rid of the game and I'll bring out a notepad and I'll start writing stuff down to keep track of what's going on.
SPEAKER_1:  So what kind of stuff do you stream? So advice?
SPEAKER_0:  You talk about relationships. Yeah, like either I talk to chat or I travel around, basically.
SPEAKER_0:  I encourage you.
SPEAKER_0:  have a conversation so we like go to countries. I've been to like Italy, I was in Italy for like...
SPEAKER_0:  one and a half months just like traveling around alone.
SPEAKER_0:  Going to cities, like.
SPEAKER_0:  having like my camera with me and like streaming.
SPEAKER_0:  powers.
SPEAKER_1:  Where's the coolest place you've been to?
SPEAKER_1:  ever
SPEAKER_0:  It's probably New Zealand. New Zealand? No.
SPEAKER_0:  After it is probably going to be Italy, I think. Because I like history.
SPEAKER_1:  Also both history because New Zealand is also beautiful.
SPEAKER_1:  It was both natural beauty and historical beauty.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  For sure. I think I just really like the Polynesian sort of culture. I think it's very interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  like the ocean people and it's just really beautiful. People are very relaxed, chilled, they're very far away.
SPEAKER_0:  which is interesting as well, because whenever they talk about politics, so they talk about...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  It's like the world, it feels really far away.
SPEAKER_1:  So where's home for you? Is Austin home?
SPEAKER_1:  Did you? It's home for me. A human being.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, we travel we've lived in a lot of places and traveled around
SPEAKER_1:  So that's what you think of home is like
SPEAKER_0:  I think so, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, if they're gonna be a place, it's probably gonna be like my childhood places, probably.
SPEAKER_0:  Like my old country house or something like that. We don't have it anymore, but...
SPEAKER_0:  Like that's like home for me, I guess.
SPEAKER_1:  So how'd you guys meet each other?
SPEAKER_1:  You're currently married.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  to each other, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. To each other. Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  than healthy food.
SPEAKER_0:  Just making sure we're on the same page. Bym intensifies
SPEAKER_1:  cool.
SPEAKER_1:  How'd you guys meet?
SPEAKER_0:  I was watching his YouTube stuff, like...
SPEAKER_0:  2018, I think, because it was the Swedish election around that time and I was interested in politics.
SPEAKER_0:  And then, um...
SPEAKER_0:  I think he said in one of his videos that he had an Instagram.
SPEAKER_0:  and that he needed people to stop DMing him.
SPEAKER_0:  that wasn't cutipies. And then I messaged him and said, am I a cutipie? And then you're like, two minutes.
SPEAKER_0:  And then that's when I was in New Zealand.
SPEAKER_0:  And I guess you wanted to escape America or like LA for a little bit.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Where were you mentally there?
SPEAKER_1:  because we've talked to this timeline.
SPEAKER_1:  Where's 2018?
SPEAKER_1:  Was it 1819?
SPEAKER_1:  Where is the low point?
SPEAKER_0:  or something a little pic car incorrect finale
SPEAKER_0:  2010. Oh, okay. 2018 was probably your peak.
SPEAKER_0:  Every day, now is my peak. What do you mean? That was my peak. Say that.
SPEAKER_1:  Nobody ever admits being past their prime.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I mean, my friend was... Okay, it was around, it was probably around the time where you were getting a lot of lefties through your community and you were really like thinking about that they would go too far. Maybe that was, I think that was still when Hasan and Vash were both in my community. Exactly. So I would say it feels like there was not really like much issues when it come to like to your stuff or like your work stuff back then. Oh, something we didn't talk about is that like, there were no politics on Twitch. I exclusively inhabited that.
SPEAKER_0:  for like two years because nobody else did it because it was a really toxic environment for politics so for a couple of years as it grew like the I kind of grew the whole space because it wasn't nobody was doing it yet what did that look like
SPEAKER_1:  like you're having.
SPEAKER_1:  political debates, political.
SPEAKER_0:  discourse. Yeah, mainly like going into YouTube people to try to argue with them or just doing politics on stream like reading stories, researching stuff, talking about stuff. But there's not like other people on Twitch to debate about politics because there was no politics. It was, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Was there a debate?
SPEAKER_1:  in the space of communism, socialism, social democrat.
SPEAKER_1:  Democrats.
SPEAKER_1:  Are you trying to outline your own position during that time?
SPEAKER_0:  I think it was mainly me fighting against conservatives because it was like Trump stuff. And then it was coming off the back of like, there was this movement called Gamergate and there was all this anti-SJW stuff on the internet. And I was like the SJW, like the progressive that was fighting on the progressive side of things. So I think that's what I was known for. But I was fighting with people off of Twitch because on Twitch there weren't very many political discussions happening.
SPEAKER_1:  So you were holding the SJW flag. Yep.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  To what degree do you still hold it? What's the best? The Steelman case for SJW.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, like, I'm still very much that SJW from 2018, 2019, but the positions have moved so much farther left that some people might not call me that anymore, I'm not sure. That's not who I'm talking to.
SPEAKER_1:  basically what is social justice for you?
SPEAKER_1:  being sensitive to the experience of others.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, being sensitive and empathetic towards the experience of others and then trying to build a better world that suits as many different types of people as possible.
SPEAKER_0:  while being aware of their names.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  So you guys met what's your from your perspective is that did she she she telling lies is it accurate? No, it's pretty accurate Okay, when'd you guys actually meet?
SPEAKER_0:  I flew out in 2019. 19, yeah, like in February. Yeah, basically there was like weird stuff happening in LA. I just come off of kind of a weird, not kind of sort of relationship and I just wanted to like go away for a while. Another company reached out to me and they had like a fun streaming device and they said they'd sponsor a trip if I went somewhere. And I was like, oh, well, I know this person. I know a couple of people in New Zealand. Malina is one of them. It's like, I'll go to New Zealand. It'll be fun.
SPEAKER_0:  And yeah, I did that for two weeks.
SPEAKER_0:  Believe in love?
SPEAKER_0:  Hehehehe
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like you're, you lack the gotcha got us into this. I'm not sure.
SPEAKER_0:  to which you have human emotions. I have quite a few.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  From your perspective, when did you fall in love with Meli Mel?
SPEAKER_0:  the minute I saw her.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, our first two weeks together were a lot of fun. We had a lot of chemistry in person.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I was kind of shocked that I wasn't thinking about it. Cause it was like, we spent like a week together and you said, I really want to tell you something. And you were like stalling that for the longest time. I think she was.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, he said that like, I love you. No, he basically just said like.
SPEAKER_0:  I really like you and it never really happens. That's what he said. I was like, oh, and I thought, hey, I thought.
SPEAKER_0:  But let's still run, we said Trump getting banned from Twitter, is that what we were talking about before?
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, yeah. Hey, you agree to me coming on here. Of course, I'm going to be doing this.
SPEAKER_1:  So how long did that take? Two weeks you said?
SPEAKER_0:  That took like a week. No, I don't know. I think it was just like. The thing is my mind processes information so quickly. Two weeks to somebody like you is actually like years for me.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, like me. Yeah. So there was like a lot of like.
SPEAKER_1:  factorial type of strategic.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, going on.
SPEAKER_0:  I was seeing like all the events.
SPEAKER_0:  like Doctor Strange or whatever in the Avengers when he's like singing to all the futures. Also when you saw me, you just saw the future. Yeah, I was looking at all. Hamilton, you know, we got theinota don' Hey,
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, you're doing like some game theoretic simulation of all the possible outcomes. Exactly. Okay
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  But no, yeah, it was probably pretty soon I realized that we had a lot of chemistry. I think before I left after my two weeks there, I was like, we need to make sure you get like a ticket to come visit me in the United States because it'll be fun and everything. And then I kind of decided that last minute too. It was like really like five hours before your flight back. We kind of realized because it was kind of like men is just like a one time thing and then.
SPEAKER_0:  That was it, but we were like, oh no, this is a lot of fun, we should probably hang out again.
SPEAKER_1:  So you realize you...
SPEAKER_1:  miss each other.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  the melancholy side of love. Okay, when did you fall in love with a student?
SPEAKER_0:  I thought he like hated me. I don't know. I thought not hated me. She still thinks I hate her. But I know.
SPEAKER_0:  No, I remember what he said that he really liked me. I was kind of a little shocked about that, because I-
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, there was a lot of random things happening in New Zealand. It was a lot of fun, but it was definitely very interesting things that happened.
SPEAKER_0:  because I was around a lot of other people as well, so I thought he might have had a really bad time.
SPEAKER_0:  But when he said that I was thinking about it more and then we spent like...
SPEAKER_0:  more time together like a week after that and then it felt like that was more like real.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think when he was about to leave, I kind of realized like, no, I really like him.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you guys ever?
SPEAKER_1:  say love to each other, like I love you.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, of course.
SPEAKER_0:  Why would you ask that? What is he saying?
SPEAKER_1:  Because I haven't I don't think I've heard you
SPEAKER_1:  The only time I've heard is to talk about love is when you're like criticizing the the red pill community saying they don't ever talk about love and relationships
SPEAKER_0:  Almost all the time I'm giving criticism to people, like I said, I'm kind of stepping in. I'm very disconnected from my own emotional experience because...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm trying to talk within there, so it's pretty rare that I'll talk about-
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  experience exactly.
SPEAKER_1:  Highly blunted, I guess. There's a lot, okay. What does that mean? I mean, what's deep in there? Is this just who you are genetically or are you running for?
SPEAKER_0:  something.
SPEAKER_0:  I think I have a pretty good understanding of myself. A lot of people make that accusation of me, but I don't think I am.
SPEAKER_1:  This is just who you are. This is just who I am, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  There's not childhood stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  Like trauma.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, it's all sorted.
SPEAKER_1:  You figured it all out? Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  in your old age?
SPEAKER_0:  As I grow every year, I figure out more and more. He didn't mention.
SPEAKER_1:  I think I heard this somewhere that this is a source of fights for the two of you, the H thing.
SPEAKER_1:  I felt the ageism throughout this whole conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  He's basically, he's saying that he gambles like with time. He's just like, I think she will be good later. And then just like, it's like an investment. Yeah. That's like what he's doing. When this treasury bond matures, I'm going to be able to cash out for a good. What do you think so far? Is the stocks going up or? He bought all but he's right.
SPEAKER_0:  It's tumultuous. What's that mean? It's like Bitcoin. Oh my god. Like Bitcoin.
SPEAKER_0:  Crypto mail.
SPEAKER_1:  All right, if you guys don't mind.
SPEAKER_1:  One interesting aspect of your relationship is you're in an open relationship.
SPEAKER_1:  What's that like?
SPEAKER_1:  from a game theoretic simulation perspective, what went into that calculation?
SPEAKER_1:  And like, how does that? Like how that started or? Yeah, how did that start? Sure.
SPEAKER_0:  The only relationships I've ever done has been open relationships since I was like in high school.
SPEAKER_0:  because I didn't really understand, like, why wouldn't you be able to, like...
SPEAKER_0:  do other things with other people, but then just like have your main partner basically.
SPEAKER_1:  So what is an open relationship, generally speaking? That means you have one main partner.
SPEAKER_0:  not a monogamous relationship, like you're somehow allowed, like in...
SPEAKER_0:  different ways you can see other people sexually.
SPEAKER_1:  sexually, but like, there's one main.
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't have to be there for some people, but I think it's probably easier and we probably don't really have time or the energy for like more than...
SPEAKER_0:  like one person to like really like.
SPEAKER_0:  What about like emotional?
SPEAKER_0:  It's really complicated, there's a lot of complicated stuff going on under the hood there.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I think broadly speaking, you've got polyamorous relationships and you've got open relationships where polyamorous is like, oh, I've got three different girlfriends and we all hang out or sometimes even live together or three boyfriends or whatever. And then you've got open relationships, which is like, oh, you can basically hook up with other people. Then you've got like your main relationship and that's it.
SPEAKER_0:  I think ours is probably somewhere in the middle of that.
SPEAKER_0:  to where we've got long-term friends, some of them we hook up with, and that's how we, yeah, it's a delicate dance that-
SPEAKER_0:  explodes every six months on its own. Does it explode? You guys fight over it?
SPEAKER_0:  We fight over some things, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's mostly because a lot of people can't handle it.
SPEAKER_0:  and they agree to something and then they realize they're way too cool. And then they get really obsessed and they think that they can like...
SPEAKER_0:  Get in there and then it gets really dramatic.
SPEAKER_1:  Have you figured it out?
SPEAKER_1:  Mike.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like we figure out things more and more like when it comes to like what's a good person for us to hang out and what's not a good person for us to hang out with or
SPEAKER_0:  Like I probably have more opinions on like who he hangs out with because he likes the fucking psychos.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so you...
SPEAKER_0:  You like this, right?
SPEAKER_0:  He likes the crazy ones, like the baby trap sort of women. That's the ones. And I don't like that because that affects me.
SPEAKER_1:  that affects your game theoretic right.
SPEAKER_1:  You like to surround yourself, like in general you've talked about.
SPEAKER_0:  with crazy people.
SPEAKER_0:  I say crazy and I really shouldn't. It's humorous. It's like, yeah. They're very unstable. Very, can be unstable, but people that are very unique.
SPEAKER_0:  Like when I meet this person, that's like... Not boring. Yeah, not boring.
SPEAKER_1:  and you said that you're progressively becoming.
SPEAKER_0:  Not boring yourself. No, I think I'm pretty stable. I don't let them affect me much.
SPEAKER_0:  So you don't think they affect your... No, if I've said that, I've said a joke. I think I've got my stuff really well figured out. It's what allows me to engage with people like this so easily because I can engage, I can make them feel seen and heard, and then if it gets insane, I can cut off and I can be chill. Very few things affect me in the long term. You guys experience jealousy?
SPEAKER_0:  Usually like whenever I feel like he's not spending the like the amount of time that I'm asking for and he spends it on his Video games or his stream or like he sees someone else like more than he sees me or something like that That would like not be good because then it effects like are really
SPEAKER_1:  relationship.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you have a good sense of like?
SPEAKER_1:  Is it literally time or is it?
SPEAKER_1:  the energy put into the...
SPEAKER_0:  It's probably like if he's with me.
SPEAKER_0:  that like the attention in the time like when he hangs out with me and then there's also probably the time. So if I feel like something else is distracting too much, like it could be work or it could be a friend or it could be anything.
SPEAKER_0:  Like if I feel like it starts to take away from like me.
SPEAKER_0:  then I'm having an issue with it.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think he really cares much. I guess the only jealous that you experience is probably when you feel like, um,
SPEAKER_0:  Like, if I get upset about him seeing someone too much.
SPEAKER_0:  and then I go see someone more. And then he's like, why can I go see my friend more, like as much as you? So like, that's the sort of like.
SPEAKER_0:  thing that we're trying to navigate on I guess.
SPEAKER_0:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  I think we are diametrically opposed sometimes in terms of how we view engagement with people or engagement with the world sometimes. So like on her end of the spectrum, like...
SPEAKER_0:  Perfect.
SPEAKER_0:  weak for her might be like
SPEAKER_0:  being in a cabin.
SPEAKER_0:  watching like Fireflies at night.
SPEAKER_0:  going hiking every morning, going swimming at the beach, because it's like you're taking in like the grandeur of nature, you're like connected with yourself, you're like very at peace, everything is like chill and cool, there's the wind, the feeling of nature, everything, that's like her peak living experiences. I like being present. Yeah, and like my peak experiences are like people trying to destroy my life, like the challenge of like navigating really complicated discussion, like, you know, several different dramatic events unfolding in my career, like these things are like very, I like the stress and the action and the entertainment and everything's like very cool for me. So when we're together.
SPEAKER_0:  She generally wants me to be more chill, but if I don't feel like I'm being stimulated a lot, then it's easy for my mind to wander. To wander somewhere else. That's kind of the issue. It's a very different way of engaging with a-
SPEAKER_1:  How can you find?
SPEAKER_1:  happiness and stillness.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like if we're just like aware of it and we're trying our best like whenever we like we're supposed to do this one thing so let's say that we want to go to New York and I'm like we should just like go out and do this one specific thing we try to find something that he enjoys doing like
SPEAKER_0:  Now that we're in Texas, we can go shooting or do something fun that he enjoys, then we can do it.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and then I think like.
SPEAKER_0:  Just like for me also to be aware that like when he spends a lot of time on crazy people, it's not because he like loves them or wants to be with them. It's just because he likes having his life destroyed. Like you said, which I don't really do. It's just a completely different thing. So like for me to like understand more like how he's thinking, because it's so different from mine, and for him to understand how I'm thinking about things and like what I prioritize.
SPEAKER_0:  In my life, I think that's like how we navigate.
SPEAKER_0:  But I think it's good, I think the differences can be good, like when we're finding a way, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  What I think you're.
SPEAKER_1:  You're relatable.
SPEAKER_1:  Ha!
SPEAKER_0:  I'm more of a you-miss year in the eye. I'm definitely very difficult to get along with. If you're dating me for more than a few years, you get an award for that.
SPEAKER_1:  war zone, that you've survived. Absolutely. You're like a veteran, you get medals.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's always like, I think there's probably been like six different, I don't think she says it anymore, but there are like six different times in our relationship where she's like, is it always like this? Is this actually right? And like every next year it's like... You were lying in the beginning of about, like you were lying about that. Well, it got more. You were like, no, it's just like right now I'm having a huge argument online about saying the N-word in private, and it's just going to be like this, and I'm going to be streaming 24 hours a day. And I'm like, when are you going to go to bed? It's been a week.
SPEAKER_1:  I did playing league come into into this.
SPEAKER_0:  a little bit, but I'm clean of league like six months right now.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you hate about legal aid? I never got- Bella, you hate that point huh.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of which, I-
SPEAKER_1:  my participation in League involved on the robot side. good
SPEAKER_0:  That's an improvement.
SPEAKER_1:   innovations. up.
SPEAKER_1:  Both with Starcraft 2 and League of Legends because OpenAI and DeepMind.
SPEAKER_1:  both participating in creating.
SPEAKER_0:  I was a professional circle of two players, so I remember when the AI started to play.
SPEAKER_0:  It's interesting the types of restrictions that you would have to put on like a gaming robot to make it like functional and not.
SPEAKER_0:  totally unfair to the other side.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, to make it human-like. Yeah, was that interesting to you, to see AI be able to play those video games?
SPEAKER_0:  I think in some ways people think things are more complicated than they actually are. And I think video games is one of those things where we're like, oh my god, there's like a million possibilities at every second and who knows? And it's like, no, there's like three or four things going on at any point in time. And I'm willing to bet that like an AI could probably solve some of these games like pretty easily, especially if there are no constraints on how they can.
SPEAKER_1:  Can I talk to you about relationships?
SPEAKER_1:  We already have so yeah, I know but more generally speaking we didn't get a chance to talk
SPEAKER_1:  about the Red Pill community. How so?
SPEAKER_1:  Well, first of all, what is the Replica community, the Metasphere in general?
SPEAKER_1:  I'd love to get both of your opinions on this. Sure.
SPEAKER_1:  I know, I know you're probably not as.
SPEAKER_1:  PAY
SPEAKER_1:  and that's all.
SPEAKER_0:  in a game that, like probably not as you, like as much as you, but I do have opinions. You do? Okay. I usually don't like speak out too much on it because I feel like there's like a language barrier. That's why I don't really do politics because-
SPEAKER_0:  This is my second language.
SPEAKER_1:  That's right. You have to know the
SPEAKER_1:  A little bit like that, yeah. How to use derogatory terms every other sentence.
SPEAKER_1:  so they understand you, right? beneftrALLY
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know anything about that. It's too many and I talked about it. Good. You need to be able to like...
SPEAKER_0:  speak really well for people to take you seriously.
SPEAKER_0:  I think. And like that's a thing, like if I don't have like the words and I don't have the, like I can't pronounce things correctly. Yeah. And a yes all person searching for words looks stupid. Essentially, that's how people view it. So everybody.
SPEAKER_1:  I have a podcast that people listen to and I mumble and they
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Wait, what's your first language?
SPEAKER_1:  Russian.
SPEAKER_1:  But I speak both languages horribly. I just not.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not like...
SPEAKER_1:  There is definitely a big disconnect between my brain and my mouth module.
SPEAKER_1:  Like.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not able to generate the thoughts efficiently. Like the things you're able to do, like the da da da da da da, like speak like that, I'm not.
SPEAKER_1:  It's very, very tough. Plus there's a huge amount of anxiety and social interaction that I have.
SPEAKER_1:  which makes speaking even harder.
SPEAKER_1:  Gotcha.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's tough. I understand. Sure.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay. That's it.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, the gotcha is both.
SPEAKER_1:  a symbol of compassion.
SPEAKER_1:  and derision.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm just letting you know I understand what you're saying. I'm just gonna sit there and stare at you and sound like. No, you can just say like, yeah, I get it. Yeah, I get it, gotcha. No, no, gotcha sounds, no, it's so short. It's like, say a longer sentence, but that means the same thing.
SPEAKER_0:  I understand you. Yeah, good. That's good. That's like, not-
SPEAKER_0:  You get chills, you know? You get chills.
SPEAKER_1:  You understand me. Yeah, it feels good. Yeah. I hear you. I hear you. I'm going to hold the other person's hand.
SPEAKER_0:  You gotta put in some emotion there, okay? Show that you have some.
SPEAKER_0:  I understand. Holy hoodies.
SPEAKER_1:  Goodbye.
SPEAKER_1:  Gotcha. What do you think about Red Pill?
SPEAKER_1:  What is it, first of all, for B1RN?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, the red pill community, obviously it's the matrix reference. The red pill that you take is when you realize what dating standards and norms really are in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  that men are providers and have to become some great thing to hunt and attract, you know, the woman who are just kind of there floating around looking for people to give them the most resources.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like coming to a realization of what the world of dating really is, broken away from the Hollywood standards and the romantic stuff that they try to sell you.
SPEAKER_0:  stories..
SPEAKER_1:  kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe you can kind of educate me on this.
SPEAKER_1:  but red pill used to be associated with
SPEAKER_1:  Just...
SPEAKER_1:  maybe anti-establishment use i don't know maybe maybe republican conservative you counselors
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, they use red pill a lot in like different communities. Like when you say the red pill community Yeah, that usually means dating the dating thing. But a lot of people say Trump voters. They're red pill Are you red-pilled on like politics or whatever people say stuff like that? Yeah
SPEAKER_1:  And then there's like the Manosphere, that's all the similar type of stuff. And Andrew Tate is somebody that represents kind of-
SPEAKER_1:  The Figurehead.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Manosphere of like the red pill stuff. Yeah, I would say so. I'm pretty sure.
SPEAKER_0:  Alright cool so
SPEAKER_1:  What are some ideas that they represent and what do you think about them?
SPEAKER_0:  I think they do a good job at speaking to disaffected young men who feel like the rest of the world has kind of left them behind or isn't willing to speak to them.
SPEAKER_0:  and they do identify some true and real problems.
SPEAKER_0:  Feels like on the left we have a really hard time doing like self-improvement or telling people how to better themselves. We focus too much on like structural or systemic issues rather than what can an individual do to uplift or empower themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  And it also feels like they do a good job at speaking to.
SPEAKER_0:  some of the positive aspects of masculinity, that it's okay to be like strong and brave and a soldier and a warrior and provide for your family and blah blah blah.
SPEAKER_0:  So I was thinking those are like positive messages like self-improvement and everything that come from the red pill community
SPEAKER_0:  What's the negative?
SPEAKER_0:  I think the analysis on how men and women interact is a way too transactional. All of the romanticism and love and chemistry is totally sucked out of it. Everything is very like.
SPEAKER_0:  sex based, like how do you basically have sex with the most amount of women possible and that's going to make you happy.
SPEAKER_0:  And then I think people's motivation sometimes are just spoken about in such a shallow derogatory way that I don't think is always reflective of reality. Like woman only wants you because you make six figures and you're tall and a guy only wants you because he wants to have sex with you and blah. Like it feels like there's a lot of that going on a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. And that misses some fundamental aspects about relationships, about meaningful relationships and so on.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think I've never heard red pill people ever ever talk about like meaningful relationships it's always just how to get in one or how to have sex really.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, what bothers you about?
SPEAKER_1:  some of that.
SPEAKER_1:  philosophy.
SPEAKER_0:  people that are like the red pill people. I feel like their solution is something that doesn't actually work out.
SPEAKER_0:  It works out for some people, people that makes a lot of money, is really successful in that sort of way.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's not gonna help most men out there. I feel like it's just like a pointless...
SPEAKER_0:  like speech to give to these like really lost guys.
SPEAKER_0:  and they really do believe that they can make.
SPEAKER_0:  they can become successful, they can...
SPEAKER_0:  get money and like when they get all these things they can't get girls but most of them is not going to achieve that ever.
SPEAKER_1:  to get the money part or become successful.
SPEAKER_0:  just become a billionaire, you know? and you will get all the girls, which is true, but not everyone can do that.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like when these guys are speaking to these men, there's like, we just care about these men out there. You know, they need to hear this.
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't really help a lot of them.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  It doesn't.
SPEAKER_1:  inspire them to develop compassion.
SPEAKER_1:  So it was the opposite sex, which is probably something required to have a meeting for.
SPEAKER_0:  relationship. And also like they seem to complain a lot about women.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, like only wanting men that have money and that's tall and that's muscular, whatever, you know, all those things.
SPEAKER_0:  um...
SPEAKER_0:  But they complain about that, but that's also kind of what they're trying to...
SPEAKER_0:  make the men try to do for themselves. So they kind of like fall into the same sort of behavior. And it seems like they're kind of unaware of that as well.
SPEAKER_0:  They're just playing a part of the game instead of trying to find a woman that doesn't look for those things and that are looking for
SPEAKER_0:  Not those things, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I actually would love to have-
SPEAKER_1:  straight up data.
SPEAKER_1:  on.
SPEAKER_1:  people.
SPEAKER_1:  in that world versus not in that world how often they get laid.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  like.
SPEAKER_1:  Literally, so.
SPEAKER_1:  I think for sure.
SPEAKER_1:  people in that world.
SPEAKER_1:  have fewer meaningful long-term relationships they're fulfilling actually help them succeed in life
SPEAKER_1:  that helps them be happy and content and all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  but just even the straight up, the shallow goal of getting laid.
SPEAKER_1:  I wonder.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh-huh. Because it's very possible that like just the roughness with which they...
SPEAKER_1:  uh treat intellectually women that might lead to
SPEAKER_1:  Lower success, not higher success.
SPEAKER_0:  It's very adversarial, which I think is always disappointing. Anything that talks about men and women, I think it's good to acknowledge differences, but when it becomes adversarial, especially when you talk about sex, sex is something that men are getting and it's something that women are giving.
SPEAKER_0:  And that type of like trade off and the way they talk about it is like, yeah, it sets people against each other in a really toxic way, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  Mm.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you talk to people from that world?
SPEAKER_1:  from the Red Pill World.
SPEAKER_1:  Like would you ever talk to somebody like Andrew Tate?
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yeah, if I had the chance to. I've been on the Fresh and Fit podcast three times and then I've got a friend Sneak-o who's like very red pill that stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  If I'm trying to talk to them, usually the...
SPEAKER_0:  It's kind of like approaching it like a scared cat. The first thing you have to do is like be very gentle and say like, I understand your issues. I understand your complaints. I know that you're, I'm scary because you think I'm gonna say like toxic masculinity and feminism and all these.
SPEAKER_0:  scary words at you. So the first thing is always to recognize it like a lot of what they talk about
SPEAKER_0:  there are like true aspects to what they're talking about that people on the left won't recognize. So I think it's good to acknowledge those things that like men and women are kind of different. We do look for different things in general when it comes to relationships. It's okay to say that, there's nothing bad there.
SPEAKER_0:  And then it'll usually be like, once I've got your trust and I'm in your bubble, like let's talk about the things that you want. And maybe some of the strategies that you're employing aren't necessarily gonna get you some of the things that you want. So for instance, if you're really worried about like shallow girls, like ruining your life, like Malina said, it's probably not best to build your entire worldview around trying to get shallow girls that are gonna ruin your life.
SPEAKER_0:  Like if your way of attracting a girl is to go to the gym, get a whole bunch of money, and try to like flaunt your wealth as much as possible, you're gonna be attracting the very same type of women that you're here like decrying on your stream.
SPEAKER_0:  I think we talked about that on the podcast. Like you probably want to have a woman that's going to be there if you lose your job. It's still there. Like that cares about the things that's not just your job.
SPEAKER_0:  It's more stable.
SPEAKER_1:  And also I don't
SPEAKER_1:  help you become a great man.
SPEAKER_1:  or grow, I feel like a great friendship and a partnership.
SPEAKER_1:  Like it helps you make you a better person. Some of the most successful people I know, I mean they have families and there's clearly dynamic there that's like.
SPEAKER_1:  that makes them, they wouldn't be that without. They're not an island, yeah. Yeah, and the kids actually are big.
SPEAKER_1:  part of that too, like for most people, if you're like a good parrot.
SPEAKER_1:  they make you step up somehow in life. You have to take responsibility for-
SPEAKER_1:  getting your shit together and excelling.
SPEAKER_1:  in ways that uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I guess the philosophy of the right pull does not quite get to.
SPEAKER_0:  That's always an interesting thing. I've asked that a couple of times where it's like...
SPEAKER_0:  Would you let...
SPEAKER_0:  your daughter.
SPEAKER_0:  date Andrew Tate.
SPEAKER_0:  it's always funny to watch them kind of like squirm around
SPEAKER_0:  Those answers sometimes.
SPEAKER_1:  But see if they don't have a daughter, like I don't have a...
SPEAKER_1:  daughter, I think your whole philosophy changes once you have a daughter.
SPEAKER_0:  Sure. Well, but even at that, like they can, they know that what they're answering, they feel a little bit weird about it. It's funny to watch them. Even they know it's like, ah, fuck.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, they might say like, I want my daughter to date like a high value male.
SPEAKER_1:  to the degree that he's a high value male, yes.
SPEAKER_1:  but like I don't think you'll feel that way.
SPEAKER_1:  the definition of high value changes completely. suspicious.
SPEAKER_1:  Certainly the stereotypical.
SPEAKER_1:  measures of value contribute to the calculation, but it's so much more than that. I think the chemistry of the whole thing is bigger. You've also mentioned...
SPEAKER_1:  Body count.
SPEAKER_1:  You guys.
SPEAKER_1:  Both have a high body count.
SPEAKER_1:  This body can't matter.
SPEAKER_1:  or depends.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you said, it's low in some people's eyes. It's high in other people's eyes.
SPEAKER_1:  Does body count matter in relationships? Does the past matter?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, the past matters. I don't think body count. To me, I don't really care. Not just as it is, no.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it could be. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  or the passes for your work
SPEAKER_0:  Like somebody tells me like they have a 200 body count and they're 16.
SPEAKER_0:  something's probably going on there that's not good. I was thinking about that too, like, because there could be like really young people that are having some sort of like mental problems going on. Or somebody's like 45 and they've like never had sex before, there's probably something going on, right? So it could be indicative, but if somebody's like in their 20s and they've had sex with, you know, 100 people or 50 people, whatever, it's, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  It's more experience.
SPEAKER_0:  Can we go?
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so that just represents your legs sexually open. And so it doesn't really necessarily mean any kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  Not necessarily. It could though.
SPEAKER_1:  The number alone doesn't mean anything.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you could meet a guy that's like, I just really, really like when I fuck a lot of people because it makes me so cool. You can meet someone like that, which is like, So the body count doesn't matter, but like where it comes from. Yeah, like why have you slept with the people that you slept with?
SPEAKER_1:  Does it hurt like the romantic aspect of the relationship knowing that there's a lot of people in the past?
SPEAKER_1:  Not for us, no.
SPEAKER_1:  is a part of the relationship from the method romantic.
SPEAKER_0:  For us? Yeah, I'd say so.
SPEAKER_0:  What? You come out for such a cold first.
SPEAKER_1:  No, I was just in my head thinking, I wanted to just say gotcha right there. Oh, nice. It's so judgmental.
SPEAKER_0:  I think when it comes to the sex thing, there's always like the way that I explain it is and I understand like
SPEAKER_0:  Um, I have to say this because
SPEAKER_0:  I don't advocate for what I do for everybody or what she does for everybody because obviously there's a whole bunch of
SPEAKER_0:  natural feelings of jealousy that pop up for a lot of people. But when people ask me, you know, it's always like, oh, like, isn't this like horrible that you guys are doing this and you don't love each other? From my perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  I can have sex with.
SPEAKER_0:  like any person and it can be sex like that's not like a special thing between two people in my eyes it's like anybody can have sex
SPEAKER_0:  but there are like certain activities and ways you can spend time with each other.
SPEAKER_0:  where you're like carving out these like precious little moments in time with a certain person that can do things that are special to that person. And those are the kind of like events that I remember more than anything else.
SPEAKER_0:  So like the idea of like...
SPEAKER_0:  Like, oh wow, I had sex with a person that was so special. Doesn't mean as much as like, you know, us traveling to like New Zealand or sharing some special moment, doing like some really fun activity or event or whatever. That's usually how I like it.
SPEAKER_0:  So a shared intimate moment.
SPEAKER_0:  I kind of agree, but I can definitely connect the romance with sex. Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm curious why you can't do that. That's where the red pill's right.
SPEAKER_0:  We also talked about-
SPEAKER_1:  misogyny, which is clearly the embodiment of that. What were you saying?
SPEAKER_1:  So there's a connection between romance and.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think it is because I think sex could be a lot of things.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  It's some sort of bonding.
SPEAKER_0:  I'd say in some way.
SPEAKER_0:  They say that you really like BDSM. You kind of like, you become submissive to someone or you take control over someone. It's like a very bonding like intimate moment, I'd say.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's romantic. The intimacy is romantic.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it is. If you can show yourself as really submissive or weak, or you have absolutely no control over yourself and you let someone else do it,
SPEAKER_0:  or you are the one being that, like you are the dominant for someone. I think that's a really like intimate thing because.
SPEAKER_0:  you show like the weakest part of yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  I just feel like I personally.
SPEAKER_1:  To me, some component of romantic, but to me, this is not judging to others. To me, maybe this call was brought up.
SPEAKER_1:  The romance increases.
SPEAKER_1:  If the number of intimate.
SPEAKER_1:  interactions,
SPEAKER_1:  are limited to one person.
SPEAKER_1:  For me, for some reason...
SPEAKER_1:  spreading it out.
SPEAKER_1:  decreases.
SPEAKER_1:  like, um...
SPEAKER_1:  exponentially.
SPEAKER_1:  the feeling of romance you feel.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know what that could be just like sort of having.
SPEAKER_1:  grown up in the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a kind of, there's the fairy tale stories and you're kind of maybe living through them.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, I think what you're saying is really normal. Like most people probably show that way.
SPEAKER_1:  But because you guys are able to successfully not do that, I just,
SPEAKER_1:  I want to question my own understanding of it.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, why is that? Why is that? Am I being very, um...
SPEAKER_1:  jealous for no reason like
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe you can maximize the number of intimate experiences if you just open up and let go of the jealousy.
SPEAKER_1:  I think, I feel like.
SPEAKER_0:  in Sweden, like in Scandinavia, very extremely just sexually open.
SPEAKER_0:  Like in general, we're not like super religious either. We're very like relaxed. We don't.
SPEAKER_0:  Like we don't feel bad about ourselves. It's just like a different sort of thing. And I would say like it's, we're more progressive when it comes to feminism and stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  It's more common that you will meet women with a higher body count than like when I meet like American girls, all of them have like vaginism, like super suppressed, like sexually in
SPEAKER_1:  Or did you just use?
SPEAKER_0:  They have like...
SPEAKER_0:  issues to like they can't relax during sex, which is hurts for them. Vaginismus. Vaginismus.
SPEAKER_0:  So like I meet so many girls that are having like a lot of issues.
SPEAKER_0:  with sex.
SPEAKER_0:  and they have like a very low body count because they just can't relax or-
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and usually they come from a very religious background.
SPEAKER_0:  So they have just been told like you cannot wear that. You cannot be like that. You can't like, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Like where I grew up.
SPEAKER_0:  It was not like that at all.
SPEAKER_0:  would you see it as more of like a casual thing?
SPEAKER_1:  So then you can just maximize.
SPEAKER_1:  The awesomeness is.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I guess I don't have trouble with it. Exactly. I think the important thing I think for everybody to realize is there's always pros and cons to everything.
SPEAKER_0:  Like my lifestyle, like obviously I get to have a lot of fun experiences. That's like a huge pro and that's super cool. And if you're like a more monogamy brain person, you're not going to get those experiences, but if you're a monogamy brain person, like when you're sharing that special moment in time with somebody else, like that moment could be really, really, really special because now it's the thing that you're showing yourself and opening yourself up to another person and they're only trusting you to do that. And that's like a really special thing that only the two of you are sharing with each other. So, I mean, like there's always like pros and cons to everything. Like I think we both would say like.
SPEAKER_0:  like doing an open relationship is probably not like, we would not recommend it. Yeah, I don't think we would, no.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I recently fasted for three days and I ate a chicken breast at the end of that and it was like the most delicious.
SPEAKER_1:  food I've ever eaten.
SPEAKER_1:  prove.
SPEAKER_1:  So like there's some aspect of fasting and scarcity and so on that.
SPEAKER_1:  And you have to figure out for your own psyche what...
SPEAKER_0:  It's the best. It's good to be a little bored or like not do something or like work because you can just enjoy the time when you're doing something really fun is more fun. Otherwise, you're just going to get numb.
SPEAKER_0:  in general, with everything.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I personally just never get bored.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, I guess the boring thing is exciting to me.
SPEAKER_1:  I just
SPEAKER_1:  You're like me.
SPEAKER_0:  Because everything I like is boring.
SPEAKER_1:  I gotta ask you, we talked about massaging, in the, he's trying to battle it out on the internet.
SPEAKER_1:  What's your...
SPEAKER_1:  What's your sense as a woman?
SPEAKER_1:  about the level of massaging and the internet in the streaming community and how to fight it.
SPEAKER_0:  For me, because I guess I get it every single day somehow, because I have an online, like I have a chat that goes live, right?
SPEAKER_0:  And, but I have like mods moderating that all the time, so I don't really need to see much of it. I think it's just pretty annoying because you get to like see it all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and it's become like background noise.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, a little bit and it's like the same comments over and over again. But it's usually for me, I don't personally care that much. I understand that other people do, especially when it comes into like.
SPEAKER_0:  when there's like a lot of sexism and stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  And when there's a lot of men not taking women seriously, I definitely get that. And I used to get that even more, like a few years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  with my accent and everything and I used to be blonde as well a few months ago. I feel like people wouldn't take me seriously because of that.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, that's a bit annoying.
SPEAKER_0:  but.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like it's pretty easy to see through when someone acts that way, and for me personally I don't really care, but...
SPEAKER_0:  Um, it's a bit annoying, like being online and like getting stuff every single day. Uh, I would say like the probably the worst thing is-
SPEAKER_0:  When you feel like you put in a lot of effort into some sort of work.
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone is just going to say, you just got that because you're a woman and you're attractive. And that's probably like the worst thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Is there a way to fight that, you think?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I don't think you can. I think it just comes up all the time. It's just like...
SPEAKER_0:  It is what it is, I guess. You just gotta keep doing whatever you do and not let it emotionally control you somehow. I think having more women in those spaces is always good. It's probably good, yeah. Like a lot of the guys you can tell online that they don't ever. Don't bring on the worst ones then. See, she's being, see, she just did it. She did the misogyny thing.
SPEAKER_0:  By having some bad women on, she's saying all women, see? Well, you know it's true.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_1:  Simply I disagree with you and I'm older than both of you and therefore wiser, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So we'll combine we're older than you. Thank you.
SPEAKER_0:  The combined wisdom. Yeah, we've got combined age.
SPEAKER_0:  It could be the same thing, also the age thing and the woman thing. A lot of people think that I'm just copying every single thing that he says, which I think is a bit annoying as well. I can never really like... A sonic user of that one. Yeah, which is a bit annoying.
SPEAKER_0:  It was about the defending police. I like friendship.
SPEAKER_1:  camaraderie and love and respect, which you.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... both have had for a time and have lost and i would like you to regain it
SPEAKER_1:  Let's try to increase not decrease the amount of love in the space. What do you think about some of the harshness of his language, which we talked about?
SPEAKER_1:  our word in the past when you used n-word
SPEAKER_1:  all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  what I used to do. I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  No, like what do you think about it? Like do you give them advice? To not speak a certain way? No, like a little more civility?
SPEAKER_1:  I was just trying to get a second opinion on this.
SPEAKER_0:  Second opinion about... Normie people, non-internet people are way more extreme than... Yeah... She's way more extreme than I am. No, that's not true. Okay, so here's the thing for me, okay? I was not online until three years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  at all. Like I would watch YouTube. That's pretty much all I would do. I wouldn't do anything else. Really, I didn't.
SPEAKER_0:  I've stopped playing video games or anything.
SPEAKER_0:  sound like extremely new to everything?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  So when I came into this world and I started seeing clips from him in the past
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think I really had much of an opinion because it just sounded like it was just a different, like words that we were using, but it didn't mean anything.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what it feels like. It was just like...
SPEAKER_0:  If you're saying the R word.
SPEAKER_0:  It's because you just want to call someone stupid, but you want to like do it a little bit more. Like, but it's not like, it didn't feel like it was like a-
SPEAKER_0:  It's not like race is more like, you know, it's not agreement on this side.
SPEAKER_0:  So like if he was saying the F word because it was just like a word to like insult someone and he was like, I don't think he was ever, I don't think you were ever homophobic back in the day or anything like that. But I think it was just like a way.
SPEAKER_0:  to express yourself maybe back then? I don't know, I didn't do it. There's no videos of me or anything because I wasn't even online back then.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so my case was, I definitely don't think.
SPEAKER_1:  Steven is homophobic or as they're in those obviously.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a good heart there.
SPEAKER_1:  and a good mind. I was just saying.
SPEAKER_0:  He just likes being mean.
SPEAKER_1:  There's some you lose yourself and forget the bigger picture that...
SPEAKER_1:  He's pushing for...
SPEAKER_1:  more effective discourse on the internet. He's like an inspiration to a lot of people, especially now.
SPEAKER_1:  of like how you can use effective conversation to make for better world to tror how to define historical
SPEAKER_1:  and so on and then you lose some of that power.
SPEAKER_1:  by losing yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  in the language, just more language of emotion versus.
SPEAKER_1:  communication. I would say...
SPEAKER_0:  area.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say something that is probably recently done in that case, because it's been joking about women a lot. It's women's fault, they're bad. It's been like-
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of jokes when it comes to misogyny, I guess, in your community. And I think it's actually turned people a little bit that way. That's why we've done the recent misogyny. Yes, so I guess that's actually true because I don't think it was pretty.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think it was clear enough. I don't think it actually was. I think you did that mistake.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, but I think back then I was even saying like, Hey, you should probably not.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, you pro- you probably should not do that.
SPEAKER_0:  Because it actually is pretty hard for me because whenever I come into his commuter, like his chat...
SPEAKER_0:  People are just gonna spam, it's like a woman moment. It's a woman moment whenever I say something, it's kind of like...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's getting pretty annoying, as I said, it's just annoying when you see it every single day.
SPEAKER_0:  in.
SPEAKER_1:  There you go, wisdom from somebody younger than you.
SPEAKER_0:  wisdom can come from.
SPEAKER_0:  All kind of people. Yeah, of course. Just sometimes very limited quantities.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  and learn something from anybody.
SPEAKER_1:  What advice would you give to young people, the both of you?
SPEAKER_1:  that you have both audiences where young people look up to you.
SPEAKER_1:  in general, if you were to give advice to somebody in high school, like...
SPEAKER_1:  Haru.
SPEAKER_1:  Create a life that you can be proud of. What would you say?
SPEAKER_0:  The most important thing that I've learned is to view people as different.
SPEAKER_0:  and not better or worse?
SPEAKER_0:  And when you view people as different instead of better or worse, you learn that there's almost something you can learn from anybody.
SPEAKER_0:  Like be open and empathetic towards other people's experiences. Nobody does anything by random choice. Like there's always reasons why people act the way they do. And as long as you're willing to kind of like be open and receptive to the lived experiences of other people, you're going to be able to gather information and create like a more cohesive and better view of the world than any of your peers will.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you have any kind of advice you can give to young folks?
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like something that I see especially in America a lot is that a lot of people kind of get told what to do early on like in high school.
SPEAKER_0:  They're supposed to become this thing.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... like education wise like they're supposed to become a doctor or this thing or whatever and they can just like give up on things that they're actually passionate about
SPEAKER_0:  So I think a lot of teenagers get really confused. They get an education and then they get that job and they hate everything and they think that...
SPEAKER_0:  when they're reaching the job, when they're reaching the journey, they're gonna get happy. That's where the happiness is gonna be. But then when they-
SPEAKER_0:  to there.
SPEAKER_0:  They just hate everything and then they become really depressed. And I've seen this so much. Like I see this all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's...
SPEAKER_0:  Pretty sad to me to see.
SPEAKER_0:  so many people that are just wasting time and then they just get really confused and...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, it's the same thing with relationships too, no one really knows what they want anymore. I feel like everyone is just kind of doing whatever like society is saying, or their parents are saying, or their friends are saying.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And they're never really doing anything that's super meaningful anymore. And like they don't...
SPEAKER_0:  So what I would say is try to find something that is important to you. It could be anything really, like some sort of passion, maybe like your friends, maybe like.
SPEAKER_0:  Like what matters to you? And like figuring those things out, I think is really important.
SPEAKER_1:  comes from being able to listen to like some inner voice.
SPEAKER_0:  It's really hard because you're living the life and like there's things happening around you. People tell you what to do and what not to do and you know.
SPEAKER_0:  No one really has their own opinions. Everyone is just kind of like.
SPEAKER_0:  listening to the cooler thing or you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Except Steven, he seems to stay on his own.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I'd say so. Something I realized too, because we just went to TwitchCon and we were talking to a lot of streamers.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... it was interesting i i thought it was interesting because the
SPEAKER_0:  The few people that I feel like I, that seemed really cool and that I look up to, like in the streaming world.
SPEAKER_0:  All of them wants to quit streaming.
SPEAKER_0:  All I want to do is do it. No one wants to do it. That's all I said.
SPEAKER_0:  and they're so successful.
SPEAKER_0:  Like they are around successful people. They're working every single day. They're working hard. They're making so much money.
SPEAKER_0:  and everyone is just complaining and like they're complaining about um
SPEAKER_0:  Like not being able to see their partner or, you know, because they need to live somewhere else. And I see these things and they seem extremely unhappy. But it's so hard for them to just cut all their success.
SPEAKER_0:  off because that's like what you...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, learn.
SPEAKER_0:  to do.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's like supposed to be like your happiness, but it isn't. Everyone is really unhappy.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, there's something about...
SPEAKER_1:  maybe streaming is different, but YouTube folks too have interacted with a few.
SPEAKER_1:  even in podcasting space.
SPEAKER_1:  People become obsessed about the views and numbers and subscribers and stuff like that.
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  So I turned, I never.
SPEAKER_1:  talk about that. I don't pay attention to that.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like that's a drug that destroys.
SPEAKER_1:  Your mind.
SPEAKER_1:  your mind as an artist, the ability to create truly unique things.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll see your mind in terms of the anxiety the ups and downs of the
SPEAKER_1:  attention mechanism.
SPEAKER_1:  uh and then also being
SPEAKER_1:  Just.
SPEAKER_1:  If something that you make is not popular but it meant a lot to you, you will think of it less.
SPEAKER_1:  because it's not popular. That's a really dangerous thing and because
SPEAKER_1:  Everyone around you is reinforcing. Like I'll get messages like.
SPEAKER_1:  Wow.
SPEAKER_1:  this thing got this many views or something.
SPEAKER_1:  Great job.
SPEAKER_1:  No, you don't get it. Like that's not, that's not.
SPEAKER_1:  Everyone is enforcing this language of views and likes and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's correlated of course, because truly impactful things will get a lot of attention.
SPEAKER_1:  often.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not on the individual local scale.
SPEAKER_1:  like temporarily is.
SPEAKER_1:  It can really fuck with your mind. I see that in the creators they become...
SPEAKER_1:  Oh
SPEAKER_1:  Addicts to the algorithm
SPEAKER_0:  lost and chasing views. Like we know friends that we know cool people and then they start streaming and eventually they go they're like chasing the dragon of like
SPEAKER_0:  And they change, like, yeah, it's like hard to engage for them anymore. This is something I've always said that, like, one of the-
SPEAKER_0:  biggest blessings and biggest curses of humanity is we are very good at acclimating like you can become paralyzed you can have all sorts of horrible things happen to you and you'll get used to it and you'll be okay you're gonna have like a good baseline but it works the other way too and that you can get more and more and more and more and you acclimate to it almost immediately there's like
SPEAKER_0:  This is a phenomenon that I bet it happens in the YouTube world, but I know what happens in the streaming world where you're streaming 1,000 viewers every day, huge event happens and you blow up and you got like 15,000 viewers for a day or two. And then it starts to go down and down and down and down and down. And then after all the drama stayed off,
SPEAKER_0:  you're at like 3000 concurrent viewers.
SPEAKER_0:  Now in the macro, you went from 1000 to 3000. That feels awesome.
SPEAKER_0:  but you actually feel like shit the whole time because you're remembering when you had 10 or 15,000 and now everything feels horrible. And you'll see people climb over time. They're like, fuck, like, but whatever that one huge stream I had, like, I've never been able to, and it's like, dude, you're doing great. Yeah, that happens a lot. There's so many people that we know that we find super, super cool. They're passionate about things. They have so much interest.
SPEAKER_0:  And then they just get like so addicted to these numbers and like all the...
SPEAKER_0:  Everything is just ruined, like all the cool things about them is ruined because they stop doing the things that they actually like.
SPEAKER_0:  to do something else that gives them more viewers and more money. And it's really sad to see. that that
SPEAKER_1:  a sacrifice that seems...
SPEAKER_1:  Temporary is that it it actually destroys you like for one time making a choice. I come across those choices often like
SPEAKER_1:  I can do this. You can kind of know.
SPEAKER_1:  what's going to be popular and not.
SPEAKER_1:  And you have to ask yourself the question, like, is this going to sacrifice?
SPEAKER_0:  Because if people are sacrificing intimate relationships, they're sacrificing time with their family, they're sacrificing time with things that they feel good about and that they like.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  That's something I kind of realized last year.
SPEAKER_0:  I was working so much and I was just grinding and grinding and grinding because it was kind of new for me and then new years came by and I was like wait what did I even do like the entire year?
SPEAKER_0:  like I travel to a bunch of places.
SPEAKER_0:  But nothing actually really meant anything to me because I felt like I was just working the entire time. I felt like I was just numb through the entire year and that was really scary.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Like I rendered a...
SPEAKER_0:  Like a super pretty house, like for a week, with my dad and my sister, because I wanted to spend time with them.
SPEAKER_0:  But the entire time I was just streaming.
SPEAKER_0:  and I actually didn't ever like calm down and just like chill with them. And I like, that's like time I'll never get back.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't give a shit about the money that I made that week, but I lost the time.
SPEAKER_0:  And like that is really important to me. And yeah, and a lot of people are doing that. And I feel like, as you said, like you can definitely see that in like artists.
SPEAKER_0:  for sure. I feel like if you look at like artists like back in the 60s or 70s, I feel like things were just so much better back then. And it feels like they were actually making music.
SPEAKER_0:  that meant something to them. They were actually making art.
SPEAKER_0:  And I feel like today everything is just kind of like whatever is cool, whatever sells, whatever, you know, sounds in a certain way. Everything is kind of the same thing. And everything that is very artistic and very cool is actually not that popular.
SPEAKER_0:  at all.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's kind of sad.
SPEAKER_1:  I think. Yeah, of course there's now bigger mechanisms platforms to spread.
SPEAKER_1:  Stuff Music
SPEAKER_1:  So as long as you can be content with not being popular.
SPEAKER_1:  I think you can still create.
SPEAKER_0:  But not like when people get a little popular they get addicted to that so fast.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, that's weird.
SPEAKER_1:  You have been somewhat good, at least from my outsider perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  Because I think you...
SPEAKER_1:  I can at least imagine you making choices that could make you more popular.
SPEAKER_1:  and you don't seem to make those choices.
SPEAKER_0:  Like having orbits of prop line. But it is very intentional, like you said. And I made that choice at every single...
SPEAKER_0:  stage of my life.
SPEAKER_0:  One is because from the perspective of being a carpet cleaner, my life is way better than that.
SPEAKER_0:  was or ever would have been. So I'm already doing way better than I ever thought. Somebody like me ever could be. But then too.
SPEAKER_0:  I
SPEAKER_0:  Super love my job.
SPEAKER_0:  Every time I wake up, every time I fly to a place to do a podcast, every time I get to talk to really cool people, like every single part of my job, I super like. If there's something I don't like, I just cut it off because I don't care. Because I'm already making plenty of money doing what I do. And why would I ever wake up and not like what I'm doing when I can like what I'm doing?
SPEAKER_1:  How do you guys find through that?
SPEAKER_1:  given that.
SPEAKER_1:  you love it and sometimes maybe lose yourself in the drug of it. How do you
SPEAKER_1:  find.
SPEAKER_1:  like work life balance together inside a relationship.
SPEAKER_1:  like time for each other.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't at all so I'm not a good person to ask.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you love more, Mel or Fector?
SPEAKER_0:  Factor is a really good game. That's like not a fair comparison, okay? You're talking about one of the best, cleanest games, best support ever made, cleanest code base. Yeah, this is.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's more factorial time for me.
SPEAKER_1:  starting to understand where the massaging comes from. By the way, is the Inspector legit a really good game? Yeah, of course.
SPEAKER_0:  See you on call.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're like, do you enjoy programming?
SPEAKER_1:  Of course, that's all I do. That's all that's...
SPEAKER_1:  Programming is...
SPEAKER_1:  is the game in itself that I enjoy probably more than anything else. But yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  very much a game like that. If you're into stuff like that, you can lose hundreds of hours very quickly too. You have a problem and then you think of a solution and then you iterate on that over and over and over again in larger, larger schemes. Sometimes you gotta redesign stuff, sometimes you gotta, it's very much like that kind of game. See us on video.
SPEAKER_1:  building a factory like what on a foreign planet or something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, it's like a bunch of you're trying to automate different problems so that you can build bigger things so that you can automate bigger problems. So you can build bigger things and automate bigger problems.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's more complicated than like a city building game, like some city type of thing.
SPEAKER_0:  I wouldn't say it's more complicated, it's more like, it's like, Factorio is like a game of like, logic.
SPEAKER_0:  Like strictly like logic, like.
SPEAKER_1:  almost like a building a circuit.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, yeah, there's like there's circuitry and you've got your an or exorga to like there's stuff like that It's very much like that like what are the enemies?
SPEAKER_1:  in the game.
SPEAKER_0:  Like what? Um, they're like, so
SPEAKER_0:  try to bite you and you can get guns and shoot and kill them. But it's like, I saw there's like shooting going on. Yeah, but that's like a minor, just like another problem to solve in the game, basically. Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Alright.
SPEAKER_1:  See what we do there? We just started talking about the game as we're trying.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh my God, that's like a game. OK, that's horrible. Anyway, is there.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that basically the struggle, not a thought struggle, how to get?
SPEAKER_1:  human.
SPEAKER_1:  like intimate human time.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like it was like that a little bit more in the past. I feel like it's been better.
SPEAKER_0:  Lately?
SPEAKER_0:  But I think it's because when we started dating, I wasn't streaming and I kind of just like.
SPEAKER_0:  gave up like my trip to New Zealand.
SPEAKER_0:  I give up. Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  left Sweden.
SPEAKER_0:  So it was just like.
SPEAKER_0:  in LA, which I hate. I hate LA. I don't like LA at all.
SPEAKER_0:  It's hard to make friends.
SPEAKER_0:  that are like real, that are into the same stuff as you. It was just really hard for me to connect with anyone, especially also like being a European and like being around Americans was very strange.
SPEAKER_0:  So the only thing I had when I came here was him.
SPEAKER_0:  And I didn't expect because we had like two weeks of hanging out. And like he would be in his computer sometimes and like do emails and stuff. But I wasn't thinking that he would stream like 12 hours a day. And it was pretty like it was pretty intense like in the beginning of it as well.
SPEAKER_0:  I realized it was really hard to get attention or get time because his...
SPEAKER_0:  love meter would be like full if I was just in the house. And that's just kind of like the way he is. And for me back then when I didn't have anything else to do.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  was kind of like a, it was kind of crazy for me. I feel like right now, because I do work as well and I have things going for me and I have other friends now that I'm made.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like it's a lot easier because I can definitely enjoy just being in separate rooms and just hearing them in the background is really nice. I can sit and paint.
SPEAKER_0:  and like in my room and I will do that for hours while I'm just like hearing a scream in the background. It's kinda like-
SPEAKER_0:  comforting that he's just there. It feels nice. I like it.
SPEAKER_1:  to you that's the sound of happiness.
SPEAKER_0:  Because I know he's right there. Yeah, it's nice and they'll come in and check on me sometimes. And it's kind of like, it's actually very comforting. It's very nice. I like it.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's kind of what a relationship is, like you do fun things together, you share moments together.
SPEAKER_0:  but also just like having someone like around you is really, really nice.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think that's probably.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe it's me growing up.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe that's what it is. And I start liking like the kind of, I feel like we're like an old couple. Like we're like 80 and we're just like around. We don't really have to talk much. It's nice.
SPEAKER_1:  That fills your love meter.
SPEAKER_1:  That's it.
SPEAKER_0:  I think I need both. I need both. I mean, okay. I think I need both. I need both.
SPEAKER_0:  You're making it sound like that I'm like craving like crazy time. I'm not saying anything. I haven't said a single thing at all. You're making face right now. I know exactly what you're thinking. There's so much judging going on. There's no judging.
SPEAKER_0:  No, but like we, I think whenever we do plan something out, like if we go on a trip like every other month once a month.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like usually that's enough.
SPEAKER_0:  as long as he's not playing Victoria the entire time. Like, if I feel like he's going on these trips with me and he's not...
SPEAKER_0:  like doing things with me or he's not interested in like spending time or like being present with me, then I'll feel like, I just feel like I'm just wasting time right now and then I get kind of disappointed.
SPEAKER_0:  But otherwise, I think this is fun. I think this is like spending time together. Cause we're doing something together. Yeah, it's fun. being apart of wonderful Halloween, and the candy and
SPEAKER_1:  My love meters
SPEAKER_1:  Your library is full. This is my social life.
SPEAKER_0:  We like to think about it that way, that I need a little bit more of this one thing, quality time. And he needs like almost zero quality time.
SPEAKER_0:  But like, let's say that we took away physical touch, you would probably not be very happy.
SPEAKER_1:  So you need physical touch, so it's not just back to where you are.
SPEAKER_0:  No, I'm a very cuddly person. I'm a good girl, with telly skin.
SPEAKER_0:  And then you're like, I guess like acts of service. Like if I do something for you, you get really happy. Like hot chocolate.
SPEAKER_0:  Like if I give him hot chocolate in the morning, he gets really happy.
SPEAKER_1:  The actual, it's not the hot chocolate, it's the giving of the hot chocolate. No, it's just the hot chocolate.
SPEAKER_0:  What?
SPEAKER_0:  But if she gives it to me, I didn't have to get it myself. Maybe it's just physical touch that you like. That's really nice.
SPEAKER_1:  Alright, well if you have to choose between Factorio and the drama.
SPEAKER_1:  or political discourse.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably political discourse, probably my calling.
SPEAKER_0:  I am a good factorial player.
SPEAKER_1:  What role exactly does factorial play in your streaming life?
SPEAKER_0:  Well right now it's just usually there are like these games that I play in the background as I have conversation because it's hard for me to just sit on the computer and just talk.
SPEAKER_0:  and not like be playing a game at the same time. So just something to keep me kind of like occupied.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I was gonna go buy like those little like widget things, I guess. Yeah, that's what yours is. Yeah, basically, yeah. It's like Minecraft or Factorio for me.
SPEAKER_1:  Alright.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, my love meter is full from this. Mel, thank you so much for joining us. Thank you for having me. This was really fun. You guys are fascinating human beings.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for existing.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm glad to live in a world where you exist. I can't wait to see what kind of beautiful.
SPEAKER_1:  thing you create next and the crazy kind of art that you create.
SPEAKER_1:  to the different people you interact with.
SPEAKER_1:  Destiny Stephen, you're an amazing human. Thank you so much for talking to me. It's an honor.
SPEAKER_1:  Hope to talk with you again. I'm talking to Ben Shapiro. You've given me a lot of inspiration.
SPEAKER_1:  It's an honor to talk to the Ben Shapiro of the left.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Well, thanks a lot for having me. I appreciate it.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with Destiny.
SPEAKER_1:  To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now, let me leave you with some words from Lewis Carroll.
SPEAKER_1:  It's no use going back to yesterday.
SPEAKER_1:  because I was a different person then.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for listening.
SPEAKER_1:  I hope to see you.
SPEAKER_1:  next time.