SPEAKER_1:  people all around the world, their lives have basically dependent on fossil fuels. And so the idea that we're going to get people off by making it so expensive that it becomes impossible for them to live good lives.
SPEAKER_1:  is almost morally reprehensible.
SPEAKER_0:  people who have the most basic science literacy, like who know the most about
SPEAKER_0:  greenhouse effect, they're at both ends of the spectrum.
SPEAKER_0:  of views on climate, dismissives and alarmed.
SPEAKER_1:  likely the worst effect of climate change.
SPEAKER_1:  The following is a conversation with Bjorn Lomborg.
SPEAKER_1:  and Andrew Ravkin.
SPEAKER_1:  on the topic of climate change.
SPEAKER_1:  It is framed as a debate.
SPEAKER_1:  but with the goal of having a nuanced conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  talking with each other.
SPEAKER_1:  at each other.
SPEAKER_1:  I hope to continue having debates like these, including on controversial topics.
SPEAKER_1:  I believe in the power of conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  to bring people together.
SPEAKER_1:  Not to convince one side.
SPEAKER_1:  or the other.
SPEAKER_1:  but to enlighten both.
SPEAKER_1:  with the insights and wisdom that each hold.
SPEAKER_1:  Bjorn Lomborg is the president of Copenhagen Consensus Think Tank.
SPEAKER_1:  and author of
SPEAKER_1:  Foss alarm.
SPEAKER_1:  Cool it and...
SPEAKER_1:  skeptical environmentalist.
SPEAKER_1:  Please check out his work at Lomborg.com that includes his books.
SPEAKER_1:  articles and other writing.
SPEAKER_1:  Andrew Ravkin.
SPEAKER_1:  is one of the most respected journalists in the world on the topic of climate.
SPEAKER_1:  He's been writing about global environmental change and risk.
SPEAKER_1:  for more than 30 years.
SPEAKER_1:  20 of it at the New York Times.
SPEAKER_1:  We check out his work.
SPEAKER_1:  in the link tree.
SPEAKER_1:  that includes his books, articles, and other writing.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the Lex treatment podcast to support it.
SPEAKER_1:  Please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now, dear friends,
SPEAKER_1:  Here's Bjorn Lomborg.
SPEAKER_1:  and Andrew.
SPEAKER_1:  Ravkin.
SPEAKER_1:  there's a spectrum of belief on the topic of climate change and the landscape of that spectrum has probably changed over
SPEAKER_1:  several decades. On one extreme, there's a belief that climate change is a hoax.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not human caused.
SPEAKER_1:  to pile on top of that, there's a belief that the institution, scientific, political, the media,
SPEAKER_1:  are corrupt and are kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  constructing this fabrication. That's one extreme and then the other extreme.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a...
SPEAKER_1:  a level of alarmism.
SPEAKER_1:  about the catastrophic impacts of climate change that lead to...
SPEAKER_1:  the extinction of...
SPEAKER_1:  uh... human civilization
SPEAKER_1:  So not just economic costs.
SPEAKER_1:  hardship, suffering, but literally the destruction of the
SPEAKER_1:  human species in the short term.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so that's.
SPEAKER_1:  spectrum and I would love to find
SPEAKER_1:  the center.
SPEAKER_1:  And my sense is, and the reason I wanted to talk to the two of you...
SPEAKER_1:  aside from
SPEAKER_1:  the humility with which you approach this topic.
SPEAKER_1:  is I feel like you're close to the center in our on.
SPEAKER_1:  different sides of that center.
SPEAKER_1:  if it's possible to define the center. Like there is a.
SPEAKER_1:  political center for center left and center right.
SPEAKER_1:  Of course, it's very difficult to define, but can you help me define what the extremes are again?
SPEAKER_1:  as they have changed over the years, what they are today.
SPEAKER_0:  And where's the center? Oh boy. Well, in a way on this issue, I think there is no center except in this.
SPEAKER_0:  if you're looking on social media or if you're looking on TV.
SPEAKER_0:  there are people who are trying to fabricate the idea as a single question.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's the first mistake.
SPEAKER_0:  We are developing a new relationship with the climate system.
SPEAKER_0:  and we're rethinking our energy systems. And those are very-
SPEAKER_0:  disconnected in so many ways that connect around climate change.
SPEAKER_0:  the first way to me to overcome this idea of.
SPEAKER_0:  There is this.
SPEAKER_0:  Polarized.
SPEAKER_0:  universe around this issue is to.
SPEAKER_0:  step back and say, well, what is this actually? And when you do, you realize it's
SPEAKER_0:  It's kind of an uncomfortable collision between old energy norms.
SPEAKER_0:  and a growing awareness of.
SPEAKER_0:  how the planet works, that if you keep adding gases that are invisible, it's the bubbles in beer.
SPEAKER_0:  If you keep adding that to the atmosphere because it accumulates, that will change everything is changing everything for thousands of years. That's already happening. What do you mean by bubbles and beer?
SPEAKER_0:  CO2, carbon dioxide.
SPEAKER_0:  main greenhouse gas. why beer?
SPEAKER_0:  Look, because I like beer. It's also in Coca-Cola. You were talking about Cola before.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  And so it's innocuous. We grew up with this idea as-
SPEAKER_0:  CO2, unless you're trapped in a room suffocating.
SPEAKER_0:  It is innocuous gas. It's plant food.
SPEAKER_0:  It's beer bubbles.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  the idea we can swiftly transition to a world.
SPEAKER_0:  where that gas is a pollutant.
SPEAKER_0:  Regulated.
SPEAKER_0:  tamp down from the top.
SPEAKER_0:  is fantastical. Having looked at this for
SPEAKER_0:  35 years, I brought along one of my tokens.
SPEAKER_0:  This is my 1988 cover story on global warming.
SPEAKER_0:  The greenhouse effect.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. Two years in.
SPEAKER_0: .
SPEAKER_0:  Jim Hansen, the famous American climate scientist, really, he stimulated this article.
SPEAKER_0:  by doing this dramatic testimony.
SPEAKER_0:  in a Senate committee that summer.
SPEAKER_0:  in May, actually spring, late spring.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a hot day.
SPEAKER_0:  And cut.
SPEAKER_0:  headlines and this was the result.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's complicated. Look what we were selling on the back cover.
SPEAKER_0:  What you see isn't what you get tobacco.
SPEAKER_1:  Cigarettes. Cigarettes.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Looking back at my own career on the climate question, it's no longer a belief fight over.
SPEAKER_0:  Is global warming real or not? You say, well, what kind of energy future do you want? That's a very different question then.
SPEAKER_0:  Stop global warming.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Um,
SPEAKER_0:  when you look at climate.
SPEAKER_0:  Actually.
SPEAKER_0:  I had this learning journey on my reporting.
SPEAKER_0:  where I started out with this as the definition of the problem.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  the 70s and 80s, pollution was changing things that were making things bad.
SPEAKER_1:  So really focusing on the greenhouse effect and the pollution.
SPEAKER_0:  But what I missed, the big thing that I missed of the first 15 years of my reporting from 1988.
SPEAKER_0:  through about 2007.
SPEAKER_0:  when I was, that period I was at the New York Times.
SPEAKER_0:  in the middle there.
SPEAKER_0:  was that we're building vulnerability to climate hazards at the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  So climate is changing.
SPEAKER_0:  But we're changing too. And where we are here in Austin, Texas is a great example.
SPEAKER_0:  Flash Flood Alley.
SPEAKER_0:  named in the 1920s west of here.
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone forgot about flesh floods, built these huge developments.
SPEAKER_0:  along these river basins.
SPEAKER_0:  that in one side starts saying global warming, global warming.
SPEAKER_0:  and the other side is not recognizing.
SPEAKER_0:  that we've built.
SPEAKER_0:  willfully.
SPEAKER_0:  greedily.
SPEAKER_0:  at.
SPEAKER_0:  vulnerability in places of utter hazard. Same things played out in Pakistan.
SPEAKER_0:  and in Fort Myers, Florida.
SPEAKER_0:  and you start to understand that we're creating a landscape of risk.
SPEAKER_0:  as climate is changing, then it feels, oh my God, that's more complex, right? But it also gives you more action points. Like, okay, well, we know how to-
SPEAKER_0:  design better. We know that today's
SPEAKER_0:  won't be tomorrow's coast.
SPEAKER_0:  work with that. And then let's chart an energy future at the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  So the story became so different, it didn't become like.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, a story you could package into a magazine article.
SPEAKER_0:  or the like.
SPEAKER_0:  And it just led me to a whole different way of.
SPEAKER_0:  Even my journalism changed over time.
SPEAKER_0:  So I don't fight these.
SPEAKER_0:  belief disbelief.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's actually...
SPEAKER_0:  kind of a waste. It's a good way to start.
SPEAKER_0:  the discussion because that's where we're at.
SPEAKER_0:  but this isn't about.
SPEAKER_0:  to me going forward from where we're at isn't about.
SPEAKER_0:  tipping that balance.
SPEAKER_0:  toward the center so much as finding opportunities to just do something about this stuff. What do you think Bjorn?
SPEAKER_1:  I agree that it's multiple questions in one.
SPEAKER_1:  And one big question, do you think it's possible to define the center, where is the center?
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's wonderful to hear Andy sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  Unconstruct.
SPEAKER_1:  the whole conversation and say we should be worried about.
SPEAKER_1:  different things and I think that's exact or we should be worried about things in a different way that makes it much more useful.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that's exactly the right way to think about it. On the other hand, that was also where you kind of ended.
SPEAKER_1:  We are stuck in a place where this very much is the conversation right now.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I think in one sense.
SPEAKER_1:  Certainly the people who used to say, oh, this is not happening. They're very, very small and diminishing crowd and certainly not right.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, but on the other hand, I think to an extent.
SPEAKER_1:  it increasing extent.
SPEAKER_1:  We've gotten into a world.
SPEAKER_1:  where a lot of people really think this is the end of the times.
SPEAKER_1:  So the OECD did a new survey of all OECD countries and it's shocking. So it shows that 60% of all people...
SPEAKER_1:  in the OCD, so the rich world.
SPEAKER_1:  believes that global warming will likely or very likely lead to the extinction of mankind.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's scary in a very, very.
SPEAKER_1:  clear way because look, if this really is true, if global warming is this meter.
SPEAKER_1:  hurtling towards Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  and we're gonna be.
SPEAKER_1:  destroyed in 12 years or whatever the number is today.
SPEAKER_1:  then clearly we should care about nothing else. We should just be focusing on making sure that that-
SPEAKER_1:  asteroid, we should send up Bruce Willis and get this done with.
SPEAKER_1:  But that's not the way it is.
SPEAKER_1:  This is not actually what the UN climate panel tells us or anything else. So I think...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, it's not so much about arcing against the people who are saying it's a, it's a hoax. That's not really where I am. I don't think that's where Andy or really where the conversation is.
SPEAKER_1:  but it is a question of sort of pulling people back from this.
SPEAKER_1:  end of the world conversation because it really skews our way that we think about problems. Also, if you really think this is the end of time and you only have 12 years,
SPEAKER_1:  Nothing.
SPEAKER_1:  that can only work in 13 years.
SPEAKER_1:  can be considered.
SPEAKER_1:  And the reality of most of what we're talking about in climate and certainly our vulnerability, certainly our energy system.
SPEAKER_1:  is going to be half to a full century.
SPEAKER_1:  and so when you talk to people and say
SPEAKER_1:  But we're really going to go a lot more renewable in the next half century. They look at you and like...
SPEAKER_1:  That's what, 38 years too late.
SPEAKER_1:  And I get that, but so I think...
SPEAKER_1:  in your question, what I'm trying to do, and I would imagine that's
SPEAKER_1:  for you as well is to try to pull people away from this precipice and this end of the world.
SPEAKER_1:  and then open it up. And I think Andy did that really well by saying, look, there's so many different.
SPEAKER_1:  sub conversations and we need to have all of them and we need to be respectful of, of, of some of these.
SPEAKER_1:  are right in the standard media kind of way.
SPEAKER_1:  But some of them are very very wrong and actually means that we end up
SPEAKER_1:  doing much less good, both on climate, but also on all the other problems the world faces. okay
SPEAKER_0:  And it just empowers people to, those who believe this, to even, to do true things that shouldn't be done,
SPEAKER_0:  sit back, even in Adam McKay's movie, the Don't Look Up movie.
SPEAKER_0:  There was that sort of nihilist crowd for those who've seen it.
SPEAKER_0:  who just say, you know, fuck this, we're...
SPEAKER_0:  And a lot of people have that, when something's too big.
SPEAKER_0:  And
SPEAKER_0:  it just paralyzes you as opposed to giving you these action points.
SPEAKER_0:  And the other thing is...
SPEAKER_0:  I hate-
SPEAKER_0:  I hate it when economists are right about stuff like the-
SPEAKER_0:  I... I... I...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm gonna have to help her with that.
SPEAKER_0:  No, no, there are these phrases like I never knew the words path dependency until probably 10 years ago in my reporting.
SPEAKER_0:  And basically says you're in a system.
SPEAKER_0:  the things around you, how we pass laws, the brokenness of the Senate.
SPEAKER_0:  Those are.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't have a climate crisis in America, we have a decision crisis.
SPEAKER_0:  as it comes to how the government works or doesn't work.
SPEAKER_0:  So those big features of our.
SPEAKER_0:  landscape are.
SPEAKER_0:  It's path dependency. When you when you screw in a light bulb.
SPEAKER_0:  Even if it's an LED light bulb, it's going into a 113, 120 year old fixture.
SPEAKER_0:  because, and actually that fixture is almost designed.
SPEAKER_0:  If you look at like 19th century gas fixtures, they had the screw in.
SPEAKER_0:  So we're like on this long path dependencies when it comes to energy and stuff like that.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't just magically transition a car fleet. A car built today will last 40 years. It'll end up in Mexico, sold on a used car, etc., etc.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  So this.
SPEAKER_0:  There is no quick.
SPEAKER_0:  even if we're true.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  where things are coming to an end in 13 years, 12 years or 8 years.
SPEAKER_1:  Most people don't believe that climate change is a hoax.
SPEAKER_1:  believe that there is an increase.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a global warming of a few degrees in the next century.
SPEAKER_1:  and then maybe debate about what the number of the degrees is.
SPEAKER_1:  And do most people believe that it's human cause?
SPEAKER_1:  at this time in the
SPEAKER_1:  in this history of discussion of climate change. So is that the center still?
SPEAKER_1:  Like is there still the-
SPEAKER_0:  debate on this. Yale University, the climate communication group there for like 13 years has done this.
SPEAKER_0:  Six Americas Study.
SPEAKER_0:  where they've.
SPEAKER_0:  charted.
SPEAKER_0:  pretty carefully and ways that I really find useful.
SPEAKER_0:  with people.
SPEAKER_0:  believe and we could talk about the word belief in the context of science too but
SPEAKER_0:  and they've identified kind of six kinds of us.
SPEAKER_0:  from dismissive to alarmed and with lots of bubbles in between. I think some of those bubbles in between are.
SPEAKER_0:  mostly disengage people who don't really deal with the issue.
SPEAKER_0:  And they've shown a drift for sure. There's much more majority now at the.
SPEAKER_0:  alarmed or engaged.
SPEAKER_0:  bubbles than just the dismissive bubble.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a durable, like with vaccination and lots of other issues, there's a durable never anything.
SPEAKER_0:  belief.
SPEAKER_0:  group but
SPEAKER_0:  on the reality that humans are contributing to climate change.
SPEAKER_0:  most Americans when you ask them.
SPEAKER_0:  And it also depends on how you write your survey.
SPEAKER_0:  I think there's a...
SPEAKER_1:  globally. I mean, when you ask around, I mean, and this is, you know, if you hear this story from the media of 20 years, of course, that's what you will believe. And it also happens to be.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that is what the science, I think, you know, it's perhaps worth saying, and it's a little depressing that you always have to say, but I think it's worth saying that I think we both.
SPEAKER_1:  really do accept the climate panel science. And there's absolutely global warming. It is an issue and it's probably just worthwhile to get it out of the way. It's an issue and it's caused by humans. It's caused by humans, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  But vulnerability, the losses.
SPEAKER_0:  that
SPEAKER_0:  are driven by climate-related events. Still, predominantly are caused by humans, but on the ground.
SPEAKER_0:  It's where we build stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  where we settle.
SPEAKER_0:  Pakistan.
SPEAKER_0:  I hear it.
SPEAKER_0:  In 1960, I just looked these data up, there were 40 million people in Pakistan. Today there are 225 million.
SPEAKER_0:  and a big chunk of them are still rural. They live in the floodplain of the amazing Indus River.
SPEAKER_0:  which comes down from the Himalayas.
SPEAKER_0:  extraordinary 5,000 year history of.
SPEAKER_0:  agriculture there, but when you put...
SPEAKER_0:  200 million people.
SPEAKER_0:  in harm's way. And this doesn't say anything about the bigger questions about.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, shame on Pakistan for having more people.
SPEAKER_0:  It just says the reality is.
SPEAKER_0:  the losses that we see.
SPEAKER_0:  in the news.
SPEAKER_0:  ARR
SPEAKER_0:  And the science finds this even though there's a new weather attribution group.
SPEAKER_0:  It's WXRisk on Twitter.
SPEAKER_0:  This does pretty good work on...
SPEAKER_0:  How much of what just happened was some tweak in the storm from global warming, from CO2 changing weather?
SPEAKER_0:  And the media glom onto that.
SPEAKER_0:  as I did in the 80s, 90s.
SPEAKER_0:  2000s.
SPEAKER_0:  But the reports also have a section on, by the way.
SPEAKER_0:  The vulnerability that was built in this region was a big driver of loss.
SPEAKER_0:  So discriminating between loss.
SPEAKER_0:  Change in.
SPEAKER_0:  What's happening on the ground?
SPEAKER_0:  and change in the climate system.
SPEAKER_0:  is never solely about CO2.
SPEAKER_0:  In fact.
SPEAKER_0:  Lawrence Bauer.
SPEAKER_0:  B-O-U-W-E-R.
SPEAKER_0:  has.
SPEAKER_0:  I first wrote on his work in 2010 in the New York Times. And basically...
SPEAKER_0:  In 2010, there was no sign in the data of climate change.
SPEAKER_0:  driving disasters.
SPEAKER_0:  Climate change is up here. Disasters are on the ground. They depend on how many people are in the way.
SPEAKER_0:  how much stuff you've built in the way.
SPEAKER_0:  And so far, we've done so much of that so fast in the 20th century particularly.
SPEAKER_0:  that it completely dominates, it makes it hard, impossible to discriminate how much of that disaster.
SPEAKER_0:  was from the
SPEAKER_0:  Change in.
SPEAKER_0:  weather.
SPEAKER_0:  from Global Warming.
SPEAKER_1:  So a function of...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  greenhouse gases.
SPEAKER_1:  to human suffering.
SPEAKER_1:  is a-
SPEAKER_0:  That's very much in our control.
SPEAKER_0:  Theoretically.
SPEAKER_1:  The point I think is exactly right that if you look at the Hurricane Ian that went through Florida.
SPEAKER_1:  You have a situation where Florida went from what 600,000 houses.
SPEAKER_1:  in 1940.
SPEAKER_1:  to seven.
SPEAKER_1:  13 million houses.
SPEAKER_1:  Sorry, 10 million houses, so 17 times more.
SPEAKER_1:  over a period of 80 years.
SPEAKER_1:  Of course you're gonna have, what? Yeah, yeah. You're gonna have lots more damage. And many of these houses now have been built on places where you probably shouldn't be building.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I think a lot of scientists are very focused on saying, can we measure whether global warming had an impact?
SPEAKER_1:  Which is an interesting science question. I think it's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's.
SPEAKER_1:  very implausible that eventually we won't be able to say it has an impact.
SPEAKER_1:  But the real question, it seems to me, is if we actually wanna make sure that people are less harmed in the future.
SPEAKER_1:  what are the levers that we can control? And it turns out that the CO2 lever doing something about climate is an incredibly difficult and slightly inefficient way of trying to help these people in the future. Whereas, of course,
SPEAKER_1:  Soning?
SPEAKER_1:  making sure that you have better housing rules, what is it, regulations, that you maybe don't have people building the flash flood?
SPEAKER_0:  Flat Alley. Flat Flat Alley. IoT.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just simple stuff. And because we're so focused on this one issue,
SPEAKER_1:  We sort of, it almost feels sacrilegious to talk about these other things that are much more in our power and that we can do something about much quicker and that would help a lot more people. So I think this is gonna be a large part of the whole conversation. Yes, climate is a problem.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's not the only problem. And there are many other things where we can actually have a much, much bigger impact at much lower cost. Maybe we should also remember those. Can you?
SPEAKER_1:  Steel Man the Case
SPEAKER_1:  of Greta.
SPEAKER_1:  who's a representative of
SPEAKER_1:  Alarmism.
SPEAKER_1:  that we need that kind of level of alarmism for people to pay attention and to think about climate change.
SPEAKER_1:  So you said.
SPEAKER_1:  this singular view.
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  is not the correct way to look at it.
SPEAKER_1:  climate change, just the emissions.
SPEAKER_1:  but for us to have a discussion.
SPEAKER_1:  Shouldn't there be?
SPEAKER_1:  somebody who's
SPEAKER_1:  really raising the concern.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you still man the case for alarmism, essentially?
SPEAKER_1:  Is there a better term than alarmism?
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  communication.
SPEAKER_1:  of like holy shit.
SPEAKER_1:  We should be thinking about this.
SPEAKER_1:  So I think, I totally understand why Greta Thunberg is doing what she's doing. I have great respect for her because if, I look at a lot of kids growing up and they're basically being told...
SPEAKER_1:  You're not going to reach adulthood or at least not, you're not going to get very far into adulthood.
SPEAKER_1:  And that, of course, you know, this is the meteor hurtling towards earth, and then this is the only thing we should be focusing on.
SPEAKER_1:  I understand why she's making that argument.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's.
SPEAKER_1:  At the end of the day it's...
SPEAKER_1:  incorrect and I'm sure we'll get around to talking about that. And one of the things is of course
SPEAKER_1:  her whole generation.
SPEAKER_1:  I can understand why they're saying, if we're gonna be dead in 12 years, why would I wanna study? Why would I really care about anything? So I totally want to sort of pull Greta and many others out of this end of the world fear.
SPEAKER_1:  but I totally get why she's doing it.
SPEAKER_1:  I think she's done a service in the sense that she's gotten more people to talk about climate.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's good because we need to have this discussion.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's unfortunate and this is just what happens in almost all policy discussions that they end up being discussions from the extreme groups because it's just more fun on media.
SPEAKER_1:  to have sort of the total deniers and the people who say, we're gonna die tomorrow. And it sort of becomes that discussion. It's more sort of a mud wrestling fight. So what do you think the mud wrestling fight is not useful or is useful for communication for?
SPEAKER_1:  effective science communication on one of the platforms you're a fan of which is twitter
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I wrote a piece recently on my sustain what column saying.
SPEAKER_0:  If you go in there.
SPEAKER_0:  for the entertainment value of seeing those.
SPEAKER_0:  Knockdown fights.
SPEAKER_0:  I guess that's useful if that's what you're looking for.
SPEAKER_0:  the thing I found Twitter invaluable for.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's a practice.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just like.
SPEAKER_0:  the workouts you do or, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  It's.
SPEAKER_0:  How do I put this tool to use today? Thinking about energy.
SPEAKER_0:  action in poor communities. How do I put this tool today?
SPEAKER_0:  learning about what really happened with E and the hurricane.
SPEAKER_0:  who was most at risk.
SPEAKER_0:  and how would you build that?
SPEAKER_0:  I hit build forward better, I hit build back.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Or you can go there and just.
SPEAKER_0:  Watch it as an entertainment value.
SPEAKER_0:  not going to get the world anywhere.
SPEAKER_1:  You don't think.
SPEAKER_1:  entertainment.
SPEAKER_1:  I wouldn't call it entertainment, but.
SPEAKER_1:  giving voice to the extremes isn't a productive way forward.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems to...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, to push back against the main narrative, it seems to work pretty well in the American system. We think.
SPEAKER_1:  Politics is totally broken, but maybe that works, that oscillation back and forth.
SPEAKER_1:  You need a grader and you need somebody that pushes back against a grader to get everybody's.
SPEAKER_1:  to uh...
SPEAKER_1:  to get everybody's attention.
SPEAKER_1:  the fun of battle.
SPEAKER_1:  Over time.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, and this gets to the point.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  People who focus on communication science, I'm not a scientist, I write about this stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  if you're going to try to pride someone.
SPEAKER_0:  with a warning.
SPEAKER_0:  Like...
SPEAKER_0:  This is three years apart.
SPEAKER_0:  Nuclear winner!
SPEAKER_0:  Nuclear winter, we'll talk about that. Global warming, well yeah, we'll talk about it. But look at that, this is three years apart in the covers of the magazine. Yeah. But then you have to save to what end? If you're not.
SPEAKER_0:  directing people to a basket of things to do.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you want political change, then it would be to support a politician.
SPEAKER_0:  If you want energy access, it would be to.
SPEAKER_0:  Look at this $370 billion, the American.
SPEAKER_0:  government just put into play on climate and say, well, how can my community benefit from that?
SPEAKER_0:  and I've been told over and over again by people in government.
SPEAKER_0:  Jigar Shah who heads this
SPEAKER_0:  giant loan program in the Energy Department.
SPEAKER_0:  He says, what I need now is like 19,500.
SPEAKER_0:  people who are worried about climate change.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe because Greta.
SPEAKER_0:  Cut the mortgage.
SPEAKER_0:  But here's the thing you could do. You can connect your local government right now with these multimillion dollar loans so you can have electric buses instead of diesel buses.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's an action pathway.
SPEAKER_0:  So without.
SPEAKER_0:  So, you know, alarm for the sake of.
SPEAKER_0:  getting attention or clicks.
SPEAKER_0:  to me is not any more valuable than.
SPEAKER_0:  watching an action movie.
SPEAKER_1:  And again, I think also it very easily ends up sort of skewing our conversation about what are the actual solutions.
SPEAKER_1:  Because, yes, it's great to get rid of the diesel bus, but probably not for the reason people think. It's because diesel buses are really polluting.
SPEAKER_1:  in the air pollution sense.
SPEAKER_1:  Right. And that is why you should get rid of them. Uh, and again, if you really want it to help people, for instance, with hurricanes, you should have better, you know, uh, rules and zoning in Florida.
SPEAKER_1:  which is a very different outcome.
SPEAKER_1:  The mud wrestling fight also gets our attention diverted towards solutions.
SPEAKER_1:  that seem.
SPEAKER_1:  Easy, fun, you know, sort of the electric car is a great example of this. The electric car somehow become almost.
SPEAKER_1:  sign that I care and I'm really going to do something about climate. Of course.
SPEAKER_1:  Electric cars are great and they're probably part of the solution and they will actually cut carbon emissions somewhat.
SPEAKER_1:  but they're an incredibly ineffective way of cutting carbon emissions right now. They're fairly expensive, you have to subsidize them a lot, and they still emit quite a bit of CO2, both because the batteries get produced and because they usually run off of power that's not totally clean. Strong words from your love, okay, let's go there. Let's go electric cars, educate us.
SPEAKER_1:  on the pros and cons of electric cars in this complex picture of climate change.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think of the efforts of Tesla and Elon Musk?
SPEAKER_1:  on pushing forward the electric car revolution.
SPEAKER_1:  So look.
SPEAKER_1:  Electric cars are great. I don't own a car, but I've been driving a Tesla. There you go, socially signaling. Yeah. But yeah, I've- We're in Texas. Well, I flew in here, so it's not like I'm in any way a virtuous guy on that path. But look, they're great cars.
SPEAKER_1:  and eventually electric cars will take over a significant part.
SPEAKER_1:  of our driving and that's it.
SPEAKER_1:  good because they're more effective, they're probably also going to be cheaper. There's a lot of good opportunities with them.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's because they've become reified as this.
SPEAKER_1:  thing that you do to fix climate. And right now.
SPEAKER_1:  They're not really.
SPEAKER_1:  all that great for climate. They you need a lot of.
SPEAKER_1:  extra material into the batteries, which is very polluting and it's also, it emits a lot of CO2.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of electric cars are bought as second cars in the US.
SPEAKER_1:  So we used to think that they were driven almost as much as a regular car. It turns out that they're more likely driven.
SPEAKER_1:  Less than half as much as a regular cars. So, you know, 89% of all Americans who have an electric car.
SPEAKER_1:  Also, however.
SPEAKER_1:  real car that they use for the long trips. And then they use the electric car for a short trip. 89%. 89, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  So the point here is...
SPEAKER_1:  that it's one of these things that become more sort of a virtuous signal and thing. And, again...
SPEAKER_1:  Once electric cars are sufficiently cheap that people will want to buy them. That's great. And they will.
SPEAKER_1:  Do some good for the environment.
SPEAKER_1:  But in reality, what we should be focusing on is instead of getting people electric cars in rich countries, because we're subsidizing typically in many countries, you actually get a sort of sliding scale. You get more subsidy the more expensive it is. We sort of subsidize this to very rich people to buy very large Teslas.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, to drive around in?
SPEAKER_1:  Whereas what we should be focusing on is perhaps getting electric motorcycles in third world developing cities
SPEAKER_1:  where they would do a lot more good.
SPEAKER_1:  They can actually go as far as you need. There's no worry about running out of them. And they would obviously, they're much, much more polluting, just air pollution wise. And they're much cheaper and they use very little battery. So it's about getting our senses right. But the electric car is not.
SPEAKER_1:  the cons.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not a conversation about is it technically really good or is it a somewhat good insight. It's more like it's a virtual signal. So just, I work with economists. I'm actually not an economist, but I like to say I claim I kind of am. But the fundamental point is we would say, well, how much does it cost to cut a ton of CO2?
SPEAKER_1:  And the answer is for most electric cars.
SPEAKER_1:  We're paying in the order of a thousand, 2,000. Norway, they pay up to $5,000 or thereabouts. Huge amount for one ton of CO2.
SPEAKER_1:  You can right now cut a ton of CO2 for about what is it $14 on the Reggie or something?
SPEAKER_1:  You can read it.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the regional greenhouse gas.
SPEAKER_1:  So you can basically cut it really really cheaply. Why would we not want to cut?
SPEAKER_1:  Dozens and dozens of tons of CO2 for the same price.
SPEAKER_1:  Instead of just cutting one ton and the simple answers, we only do that because we're so focused on the electric. Momentureup,
SPEAKER_1:  typical European, come here in Texas, Tomcat can't have my Ford F-150.
SPEAKER_0:  But now you can have your F-150 Lightning. That's true. That's true. I'm just joking. Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  But what do you think about electric cars? If you could just link on that moment and-
SPEAKER_1:  this particular element of helping reduce.
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you talked about the middle in the beginning and you know.
SPEAKER_0:  I loved moving through the hybrid. The Prius was fantastic. It did everything our other sedan did, but it was 60 miles per gallon.
SPEAKER_0:  performance and
SPEAKER_0:  you don't have range anxiety because it has a regular engine too.
SPEAKER_0:  We still have a Prius. We also inherited my dad, dear dads.
SPEAKER_0:  year 2000 Toyota Sienna, which is an old.
SPEAKER_0:  100,000 mile.
SPEAKER_0:  Minivan.
SPEAKER_0:  And we use it all the time to do the stuff we can't do in the.
SPEAKER_0:  in the Prius. like what wine
SPEAKER_0:  taking stuff to the dump. all I mean
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of the size.
SPEAKER_0:  the vehicle. Yeah, size and just convenience factor for a bigger vehicle.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I would love to feel fully electrified.
SPEAKER_0:  transportation world is kind of exciting.
SPEAKER_0:  I think what Elon did with Tesla, I remember way, way back in the day when the first models were coming out, it was very slick Ferrari style.
SPEAKER_0:  cars and I thought this is cool and you know there's a history of
SPEAKER_0:  privileged markets testing new technologies. And I'm all for that.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's done a huge service prodding.
SPEAKER_0:  so much more R&D.
SPEAKER_0:  And once GM and Ford started to realize, oh my God.
SPEAKER_0:  This is a real phenomenon, you know, getting them in the game.
SPEAKER_0:  There was that.
SPEAKER_0:  documentary.
SPEAKER_0:  who killed the electric car.
SPEAKER_0:  which seem to imply that.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there's...
SPEAKER_0:  there were fights to keep this tamped down.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's...
SPEAKER_0:  It's fundamentally cleaner, fundamentally better. If
SPEAKER_0:  But then you have to manage these bigger questions.
SPEAKER_0:  We're going to do a build out here.
SPEAKER_0:  How do you make it?
SPEAKER_0:  Fair.
SPEAKER_0:  as you were saying, who actually uses transport cars?
SPEAKER_0:  And Jagir Shah, that guy at the energy department I mentioned, who has all this money to give out.
SPEAKER_0:  He wants to give loans to...
SPEAKER_0:  if you had an Uber fleet.
SPEAKER_0:  Those Uber drivers, they're the ones who need.
SPEAKER_0:  electric cars.
SPEAKER_0:  as his work and there was a recent story in Grist also.
SPEAKER_0:  said that most of the sales of Teslas are the high end of the market. They're 60, $80,000 vehicles.
SPEAKER_0:  Each year, like.
SPEAKER_0:  The hummer, the electric hummer, I can't, there was a.
SPEAKER_0:  Data point on that.
SPEAKER_0:  astonishing data point, the battery in that Hummer.
SPEAKER_0:  weighs more than
SPEAKER_0:  I'd have to look it up.
SPEAKER_0:  It weighs more than your car. Yeah, I think it might've been the Prius. And think of the material costs there. Think of where that battery, the Cobalt and the lithium, where does this stuff come from?
SPEAKER_0:  build this stuff out.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm all for it, but.
SPEAKER_0:  We have to be honest and clear about.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a new resource rush.
SPEAKER_0:  like the oil rush back in the early 20th century.
SPEAKER_0:  And those impacts have to be figured out too.
SPEAKER_0:  and if they're all big hummers.
SPEAKER_0:  for rich people.
SPEAKER_0:  There's so many contrary arguments to that, I think we have to figure out a way.
SPEAKER_0:  Oui.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't like the word we.
SPEAKER_0:  I use it too much, we all do.
SPEAKER_0:  but we all do.
SPEAKER_1:  refer when you say we we human
SPEAKER_0:  We, society, we, government, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  There has to be some.
SPEAKER_0:  thought and attention put to where you put these incentives so that you get the best use of this technology for
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  for the carbon benefit for the conventional sooty pollution benefit.
SPEAKER_0:  for the transportation benefit.
SPEAKER_0:  Can I sub?
SPEAKER_1:  back and ask a sort of big question. We'll mention economics.
SPEAKER_1:  Journalism.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  How does an economist and a climate scientist and a journalist...
SPEAKER_1:  that writes about climate, see the world differently. What are the strengths and potential blind spots of each discipline?
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, that's just sort of...
SPEAKER_1:  just so people...
SPEAKER_1:  may be aware, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  You gonna fall into the economics camp a bit?
SPEAKER_1:  There's climate scientists.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's climate scientists.
SPEAKER_1:  adjacent
SPEAKER_1:  people like who hang some of my best friends are climate scientists kind of which is I think where you fall in because you're a journalist. You've been writing it so you're not.
SPEAKER_1:  completely
SPEAKER_1:  in
SPEAKER_1:  the trenches of doing the work, you're just stepping into the trenches every once in a while.
SPEAKER_1:  So can you speak to that maybe Bjorn like what's?
SPEAKER_1:  What does the world look like to an economist?
SPEAKER_1:  Let's try to empathize with these beings that, you know. Unfortunately has fallen into the disreputable economics. So I think the main point that...
SPEAKER_1:  that I've been trying for a long time. And I think that's also a little bit what Andy has been talking about.
SPEAKER_1:  For a very long time, the whole conversation was about what does the science tell us? Is global warming real?
SPEAKER_1:  And to me, it's much more.
SPEAKER_1:  What can we actually do?
SPEAKER_1:  What are the?
SPEAKER_1:  policies that we can take.
SPEAKER_1:  and how effective are they going to be? So the conversation we just had about electric cars is a good example of how an economist think about
SPEAKER_1:  You gotta, this is not a question about whether you feel morally virtuous or whether you can sort of display how much you care about the environment. This is about how much you actually ended up.
SPEAKER_1:  affecting the world.
SPEAKER_1:  And the honest answer is that electric cars right now are just more sub colony of both cars, not the driving ones.
SPEAKER_1:  decade or so.
SPEAKER_1:  will have a fairly small impact. And unfortunately right now at a very high cost because we're basically subsidizing these things at five or $10,000 around the world per car. That's just not, it's not really sustainable, but it's certainly not a very great way to cut carbon emissions.
SPEAKER_1:  So I would be the kind of guy and economist would be the...
SPEAKER_1:  types of people who would say, is there a smarter way where you for less money.
SPEAKER_1:  can cut more CO2 and the
SPEAKER_1:  Obvious answer is yes.
SPEAKER_1:  That's what we've seen, for instance, with fracking.
SPEAKER_1:  The fact that the US went from a lot of coal
SPEAKER_1:  a lot of gas because gas became incredibly cheap.
SPEAKER_1:  because gas emits about half as much as coal does when you use it for power.
SPEAKER_1:  that basically cut more carbon emissions than pretty much any other single thing.
SPEAKER_1:  And we should get the rest of the world in some sense to frack because it's really cheap.
SPEAKER_1:  There are some problems and absolutely we can also have that conversation. No technology is problem free.
SPEAKER_1:  but fundamentally it's an incredibly cheap way.
SPEAKER_1:  to get.
SPEAKER_1:  people to cut a lot of CO2.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not the final solution because it's still a fossil fuel, but it's a much better fossil fuel, if you will.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's much more realistic to do that.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's one part of the thing. The other one is when we talked about, for instance, how do we help people in Florida who gets hit by a hurricane, or how do we help people that get damaged in flash floods, or people who are in heat waves, and the symbol.
SPEAKER_1:  The simple answer is there's a lot of very, very cheap and effective things that we could do first.
SPEAKER_1:  So most climate people will tend to sort of say.
SPEAKER_1:  We got to get rid of all carbon emissions. We got to change our entire, the engine that sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  powers the world and has powered us for the last 200 years.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's all good and well, but it's really, really hard to do. And it's probably not going to do very much.
SPEAKER_1:  And even if you succeed it, it would only help.
SPEAKER_1:  future victims of future hurricanes.
SPEAKER_1:  in Florida a tiny, tiny bit at best.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  Instead, let's try to focus on not getting people to build right on the waterfront where you're incredibly vulnerable and where you're very likely to get hit where we subsidize people with federal insurance again, which is actually losing money. So we're much more about saying, it's not a science question. I just take the science for granted. Yes, there is a problem with climate change, but it's much more about saying.
SPEAKER_1:  How can we make smart decisions? I can ask you about blind spots.
SPEAKER_1:  When you reduce stuff to numbers, the cost and benefits.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there stuff you might miss?
SPEAKER_1:  about
SPEAKER_1:  that are important to the flourishing of the human species.
SPEAKER_1:  Everyone will have to say, of course there must be blind spots.
SPEAKER_1:  but I don't know what they are. Yeah, I'm sure Andy would probably be better at telling me what they are. So we try to incorporate all of it, but obviously we're not successful. You can't incorporate everything, for instance, in the cost benefit analysis.
SPEAKER_1:  But the point is in some way.
SPEAKER_1:  I would worry a lot about this if we were, you know, sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  close to perfection human race, we're doing almost everything right, but we're not quite right then we need to get the last digits right. But I think it's much more the point that I tried to make before that we're all focused on going-
SPEAKER_1:  to an electric car or something else rather than.
SPEAKER_1:  fracking, we're all focused on cutting carbon emissions instead of reducing vulnerability. So we're similarly getting orders of magnitude wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  uh and and
SPEAKER_1:  while I'm sure I have blind spots, I think they're probably not big enough to overturn that point. Andy, why is Bjorn and economists are all wrong about every-
SPEAKER_0:  everything.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, the models, we could spend.
SPEAKER_0:  A whole day on models.
SPEAKER_0:  There are economic models. There's this thing called optimization models.
SPEAKER_0:  There were two big ones used to assess the.
SPEAKER_0:  US plan, this new big
SPEAKER_0:  IRA.
SPEAKER_0:  inflation reduction package.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  they're fine. They're a starting point for understanding.
SPEAKER_0:  what's possible, but as this gets to the journalism part or the public part
SPEAKER_0:  You have to look at the caveats. You have to look at the caveats.
SPEAKER_0:  What model?
SPEAKER_0:  Economists expressly exclude.
SPEAKER_0:  things that are not modelable.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you look in the fine print on the repeat project, the Princeton.
SPEAKER_0:  version of.
SPEAKER_0:  the assessment of the recent.
SPEAKER_0:  giant legislation.
SPEAKER_0:  The fine print.
SPEAKER_0:  is the front page.
SPEAKER_0:  For me.
SPEAKER_0:  is a deep diving journalist because it says.
SPEAKER_0:  We didn't include any sources of friction.
SPEAKER_0:  Meaning.
SPEAKER_0:  resistance to putting new transmission lines through your community.
SPEAKER_0:  or
SPEAKER_0:  people.
SPEAKER_0:  who don't want...
SPEAKER_0:  Mining.
SPEAKER_0:  in America.
SPEAKER_0:  because we've...
SPEAKER_0:  exported all of our mining. We mine our
SPEAKER_0:  Cobalt and Congo, you know, and trying to get a new mine in Nevada.
SPEAKER_0:  was a fraught fight that took more than 10 years for lithium.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're excluding.
SPEAKER_0:  those elements from your model, which on the surface.
SPEAKER_0:  makes this $370 billion package.
SPEAKER_0:  have an emissions reduction.
SPEAKER_0:  trajectory that's really pretty good.
SPEAKER_0:  And you're not saying in your first line, by the way, these are the things we're not considering.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the job of a journalist.
SPEAKER_1:  all of human history with that one.
SPEAKER_0:  word friction.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, well inertia.
SPEAKER_0:  Friction implies there's a force that's already being resisted.
SPEAKER_0:  But there's also inertia, which is a huge part of our.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, we have a status quo bias.
SPEAKER_0:  the scientists that I.
SPEAKER_0:  in grappling with the climate problem.
SPEAKER_0:  As a journalist, I paid too much attention to climate scientists.
SPEAKER_0:  That's why I wrote my articles.
SPEAKER_0:  focused on climate change.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was 2006, I remember.
SPEAKER_0:  Now, pretty clearly...
SPEAKER_0:  I was asked by the weekend review section of the New York Times to write a sort of a weekend thumb sucker, we call them.
SPEAKER_0:  on, you know, you're sitting, you're sitting, suck your thumb and think about something.
SPEAKER_0:  Why is everybody so pissed off about climate change? It was after Al Gore's movie, the Al Gore movie came out in Convened Truth, Hurricane Katrina.
SPEAKER_0:  Senator Inhofe.
SPEAKER_0:  in the Senate from Oklahoma wasn't yet throwing snowballs, but.
SPEAKER_0:  It was close to that. And so I looked into what was going on. Why is this so heated?
SPEAKER_0:  in 2006.
SPEAKER_0:  The story is called Yelling Fire on Hot Planet.
SPEAKER_0:  And.
SPEAKER_0:  That was the first time, this is after 18 years of writing about global warming.
SPEAKER_0:  That was the first time I interviewed a social scientist.
SPEAKER_0:  not a climate scientist.
SPEAKER_0:  Her name is Helen Ingram.
SPEAKER_0:  She's at UC Irvine.
SPEAKER_0:  and she...
SPEAKER_0:  laid out for me the factors that.
SPEAKER_0:  determine why people vote, what they vote for, what they think about politically.
SPEAKER_0:  and they were the antithesis of the climate problem.
SPEAKER_0:  to use the words.
SPEAKER_0:  She said people.
SPEAKER_0:  Go in the voting booth.
SPEAKER_0:  thinking about things that are soon.
SPEAKER_0:  salient.
SPEAKER_0:  and certain.
SPEAKER_0:  and climate change is complex, has long time scales.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  That really jogged me and then I between 2006, 2010.
SPEAKER_0:  I started interviewing other social scientists and I...
SPEAKER_0:  This was by far the scariest.
SPEAKER_0:  Science of all.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the climate in our heads.
SPEAKER_0:  or inconvenient minds.
SPEAKER_0:  and in how that translates into.
SPEAKER_0:  political norms and stuff really became the monster, not the climate system.
SPEAKER_0:  Is there social dynamics?
SPEAKER_1:  to the scientists themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  because uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I've gotten to witness a kind of...
SPEAKER_1:  flocking behavior with scientists.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's almost like a flock of birds within the flock.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot of disagreement.
SPEAKER_1:  and fun debates.
SPEAKER_1:  and everybody trying to prove each other wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  but they're all kinda headed in the same direction.
SPEAKER_1:  and you don't want to be the bird that kind of leaves that flock. No. So like there's an idea of that science is a mechanism.
SPEAKER_1:  will get us towards the truth.
SPEAKER_1:  but...
SPEAKER_1:  It'll definitely get us somewhere.
SPEAKER_1:  but it could.
SPEAKER_1:  be not the truth in the short term.
SPEAKER_1:  In the long term, a bigger flock will come along.
SPEAKER_1:  and it will get us to the truth, but there's a sense.
SPEAKER_1:  that I don't know if there's a mechanism within science to like...
SPEAKER_1:  Snap out of it if you're done the wrong track. Usually you get it right, but...
SPEAKER_1:  Sometimes you don't, when you don't it's very.
SPEAKER_0:  costly.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's so many factors that line up to.
SPEAKER_0:  perpetuate.
SPEAKER_0:  that flocking behavior.
SPEAKER_0:  One is media attention.
SPEAKER_0:  comes in.
SPEAKER_0:  The other is funding comes in.
SPEAKER_0:  National Science Foundation or whatever, European foundations pour a huge amount of money into the first two things.
SPEAKER_0:  related to climate.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you're.
SPEAKER_0:  And then your narrative in your head is...
SPEAKER_0:  shaped by that aspect of the climate problem.
SPEAKER_0:  that's in the spotlight.
SPEAKER_0:  I started using this hashtag.
SPEAKER_0:  years back, narrative capture.
SPEAKER_0:  be wary of narrative capture?
SPEAKER_0:  where you're...
SPEAKER_0:  you're on a train and everyone's getting on the train.
SPEAKER_0:  this is in the media too, not just science, and it becomes self-sustaining.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  and contrary indications are ignored or downplayed.
SPEAKER_0:  No one does replication science because your career doesn't advance through.
SPEAKER_0:  replicating someone else's work.
SPEAKER_0:  So those contrary indications are.
SPEAKER_0:  are not necessarily.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, really dug in on.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is for, this is way beyond climate. This is of many fields. As you said, you might've seen this in AI and it's really hard.
SPEAKER_0:  See you.
SPEAKER_0:  find it's another form of path dependency. The term I used.
SPEAKER_0:  for.
SPEAKER_0:  but breaking narrative capture.
SPEAKER_0:  to me.
SPEAKER_0:  for me has come mostly.
SPEAKER_0:  from stepping back.
SPEAKER_0:  and reminding myself of the basic principles of journalism. Journalisms.
SPEAKER_0:  basic principles are useful for anybody.
SPEAKER_0:  confronting a big enormous dynamic.
SPEAKER_0:  complex thing is...
SPEAKER_0:  to what where when why.
SPEAKER_0:  just be really rigorous about.
SPEAKER_0:  Not assuming.
SPEAKER_0:  because there's a fire in Boulder.
SPEAKER_0:  or
SPEAKER_0:  a flood in Fort Myers, that climate, which is in your head because you're part of the climate team at the New York Times or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  is the front.
SPEAKER_0:  is the foreground part of this problem.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the psychological challenge of that?
SPEAKER_1:  If you incorporate the fact that if you.
SPEAKER_1:  try to step back and have nuance.
SPEAKER_1:  you might get attacked by...
SPEAKER_0:  the others in the flock.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, I was. Well, you've certainly been.
SPEAKER_1:  you get attacked.
SPEAKER_1:  continuously.
SPEAKER_1:  from different sides.
SPEAKER_1:  So let me just ask about that. How does that feel?
SPEAKER_1:  and how do you continue thinking clearly.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  continuously try to have humility and step back and not get defensive.
SPEAKER_1:  in that on.
SPEAKER_1:  as a communicator.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  There are other things happening at the same time, right? I'm now 35 years into them.
SPEAKER_0:  almost 40 years into my journalism career.
SPEAKER_0:  So I have some independence. I'm free from the obligations of-
SPEAKER_0:  I don't really need my next paycheck. I live in Maine now in a house I love. I own it outright. It's a great privilege and honor.
SPEAKER_0:  And.
SPEAKER_0:  as the result of.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of hard work.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I'm freer to think freely.
SPEAKER_0:  and I know my colleagues in newsrooms when I was at the New York Times, in the newsroom.
SPEAKER_0:  you become.
SPEAKER_0:  captive to a narrative.
SPEAKER_0:  just as you do.
SPEAKER_0:  out in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  The New York Times had a narrative about Saddam Hussein.
SPEAKER_0:  drove us into.
SPEAKER_0:  that war, the times sucked right into that.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll perpetuate it.
SPEAKER_0:  I think we're in a bit of a narrative.
SPEAKER_0:  We.
SPEAKER_0:  the media.
SPEAKER_0:  My friends at the Times and others are on a train ride.
SPEAKER_0:  on climate change depicting it in a certain way.
SPEAKER_0:  that
SPEAKER_0:  Really, I saw problems with how they handled the Joe Manchin.
SPEAKER_0:  issue in America, the West Virginia senator.
SPEAKER_0:  They really kind of piled on and.
SPEAKER_0:  zoomed in on his investments.
SPEAKER_0:  which is really important to do, but they never pulled back.
SPEAKER_0:  and said, by the way, he's.
SPEAKER_0:  rare species. He's a Democrat in West Virginia.
SPEAKER_0:  and which seat would be otherwise occupied by a Republican. There'd be no talk of a climate deal or any of that stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  without him.
SPEAKER_0:  But once you're starting to frame a story in a certain way, you...
SPEAKER_0:  carried along and
SPEAKER_0:  As you said, sometimes it breaks and a new norm arrives.
SPEAKER_0:  climate train is still kind of rushing forward.
SPEAKER_0:  and missing.
SPEAKER_0:  opportunity to cut it into its pieces.
SPEAKER_0:  and say, well, what's really wrong with Florida?
SPEAKER_0:  And it's for me when you ask you about how I handle the.
SPEAKER_0:  slings and arrows and stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  It's partially because I'm past.
SPEAKER_0:  worrying about it too much.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it was pretty intense, 2009 Rush Limbaugh.
SPEAKER_0:  suggested I kill myself on his radio show. It's a really great time. What was that about?
SPEAKER_0:  I had
SPEAKER_0:  Actually, this was a meeting in Washington.
SPEAKER_0:  2009.
SPEAKER_0:  on population at the Wilson Center.
SPEAKER_0:  I couldn't be there. So actually this is pre-COVID, but I was zooming in or something like Skyping in.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  in a playful way. I said, well, if you really want to worry about
SPEAKER_0:  carbon.
SPEAKER_0:  This is during the debate over.
SPEAKER_0:  carbon tax.
SPEAKER_0:  model for a bill in America.
SPEAKER_0:  we should probably have a carbon tax for kids.
SPEAKER_0:  because a bigger family in America is a big source of.
SPEAKER_0:  more emissions. It was kind of a playful thought bubble.
SPEAKER_0:  some right-wing blogger blogged about it, it got into Rush's pile of things to talk about.
SPEAKER_0:  And the clip is really fun.
SPEAKER_1:  awesome meetings, so.
SPEAKER_1:  If humans...
SPEAKER_1:  are bad for the environment.
SPEAKER_1:  I reckon benefits will be built amongst different categories of strokes, but would provide an action-packed
SPEAKER_1:  I can imagine
SPEAKER_0:  That's amazing. He was very explicit. That's how you know you've made it. He said.
SPEAKER_0:  Mr. Revkin of the New York, Andrew Revkin of the New York Times, if you really think that people are the worst thing that ever happened to.
SPEAKER_0:  this planet. Why don't you just kill yourself and save the planet by dying?
SPEAKER_0:  it was tough for you
SPEAKER_0:  It was tough for my family. To me, it did generate some interesting calls and stuff in my...
SPEAKER_0:  my voicemail.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  But on the left I was also...
SPEAKER_0:  undercut, Roger Pilkey Jr.
SPEAKER_0:  prominent researcher of
SPEAKER_0:  climate risk and climate policy, UC Boulder.
SPEAKER_0:  was actively.
SPEAKER_0:  his career track was.
SPEAKER_0:  derailed purposefully by people who just thought his message was-
SPEAKER_0:  too off.
SPEAKER_0:  Off the path.
SPEAKER_0:  when you, you know...
SPEAKER_0:  Even.
SPEAKER_0:  dealing with this for a very long time.
SPEAKER_1:  So, I just want to get back to the science. I don't think the science get it so much wrong as it just becomes accepted.
SPEAKER_1:  to make certain assumptions as you just said, we assume no friction.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's a way that you kind of model the world that ends up being also a convenient message.
SPEAKER_1:  in many ways and I think the main convenient message in climate and it's not surprising if you think about it.
SPEAKER_1:  The main convenient message is.
SPEAKER_1:  that the best way to do something about all the things that we call climate.
SPEAKER_1:  is to cut CO2.
SPEAKER_1:  And that turns out to only sometimes be true and with a lot of caveats. But that's sort of the message. And it takes a long time. Yes, it's really, really difficult to do in any meaningful sort of timeframe.
SPEAKER_1:  And if you challenge that.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, you're outside the flock and you get attacked. I've always, so somebody told me once, I think it's true, they say at the Harvard Law School, if you have a good case, pound the case.
SPEAKER_1:  If you have a bad case, pound the table.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, and so I've always felt that when people go after me, they're kind of pounding to table there, you know, they're
SPEAKER_1:  literally screaming, I don't have a good case. I'm really annoyed with what you're saying. And so to me, that actually means.
SPEAKER_1:  It's much more important to make this argument.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, sure. I mean, I would love-
SPEAKER_1:  you know, everyone just saying, oh, that's a really good point. I'm going to use that. But, you know, uh, we're, we're stuck in a situation, certainly in a conversation where.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of people have invested a lot of time and energy on saying.
SPEAKER_1:  We should cut carbon emissions. This is the way.
SPEAKER_1:  to help humankind. And just be clear, I think we should cut carbon emissions as well.
SPEAKER_1:  but we should also just be realistic about what we can achieve with that. and what are all the other things
SPEAKER_1:  that we could also do.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, and it turns out that a lot of these other things are much cheaper, much more effective will help much more, much quicker.
SPEAKER_1:  And so getting that point out.
SPEAKER_1:  is just incredibly important for us to get it right. So in some sense, to make sure that we don't do another Iraq and we don't do another, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Lots of stupid decisions. I mean, this is one of the things mankind is very good at. And I guess I see my role and I think that's probably also how you see yourself is trying to, you know,
SPEAKER_1:  Get everyone to do it slightly less wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  So let me ask you about a deep psychological effect for you.
SPEAKER_1:  There's also a drug of martyrdom.
SPEAKER_1:  So whenever you stand against the flock.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a... you wrote...
SPEAKER_1:  A couple of really good books on the topic.
SPEAKER_1:  their most recent false alarm.
SPEAKER_1:  I stand as the holder of truth.
SPEAKER_1:  that everybody who is alarmist is wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  And here's just simple calm way to express the facts of the matter.
SPEAKER_1:  and that's very compelling to a very large number of people.
SPEAKER_1:  They want to make a martyr out of you.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that, are you worried about your own mind?
SPEAKER_1:  uh... being corrupted by that by enjoying
SPEAKER_1:  standing against the crowd.
SPEAKER_1:  No, no, no, there's very little, I guess I can see what you're saying sort of in a literary way or something. Yeah, so I'm being poetic here. Yeah, there's very little.
SPEAKER_1:  or sort of usefulness in annoying a lot of people. Whenever I go to a party, for instance.
SPEAKER_1:  I know that there's a good chance people are gonna be annoyed with me.
SPEAKER_1:  And I would love that not to be the case. But what I try to do is, so I try to be very polite and sort of not.
SPEAKER_1:  We are-
SPEAKER_1:  push people's buttons unless they sort of actively say, so you're saying I'll-
SPEAKER_1:  kind of stupid stuff on the climate, right? And then try to engage with them and say, well, what is it you're thinking about? And hopefully, you know, during that party, and then it ends up being a really bad party for me. But anyway, so I'll end up.
SPEAKER_1:  Possibly convincing one person that I'm not totally stupid
SPEAKER_1:  But no, I'm not playing the martyr and I'm not enjoying that.
SPEAKER_0:  The... is that interesting?
SPEAKER_0:  The, I mean, the, the, um.
SPEAKER_0:  Martyr complexes all around the climate question. Michael Mann at the far end of the spectrum of
SPEAKER_0:  Activism.
SPEAKER_0:  from where Bjorn is, is a climate scientist who...
SPEAKER_0:  was actively attacked by
SPEAKER_0:  in Hoffman.
SPEAKER_0:  West Virginia politicians.
SPEAKER_0:  really abused in many ways. He had come up with a very prominent model of
SPEAKER_0:  looking at long-term records of climate change.
SPEAKER_0:  and got this hockey stick for temperature.
SPEAKER_0:  He definitely sits there in a certain kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  because of that.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's not.
SPEAKER_0:  Unique.
SPEAKER_0:  any particular vantage point in the.
SPEAKER_0:  the spectrum of sort of prominent people on the debate.
SPEAKER_1:  Andrew, you co-wrote the book, The Human Planet, Earth at the Dawn.
SPEAKER_1:  of the...
SPEAKER_1:  Anthropocene.
SPEAKER_1:  which is the new age when humans are actually having impact on the environment. Let me ask the question of.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you find most beautiful and fascinating about?
SPEAKER_0:  our planet Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  It'd be cheap to say everything, but just walking here this morning under the bridge.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... over the colorado river
SPEAKER_0:  seeing the birds, knowing there's bat colonies, massive bat colonies around here that I got to visit a few years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  I experienced one of those.
SPEAKER_0:  Explosions.
SPEAKER_0:  It's mind blowing.
SPEAKER_0:  the
SPEAKER_0:  I've.
SPEAKER_0:  been really lucky as a journalist to have gone to the North Pole, to camp on the sea ice with Russian help.
SPEAKER_0:  This is a camp that was set up for tourists coming from Europe every year.
SPEAKER_0:  They were scientists.
SPEAKER_0:  on the sea ice, floating on the 14,000 foot deep.
SPEAKER_0:  Arctic Ocean.
SPEAKER_0:  I was with them for several days. I wrote a book about that too along with my reporting.
SPEAKER_0:  been in the depths of the Amazon.
SPEAKER_0:  rainforests have been when I was very young.
SPEAKER_0:  I was a crew on a sailboat that sailed two thirds of the way around the world.
SPEAKER_0:  I was halfway across the Indian Ocean, again, and 14,000 foot deep.
SPEAKER_0:  water, we were just, there was no wind.
SPEAKER_0:  And we were, this was way before I was a journalist, 22, 23 years old.
SPEAKER_0:  and we went swimming, swimming in 14,000 foot deep water.
SPEAKER_0:  500 miles from land, the Western Indian Ocean, halfway between.
SPEAKER_0:  Somalia and
SPEAKER_0:  Maldives.
SPEAKER_0:  Is it like so mind boggling, chillingly?
SPEAKER_0:  fantastical thing.
SPEAKER_0:  with a mask on looking at your shadow.
SPEAKER_0:  going to the vanishing point below you, looking over at the boat, which is a 60 foot boat, but just looks like a toy.
SPEAKER_0:  and then getting back on and being beholden to the elements, a sailboat heading toward.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the immensity and the power of the elements. And then, you know, and then.
SPEAKER_0:  The Human.
SPEAKER_0:  qualities are unbelievable. You know, the Anthropocene.
SPEAKER_0:  played a bit of a role as a journalist and.
SPEAKER_0:  waking people up to the idea that this era called the Holocene in the last 11,000 years.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, since the last Ice Age.
SPEAKER_0:  had ended. I wrote.
SPEAKER_0:  my 1992 book on global warming.
SPEAKER_0:  Thinking about all that we're just talking about. Thinking about...
SPEAKER_0:  the wonders of the planet, thinking about the impact of humans so far in our.
SPEAKER_0:  explosive growth in the 20th century.
SPEAKER_0:  I wrote that perhaps earth scientists of the future.
SPEAKER_0:  We'll name this.
SPEAKER_0:  post-holocene.
SPEAKER_0:  era for its formative element for us.
SPEAKER_0:  because we're kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  in charge in certain ways, which is hubristic at the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  the variability of the climate system is still profound without global warming.
SPEAKER_1:  powerful, beautiful organism that is Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  the all the different sub-organisms that are on it. Do you see humans as a kind of parasite on this earth? No, no.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  as something that helps the flourishing of the entire organism.
SPEAKER_1:  that can.
SPEAKER_1:  can.
SPEAKER_1:  intelligence.
SPEAKER_1:  Hasn't yet.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, aren't we on a...
SPEAKER_1:  So the ability of the collective intelligence of the human species.
SPEAKER_1:  to develop all these kinds of technologies.
SPEAKER_1:  and to be able to have Twitter to introspect onto itself.
SPEAKER_0:  Of course. We should get Twitter to be an animal. I think we're doing a...
SPEAKER_0:  In a way we are. It's catch up. Always in catch up mode, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I was at the Vatican.
SPEAKER_0:  for a big meeting in 2014 on sustainable humanity, sustainable nature our responsibility.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was a week of...
SPEAKER_0:  presentations by like Martin Reese, who's this.
SPEAKER_0:  famed British scientist, physicist who...
SPEAKER_0:  Been on this podcast.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, he's, you know, he's.
SPEAKER_0:  fixated on existential risk, right? Yes, he is. There's a week of this stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  The meeting was kicked off by...
SPEAKER_0:  I wrote about it in the Cardinal Marodiaga who is I think from El Salvador. He's one of the Pope's kind of posse.
SPEAKER_0:  He gave one of the initial speeches and he said, nowadays.
SPEAKER_0:  Mankind.
SPEAKER_0:  looks like a technical giant.
SPEAKER_0:  and an ethical child.
SPEAKER_0:  Meaning art.
SPEAKER_0:  Technological wizardry is unbelievable, but it's way out in front of our ability to step back and kind of like...
SPEAKER_0:  consider in the full dimensions we need to.
SPEAKER_0:  Is it helping everybody?
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  what are the consequences of CRISPR?
SPEAKER_0:  genetics technology.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's no single answer to that.
SPEAKER_0:  if I'm in the African Union.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm just using this as an example.
SPEAKER_0:  CRISPR has emerged so fast, it can do so much.
SPEAKER_0:  by changing the nature of nature.
SPEAKER_0:  in a kind of a programming way, you know, building genes.
SPEAKER_0:  not just transferring them from one organism to another.
SPEAKER_0:  We've only just begun to taste.
SPEAKER_0:  The fruits of that literally.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and it can wipe out a mosquito species. We know how to do that now. You can like literally.
SPEAKER_0:  take out the dengue-causing mosquito.
SPEAKER_0:  The scientists have done the work.
SPEAKER_0:  you think, okay, cool. Well, that's great. Now there's this big fight over whether that should happen.
SPEAKER_0:  African Union and I'm with their.
SPEAKER_0:  view.
SPEAKER_0:  says, hey, if we can take out a mosquito species that's.
SPEAKER_0:  causing.
SPEAKER_0:  Horrific.
SPEAKER_0:  chronic loss through dengue.
SPEAKER_0:  which I had once in Indonesia, it's not fun.
SPEAKER_0:  And.
SPEAKER_0:  We should.
SPEAKER_0:  Do it.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, and.
SPEAKER_0:  Europe. What's the other side of the argument? What's the other side of the argument?
SPEAKER_0:  They're they're saying using their
SPEAKER_0:  Capital P precautionary.
SPEAKER_0:  principle.
SPEAKER_0:  Says, no, we can't meddle with nature.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is just like we were talking with climate, you know, there's the real-time question and the long-term question.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's the.
SPEAKER_0:  People who are just facing the need to get through the day and be healthy and survive and have enough food.
SPEAKER_0:  which is not integrated sufficiently at all into the climate.
SPEAKER_0:  Stop climate change debate.
SPEAKER_0:  and those who like are trying to cut CO2.
SPEAKER_0:  which will have a benefit.
SPEAKER_0:  in the future by limiting the fat tail.
SPEAKER_0:  outcomes of this.
SPEAKER_0:  journey we're on.
SPEAKER_0:  So when I think about the Anthropocene, I think about...
SPEAKER_0:  this planet.
SPEAKER_0:  I love.
SPEAKER_0:  that we're here right now. I love that our species has these capacities.
SPEAKER_0:  I would love.
SPEAKER_0:  there to be a little bit more reflection.
SPEAKER_0:  and where things come from and where they might go.
SPEAKER_0:  whether you're a student, a kid.
SPEAKER_0:  What's your role?
SPEAKER_0:  The wonderful thing about the complexity of it is everyone can play.
SPEAKER_0:  role if you're an artist.
SPEAKER_0:  or a designer.
SPEAKER_0:  or architect.
SPEAKER_0:  or economist.
SPEAKER_0:  or a podcaster.
SPEAKER_0:  Whatever you do, just tweak a little bit toward.
SPEAKER_0:  examining these questions, stepping back from the simplistic.
SPEAKER_0:  Label throwing.
SPEAKER_0:  toward.
SPEAKER_0:  what actually is the problem in front of me.
SPEAKER_0:  whether it's in...
SPEAKER_0:  Pakistan.
SPEAKER_0:  or.
SPEAKER_0:  or in.
SPEAKER_0:  Boston or wherever, you know, Florida.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you find beautiful about this collective intelligence machine we have from an economics perspective? It's kind of
SPEAKER_1:  fascinating they were able to
SPEAKER_1:  There is a machine to it that we've built up.
SPEAKER_1:  that's able to represent interests and desires and value.
SPEAKER_1:  Hopes and dreams.
SPEAKER_1:  in sort of monetary ways.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... that we can
SPEAKER_1:  trade with each other, we can make agreements with each other, we can represent our goals.
SPEAKER_1:  build companies that actually help.
SPEAKER_1:  and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you just step back every once in a while and marvel at the fact that
SPEAKER_1:  A few billion of us are able to.
SPEAKER_1:  Somehow not.
SPEAKER_1:  create complete chaos and actually collaborate.
SPEAKER_1:  and have collaborative disagreements that ultimately.
SPEAKER_1:  or so far have left.
SPEAKER_1:  led to progress.
SPEAKER_1:  I think fundamentally the point, apart from the fact that we should just...
SPEAKER_1:  being joyful of the fact that.
SPEAKER_1:  humans live here. I think it's incredibly important to remember.
SPEAKER_1:  how much progress we've had.
SPEAKER_1:  Most people just don't stop to think about those stats. I get that in the normal bustle of day. But just, you know, uh-
SPEAKER_1:  In 1900, the average person on the planet lived to be 32 years.
SPEAKER_1:  32 years, that was our average life expectancy. Today it's about 74.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, so-
SPEAKER_1:  We've literally got two lifetimes on this planet, each one of us.
SPEAKER_1:  And every year you live.
SPEAKER_1:  In the rich world, you get to live three months longer and the poor world is about four months longer.
SPEAKER_1:  because of medical advances, because we get better at dealing both with cancer and especially right now with heart disease.
SPEAKER_1:  These are amazing achievements. Of course, it's a very very small part of it. We're much better fed. We're much better educated We've gone from a world where
SPEAKER_1:  virtually everyone or.
SPEAKER_1:  90% were illiterate.
SPEAKER_1:  to a world where more than 90% illiterate, this is an astounding opportunity. And 200 years ago...
SPEAKER_1:  95%? 94%?
SPEAKER_1:  of the world.
SPEAKER_1:  extremely poor that is less than a dollar a day.
SPEAKER_1:  today that for the first time in 2015, it was down below 10%.
SPEAKER_1:  So there, and again, these are kind of boring statistics, but they're also astounding.
SPEAKER_1:  testaments of how well humanity has done. So just on the point of.
SPEAKER_1:  We've kind of just been focused on making our own world better.
SPEAKER_1:  And in many ways, so we've hunted a lot of big animals, either to extinction or down to much, much smaller populations, it's much smaller populations, fish in the ocean. So there's a lot of things that sort of bear the brunt of our success. It's not because we're evil in that sense, it's just because we didn't care all that much about them. I think it is important as one funnel of that, I'm not gonna make a big deal out of it, but the fact that we're putting out more CO2 in the atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  Because CO2, as you also mentioned before, it's actually plant food. If you're a greenhouse grower, you know if you put in CO2 in your greenhouse, you actually get bigger and plumper tomatoes. And that's essentially what we're doing in the world. This has overall bad consequences, and that's why we should be doing something about it. But one of the
SPEAKER_1:  Good?
SPEAKER_1:  side effects is actually that the world is getting greener.
SPEAKER_1:  so we get much more green stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know. And this is where I sort of show my economist roots, because if you just measure all living stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  in.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, in tons.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, so in wait.
SPEAKER_1:  there's actually more.
SPEAKER_1:  living stuff than there were 100 years ago, because elephants and all these other big fish and stuff are actually really, really small fraction of the world. So we have an enormous amount of life stuff, but that doesn't even measure it. It's mostly just wood.
SPEAKER_1:  of the wooden green stuff that has dramatically increased in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  We're still not there from what it was in 1500. So we've still cut down the world a lot, but we're actually making a much greener world. Again, not because we really cared or thought about it, but just sort of a side effect of what we're doing. I think the crucial bit to remember is
SPEAKER_1:  When you're poor?
SPEAKER_1:  and you worry about what's going to happen the next day.
SPEAKER_1:  This is just not your main issue. Am I killing too many large animals in the world?
SPEAKER_1:  when you're rich and you can actually sit in a podcast in a convenient place in Austin, you can also start thinking about this. So one of the-
SPEAKER_1:  Crucial bits, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  If we want to get the rest of the world to care about
SPEAKER_1:  the environment, care about climate, care about all these other issues.
SPEAKER_1:  We really need to get them out of poverty first.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's a simple point that we often forget.
SPEAKER_0:  and get them connected to all these gifts. Todd, thank you for being involved in this interview today and your shredded
SPEAKER_0:  I-I-
SPEAKER_0:  I have these memories of...
SPEAKER_0:  I was reporting on the next big earthquake that's going to devastate Istanbul.
SPEAKER_0:  in 2009.
SPEAKER_0:  I was in a slum.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  immigrant.
SPEAKER_0:  poor neighborhood.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  walking around with an engineer pointing out to the buildings that were going to fall down.
SPEAKER_0:  This is all known. There was an earthquake in 1999 and the next one's coming.
SPEAKER_0:  One of my advantages in covering climate is I've covered other kinds of disasters too, so it keeps my context.
SPEAKER_0:  Me in touch with other.
SPEAKER_0:  things we could do. So I'm walking around and interviewing everybody. I went to the school that's being retrofit. They actually were getting ahead of it there. The World Bank provided some funding to.
SPEAKER_0:  put in iron.
SPEAKER_0:  bars in the brick building.
SPEAKER_0:  And I met these kids.
SPEAKER_0:  And they came, when you're a journalist with a camera and stuff in a pad.
SPEAKER_0:  You get swarmed by kids.
SPEAKER_0:  mostly in developing countries. These kids are running up to me.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  They were going like...
SPEAKER_0:  Are you American or just?
SPEAKER_0:  They were saying Facebook.
SPEAKER_0:  PISS M-
SPEAKER_0:  And I went.
SPEAKER_0:  That's interesting and they led me.
SPEAKER_0:  there, a little community center that had a bank of eight or 10.
SPEAKER_0:  flimsy computers.
SPEAKER_0:  And they're all there playing a farm. There was a game that was hot at that time on Facebook farm.
SPEAKER_0:  Farmville? Farmville, yeah. And my son back in the Hudson Valley.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember him playing it and.
SPEAKER_0:  And I thought, wow.
SPEAKER_0:  That is so freaking cool.
SPEAKER_0:  these kids and actually I became Facebook friends with a couple of them afterwards. we traded our gifts.
SPEAKER_0:  And I thought back to my youth when...
SPEAKER_0:  we had pen pals, I would write a letter to a kid in West Cameroon.
SPEAKER_0:  and he would write back.
SPEAKER_0:  and it took weeks.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a crinkly letter and I never met him.
SPEAKER_0:  And now you can kind of connect with people and.
SPEAKER_0:  And that all...
SPEAKER_0:  my blogging. At the New York Times, I was doing my regular reporting, but I launched a blog in 2007 called.earth.
SPEAKER_0:  which was all about what you were just describing, the newosphere, the connected world. That's a term from these.
SPEAKER_0:  to early 20s, a Russian guy in early.
SPEAKER_0:  Farnadsky and.
SPEAKER_0:  a French theologian and scientist, which is so interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  Teard de Chardin.
SPEAKER_0:  They had this idea.
SPEAKER_0:  in the early 20th century that.
SPEAKER_0:  We're creating a planet of the mind.
SPEAKER_0:  that human intelligence.
SPEAKER_0:  can foster.
SPEAKER_0:  a better Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  And I just became smitten with that, especially meeting kids in Istanbul slums who are on Facebook looking at connectedness. What can you do with these tools?
SPEAKER_0:  which is what drives me with my work now.
SPEAKER_0:  And, um...
SPEAKER_0:  But then there are these counter weight, counter.
SPEAKER_0:  currents that.
SPEAKER_0:  if the connectedness can cut back, you know, it allowed.
SPEAKER_0:  Al-Qaeda to recruit.
SPEAKER_0:  Use decapitation videos to recruit.
SPEAKER_0:  distributed, disaffected young people into extremism.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's lots of-
SPEAKER_0:  These systems are just like every other tool, right? They're just-
SPEAKER_0:  for good or ill.
SPEAKER_0:  and the efficiency thing.
SPEAKER_0:  the economics.
SPEAKER_0:  of the world, which I also wrote about a little bit.
SPEAKER_0:  late 20th century it was so cool that
SPEAKER_0:  everything became so efficient.
SPEAKER_0:  that our supply chains.
SPEAKER_0:  Just in time.
SPEAKER_0:  manufacturing, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  getting the stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  from where the sources of the material are to the car factory and to get the car to the floor just in time for someone to buy it.
SPEAKER_0:  And everyone got totally sucked in by that, including me. It's great, you know, super efficient, cheaper.
SPEAKER_0:  And then COVID.
SPEAKER_0:  and the whole supply chain.
SPEAKER_0:  concept crumbled.
SPEAKER_0:  And one of the big lessons there, hopefully.
SPEAKER_0:  and this is relevant to sustainability generally.
SPEAKER_0:  is.
SPEAKER_0:  Efficiency matters, but resilience matters too, and resilience is inefficient.
SPEAKER_0:  You need redundancy?
SPEAKER_0:  or
SPEAKER_0:  or a variety of.
SPEAKER_0:  options, right? Which is not what corporate companies think about, which is not what...
SPEAKER_0:  If you're only focused on a bottom line short term.
SPEAKER_0:  Timeline.
SPEAKER_0:  those disruptions are not what you're thinking about. You're still thinking about, can we get that widget here just in time for this thing to happen? And then on we go.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  I love the no sphere.
SPEAKER_0:  This new-esphere.
SPEAKER_0:  idea of the connectedness is fantastic. Oh wait another thing like-
SPEAKER_0:  in the early 90s.
SPEAKER_0:  when I wrote my first book on global warming.
SPEAKER_0:  It was for an exhibition at the Museum of Natural History. The Environmental Defense Fund was involved. They were like a partner.
SPEAKER_0:  one of these longstanding environmental groups.
SPEAKER_0:  And they're very old fashioned. It's mostly lawyers really, just using the Clean Air Act, Clean Water Act to litigate against pollution.
SPEAKER_0:  And now...
SPEAKER_0:  EDF is vastly bigger.
SPEAKER_0:  And they're actually, this coming year, they're launching a satellite, an environmental group.
SPEAKER_0:  is launching MethaneSat.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's providing a view, an independent view of where there's this gas.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the same thing, natural gas is basically methane.
SPEAKER_0:  you have a leak, whether it's in Siberia or in
SPEAKER_0:  Oklahoma.
SPEAKER_0:  You can cross-reference, you can ground, you can.
SPEAKER_0:  identify the hotspot you can.
SPEAKER_0:  know where the problem is to fix in so many ways. And that's just one example. I'm like-
SPEAKER_0:  If someone had told me in 1993 that EDF was going to launch a methane satellite, I would have laughed out loud.
SPEAKER_0:  So technology plays a huge role.
SPEAKER_0:  if it's kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, employed.
SPEAKER_0:  with these.
SPEAKER_0:  the bigger vision and leadership.
SPEAKER_0:  So Bjorn you wrote...
SPEAKER_1:  One of the books you wrote, the most recent one called False Alarm.
SPEAKER_1:  how climate change panic costs us trillions.
SPEAKER_1:  hurts the poor.
SPEAKER_1:  and fails to fix the planet.
SPEAKER_1:  Good title by the way, very intense, makes me want to read it.
SPEAKER_1:  What is?
SPEAKER_1:  likely the worst effect of climate change.
SPEAKER_1:  First, let me just, my editor actually hated the subtitle because it gives away the whole book.
SPEAKER_1:  basically tells you what the book tries to make. I think that's exactly what it should be. It's about getting this conversation out in the public sphere.
SPEAKER_1:  The worst thing that climate change can do...
SPEAKER_1:  is like the worst thing that anything can do is that it wipes out everything and we all die.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's not like.
SPEAKER_1:  If you're just looking for worst case outcomes.
SPEAKER_1:  Anything can get.
SPEAKER_1:  to the worst case outcome.
SPEAKER_1:  Imagine if we suggest what's the worst thing that could happen from HIV.
SPEAKER_1:  It breaks down...
SPEAKER_1:  one or more African states because we don't fix it. And then you get sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  biological warfare and terrorism throw in that in the mix and then you get someone who makes a virus and kills the whole world.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, you can make-
SPEAKER_1:  Worst case scenarios for everything. Well, let's just call it. I get the point. Sorry for any interruption.
SPEAKER_1:  And I appreciate worst case analysis because I am a fundamental computer scientist and that was the thing that defined the discipline.
SPEAKER_1:  of the measure the quality of the algorithm, when you measure what is its worst case performance.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the big O notation. That's how you discuss algorithms. What is the worst?
SPEAKER_1:  possible.
SPEAKER_1:  thing.
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of performance this thing can do.
SPEAKER_1:  for climate change. Let's even go.
SPEAKER_1:  Crazy.
SPEAKER_1:  What is exactly the worst case scenario for climate change?
SPEAKER_1:  because uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I have to be honest and say I haven't.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... really paid it
SPEAKER_1:  deep attention, I just have a lot of colleagues who.
SPEAKER_1:  think about climate and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's a kind of in the alarmism, there was a sense why this is, this is a very serious problem.
SPEAKER_1:  and then.
SPEAKER_1:  the sentence would never finish.
SPEAKER_1:  What exactly is the problem with the extinction of the human species? Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  with a virus, I understand how that can possibly happen.
SPEAKER_1:  What is the mechanism by which the human species becomes extinct because of climate change?
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not sure I would want to be able to argue that because it really requires you to have sort of very, very extreme parameter choices all down the line.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's more, it's this kind of idea that we hit some of these unexpected outcomes.
SPEAKER_1:  So for instance, the West Ind Arctic ice sheet melts really, really quickly. It doesn't look like that can happen really, really quickly, but let's just say that this could happen within a hundred years or something. So we basically get what...
SPEAKER_1:  seven meters, what is that? 20 feet of sea level rise.
SPEAKER_1:  That will be a real challenge to a lot of places around the world.
SPEAKER_1:  This would have significant cost. It's likely. And there's actually been a study that's tried to estimate, could we deal with that? And the short answer is yes, if you're fairly well off. If you're a Holland, you can definitely deal with it.
SPEAKER_1:  It's also likely that most
SPEAKER_1:  developing countries are going to be much closer to Holland.
SPEAKER_1:  towards the end of the century because they'll be much richer. So they can probably handle it, but it will be a real challenge. May I ask a dumb question? What happens when the sea...
SPEAKER_1:  level rises exactly, what is the painful aspect of that?
SPEAKER_1:  It is that all of your
SPEAKER_1:  current infrastructure in a lot of coastal cities around the world that are literally built on, you know, Jakarta is a good example, that are literally built on the...
SPEAKER_1:  of inches above the sea level. If you then get a sea level rise, so let us say
SPEAKER_1:  What would 20 feet of that would be like a third or a fourth of a foot every year.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I see no evidence that that's even.
SPEAKER_1:  Hold on a second. Let's, we're not talking about evidence. No talking about worst case analysis and algorithm. And so, so basically you would see your infrastructure, all your stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  very quickly being very, very challenged.
SPEAKER_1:  and you basically have to put up.
SPEAKER_1:  Huge seawalls.
SPEAKER_1:  Or migrate out of that area. Very quickly.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, very quickly as in 50 years or something. Right like-
SPEAKER_1:  I is that.
SPEAKER_1:  as a human species.
SPEAKER_1:  were not able to respond.
SPEAKER_1:  to that kind of story. Of course we are.
SPEAKER_1:  And, and look again, the.
SPEAKER_1:  point here is
SPEAKER_1:  then there's a lot of other arguments. And I should just put the disclaimer, this is not what I think is correct, but you're asking me what's the worst case outcome that you have a
SPEAKER_1:  So most of global warming is really about
SPEAKER_1:  that we.
SPEAKER_1:  We're used to one way of doing things. So, you know, we live in Jakarta because it's right next to the sea. We're used to the sea being at this level. We grow our crops.
SPEAKER_1:  because we're used to, you grow corn here, you grow wheat here, because we're used to that's where the precipitation and the temperature is the right for this kind of crop.
SPEAKER_1:  If
SPEAKER_1:  This changes and this is the same thing with, with, you know, with houses, if it gets colder, if it gets warmer, it's suddenly uncomfortable because you've built your house wrong. So our infrastructure will be wrong if the world changes. And that's what climate change does. At a large scale. Yes. And so this is a problem in most of these sentences.
SPEAKER_1:  But if you then sort of take it to the extreme and say, well, imagine that you're going to get a huge sea level rise. Imagine that you're going to get a very different sort of precipitation. For instance, the rain season, monsoon in the Indian subcontinent changes dramatically. That could affect a lot of agriculture and make it really hard to imagine that you could feed India well.
SPEAKER_1:  There are these kinds of things where you can imagine and then that this would be very difficult to deal with.
SPEAKER_1:  And then if you add all of it up.
SPEAKER_1:  You could possibly get sort of a system collapse because you know, you just have too many problems and it's impossible to model those kinds of things. So...
SPEAKER_1:  What I understand.
SPEAKER_1:  is the sea of Arise itself.
SPEAKER_1:  isn't.
SPEAKER_1:  the destructive thing. It's the fact that it creates migration patterns and human tension, battle over resources.
SPEAKER_1:  and see start to get these.
SPEAKER_1:  These
SPEAKER_1:  human things, human conflict.
SPEAKER_1:  So the big negative impact won't be necessarily from the fact that you have to move your house.
SPEAKER_1:  It's the fact that once you move your house, that means something else down the line, and this is secondary tertiary effects.
SPEAKER_1:  that can have potentially to wars, military conflict.
SPEAKER_1:  can have dist...
SPEAKER_1:  destabilize entire economies all that kind of stuff because of the migration is it possible tomorrow those kind of things
SPEAKER_1:  So there are people who looked at this and surprisingly, again, most people will move within their country for a lot of different reasons, but mainly language and political structure. You have your money, you have your relationships there. So it's not like we're gonna see these big moves from southern Mexico and Central America up to the US or from Africa up to the EU. That's not predominantly because of climate. That's because there's a lot of welfare opportunity. You can make your life much, much better and you can become much more productive if you move into a richer country. So yes, there are these issues. Again, you're asking me for sort of what is it that could really sort of break down the world.
SPEAKER_1:  I think the-
SPEAKER_1:  fundamental point is to recognize
SPEAKER_1:  that it's not like we haven't dealt with huge challenges in the past.
SPEAKER_1:  And we've dealt with them really well. So just one fun thing, I encourage everyone to just look that up on, on Wikipedia, the rising of Chicago.
SPEAKER_1:  So in the 1850s.
SPEAKER_1:  Chicago is a terribly dirty place and they didn't have good sewers.
SPEAKER_1:  And so they decided and we can't really make up all my, they decided to raise.
SPEAKER_1:  Chicago one to two feet.
SPEAKER_1:  And so they simply took one block at a time. They put like 50,000 jacks underneath a building and they would just raise the building and then they'd go on to the next building. They raised all of Chicago.
SPEAKER_1:  One or two feet.
SPEAKER_1:  This is almost 200 years ago. Of course we will be able to deal with these things. I'm not saying it will be fun or that it will be cheap.
SPEAKER_1:  Of course, we would rather not have to deal with this.
SPEAKER_1:  but we're a very inventive species. And so it's very unlikely that we'll not be able to. What about COVID pandemic just said hold my beer.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... other responsive
SPEAKER_1:  human civilization to the
SPEAKER_1:  COVID pandemic.
SPEAKER_1:  seems to have not.
SPEAKER_1:  They didn't find the carjacks. It seems to have not been as effective as I would have.
SPEAKER_1:  of four.
SPEAKER_1:  as a human that believes in the basic competence of leadership and all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems that given the COVID pandemic.
SPEAKER_1:  luckily did not turn out to be.
SPEAKER_1:  a pandemic that would eradicate most of the human species, which is something you always have to consider.
SPEAKER_1:  and worry about.
SPEAKER_1:  I would have hoped we would have less economic impact and
SPEAKER_1:  would respond more effectively.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of policy, in terms of socially.
SPEAKER_1:  medically all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  If the COVID pandemic brought the world to its knees, then what does?
SPEAKER_1:  a sea level rise. I think there's a different kind of thing that happened in the COVID.
SPEAKER_1:  politicians and a lot of politicians, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  Made.
SPEAKER_1:  certainly suboptimal decisions.
SPEAKER_1:  but I also find the fact that we actually managed to get a vaccine.
SPEAKER_1:  in a year.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, we should not be, uh, you know, sort of unaware of the fact that yes, we did a lot of stupid stuff and a lot of people were really, really annoyed.
SPEAKER_1:  Fundamentally, we fixed this.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, we could have done it.
SPEAKER_1:  better and prettier. I mean, I rode through the COVID pandemic in southern Sweden.
SPEAKER_1:  So and
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, we can have that whole conversation. It was certainly much easier to live there than, than many other places. But the fundamental point was...
SPEAKER_1:  We actually fixed it. So yes, we'll do, and we'll do that with climate. We'll make a lot of bad decisions and we'll waste a lot of money.
SPEAKER_1:  like we do with all other problems.
SPEAKER_1:  But are we going to fix this?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you add on to that uncomfortable discussion of what's the worst thing that could possibly happen?
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not worried about the sea level rise component, certainly not nearly as much as the heat and disruption of agriculture patterns and...
SPEAKER_0:  water supplies and a lot of it relates to
SPEAKER_0:  Again, path dependency in history.
SPEAKER_0:  farmers are the heroes of humanity all through history because they're incredibly adaptable.
SPEAKER_0:  if you give them.
SPEAKER_0:  access to resources.
SPEAKER_0:  In some cases, it's just crop insurance.
SPEAKER_0:  which is really basically still impossible to get in big chunks of Africa.
SPEAKER_0:  to get you through those hard spots.
SPEAKER_0:  But the heat issue is the one that's most
SPEAKER_0:  The most basic element related to global warming from CO2.
SPEAKER_0:  build up.
SPEAKER_0:  is hotter.
SPEAKER_0:  Heatwaves.
SPEAKER_0:  There's still some.
SPEAKER_0:  lack of evidence of.
SPEAKER_0:  the intensification, but the.
SPEAKER_0:  duration and.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  That's what really matters for heat, is how many days.
SPEAKER_0:  seems to be very powerfully linked to global warming.
SPEAKER_0:  And so how many people die as a result of that is.
SPEAKER_0:  important.
SPEAKER_1:  talking about.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe you can also educate me. What's the average projection for the next?
SPEAKER_1:  100 years of the temperature rises at two.
SPEAKER_0:  two degrees Celsius. Well, yeah. Although this gets us into the modeling realm.
SPEAKER_0:  You're assuming, you have to assume different emissions.
SPEAKER_0:  possibilities.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to assume.
SPEAKER_0:  We still don't know the.
SPEAKER_0:  basic physics like how many clouds form.
SPEAKER_0:  in a warming climate and how that relates to limiting warming.
SPEAKER_0:  aspects of the fundamental warming question.
SPEAKER_0:  DeepLand's hurt, but the dip.
SPEAKER_1:  The debate is like two, three or four sub-
SPEAKER_0:  I'll see you. It's in that range.
SPEAKER_1:  thing is.
SPEAKER_1:  All of those are bad for...
SPEAKER_1:  This is an educational question. Sure.
SPEAKER_1:  It doesn't seem like that much.
SPEAKER_1:  from a weather perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  if you just turn up the AC and so on in your own personal home
SPEAKER_1:  But it is, from a global perspective, a huge impact on it.
SPEAKER_0:  agriculture.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, yeah, and getting back to sea level and glaciers.
SPEAKER_0:  The melting point of ice is a...
SPEAKER_0:  is a number.
SPEAKER_0:  And so if you pass that number, things start to change.
SPEAKER_0:  What became known about Antarctica and Greenland more is that it's ocean.
SPEAKER_0:  temperature.
SPEAKER_0:  the seawater in and around and under these ice sheets.
SPEAKER_0:  because it kind of gets under.
SPEAKER_0:  parts of Antarctica.
SPEAKER_0:  is what's driving.
SPEAKER_0:  the
SPEAKER_0:  dynamics that could lead to.
SPEAKER_0:  more abrupt change.
SPEAKER_0:  more than air temperature.
SPEAKER_0:  Glaciers, these big ice sheets live or die based on...
SPEAKER_0:  how much snow falls and how much.
SPEAKER_0:  leaves every year.
SPEAKER_0:  and.
SPEAKER_0:  I was up on the greenlit ice sheet.
SPEAKER_0:  2004.
SPEAKER_0:  written about it forever since then.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the same amount of water that's in the Gulf of Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, God or some great force came down and flash flows the Gulf of Mexico and plunked it up on land. That's the ocean. It's a lot of water.
SPEAKER_0:  That's 23 feet.
SPEAKER_0:  See you level rise if you.
SPEAKER_0:  but you were not gonna melt it all.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  the pace at which that.
SPEAKER_0:  Erosion begins.
SPEAKER_0:  and becomes sort of a runaway train.
SPEAKER_0:  is still.
SPEAKER_0:  Not well understood.
SPEAKER_0:  that changed from like.
SPEAKER_0:  Hey.
SPEAKER_0:  manageable level of.
SPEAKER_0:  sea level rise from these ice sheets.
SPEAKER_0:  to something that becomes truly unstoppable or that has these discontinuities where you get a lot more all of a sudden.
SPEAKER_0:  To me, it's in the realm of
SPEAKER_0:  what I've taken to calling known unknowables. Like don't count on another.
SPEAKER_0:  IPCC report magically including science that says, aha, now we know it's going to be five feet by 2100.
SPEAKER_0:  Because there's a lot of negative learning in science. This may be true in your body of science too.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a guy named Jeremy Bassas, B-A-S-S-I-S.
SPEAKER_0:  who wrote a paper about the...
SPEAKER_0:  this Westantic.
SPEAKER_0:  the idea that you could get this.
SPEAKER_0:  sudden cliff.
SPEAKER_0:  breakdown of these ice shelves around Antarctica leading to rapid sea level rise.
SPEAKER_0:  He did more modeling and physics and it turns out that you end up with
SPEAKER_0:  It's a much more progressive and self-limiting phenomenon.
SPEAKER_0:  But those papers don't get any attention in the media.
SPEAKER_0:  because they're not scary and they're sort of after the fact.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  Just this past year, there's been this cycle around.
SPEAKER_0:  The word collapse.
SPEAKER_0:  and Antarctic ice.
SPEAKER_0:  It started.
SPEAKER_0:  actually several years ago with the idea that the West Antarctic Ice Sheet is particularly vulnerable.
SPEAKER_0:  and some paper, everyone, the science community, like the birds we were talking about flocks to it.
SPEAKER_0:  Some high-profile papers are written.
SPEAKER_0:  And then a deeper inquiry reveals, eh, you know, it's more complicated than that.
SPEAKER_0:  and we, the journalists, the media.
SPEAKER_0:  So pundits don't pay attention to.
SPEAKER_0:  That.
SPEAKER_0:  And actually.
SPEAKER_0:  which is why I started to develop kind of a dictionary. I call it watch words, like words if you're out there.
SPEAKER_0:  You're just a public person. You're a person. You want to know what's really going on.
SPEAKER_0:  You hear these words like collapse.
SPEAKER_0:  in the context of ice.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you do with that?
SPEAKER_0:  And so I've created conversations around these words.
SPEAKER_0:  Geologists and ice scientists use the word collapse.
SPEAKER_0:  They're talking about a centuries long process.
SPEAKER_0:  They're not talking about the World Trade Center.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  scientists.
SPEAKER_0:  would do well to be more careful with words like that.
SPEAKER_0:  unless your focus is what we were saying earlier.
SPEAKER_0:  your idea that alarming people will.
SPEAKER_0:  spur them to act.
SPEAKER_0:  then you use that word carelessly.
SPEAKER_1:  Can I just follow up on the other point that you said, you know, two, three, four degrees, you know, that doesn't sound like much. I can just crank up the air.
SPEAKER_1:  air conditioning. I think that sort of touches on a really, really important point.
SPEAKER_1:  that for most rich people.
SPEAKER_1:  much of climate change.
SPEAKER_1:  is not really gonna be.
SPEAKER_1:  all that impactful, it still will have an impact.
SPEAKER_1:  But fundamentally, if you're well off.
SPEAKER_1:  you can mitigate a lot of these impacts.
SPEAKER_0:  there's a young scientist at Carnegie Mellon, Destiny Nock.
SPEAKER_0:  She just was the lead author on a study.
SPEAKER_0:  with poor.
SPEAKER_0:  and prosperous households do in a heat wave.
SPEAKER_0:  when they have access to air conditioning.
SPEAKER_0:  in a poor household.
SPEAKER_0:  You wait.
SPEAKER_0:  they found through science.
SPEAKER_0:  They delay turning on the air conditioner.
SPEAKER_0:  four to seven degrees more of heating before they start to use the air conditioner.
SPEAKER_0:  And that create adverse outcomes if you have an asthmatic in the house, an old person.
SPEAKER_0:  you're endangering their lives. And that's just a little tiny microscopic.
SPEAKER_0:  fractal example of this powerful real phenomenon that there's a divide.
SPEAKER_0:  and vulnerability and it's not just.
SPEAKER_0:  based on where you live.
SPEAKER_0:  This is families in Pittsburgh.
SPEAKER_0:  We're not talking about, you know, Botswana.
SPEAKER_0:  So that divide in capacity to deal with.
SPEAKER_0:  environmental stress is.
SPEAKER_0:  something you can really work on and it gets hidden.
SPEAKER_0:  in all this talk of climate crisis.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's one of the important parts is both to say, look.
SPEAKER_1:  If.
SPEAKER_1:  Seven.
SPEAKER_1:  billion people sorry 8 billion people
SPEAKER_1:  will now have all experienced this, even though for each one of them, it's manageable, it's still a big problem because it's, you know, eight billion people living through this. And the second- And the air conditioning eight billion people. And then it's the point of getting-
SPEAKER_1:  to realize it's very, very much about how do you help the world's poor.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's very much about making it more affordable, basically getting them out of poverty. And remember, getting out of poverty doesn't just mean that they can now afford to air condition themselves, but they get better education, they get better opportunities, they get better lives in so many other ways.
SPEAKER_1:  And then...
SPEAKER_1:  at the end of it, it's not just about making sure that we focus on this one problem.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's recognizing that these families and have lots of different issues that they would like us to focus on.
SPEAKER_1:  climate and heat waves just being one of them.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's sort of taking progressive steps back and realizing, all right, okay, this is a problem.
SPEAKER_0:  not the end of the world. And one tiny little last example, we mentioned Jakarta at the beginning.
SPEAKER_0:  It's really valuable to look around the world places that are sort of leading indicator places.
SPEAKER_0:  whether it's sea level rise or heat.
SPEAKER_0:  And you can do that.
SPEAKER_0:  Jakarta is sinking. Hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  Like a foot a year, literally a foot a year. It's some insane number.
SPEAKER_0:  from withdrawing groundwater from.
SPEAKER_0:  gas withdrawal from, it's a delta, it's sediment, it's built on sediment.
SPEAKER_0:  I wrote a piece ages ago at the New York Times calling it Delta Blues, you know, the musicians..
SPEAKER_0:  So what are they doing? They're moving. They're moving the capital to another country. So, what are they doing? They're moving.
SPEAKER_0:  area
SPEAKER_0:  And so that says to me.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a lot of plasticity too. It's a city that's going through this.
SPEAKER_0:  That rate of sea level.
SPEAKER_0:  of their relationship with the sea level.
SPEAKER_0:  through sinking is way faster than what's happening with global warming.
SPEAKER_0:  So look there, look to those kinds of places and you can start to build.
SPEAKER_1:  Tokyo had the same thing in the 1930s, so we're also withdrawing.
SPEAKER_1:  a lot to water way too fast. And so, you know, one of the obvious things is maybe you should stop withdrawing water so fast.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and again, we seem to almost be intent on finding the most politically correct way to fix a problem or the most...
SPEAKER_1:  the thing that sort of gets the most clicks instead of the thing that actually works the best
SPEAKER_1:  So a lot of these things are really not rocket science solutions. Well, we'll get there. Let me add one more on top of the pile of the worst case analysis. So what people talk about which is hurricanes and earthquakes.
SPEAKER_1:  does is their connection.
SPEAKER_1:  that's well understood between climate change.
SPEAKER_1:  and the increased
SPEAKER_1:  frequency and intensity of hurricanes and earthquakes.
SPEAKER_0:  I've dug in on both a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  The earthquake.
SPEAKER_0:  connection to climate change I'm not worried about compared to just the earthquake risk that we live with in many parts of the world already.
SPEAKER_0:  The Himalayas.
SPEAKER_0:  even with that earthquake in 2015 in Kathmandu.
SPEAKER_0:  that whole range.
SPEAKER_0:  is overdue.
SPEAKER_0:  IV
SPEAKER_0:  major earthquakes and what has happened in the last 50 years.
SPEAKER_0:  since they last had big earthquakes, huge development, big cities.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of informal construction.
SPEAKER_0:  like the stuff I wrote about in Istanbul.
SPEAKER_0:  where the family.
SPEAKER_0:  builds another layer and another, they put a floor on every time someone gets married has kids, you put another floor in the house. And unfortunately that's, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  What was the term?
SPEAKER_0:  Turkish.
SPEAKER_0:  engineer.
SPEAKER_0:  Rubble in waiting.
SPEAKER_0:  It's rubble and waiting and we're looking at it, you know, videotaping it.
SPEAKER_0:  There are people playing there. So don't worry about the Earthquake connection or climate change.
SPEAKER_0:  The Hurricanes I've written about for decades.
SPEAKER_0:  and the most illuminating body of science.
SPEAKER_0:  Drive.
SPEAKER_0:  dug in on literally.
SPEAKER_0:  Related to hurricanes is this field that's emerged gets a tiny bit of money compared to like climate modeling.
SPEAKER_0:  called Paleo-Tempestology.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like paleontology, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  They look for evidence of past hurricanes along coasts.
SPEAKER_0:  that we care about.
SPEAKER_0:  and they dig down into the lagoons.
SPEAKER_0:  behind the barrier beaches along Florida or the Carolinas or in Puerto Rico.
SPEAKER_0:  And what you have is a history book of past hurricanes.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's mud, mud, mud, mud, mud, mud, mud, mud, you know, accumulating over centuries. And then there's
SPEAKER_0:  layer of sand.
SPEAKER_0:  and seashells. And what that indicates is that there was a great storm.
SPEAKER_0:  came across the beach, pushed a lot of sediment into the mud.
SPEAKER_0:  And then there's mutt, mutt, mutt, mutt, mutt, mutt.
SPEAKER_0:  And when you look at that work...
SPEAKER_0:  I first wrote about this in 2001 in the Times, a long...
SPEAKER_0:  Story in then.
SPEAKER_0:  kept track of these.
SPEAKER_0:  Intrepid scientists.
SPEAKER_0:  putting these core tubes down.
SPEAKER_0:  It shows you that we're in a landscape where...
SPEAKER_0:  big bad hurricanes are.
SPEAKER_0:  They're the norm.
SPEAKER_0:  Something that's rare and big is.
SPEAKER_0:  Something that's extreme, when you think about the word extreme, right, it means it's at the end of the spectrum of what's possible.
SPEAKER_0:  They're rare.
SPEAKER_0:  rare in human time scales.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Hurricane Michael four years ago devastated, category five came ashore.
SPEAKER_0:  in the Panhandle of Florida.
SPEAKER_0:  level that much photograph.
SPEAKER_0:  Mexico Beach.
SPEAKER_0:  And um...
SPEAKER_0:  People.
SPEAKER_0:  actually the Tallahassee National Weather Service said unprecedented.
SPEAKER_0:  hurricane.
SPEAKER_0:  The damage was unprecedented.
SPEAKER_0:  because there hadn't been a community there before.
SPEAKER_0:  But the hurricane was not unprecedented at all. If you look at the history, and this is published research, just that no one bothers to-
SPEAKER_0:  We have this blind spot.
SPEAKER_0:  for a.
SPEAKER_0:  the longer time scale you need to examine if you're thinking about big bad things that are rare.
SPEAKER_0:  and hurricanes.
SPEAKER_0:  are still.
SPEAKER_0:  Rare, I-
SPEAKER_0:  was recently covering Fort Myers, the awful devastation.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a young climate scientist at.
SPEAKER_0:  Florida.
SPEAKER_0:  Gulf Coast University, Joe Muller.
SPEAKER_0:  who's done that paleotempastology work there, right in Fort Myers. She lives there and she was away in London at a meeting of reinsurance companies that reinsure all the world's big bad risks.
SPEAKER_0:  when this was happening.
SPEAKER_0:  but she has done the work that shows it's a thousand year record of past hurricanes and it's super sobering.
SPEAKER_0:  when you consider how fast.
SPEAKER_0:  people have moved into.
SPEAKER_0:  Florida.
SPEAKER_0:  and built vulnerably in an area.
SPEAKER_0:  that hurricanes will hammer.
SPEAKER_0:  that part of the fundamental dynamics of the Gulf of Mexico and the storms come off of Africa.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a place where they would come.
SPEAKER_0:  Now the question of global warming impact is.
SPEAKER_0:  subtle. There are aspects of hurricanes.
SPEAKER_0:  that haven't changed.
SPEAKER_0:  there's aspects like rainfall.
SPEAKER_0:  that seem pretty.
SPEAKER_0:  powerfully linked to global warming.
SPEAKER_0:  warmer atmosphere holds more moisture. So when you have a big disturbance like a...
SPEAKER_0:  the heat engine of a hurricane comes through it.
SPEAKER_0:  get more rain.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  this rapid intensification, you know, how quickly these storms.
SPEAKER_0:  jump from like, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Category one to five or four.
SPEAKER_0:  before they hit.
SPEAKER_0:  is a new area of science. So I think it's still.
SPEAKER_0:  early days in knowing.
SPEAKER_0:  because no one was looking for that.
SPEAKER_0:  There were no data back-
SPEAKER_0:  300 years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, when these...
SPEAKER_0:  big bad previous hurricanes came to know whether they were rapidly intensified or not.
SPEAKER_0:  So as a journalist, I try to.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, keep track of what we don't know, not be too...
SPEAKER_0:  constrained and
SPEAKER_0:  Think about new science as being.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  robust unless it's considering and actually actively.
SPEAKER_0:  stating that
SPEAKER_0:  We don't really know what's going on with earlier hurricanes.
SPEAKER_0:  And all of that is swamped.
SPEAKER_0:  Ultimately, literally.
SPEAKER_0:  by the vulnerability, building vulnerability.
SPEAKER_0:  in these areas. If there's a marginal change in a storm...
SPEAKER_0:  and you've quadrupled or sextupled.
SPEAKER_0:  how much stuff and how many people are in the way.
SPEAKER_0:  And if some of those people are poor and vulnerable.
SPEAKER_0:  or elderly and
SPEAKER_0:  Can't swim.
SPEAKER_0:  you're creating a landscape of destruction.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of the human suffering that has to do with storms is about
SPEAKER_1:  where and how you build.
SPEAKER_1:  versus the frequency and the intensity of storms. So you didn't quite answer the question.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, when I'm having a beer with people at a bar and they say, Hey, why are you having a beer? We're all going to die because of climate change. Usually what they bring up.
SPEAKER_1:  And I'm just trying to add some levi-
SPEAKER_0:  This is good.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, usually what they bring up is, you know, the hurricanes and the recent, most recent hurricanes saying like this, they're, they're getting crazy hurricanes all the time. They're getting.
SPEAKER_1:  more intense, more frequent and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  That's is there.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm sure there's incredible science going on trying to look at this.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there, is it possible?
SPEAKER_1:  Is there evidence and is it possible to have evidence?
SPEAKER_1:  that there's a connection.
SPEAKER_1:  between.
SPEAKER_1:  what we can call global warming and the increased frequency and intensity of storms. the
SPEAKER_0:  No, thank you.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you added intensity, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  It's, it's...
SPEAKER_0:  Let me just get into this a tiny bit more.1509
SPEAKER_0:  I grew up with them in Rhode Island in my youth and there was a very active period of hurricanes in New England.
SPEAKER_0:  in the 50s and 60s, 70s.
SPEAKER_0:  And then.
SPEAKER_0:  in the North Atlantic generally was very, very active.
SPEAKER_0:  50 when I was a kid.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  dynamics of them forming off of Africa and coming here circling up the coast was just primetime.
SPEAKER_0:  Then there was like
SPEAKER_0:  what Kerry Emanuel, who's the.
SPEAKER_0:  must
SPEAKER_0:  experienced hurricane climate scientists around at MIT.
SPEAKER_0:  He was in, he's in this story. He's in my 1988 article.
SPEAKER_0:  He-
SPEAKER_0:  and colleagues have found and others that.
SPEAKER_0:  There's what they call the hurricane drought.
SPEAKER_0:  from like the 70s through about 1994.
SPEAKER_0:  in the Atlantic, specifically the Atlantic basin.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  been a lot of questions about that. People thought it was ocean circulation, something about the the currents.
SPEAKER_0:  This is multi-decade old.
SPEAKER_0:  variabilities in the oceans, right?
SPEAKER_0:  And then now it looks.
SPEAKER_0:  Robustly, I can't find a climate scientist who disagrees.
SPEAKER_0:  that the thing that caused the drought.
SPEAKER_0:  was pollution, smog.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  significantly in Europe. And you're saying, well, how does smog in Europe relate to hurricanes?
SPEAKER_0:  crossing the Atlantic and getting to.
SPEAKER_0:  the United States. It's because of
SPEAKER_0:  The smog was changing.
SPEAKER_0:  the behavior of the Sahara Desert, which is just south of Europe.
SPEAKER_0:  And the Sahara Desert kills hurricanes.
SPEAKER_0:  sand and dust coming off the Sahara. You can see this every year when that's active.
SPEAKER_0:  stifles these big storms at the point right in their nursery. They all form.
SPEAKER_0:  there's this area for hurricanes off of West Africa.
SPEAKER_0:  That's like the nursery zone.
SPEAKER_0:  And so if you're stifling those heart gains because of pollution,
SPEAKER_0:  in Europe.
SPEAKER_0:  before the Clean Air Act's kind of cleanups.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And then that goes away.
SPEAKER_0:  None of that has anything to do with global warming.
SPEAKER_0:  That's another kind of forcing in the climate system, a local one that created a regional dynamic.
SPEAKER_0:  that created a quiet period.
SPEAKER_0:  when all these friends in the bar...
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe they were born.
SPEAKER_0:  in the 90s or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  They grew up in an area of like.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  No, hurricanes weren't a big deal.
SPEAKER_0:  And now we have an end to that drought because we cleaned up the air pollution.
SPEAKER_0:  the sooty kind of air pollution, sulfury.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Anyone who says global warming, global warming without saying, well, that's in there too, is kind of missing.
SPEAKER_0:  And when you look globally...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there's still, I think it was at 90 or so hurricanes a year, cyclones, hurricanes, typhoons.
SPEAKER_0:  globally. That hasn't changed. The number of
SPEAKER_0:  these tropical storms that reach.
SPEAKER_0:  that ferocity has not changed.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just a fundamental dynamic of.
SPEAKER_0:  And by the way, on the long time scale, the models.
SPEAKER_0:  still indicate.
SPEAKER_0:  as you warm the planet. And remember the Arctic warms quicker.
SPEAKER_0:  This is something people probably understand.
SPEAKER_0:  you're actually evening out the imbalance between the heat at the equator
SPEAKER_0:  and the cold at the...
SPEAKER_0:  in the northern part of the hemisphere.
SPEAKER_0:  and that calms the whole system down. So there could be fewer hurricanes.
SPEAKER_0:  later in the century because of global warming.
SPEAKER_0:  And for me, that's a lot of information, but if I'm in a bar...
SPEAKER_0:  I start with, what do you care about?
SPEAKER_0:  about safety.
SPEAKER_0:  care about security, you care about.
SPEAKER_0:  having everybody safe, not just you. You get in your car and you can evacuate. What about the old person?
SPEAKER_0:  you know, or the poor family.
SPEAKER_0:  who can't do that, they're not gonna leave their house.
SPEAKER_0:  What are we doing to limit vulnerability now?
SPEAKER_0:  I circle back to that over and over again. I have like a pocket card.
SPEAKER_0:  graphic card I created about risk.
SPEAKER_0:  What we really care about is climate risk.
SPEAKER_0:  Like who's at risk?
SPEAKER_0:  What's driving the risk?
SPEAKER_0:  How do you reduce that? It's a card, you can almost pull it out in a bar. I should print them. You should do that. A risk is the hazard.
SPEAKER_0:  Risk is the hazard, like, you know, the hazard is.
SPEAKER_0:  is a storm.
SPEAKER_0:  times exposure.
SPEAKER_0:  how many people.
SPEAKER_0:  how much stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  Factoring in.
SPEAKER_0:  Vulnerability.
SPEAKER_0:  or resilience.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Climate change is changing the hazard.
SPEAKER_0:  for some things, not for tornadoes, not for everything.
SPEAKER_0:  Exposure?
SPEAKER_0:  is this expanding bullseye. This is another hashtag, expanding bullseye.
SPEAKER_0:  out there and look for that and you'll see.
SPEAKER_0:  pushing these two geographers.
SPEAKER_0:  Do this for every hazard. wildlife
SPEAKER_0:  Earthquake.
SPEAKER_0:  flood.
SPEAKER_0:  Coastal Storm.
SPEAKER_0:  and we're building and expanding bullseye in an area where nature is throwing darts.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of the darts are getting bigger because of global warming. Some of the darts we don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you do?
SPEAKER_0:  What do you do? Well, you get out of the way. You don't want to be on the dartboard.
SPEAKER_0:  And that, it just simplifies the whole formula.
SPEAKER_0:  To me, it's kind of a transformational.
SPEAKER_0:  potential.
SPEAKER_0:  to go into a bar. Maybe I should print these things. 100%.
SPEAKER_1:  as you go to the with you
SPEAKER_0:  They should be coasters in bars.
SPEAKER_1:  fascinating about smog and I mean just
SPEAKER_1:  It's nice to be reminded about how complicated and fascinating the weather system is. Let me try to answer the questions slightly quicker before your friends have drunk too much.
SPEAKER_1:  Never enough. Or not enough.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  So if you look at.
SPEAKER_1:  the amount of the number of hurricanes, as Andy rightly pointed out.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  It doesn't look like it's changing. So we see more because we have now much better detection systems with satellites.
SPEAKER_1:  But if you look since 1980, when we have good satellite coverage, for instance last year,
SPEAKER_1:  was the year that had the lowest number of hurricanes in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  And you're sort of like, that's odd because it's probably the year where I heard the most about hurricanes.
SPEAKER_1:  And what that tells you is that just because you hear a lot about hurricanes doesn't actually mean
SPEAKER_1:  that there is a lot of hurricanes. You can't just go that way. If you remember in the 1990s and 2000s,
SPEAKER_1:  There was an enormous amount of talk about how violence, how crime was getting worse in the US, while all the objective indicators showed that it was going down.
SPEAKER_1:  There's sufficient amount of violence.
SPEAKER_1:  that you can fill every radio and TV show with a new crime.
SPEAKER_1:  And so if you get more and more TV shows that talk about crime,
SPEAKER_1:  Actually, most people end up thinking that there's more crime while the real number is going down.
SPEAKER_1:  The reality here is...
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  climate change.
SPEAKER_1:  will probably affect.
SPEAKER_1:  hurricanes in the sense that they'll
SPEAKER_1:  be the same number, slightly fewer as Andy was mentioning.
SPEAKER_1:  but they will likely be somewhat stronger.
SPEAKER_1:  This seems to be...
SPEAKER_1:  the best outcome. We're not sure, but this seems to be the outcome. And it's important to remember
SPEAKER_1:  Stronger is worse.
SPEAKER_1:  then fewer is better.
SPEAKER_1:  So overall.
SPEAKER_1:  Climate will make...
SPEAKER_1:  the world a little bit worse.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's the sort of bottom line, and that's the real issue here.
SPEAKER_1:  all the other things, the fact that people are much more vulnerable is just vastly outweigh this, which is why if you look at the impact...
SPEAKER_1:  of hurricanes and impact of pretty much everything.
SPEAKER_1:  It is typically going down.
SPEAKER_1:  If you look, for instance, in percent of GDP, you have to look at percent of GDP because if you have twice as many houses, obviously the same kind of impact will have twice.
SPEAKER_1:  the impact or if they're worth twice as much.
SPEAKER_1:  If you do that in percent of GDP and even the UN says that's how you should measure it, it's going down.
SPEAKER_1:  Why is that?
SPEAKER_1:  It's because we're becoming more resilient. Yeah. Just simply we, you know, if you look at what happens with when hurricanes come in, we have much better prediction in the long run.
SPEAKER_1:  That means you now know two or three days out.
SPEAKER_1:  that there's a big hurricane that's likely to come here? What does that mean? All the-
SPEAKER_1:  things that can be moved. So typically all buses, all trucks.
SPEAKER_1:  Everything that's not bolted down will leave this area. And so you'll get less damage from that. You will have more people knowing, oh, this is gonna be a big one. They moved to their relatives somewhere else. So you'll have fewer people being vulnerable.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a lot of- If people are responsive and aware. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot of ways you can do this.
SPEAKER_1:  The outcome, and this is important for the whole conversation, the outcome is...
SPEAKER_1:  that we're actually becoming less vulnerable.
SPEAKER_1:  and the
SPEAKER_1:  Damages are-
SPEAKER_1:  becoming smaller, not bigger, but...
SPEAKER_1:  had there not been global warming.
SPEAKER_1:  it would probably have gone down even faster.
SPEAKER_1:  So we would have become even better off.
SPEAKER_1:  quicker.
SPEAKER_1:  had there been no global warming.
SPEAKER_1:  But this is a crucial difference, and this is what I find really hard to communicate.
SPEAKER_1:  Climate change is not this.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh my God, everything is going off the charts and we're all going to be doomed kind of thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Climate change is a thing that means we're going to get better.
SPEAKER_1:  slightly slower.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's a very, very different kind of attitude. It's one of the many problems rather than, this is the end of all of us.
SPEAKER_0:  And by the way, if you look at what's happening in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  The data also show...
SPEAKER_0:  in rich places and poor places, we still are moving into zones of hazard faster than climate is changing.
SPEAKER_0:  Beth Tellman.
SPEAKER_0:  was at Columbia and she moved to Arizona.
SPEAKER_0:  She and colleagues at this outfit called Cloud to Street.
SPEAKER_0:  did an amazing study showing.
SPEAKER_0:  This is a year or so ago I wrote about showing.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, we're moving into zones of hazard, which it applies to me.
SPEAKER_0:  Just what Bjorn was saying that.
SPEAKER_0:  We wouldn't be, people wouldn't be doing that if.
SPEAKER_0:  They thought that was going to lead to devastation. And this is today.
SPEAKER_0:  We're doing this now and it's flood.
SPEAKER_0:  Flood zones, wildfire zones.
SPEAKER_0:  So that means there's these things to do.
SPEAKER_0:  There's so much plasticity in human behavior and how we build and...
SPEAKER_0:  where we build. You can make a big, big change in the outcomes.
SPEAKER_1:  Wait, one of the things to remember is, you know, people move...
SPEAKER_1:  to where hurricanes hit because when they're not there, it's a really beautiful place to be. Yeah, yeah. Right, so in many ways, we make the trade-offs and say, look, I'm happy to live.
SPEAKER_1:  have an ocean view and then maybe a hurricane is going to hit. Of course, it becomes a lot easier than when the federal government is actually subsidizing your risk.
SPEAKER_1:  By saying, we'll ensure you're really cheaply. Uh, and that's one of the things that we should stop doing.
SPEAKER_1:  We should actually tell people, look, if you want to live where hurricanes hit, maybe you should be more careful.
SPEAKER_0:  By the way, what I was saying about...
SPEAKER_0:  past storms, the paleotempestology.
SPEAKER_0:  past fires, it's the same thing. We've suppressed fire.
SPEAKER_0:  in the United States for 100 years through much of the West.
SPEAKER_0:  through.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  wanting to save the forests, you know, the whole smokey the bear thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't stop.
SPEAKER_0:  when these are landscapes that evolved to burn.
SPEAKER_0:  And what happened in the last 100 years?
SPEAKER_0:  people love the West. We love these environments. We love to live with the trees.
SPEAKER_0:  the Boulder County area.
SPEAKER_0:  explosive development in zones of implicit hazard.
SPEAKER_0:  leads to big bad outcomes when conditions align and climate change is worsening some of those conditions and sometimes it's really counterintuitive.
SPEAKER_0:  wet season builds more grass.
SPEAKER_0:  Dry season comes along, parches the grass.
SPEAKER_0:  Then comes a human ignition. It's almost always human ignitions.
SPEAKER_0:  And then you have this disaster where a thousand homes burn in Boulder County.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  There's so many elements there that can be worked on.
SPEAKER_0:  Give me confidence.
SPEAKER_0:  that we can.
SPEAKER_0:  change these outcomes. Natural disasters are not natural disasters.
SPEAKER_0:  designed really, some people say.
SPEAKER_1:  Can I take a quick aside and ask about-
SPEAKER_1:  terminology of climate change and global warming. Yeah, you use it.
SPEAKER_1:  interchangeably.
SPEAKER_1:  It isn't a side, but.
SPEAKER_1:  That's one that's worthy of taking.
SPEAKER_1:  Do those carry different meanings?
SPEAKER_1:  And has that meaning changed over the years?
SPEAKER_1:  Between those two terms, are they really equivalent?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, some people say there was this industry or...
SPEAKER_0:  propagandistic shift from.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's see, what was it? Which came first? Oh no, they're going to climate change now. Like it's a new thing. We're just
SPEAKER_0:  It's ridiculous.
SPEAKER_0:  The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change.
SPEAKER_0:  In 1988, it wasn't the Intergovernmental Panel on Global Warming.
SPEAKER_0:  It was on climate change.
SPEAKER_0:  So this...
SPEAKER_0:  These terms have been there, they've been sort of evolving. When I wrote this cover story, it was the greenhouse effect.
SPEAKER_0:  So green and that's fall.
SPEAKER_1:  on a favorite greenhouse effect is not
SPEAKER_0:  often talked about. Well, it's really that's the physical effect that's holding in the heat. But see, it's not a good there's terms that mean.
SPEAKER_1:  stuff and there's terms that actually used in public discourse.
SPEAKER_1:  to designate what your.
SPEAKER_1:  A whole.
SPEAKER_1:  umbrella of opinions you have.
SPEAKER_1:  And I guess it's somebody, me, who doesn't pay attention.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... to this carefully
SPEAKER_1:  You have to use terms carefully. Sure. Because people will-
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  and and new that rose into the topic will often use terms
SPEAKER_1:  to mean exactly what they mean, like literally.
SPEAKER_1:  but they actually have political implications and all that kind of stuff. I guess I'm asking, is there like...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, is, is there, uh, are you signaling something by using
SPEAKER_1:  global warming versus climate change, are people have calmed down in terms of
SPEAKER_0:  of the use of these. You've got an
SPEAKER_0:  newspapers made it worse.
SPEAKER_0:  Now they have their style book, you know, every newspaper has a.
SPEAKER_0:  They they
SPEAKER_0:  prescribed, they don't want their reporters to use any of those terms anymore. They call it climate crisis.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh no.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yeah. Global heating. It's literally in their rule book.
SPEAKER_0:  global heating that's all
SPEAKER_1:  more intense. And that was the point.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I wrote about the global heating.
SPEAKER_0:  more than a decade ago, that's been around. But you know, so they're
SPEAKER_0:  They're doing the...
SPEAKER_0:  What was the movie where the?
SPEAKER_0:  the comedy, the rock and roll comedy where he sets his, his amplifier goes to 11. You know, the idea that you turn up the rhetorical volume that's going to change people's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's ridiculous. So for me, I use global warming and climate change interchangeably. And I think it's fair. There's some technical ways that you can differentiate them. But the reality is global warming is probably a better way to describe a lot of it, because this is really what is the main driver of what we worry about. Climate change seems a little diffuse, but it's convenient to, when you talk about climate all the time, that you can call both of them. But I think the climate crisis and the climate catastrophe
SPEAKER_1:  is really sort of the amping up.
SPEAKER_1:  of a catastrophe and again as we've talked about before.
SPEAKER_1:  If it really were true, we should
SPEAKER_1:  help people.
SPEAKER_1:  But if it's not true, and I think there's a lot of reasons why this is not a, you know, a climate catastrophe, this is a problem. Uh, we're actually doing everyone a disservice because we end up making people so worried that they say, we got to fix this in 12 years or whatever the number is.
SPEAKER_1:  And also that it makes it almost impossible to have a conversation of, well, maybe we should be focusing on vulnerability first. And a lot of people, and I think a lot of well-meaning.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... and well-intentioned people
SPEAKER_1:  feel that it's almost sacrilegious to say it's about vulnerability because you're taking away
SPEAKER_1:  You, the guilt of climate change, you're taking away our focus on, on, on dealing with climate change, whereas I think we would say it's about stuff that actually works and doing that for.
SPEAKER_0:  By and by making it about
SPEAKER_0:  carbon dioxide, you're implicitly making it about fossil fuels.
SPEAKER_0:  which implicitly gives you another great narrative, good guy, bad guy.
SPEAKER_0:  It's these big companies.
SPEAKER_0:  Where's the source of-
SPEAKER_1:  alarmism.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  Is it the IPCC, the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change? There's a chain here.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there somebody to blame along the chain or is this some kind of weird complex system where everybody encourages each other?
SPEAKER_1:  Can you point to one place? Is it the media?
SPEAKER_1:  Is it the scientists? I think the UN climate panel is fundamentally a really good climate research group.
SPEAKER_1:  You can have some quibbles with the way that they summarize it in politically coordinated documents and stuff. But fundamentally, I think they do a good job.
SPEAKER_1:  of putting together all the research.
SPEAKER_1:  This also means it's incredibly boring to read, which is why virtually nobody does. I'm sure you have, but I'm pretty sure a lot of-
SPEAKER_1:  climate journalists have never sort of looked past the, at least the summary for policymakers. So they- You're on a climate panel, they do like a, they do predictions as well? No, well, they pull together all the stuff that people have published in the period literature.
SPEAKER_1:  and then try to summarize it and basically tell you what's up and down with climate change.
SPEAKER_1:  They do that in four.
SPEAKER_1:  four large volumes every four to five, six, seven years or something.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, and, um, and yes, it's, it's, you know, I think it's the gold plated version of what we know. Uh, there tends to be a lot of.
SPEAKER_1:  Umm...
SPEAKER_1:  Well, this is what they say. Actually, they say so many different places with so many different people that it's not quite clear exactly what they're saying often. You can find contradictions between one volume with one set of authors and another. But, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I think this is fundamentally the right.
SPEAKER_1:  way that we know about.
SPEAKER_1:  climate.
SPEAKER_1:  but then it gets translated into
SPEAKER_1:  How do you know about this? When most people don't read these 4,000 pages, you read a new story.
SPEAKER_1:  in a newspaper.
SPEAKER_1:  And that new story will be very, very heavily slanted towards, you know, if, if you say, so sea levels could rise somewhere between one and three foot.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you hear?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, you obviously hear the three foot. Three foot is just more fun, more scary, more interesting than one foot.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's that way with all of these, you know, so what was the prediction for temperature rises? It's somewhere from not very scary to pretty damn scary. And again, you hear the pretty damn scary all the time.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, and, and then there's, there's obviously always researchers who are saying, well, but actually could be a little more scary than that.
SPEAKER_1:  And then there are likewise research who say, well, it's probably not going to be as scary as that.
SPEAKER_1:  And most of the journalists will.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, interview. Do you really put the blame fundamentally on the journalist? I put it on the media setup. Look, media is simply trying to get.
SPEAKER_1:  clicks or sell newspapers.
SPEAKER_1:  And if you were just going to say.
SPEAKER_1:  This is not a big issue. It just doesn't sell anything. But I think you're probably much better able to.
SPEAKER_1:  address this.
SPEAKER_0:  Folks can Google for my name Revkin and.
SPEAKER_0:  the words front page thought.
SPEAKER_0:  in the newsroom.
SPEAKER_0:  every afternoon.
SPEAKER_0:  Now we have a 24-7 news cycle, so it's different.
SPEAKER_0:  back in the day, the New York Times, when it was flourishing.
SPEAKER_0:  print institution. Every afternoon there was a front page meeting.
SPEAKER_0:  and the big PoohBah editors go in there.
SPEAKER_0:  and the desk editors come in with their pitches for the day.
SPEAKER_0:  and my friend Corey Dean, who is the science editor for a chunk of my time.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I remember having a conversation with her about.
SPEAKER_0:  some new study of, I think it was Greenland, the ice sheet.
SPEAKER_0:  I laid it out for her and she said, where's the front page thought in that?
SPEAKER_0:  So we're all set up.
SPEAKER_0:  Look for the...
SPEAKER_0:  That's scary, but you know.
SPEAKER_0:  The news environment has gotten so much worse than.
SPEAKER_0:  than 10 or 20 years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  least you had filters and...
SPEAKER_0:  limited number of outlets and there was some sense you could
SPEAKER_0:  track was.
SPEAKER_0:  or bad. There's lots of problems with that system too. But now you have an information buffet.
SPEAKER_0:  So if you want to be alarmed or you want to be...
SPEAKER_0:  stay in the tribe of those who think this is utter bull, you can find your
SPEAKER_0:  flow.
SPEAKER_0:  and.
SPEAKER_0:  That is Lid.
SPEAKER_0:  But getting back to this specific question, the 2018 IPCC report, which was a special report commissioned
SPEAKER_0:  learn about the difference between 1.5 degrees of warming and 2.
SPEAKER_0:  which sounds so weird and technocratic and
SPEAKER_0:  Complicated.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the one that generated the whole.
SPEAKER_0:  meme about eight years left.
SPEAKER_1:  12 years. Till doomsday.
SPEAKER_0:  23rd and that's the one.
SPEAKER_0:  This was the idea that there's a point we're going to.
SPEAKER_0:  If we don't.
SPEAKER_0:  cut emissions in half by whatever it was, 2050, we're doomed.
SPEAKER_0:  that emerged from that specific report.
SPEAKER_0:  And it wasn't something that was in the report. It was in the spin around the report.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's what.
SPEAKER_0:  captivated Greta appropriately as a young person going, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  and with her unique vantage point and stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  That rep, I still need to dig in and write something deeper about.
SPEAKER_0:  what happened with that particular dynamics.
SPEAKER_0:  created this recent burst of
SPEAKER_0:  We're doomed.
SPEAKER_0:  Rhetoric.
SPEAKER_0:  I think you're.
SPEAKER_0:  focusing on.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It's all in the external.
SPEAKER_0:  interpretations, which journalism laps up.
SPEAKER_0:  because we're looking for the front page thought.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's not just the journalists, it's the whole system.
SPEAKER_0:  NGOs, environmental groups.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're, if.
SPEAKER_0:  and developing country.
SPEAKER_0:  well-meaning leaders in developing countries.
SPEAKER_0:  because of the structure of this treaty that goes back to 1992.
SPEAKER_0:  Paris Agreement as part of.
SPEAKER_0:  There now.
SPEAKER_0:  really looking for a way to portray this as a CO2 problem.
SPEAKER_0:  Not a vulnerability.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, there's a vulnerability aspect, but in Pakistan, they're
SPEAKER_0:  climate minister, which they didn't even have a climate minister five years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  is blaming everything that happened in Pakistan on carbon dioxide warming the climate creating this.
SPEAKER_0:  when a lot of what was going on was also on the ground.
SPEAKER_0:  and you can blame colonialism, Pakistan's history, and all kinds of things.
SPEAKER_0:  but under the treaty, you want it to be about CO2.
SPEAKER_0:  because that puts the onus on rich countries.
SPEAKER_0:  You're not paying us.
SPEAKER_0:  Where's our money? And they're right.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, in the context of what everyone agreed to.
SPEAKER_0:  There was supposed to be $100 billion a year.
SPEAKER_0:  from rich countries to poor countries. Starting in 2020, it didn't happen. It's like.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically.
SPEAKER_0:  Some money is flowing, but it's not really made up money. Yeah, and so that whole dynamic.
SPEAKER_0:  latch onto the climate science and they, you know, so they're there.
SPEAKER_0:  and they're very handy, quotable people.
SPEAKER_0:  you have a justice angle, you have bad guys and good guys.
SPEAKER_0:  which fits all of these narrative threads to come together into.
SPEAKER_0:  this information storm we're still living with.
SPEAKER_1:  And then of course, it's not Pakistan's fault either. I mean, it also actually almost all leaders now say it's because of climate, because then it's not.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, we didn't do anything wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  In Germany, for instance, when we had that flood last year.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not impossible that climate had a part in that.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's very, very clear that the main reason why so many people died in Germany and Belgium.
SPEAKER_1:  was because the alarm systems didn't work.
SPEAKER_1:  And this was.
SPEAKER_1:  plainly the local leaders in Germany. Now, if I'm stuck here and basically have caused the death of 200 people,
SPEAKER_1:  Would I rather say, yeah, that's on me or would I?
SPEAKER_1:  climate. It's just such an easy scapegoat. I don't want to place it all on the journalists, I think, because there's a lot of
SPEAKER_1:  If I were to think about, what did you call it? Front.
SPEAKER_1:  pitch dot.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot of really...
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  narratives.
SPEAKER_1:  that's a
SPEAKER_1:  result in destruction of the human species. So nuclear war.
SPEAKER_1:  pandemics, all that kind of stuff. It seems that climate is a sticky one.
SPEAKER_1:  So the fact that it's sticky means there's other interests that play like you guys are talking about.
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of politics, all that kind of stuff. So it's not just a journalist.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like journalists will try anything for the front page.
SPEAKER_1:  You won't stick unless there's...
SPEAKER_1:  bigger interests at play for which these narratives are useful.
SPEAKER_1:  So journalists will just throw stuff out there and see if it.
SPEAKER_1:  get clicks and.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like a first spark maybe.
SPEAKER_1:  It's maybe a tiny catalyst of the initial stuffs, but it has to be picked up by the politicians, by interest groups and all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask you, if you want to about the...
SPEAKER_1:  First part of the subtitle.
SPEAKER_1:  How climate change panic costs us trillions.
SPEAKER_1:  How does climate change panic cost Australians?
SPEAKER_1:  So we're basically deciding to make policies that'll have.
SPEAKER_1:  Fairly little impact.
SPEAKER_1:  even in 50 or 100 years.
SPEAKER_1:  that literally cost trillions of dollars.
SPEAKER_1:  So, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  give you two examples. So the European Union is trying to go to
SPEAKER_1:  Net zero.
SPEAKER_1:  So our attempt to go halfway there by 2030.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... will cost about a trillion dollars a year
SPEAKER_1:  And yet the net impact will be almost unmeasurable by the end of the century.
SPEAKER_1:  Why is that?
SPEAKER_1:  That's because the EU and the rich countries is a fairly small part of the emissions that are gonna come out in the 21st century. Now, we used to be a big part of it, but that's mainly because nobody else, it was just the US and Europe and a few others put out CO2 in the 20th century.
SPEAKER_1:  So we used to be big.
SPEAKER_1:  but in the 21st century will be a small bit player.
SPEAKER_1:  And so we're basically spending a lot of money.
SPEAKER_1:  And remember a trillion dollars is a lot of money that could have been spent on a lot of things that could have made humanity better.
SPEAKER_1:  on something.
SPEAKER_1:  that will only make us
SPEAKER_1:  tiny bit better.
SPEAKER_1:  It will do some good.
SPEAKER_1:  But the reasonable estimates is if you do a cost benefit analysis and again
SPEAKER_1:  Technically, it's really, really complicated, but the basic idea is very, very simple. You just simply say, what are all the costs?
SPEAKER_1:  on one side.
SPEAKER_1:  And what are all the benefits? So the costs are mainly that we have to live with more expensive energy. You have to.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to have more complicated services, that kind of thing. The benefit is that you cut carbon emissions and that eventually means that you'll have less climate damage, you'll have lower temperature rises and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  if you try to weigh up all of those.
SPEAKER_1:  it's reasonable to assume.
SPEAKER_1:  that the EU policies will deliver for every dollar you spend.
SPEAKER_1:  It'll deliver less than a dollar, probably about 30 cents.
SPEAKER_1:  back on the dollar, which is a really bad way to spend dollars because there's lots of other things out in the world where you could do, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  multiple, you know, so for instance, if you think about tuberculosis or, uh, education of, of, of small kids or nutrition for small kids and that, those kinds of things, every dollar you spend will do like 30 to a hundred dollars worth of good. So they're much, much better places where you could spend this money.
SPEAKER_1:  Likewise, the US is thinking of going net zero by 20.
SPEAKER_1:  50. It's not actually going to happen, but it's sort of a thing that everybody talks about Biden is talking a lot about it.
SPEAKER_1:  If you look at the models that indicate how much will that cost?
SPEAKER_1:  It's not impossible that this will cost somewhere between 2 and 4.
SPEAKER_1:  trillion dollars.
SPEAKER_1:  per year by mid-century.
SPEAKER_1:  And remember, if the US went carbon neutral.
SPEAKER_1:  today.
SPEAKER_1:  by the end of the century that would reduce temperatures by about 0.3F.
SPEAKER_1:  just be able to measure it. You probably wouldn't in real life, but you know.
SPEAKER_1:  just be able to measure it.
SPEAKER_1:  again.
SPEAKER_1:  This is not saying that there's not some good coming out of it, but you're basically spending an enormous amount of money on fairly small benefits.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's my main point.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, this reminds me of what we were saying earlier about...
SPEAKER_0:  the things that models don't integrate and the things that cost benefit leave out because you really can't go there.
SPEAKER_0:  One of the issues facing the world right now is the reality that we're reminded of.
SPEAKER_0:  that energy availability is a geopolitical.
SPEAKER_0:  destabilizer if you
SPEAKER_0:  Have.
SPEAKER_0:  Uneven.
SPEAKER_0:  Access to energy.
SPEAKER_0:  and you have Vladimir Putin coming into office or something else happening.
SPEAKER_0:  disrupts that system, you're.
SPEAKER_0:  vastly increasing poverty.
SPEAKER_0:  This is playing out across the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Fertilizer process, fertilizer comes from gas.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  National gas.
SPEAKER_0:  If you can envision a world.
SPEAKER_0:  later in the century.
SPEAKER_0:  where we no longer beholden on this material in the ground, at least.
SPEAKER_0:  fossil fuels, you know, cobalt and lithium for batteries.
SPEAKER_0:  That's pretty cool.
SPEAKER_0:  because you're taking away geopolitical instability.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's not factored in, right? That's like way outside of what you would factor in. But it does feel like to me, if I was going to make the case for
SPEAKER_0:  You can choose your trillions, whatever that.
SPEAKER_0:  Investing big.
SPEAKER_0:  isn't for these marginal things, it's for...
SPEAKER_0:  looking at the big picture, a world of abundant energy.
SPEAKER_0:  that doesn't come from a black rock.
SPEAKER_0:  or a gooey liquid when you burn it.
SPEAKER_0:  Great.
SPEAKER_1:  But isn't that what the proposals are is investing.
SPEAKER_1:  in different kinds of energy, renewable energy.
SPEAKER_0:  But I don't think most people are making that case.
SPEAKER_1:  in the...
SPEAKER_1:  In the trillion and the T costs, what's in corporate? What are the big costs there?
SPEAKER_1:  So the big cost is that you have.
SPEAKER_1:  slightly lower productivity gains. So basically again, yeah, and this is sort of the opposite of what we just talked about about climate change.
SPEAKER_1:  We're going to get richer and richer in the world. This is all models, also the UN. This is really the only way that you can get big.
SPEAKER_1:  climate change is because everybody gets a lot richer, so also the developing world gets a lot richer. So we're likely to get richer.
SPEAKER_1:  But one of the things that drive our wealth production.
SPEAKER_1:  is the fact that we have ample and cheap and available energy.
SPEAKER_1:  If you make that slightly harder, which is what you do with climate legislation, because you're basically telling people you have to use a source of energy that you'd rather not have used had-
SPEAKER_1:  because if people wanted to do it, we'd already have solved the problem. So you basically tell them, you got to use this wind turbine instead of this, natural gas plant or you know.
SPEAKER_1:  That kind of thing.
SPEAKER_1:  It makes, it's not that you suddenly become poor or anything. It simply makes production slightly harder. What do you do when the wind is not blowing kind of thing? And of course we have lots of ways to...
SPEAKER_1:  somewhat mitigate that, but it's a little more costly, a little more complicated, a little less convenient. And that means you grow a little less.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the main problem with these policies, that it simply makes you somewhat less well-off. So energy becomes more inefficient.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  Lemme...
SPEAKER_1:  challenge you here.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... try to steal man some critics
SPEAKER_1:  So you have critics.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  I would love you to take it seriously and sort of consider this.
SPEAKER_1:  criticism and trying to steal man their their case
SPEAKER_1:  There's a bunch.
SPEAKER_1:  I could mention.
SPEAKER_1:  This this
SPEAKER_1:  list of criticisms.
SPEAKER_1:  from Bob Ward in London School of Economics. I don't know if you're familiar with him, but just on this point...
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of one of the big costs being an energy.
SPEAKER_1:  He criticizes your recent book in saying
SPEAKER_1:  You consider the $143 billion in annual support for renewable energy, but ignore
SPEAKER_1:  the $300 billion in fossil fuel subsidies.
SPEAKER_1:  So a lot of the criticism has to do...
SPEAKER_1:  with while you're cherry picking the models.
SPEAKER_1:  which the models are always cherry picking anyway.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you want to take those seriously, so...
SPEAKER_1:  uh... he claims that you ignore
SPEAKER_1:  you're not.
SPEAKER_1:  Fully modeling the cost.
SPEAKER_1:  the trade off here, how expensive.
SPEAKER_1:  is the renewable energy and how expensive is the fossil fuel? Can you steal man's case?
SPEAKER_1:  So two things. The first, the quote.
SPEAKER_1:  It's absolutely true that the world spends a large chunk of money on fossil fuels. And that's just stupid. And we should stop doing it.
SPEAKER_1:  We should also recognize that this is not rich countries. This is not the countries where we're talking about climate change. This is poor countries. This is Saudi Arabia. No, that's actually not a terribly poor country. It's China, it's Indonesia, it's Russia. It's places where you're basically paying off your population, just like that you subsidize bread, you make sure that they don't rebel by making
SPEAKER_1:  cheap fuels available. That's dumb.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's not like they, you know, they don't know what they're doing. They're mostly doing this for things that have nothing to do with climate. So I totally agree. We should get rid of it. It's hard to do. Indonesia is actually somewhat managed to, you know, to get rid of it. Because remember if you spend a lot of money on fossil fuel subsidies, you're basically subsidising the rich because
SPEAKER_1:  Poor people don't have a car. It's the rich people who can now buy very cheap gasoline. That's, you know, that's
SPEAKER_1:  unjust as well. So it's dumb in so many different ways. I would never argue that you shouldn't overturn assholes.
SPEAKER_1:  Plenty of time said we should stop that.
SPEAKER_1:  But we should also recognize these are mostly regimes that are not going to be taken over by either by my argument or Bob Ward's or anyone else's. They're doing this for totally different reasons.
SPEAKER_1:  On the model side.
SPEAKER_1:  There is virtually no model.
SPEAKER_1:  that don't show economic model, that don't show this has a cost.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's the fundamental point is.
SPEAKER_1:  This is a basic point from economics. The system is already working most effectively because if it wasn't, you could actually make money.
SPEAKER_1:  changing over.
SPEAKER_1:  So if you want to have a change outside of what the system is already doing, it's because you're saying you have to do something that you rather not want to do, namely use an energy source that is less convenient or less cost effective and so on, and that will incur a cost.
SPEAKER_1:  Now, there's huge discussion about just exactly how much cost is that. So there's definitely cost.
SPEAKER_1:  is the cost going to be one or five trillion? That's absolutely a discussion about where do you take your models from? I try to do...
SPEAKER_1:  And again, this is not possible everywhere. I try to actually take
SPEAKER_1:  the average of all of the economic models. So there's a group called the Stanford Energy Modeling Forum, which
SPEAKER_1:  tries to pull together all these different groups that do the modelling. So some models.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of this cost actually comes down to...
SPEAKER_1:  the fact that we don't quite know how much more fossil fuels you're going to need in the future. And so if your projections are you're not going to use that much.
SPEAKER_1:  The cost of reducing it is going to be very small. If you think you're going to use a ton of extra fossil fuels and you have to reduce it, the cost is going to be bigger.
SPEAKER_1:  So I think that's just one of the variables that's oh yeah. And there's many, many, many more.
SPEAKER_1:  I think the point here is to say.
SPEAKER_1:  that if you take the average of all the best models that's sort of aggregated, for instance at the Stanford Energy Modeling Forum,
SPEAKER_1:  Pretty secure ground.
SPEAKER_1:  And so again, I would argue that Bob Ward.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, I've had a lot of run ins with Bob Bord and he has a very different set of views on things.
SPEAKER_1:  But I just don't think he's right in saying that I'm cherry picking. Well, yes. And I mean, he also has similar criticism about the estimate of the EU cost of climate action.
SPEAKER_1:  based on the NOP 2013 model.
SPEAKER_1:  But ultimately these criticisms have to do with what are the sources for the different models.
SPEAKER_1:  And just very briefly, I mean, I'm laying it out very transparently where I get these models, where I get these estimates from in the book. I've really tried to document this. And yes, I mean, look, there's nobody who sort of
SPEAKER_1:  has all the information and gets everything right in all of these areas. I think most of Pogport's argument is not a...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, uh-
SPEAKER_1:  Good.
SPEAKER_1:  faith effort to sort of
SPEAKER_1:  improve on these estimates. He's right in saying some of these estimates, we only have a few estimates.
SPEAKER_1:  And yeah, I'd like to have more of them. One thing I should mention is that there is very little interest in general and there's very little funding in finding out how much do our climate policies cost.
SPEAKER_1:  because that's just inconvenient to everyone in the whole game. Who wants to know that?
SPEAKER_1:  that, you know, for instance, would you want to fund?
SPEAKER_1:  something that says that the Inflation Reduction Act is not going to be very effective. Of course, you don't want to do that. Again, it's a little bit the flock of birds will look at something else.
SPEAKER_1:  And what I think is...
SPEAKER_1:  given that we're paying for it at the end. This is public money. We're deciding we're gonna spend money here rather than there. Let's at least look at what are the best estimates out there. I would love to have more estimates. More estimates is always better. And just a quick comment on the good faith part.
SPEAKER_1:  Me as a consumer, looking for truth is hard to find who's good faith and not.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's not only are you looking for.
SPEAKER_1:  sort of accurate information.
SPEAKER_1:  You're also trying to infer about the communicator of that information.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. It's very difficult. It's, it's, um. And you know, you put me on the, on the podcast. Of course I'm going to say it.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm a trustworthy guy. Well, I mean, but we believe we're trustworthy too, but.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, I've been reading.
SPEAKER_1:  for various reasons, but mostly because I've been traveling to Ukraine and thinking just about the peoples.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  suffering through war. I've been reading a lot about World War II and Stalin and Hitler.
SPEAKER_1:  And, you know, from the perspective of Hitler...
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  He...
SPEAKER_1:  really believed he's doing good.
SPEAKER_1:  for the world than...
SPEAKER_1:  He was...
SPEAKER_1:  communicating from his perspective in good faith.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  He started to believe, I think, early on his own propaganda.
SPEAKER_1:  Even your understanding and perception of the world completely shifted.
SPEAKER_1:  It's very, very, very, too.
SPEAKER_1:  to understand who to trust.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  And just because it's a consensus in a particular community.
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't necessarily mean it's a source of trust.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, basically...
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know how to operate in this world.
SPEAKER_1:  except to have a humility and constantly questioning your assumptions.
SPEAKER_1:  but not so much that you're completely out in the ocean not knowing what is true and not.
SPEAKER_1:  weird world because I ultimately
SPEAKER_1:  bigger than climate.
SPEAKER_1:  My hope is to have...
SPEAKER_1:  institutions that can be trusted.
SPEAKER_1:  and that's been very much under attack.
SPEAKER_1:  in as part of the climate debate as part of the
SPEAKER_1:  COVID debate as part of all these discussions.
SPEAKER_1:  and science.
SPEAKER_1:  to me is one of the sources.
SPEAKER_1:  of truth and the fact that that's under question now is something that hurts me on many levels.
SPEAKER_0:  deeply.
SPEAKER_0:  You said something earlier that I took a note down here and I can't find it about cooperation. It was like collaborative cooperation or something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  To me...
SPEAKER_0:  There was a point like in 2013.
SPEAKER_0:  after just dealing with everything you've been grappling with.
SPEAKER_0:  And what it...
SPEAKER_0:  you know you don't know how this is going to work out.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you work on?
SPEAKER_0:  And one morning I made a list of words that kind of summarized.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically system properties that give you confidence.
SPEAKER_0:  in the system.
SPEAKER_0:  Trust or?
SPEAKER_0:  And there are transparency is one.
SPEAKER_0:  as you were saying earlier.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Connectivity is another.
SPEAKER_0:  so that everyone's connected.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  On the subsidy issue, for example.
SPEAKER_0:  their young entrepreneurs in Nairobi.
SPEAKER_0:  who are selling.
SPEAKER_0:  ingeniously using Nairobi's digital currency.
SPEAKER_0:  Propane, the fuel that's in our...
SPEAKER_0:  Backyard BBQ grills.
SPEAKER_0:  which comes out of a gas wells, but it's a separate fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  in little to increments that poor people can use instead of charcoal.
SPEAKER_0:  and LPG subsidies are helping them.
SPEAKER_0:  get people off of charcoal, which is horrific.
SPEAKER_0:  TRAGE
SPEAKER_0:  from the source through the.
SPEAKER_0:  warlords in Somalia and elsewhere who are.
SPEAKER_0:  getting the money.
SPEAKER_0:  to the pollution in houses.
SPEAKER_0:  So having.
SPEAKER_0:  Be sure, being sure when we're having these big debates about who the World Bank is going to give loans to.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm drawing a simple line, no more fossil fuel subsidies.
SPEAKER_0:  hurts.
SPEAKER_0:  a really good valuable.
SPEAKER_0:  Small scale but...
SPEAKER_0:  Scalable.
SPEAKER_0:  way to have people not die from cooking smoke in their houses and take down for us.
SPEAKER_0:  But that only is considered if they're in the conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  So connectivity, full connectivity, digital access.
SPEAKER_0:  So those entrepreneurs are in the mix of people. When you're thinking about subsidies, you're not just thinking about big bad Exxon, you're thinking about this.
SPEAKER_0:  little company in Nairobi, Pago LPG, I think is the name.
SPEAKER_0:  In India, the same thing.
SPEAKER_0:  So you can list those properties of systems.
SPEAKER_0:  And the IPCC wasn't originally transparent.
SPEAKER_0:  when I started writing about it in 1988, 1990.
SPEAKER_0:  And now it's way more transparent. A more public review.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's even better than it was. It's like a really good example of a science process of assessing the science.
SPEAKER_0:  providing periodic output to the world.
SPEAKER_0:  and iteratively improving the model going forward because of critique, because of...
SPEAKER_0:  because of scrutiny.
SPEAKER_0:  and finding better ways for that to interface with people so they have information they can use from that big thing.
SPEAKER_0:  and the media are not doing a good job.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  because of this.
SPEAKER_0:  Front page thoughtism.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  But we can all, you know, I work partially in academia, Columbia.
SPEAKER_0:  on an initiative partially in communication innovation. How can we?
SPEAKER_0:  have an open landscape of access to information matters. How can you...
SPEAKER_0:  What can you do to foster better conversations?
SPEAKER_0:  so that words like collapse aren't just thrown around like.
SPEAKER_0:  ambulance.
SPEAKER_0:  And so system properties give you confidence, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  And then you don't have to be flailing around for...
SPEAKER_0:  Bjorn or Tom Friedman or
SPEAKER_0:  That wasves, thank you very much.
SPEAKER_0:  You can always right now find your.
SPEAKER_0:  You're...
SPEAKER_0:  your character to follow.
SPEAKER_0:  But I think what would be better is if you actually develop some skills to just have a basic ability.
SPEAKER_0:  know how to cut to the chase.
SPEAKER_1:  Can I just follow up on that because...
SPEAKER_1:  One of the things that I try to do and so my day job is actually something else I work with I think called the Copenhagen consensus.
SPEAKER_1:  where we work with more than 300 of the world's top economists and we work with seven Nobel laureates in economics.
SPEAKER_1:  And the point there is really to talk about Where can you spend a dollar?
SPEAKER_1:  and do.
SPEAKER_1:  The most good for the world.
SPEAKER_1:  That's basically.
SPEAKER_1:  thing that we try to do. And as you rightly point out, look, there are lots of different estimates of what can you do, for instance, on climate, what can you do on tuberculosis, what can you do for vulnerability in all kinds of different ways.
SPEAKER_1:  And if these were all sort of, well, you can spend a dollar here and do 2.36, but you can spend a dollar here and do 2.34 over here.
SPEAKER_1:  I would worry a lot, but that's not how the world works because we're terribly inefficient.
SPEAKER_1:  So they're literally.
SPEAKER_1:  Lots and lots of amazing things you can do out there. There's a lot of low hanging fruit. And there's a lot of not terribly great.
SPEAKER_1:  things that you can do.
SPEAKER_1:  And unfortunately, one of the things that I try to sort of battle is that, you know, we get a lot of things, right? That's why, you know, the world is a lot better than what it used to be. The things that are sort of left.
SPEAKER_1:  left over are often.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, the boring things that happen to be incredibly effective and the exciting things that are often not that terribly effective.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I think
SPEAKER_1:  One way to look at this is basically to have people do cost benefit across a wide range of areas. And we try to get a lot of different economists to do this, and they come up with different numbers and different models and different results.
SPEAKER_1:  But if you sort of consistently get that some things.
SPEAKER_1:  give you in tens or maybe even hundreds of dollars back per dollar.
SPEAKER_1:  Remember, this is not actually you getting rich, it's the world getting rich.
SPEAKER_1:  that the world gets better.
SPEAKER_1:  worth $100.
SPEAKER_1:  for every dollar you spend. And over here, you can spend a dollar and do somewhere between 30 cents and maybe a couple of dollars.
SPEAKER_1:  you should probably be focused on the other opportunity first. And that's really the point that I try to make with climate.
SPEAKER_1:  There are some smart things we can do and I hope we get to talk about them.
SPEAKER_1:  in climate.
SPEAKER_1:  but there's also a lot of sort of the standard approaches to fixing climate.
SPEAKER_1:  turns out to be.
SPEAKER_1:  very likely below $1 back in the dollar and certainly not.
SPEAKER_1:  even if you're very optimistic, it'll be like two or three.
SPEAKER_1:  whereas many other things are just fantastically.
SPEAKER_1:  better investment. Like the thing I've been advocating, a modest proposal to eat the children of the poor in england.
SPEAKER_1:  Was that in Jonathan Swift modest proposal from a few centuries ago?
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  So it's not just cost benefit, it's also in the context of what is moral and not and all that. The full complexity of it.
SPEAKER_0:  You just hit on something really important. You know, having been on this beat for so long, and again on the disaster beat as well, earthquakes.
SPEAKER_0:  I can't tell you how many disasters science.
SPEAKER_0:  Experts keep telling me.
SPEAKER_0:  Like everyone says, preparedness, invest for preparedness.
SPEAKER_0:  A strict cost benefit analysis will always tell you a dollar.
SPEAKER_0:  invested in.
SPEAKER_0:  resilience before a community gets hit by whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  is worth 10.
SPEAKER_0:  You'll always have to spend 10 after.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's fine to do the cost benefit stuff, but it's just the baseline.
SPEAKER_0:  Then you have to look at the social science, which shows...
SPEAKER_0:  or history, which shows you how few times we do it.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like we just don't do it, therefore.
SPEAKER_0:  You can bang that drum.
SPEAKER_0:  Your work is valuable, but it's really constrained.
SPEAKER_0:  because show me in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  where that does happen and then...
SPEAKER_0:  how you turn that success, which is basically something not happening.
SPEAKER_0:  into the story.
SPEAKER_1:  Just very briefly, we try to, so we do this for a lot of countries. So we did it for Haiti, for instance.
SPEAKER_1:  funded by the Canadian Development Ministry because they're basically saying, we spent a billion dollars in Haiti since the earthquake and we really can't tell the difference. So they want it to find, I mean, they actually say that, right? And so they said, we want to find out what are the really smart things you can do in Haiti.
SPEAKER_1:  And so we, we, uh, together with lots of people in Haiti and all the, you know, the business community and the political community and the religious community and labor community and everybody else.
SPEAKER_1:  what are the smart things to do? And then we had economists evaluate it. And there are a lot of these things that everybody wanted that were not all that smart.
SPEAKER_1:  There's actually a lot of smart things and yes.
SPEAKER_1:  The politicians didn't pick most of them.
SPEAKER_1:  So our senses.
SPEAKER_1:  We try to give people, you're thinking about these 70 things.
SPEAKER_1:  you should actually just think about these 20 things. And then we consider ourselves incredibly lucky if they actually do one of them. So you wrote the book, how to spend $75 billion to make the world a better place.
SPEAKER_1:  So, can we just list some of the things?
SPEAKER_1:  If you got $75 billion, how do you spend them?
SPEAKER_1:  All right, so there's some incredibly good and very, very well-documented things that you could spend money on. So we have two.
SPEAKER_1:  big infectious diseases that almost nobody think about.
SPEAKER_1:  because we only think about COVID.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, but-
SPEAKER_1:  tuberculosis used to be the world's biggest infectious disease killer.
SPEAKER_1:  It still kills about one and a half million people every year
SPEAKER_1:  The reason why we don't
SPEAKER_1:  you know, really worry about it is because
SPEAKER_1:  We fixed it a hundred years ago.
SPEAKER_1:  we know how to fix it. It's just basically getting medication to people. It's also about getting them to take it while, when they're-
SPEAKER_1:  sort of been cured because you need to take it for four to six months. And that's actually hard to do. So you also need to incentivize that in some kind of way. It turns out it's incredibly cheap.
SPEAKER_1:  to basically save almost all of the 1.5 million people.
SPEAKER_1:  These are people that die in the
SPEAKER_1:  of their lives. They're typically parents, so you would also have a lot of knock-on effects.
SPEAKER_1:  And basically we find for a couple billion dollars.
SPEAKER_1:  you could save the vast number of these, not all of them, but you could save the vast number of them, it would also improve.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, outcomes in all kinds of other ways. Likewise with malaria, another, it has some somewhat better PR. It's funny to think of malaria as PR and tuberculosis, they need to improve their PR department. Well, but yeah. Those mosquitoes or the good PR. By far the biggest infectious disease.
SPEAKER_1:  that got good PR, if you will, was HIV. And I'm not trying to compare it and say, oh, it's.
SPEAKER_1:  worse or better to have HIV than tuberculosis or anything. But I'm simply saying we are underfunding because it doesn't really get the public attention.
SPEAKER_1:  We just, yeah, we don't really care. But spending money on that has, in terms of benefit, a much bigger impact. So every dollar you spend on TP.
SPEAKER_1:  will probably do about $43 worth of good.
SPEAKER_1:  So it'll do an amazing amount of good, basically because it'll save lives. It'll make sure parents stay with their kids and be more productive in their communities and it'll have a lot of knock-on effects.
SPEAKER_1:  It's incredibly cheap to do.
SPEAKER_1:  Same thing with malaria, it's mostly mosquito nets that we need to get out. And you're saying just to contrast with climate change, the dollar you spend on...
SPEAKER_1:  No, not climate change, but decreasing emissions.
SPEAKER_1:  does not come close to the $43 benefit.
SPEAKER_1:  No, nobody would ever argue that. So very, very enthusiastic climate.
SPEAKER_1:  advocates would probably say it'll do two or three dollars worth of good for every dollar. So it's still worthwhile to do, that's what they would say. I would argue, and I think a lot of the evidence seems to side that way, that a lot of the things that we're doing deliver actually less than a dollar back.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's certainly not nearly the same kind of place.
SPEAKER_1:  But there's many, many other things. And just if you'll allow me to. It's crazy, I love this. But yeah, there are lots of other things, for instance, e-procurement.
SPEAKER_1:  So, you know, it's incredibly boring. So most developing countries, well, actually most governments spend most of their money on procurement as typically incredibly corrupt.
SPEAKER_1:  So we did this project for Bangladesh.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, where can you explain procurement? Yes. So that's what governance buying stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  So a large part of the government revenue is spent on buying anything from Post-it notes.
SPEAKER_1:  to roads.
SPEAKER_1:  And obviously, roads are much, much more expensive. It's mostly infrastructure stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  hugely corrupt.
SPEAKER_1:  For instance in Bangladesh
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  It would already have been decided among the ruling elite in that local area, who's going to get this. So they'll have this bidding competition where you have to hand in an envelope, a seal envelope with your bid on it.
SPEAKER_1:  You put a goon outside the office. So you literally physically can't get in with your bid.
SPEAKER_1:  Now what we found in this is, you know, I'm not.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not claiming any sort of ownership to this. A lot of smart people have done this way before. We're just simply-
SPEAKER_1:  proving that it's a good idea.
SPEAKER_1:  It turns out that if you put this on eBay essentially, so if you do an e-procurement system where bidders can come in,
SPEAKER_1:  Suddenly it becomes harder to put up the goon. You can still do it, but it's harder to do it.
SPEAKER_1:  It also means you get bids from all over Bang'llit Ashley
SPEAKER_1:  And in general, you'll get bits from all over. Actually, turns out you get better quality. But most important is
SPEAKER_1:  you get it much cheaper.
SPEAKER_1:  So basically, you can simply save money. So we did a scaled experiment in Bangladesh where we had about 4% go to be e-procurement. And you could compare what it would have cost and then what it did cost.
SPEAKER_1:  And the average reduction was, as I remember, it's 7%.
SPEAKER_1:  And the finance minister loved it.
SPEAKER_1:  because that basically gives him a lot more money or you can buy more stuff at the same cost. No, this is corruption.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's basically you get rid of some corruption. There'll still be corruption, but less corruption. Ukraine has actually been big on this. Yeah, I've talked to them. I talked to the digital transformation minister. It's kind of incredible. I mean, this is before the war, but still.
SPEAKER_1:  working.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  It's like the entirety of the government is in an app.
SPEAKER_1:  And that...
SPEAKER_1:  one of the big effects.
SPEAKER_1:  is the reduction of corruption.
SPEAKER_1:  And not like from a, this was a politician say to say, we've reduced, we've taken these actions through this court. No, literally is just.
SPEAKER_0:  much more difficult to be corrupt. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  The incentives aren't quite there and there's friction.
SPEAKER_1:  for corruption. Yeah. Oh yeah. You can spend a little bit of money.
SPEAKER_1:  and you can make a huge benefit. There's still about 70 countries that haven't gotten e-procurement.
SPEAKER_1:  Obviously they should do that.
SPEAKER_1:  Food for small kids, another thing.
SPEAKER_1:  So, you know, basically, yeah, it's morally wrong that people are starving.
SPEAKER_1:  But it also turns out that it's a really, really
SPEAKER_1:  dumb thing not to get kids good food. If you get them good food.
SPEAKER_1:  that brains develop more.
SPEAKER_1:  so that when they get into school, they learn more.
SPEAKER_1:  And so when they come out in adult lives.
SPEAKER_1:  been much more productive.
SPEAKER_1:  So we can actually make.
SPEAKER_1:  every kid in especially in developing countries much more productive.
SPEAKER_1:  by making sure they get good food. So getting good food is not cost free. So it probably cost about $100, both in you need some directed advertisement, you need to make sure that you actually get some of the food out there, that you help the families, and you also make sure you don't just give it to everyone, because then it becomes a lot more expensive.
SPEAKER_1:  If you do that right, it costs about $100 per kid.
SPEAKER_1:  But per kid or per two years. So it's for their first two years of life.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  And if you do that...
SPEAKER_1:  you then get a benefit in that they become smarter and go longer to school and they actually learn more and become more productive of $4,500. Remember, this is far into the future. So this is discounted. The benefit is actually much higher. And this is one of the things that we also have a conversation about in climate change because all, and when you talk about climate change.
SPEAKER_1:  Cost and benefits, all the costs are now, and all the benefits are in the future. But it's just like that in education. You know all the costs are now.
SPEAKER_1:  all the benefits are far into the future.
SPEAKER_1:  And if you try to do that right, and that's a whole other conversation that we could have, then it turns out that for every dollar spent.
SPEAKER_1:  you do $45 worth of good.
SPEAKER_1:  Again, remember about a third of all kids that go to school right now.
SPEAKER_1:  Just don't learn.
SPEAKER_1:  Pretty much anything?
SPEAKER_1:  And if we could make them more productive in the school system, we have another proposal on how to do that in the, in the school system. But, you know, by just simply making sure that they're, that they're smarter when they get into school.
SPEAKER_1:  We've been focusing so much on making the education system.
SPEAKER_1:  better which is really hard.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's actually really easy to make the kids.
SPEAKER_1:  smarter than we say the education system is not working well that's what talking about that
SPEAKER_1:  the American education system we're talking about globally. Yes, we're talking about globally. So about a third of the teachers in developing countries.
SPEAKER_1:  have a hard time passing the tests of the things they have to teach their students. All these students have lots of other issues. They need to do farm work.
SPEAKER_1:  constantly considering, should I just go out and start working instead? Uh, you know, there's, there's constant disruption. There's a lot of teachers that don't show up in India. You know, you have, uh, you have this absurd situation where all the teachers are
SPEAKER_1:  basically.
SPEAKER_1:  paid and hired for eternity for the rest of their lives.
SPEAKER_1:  And so not surprisingly, a lot of them decide not to show up. So now they've hired.
SPEAKER_1:  Assistant teachers.
SPEAKER_1:  that basically have taken over. So they're paying, you know, for, I think it's 7 million teachers.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not saying they're not all not working, but a lot of them are not working as much as they should. We now hired another 7 million teachers that will eventually stop working as well. They're working much better right now because they're not on permanent contracts, but eventually they'll get on permanent contracts and then you have the same problem again. There's lots of these issues. And it's just simply about saying...
SPEAKER_1:  We can't fix all problems.
SPEAKER_1:  but there are some problems that are incredibly easy to solve and there are some that are incredibly hard to solve. Why don't we start with solving the easy and effective ones?
SPEAKER_1:  And this of course bears on that whole conversation on climate change, because in some ways, you know, that's also Andy's point of saying, look, if you want to save people from the impacts of hurricanes, let's fix this simple, easy things about vulnerability first.
SPEAKER_1:  Whereas we have somehow latched onto this. Let's fix the hardest thing to do.
SPEAKER_1:  which is to get everyone to stop using fossil fuels, which is basically what's driven the last 200 years of development.
SPEAKER_1:  That's gonna be.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a tall order, no matter how you look at it.
SPEAKER_0:  There's some really cool elements that.
SPEAKER_0:  You guys just brought up.
SPEAKER_0:  You mentioned that word moral before? I wasn't-
SPEAKER_0:  I latched on to it because it relates to...
SPEAKER_0:  these timescales that really are immeasurable. If you know it's going to take decades to-
SPEAKER_0:  confirm.
SPEAKER_0:  the benefit of some investment now.
SPEAKER_0:  That implies you're doing the investment.
SPEAKER_0:  with some moral imperative.
SPEAKER_0:  not because you can.
SPEAKER_0:  Do it.
SPEAKER_0:  spreadsheet.
SPEAKER_0:  and come out with a number.
SPEAKER_0:  And that process, letting go of the need.
SPEAKER_0:  for kind of a mechanistic cost benefit.
SPEAKER_0:  thinking about kids' education in poor countries.
SPEAKER_0:  or...
SPEAKER_0:  several things we talked about.
SPEAKER_0:  seems to be really important and it's very hard for all of us to do.
SPEAKER_0:  Philanthropists suck at it.
SPEAKER_0:  I worked at National Geographic Society for a year, building some new programs when they got a big infusion of money.
SPEAKER_0:  They have a whole department that's called M&E. It's measurement and evaluation.
SPEAKER_0:  which is if you don't prove it.
SPEAKER_0:  It goes away.
SPEAKER_0:  I mentioned Spotify earlier, Spotify killing a climate podcast.
SPEAKER_0:  because that podcast didn't measure.
SPEAKER_0:  measure out for their.
SPEAKER_0:  impact what they want to do.
SPEAKER_0:  And if we're always making the judgments based on strict cost benefit, we're going to miss.
SPEAKER_0:  larger realities.
SPEAKER_0:  Another thing is, a really exciting example of what you're talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of.
SPEAKER_0:  Ukraine with the trust and lack of less corruption and stuff was in India.
SPEAKER_0:  for all of his issues. Moaty.
SPEAKER_0:  recognized.
SPEAKER_0:  that middle class people in India cook on LPG, propane, or on piped gas, natural gas if they're in cities.
SPEAKER_0:  Much cleaner, much.
SPEAKER_0:  Healthier.
SPEAKER_0:  in so many ways and actually.
SPEAKER_0:  compared to like chopping down trees and cooking on wood, it's actually better for the climate, even though it's a fossil fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  So he-
SPEAKER_0:  He and others, there was an American scientist, Kirk Smith, who worked this all out.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  If you find a way, they were getting a subsidy. They had that energy subsidy. You were talking about many poor countries.
SPEAKER_0:  subsidize energy just to stay in office, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  to make something cheap that everyone wants.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  but they wanted to shift the subsidy away from the middle class.
SPEAKER_0:  See the poor people.
SPEAKER_0:  or cooking on firewood and...
SPEAKER_0:  dying young from pneumonia.
SPEAKER_0:  And the critical factor was India's digital currency.
SPEAKER_0:  India went through digital.
SPEAKER_0:  economy.
SPEAKER_0:  Very poor families there now. If you have a phone, basically that's your bank.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  you could make the case to the public that we're going to be starting to shift your.
SPEAKER_0:  LPG your propane subsidy to poor people.
SPEAKER_0:  But we know they're poor.
SPEAKER_0:  we know they're not just gonna be using it behind their restaurant.
SPEAKER_0:  which was when it was a general subsidy.
SPEAKER_0:  people were hoarding the LPG.
SPEAKER_0:  and the system has worked.
SPEAKER_0:  They've shifted a lot of
SPEAKER_0:  capacity to cook on a clean blue flame that turns off and on.
SPEAKER_0:  in homes that previously where the woman would spend hours collecting firewood.
SPEAKER_0:  Smokey fire, cooking, clean the pots and start all over again.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's all built on trust, built on the digital economy and the same thing in Nairobi.
SPEAKER_0:  So that excites me every day with all the doomism.
SPEAKER_0:  I just hope people can literally.
SPEAKER_0:  Take a breath.
SPEAKER_0:  Look for these examples.
SPEAKER_0:  that show the potential when you have.
SPEAKER_0:  a trustworthy system.
SPEAKER_0:  when you have a clear path to making lives better.
SPEAKER_0:  And then knowing, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  That kid.
SPEAKER_0:  having electric light as opposed to a kerosene lamp.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't know how much that's gonna improve his homework.
SPEAKER_0:  and lead to a better outcome.
SPEAKER_0:  but we know from history that sometimes it does.
SPEAKER_0:  Ban Ki-moon, former secretary general. The most powerful story I ever heard from a UN.
SPEAKER_0:  Secretary General.
SPEAKER_0:  It was like 2012 when they were rolling out.
SPEAKER_0:  this sustainable energy for all initiative, which is not just.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just like getting people energy they need to.
SPEAKER_0:  Survive and thrive.
SPEAKER_0:  He was growing up in post-war Korea.
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone was poor. Everything was broken, destroyed.
SPEAKER_0:  Sadly.
SPEAKER_0:  like so much of many parts of Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  he would do his homework by kerosene lamp.
SPEAKER_0:  He said when he was studying for his finals, his mom would give him a candle.
SPEAKER_0:  This was a brighter flame.
SPEAKER_0:  Better grades maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  and he became Secretary of State.
SPEAKER_1:  the hell of a story.
SPEAKER_1:  So which...
SPEAKER_1:  Climate change, which policies work, which don't?
SPEAKER_1:  which are when we look at this formula of $1 in.
SPEAKER_1:  $45 out.
SPEAKER_1:  for climate change.
SPEAKER_1:  What?
SPEAKER_1:  dollar in what policies for dollar in.
SPEAKER_1:  and dollar out are good.
SPEAKER_1:  So we actually did a whole project back in 2009 when
SPEAKER_1:  when the whole world circus was coming to Copenhagen.
SPEAKER_1:  And we were going to save the world there.
SPEAKER_1:  We brought together about 50 climate economists and three Nobel laureates to look at where can you spend a dollar and do the most good for climate.
SPEAKER_1:  And what they found was a lot of these things as we've been talking about before, that basically investing in the current sort of technology that we're talking about.
SPEAKER_1:  trying very hard.
SPEAKER_1:  is.
SPEAKER_1:  Best app.
SPEAKER_1:  Pretty.
SPEAKER_1:  dicey outcome, much of it is probably less than a dollar back in the dollar.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, there's some, uh, investments on, on, uh, adaptation for instance, that's pretty good, but it's sort of two, $3 back on the dollar.
SPEAKER_1:  The obvious thing is that you built a dyke.
SPEAKER_1:  for a sea level rise.
SPEAKER_1:  or that you get some apps that people know that there's a hurricane coming. So you can adapt to- The data infrastructure, right? Yes. The physical and the digital infrastructure. Yes. The fact is that people are really good at doing this already.
SPEAKER_1:  because they have a strong incentive to do it. So the extra thing that governments can do outside is somewhat good, but it's not.
SPEAKER_1:  amazing or anything. What we found by far the best investment.
SPEAKER_1:  in the long run.
SPEAKER_1:  was on investment in energy innovation.
SPEAKER_1:  So, and I think this also sort of corresponds with what we would.
SPEAKER_1:  think in general.
SPEAKER_1:  If we could innovate, for instance, Bill Gates is arguing we should have fourth generation nuclear. So the next
SPEAKER_1:  more advanced than what we currently have in third generation nuclear, which would be an industrial scale process. Just building these modular nuclear power plants.
SPEAKER_1:  they would be, instead of being this artwork that we design once for every different plant, which is one of the reasons why they're so expensive, they would just be mass produced and you would have one, you know, they all be recognized in one go. So it'd be much cheaper. They would also be passively safe. So if all the power goes.
SPEAKER_1:  They'll shut down, rather than go boom.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's another very good thing. And then they'll also be very hard to transform into nuclear weapons.
SPEAKER_1:  So you can actually imagine them being out in a lot of different places where we'd perhaps be a little worried about having plutonium lying around. Now, this is all still being worked out, but imagine if that actually comes out. And again, remember, the other three generations, we were also told that it will be incredibly safe and it will be incredibly cheap.
SPEAKER_1:  and it didn't turn out that way. So let's wait, but it could be.
SPEAKER_1:  And so the argument is...
SPEAKER_1:  invest in these ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  for instance, fourth generation nuclear.
SPEAKER_1:  and if forced generation nuclear becomes cheaper than fossil fuels.
SPEAKER_1:  We're done.
SPEAKER_1:  everyone will just switch, not just rich, well-meaning Americans or Europeans.
SPEAKER_1:  but also the Chinese, the Indians, everybody in Africa, the rest is Indian subcontinent.
SPEAKER_1:  That's how you fix these issues, right? So the idea here is to say...
SPEAKER_1:  Instead of.
SPEAKER_1:  thinking that we can sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  push people to do stuff they really don't want to do.
SPEAKER_1:  which is basically saying let's use more of the solar and wind that you would otherwise have invested in.
SPEAKER_1:  force people to buy an electric car by giving huge subsidies because otherwise they're.
SPEAKER_1:  Clearly not.
SPEAKER_1:  all that interest in buying it and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  Get the innovation such that.
SPEAKER_1:  they become cheaper.
SPEAKER_1:  then fossil fuels and everyone will switch.
SPEAKER_1:  This is how we've solved problems in the past, if you think. In Los Angeles in the 1950s, it was a hugely polluted place, mostly because of cars.
SPEAKER_1:  The standard climate approach today would be to tell everyone in Los Angeles, I'm sorry, could you just walk instead? And of course, that just doesn't work. That doesn't pay off. You never get politicians voted in office, or at least staying in office, if you make that kind of policy. What did solve the problem?
SPEAKER_1:  was the innovation of the catalytic converter.
SPEAKER_1:  You basically get the Zalib Gizmo and it cost a couple hundred dollars and you put it on your tailpipe.
SPEAKER_1:  and then you can drive around basically almost not pollute.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's how you fix the air pollution in Los Angeles.
SPEAKER_1:  Basically we've.
SPEAKER_1:  solved all problems in humanity. Amanda let here some big class
SPEAKER_1:  difficult problems with innovation. We haven't solved it by telling everyone, I'm sorry, could you be a little less comfortable and a little more cold and a little poor?
SPEAKER_1:  and believing that that can go on for decades.
SPEAKER_1:  And while it-
SPEAKER_1:  possibly works in some pockets of the US, and I think actually in large parts of Europe at least, it used to, the war in Ukraine is definitely sort of changing that whole perspective. But yeah, there's a willingness to say, we're gonna suffer a little, but then we'll fix this problem. But the point is, we're gonna be willing to suffer a little. And so-
SPEAKER_1:  Fix a tiny bit of the...
SPEAKER_1:  climate problem instead of actually focusing on innovation. So what we found was if you spend a dollar on innovation,
SPEAKER_1:  you will probably avoid about $11 of climate damage in the long run.
SPEAKER_1:  which is a great investment.
SPEAKER_1:  And the terrible thing is...
SPEAKER_1:  We have not been doing this. So because everybody is focused on saying, we need this solution within the next 12 years.
SPEAKER_1:  It means you're not thinking about the innovation. We're actually spending less money, not more money on innovation globally. So everyone is focusing on...
SPEAKER_1:  of reducing carbon emission versus innovating on alternate energy. You're basically focusing on putting the existing solar panels or wind turbines which are either.
SPEAKER_1:  just about inefficient or inefficient.
SPEAKER_1:  instead of making the next generation or it's more likely the 10th generation after that.
SPEAKER_1:  that comes with lots of battery backup power or fourth generation nuclear, or Craig Venter has this great idea, Craig Venter, the guy who cracked the human genome back in 2000, he has this idea of growing algae out on the ocean surface. These algae, they'd be genetically modified and they would basically soak up sunlight and CO2.
SPEAKER_1:  and produce oil.
SPEAKER_1:  then we could basically just grow our own Saudi Arabia out on the ocean surface and we'd harvest it
SPEAKER_1:  We'd keep our entire fossil fuel economy.
SPEAKER_1:  but it not be net zero because.
SPEAKER_1:  We just soaked up the CO2 out there. $1 invested in the portfolio of different ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  Gives $11 back.
SPEAKER_0:  I first wrote about that in the New York Times. It was one of my actual page one stories.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  In 2006, it was declining R&D.
SPEAKER_0:  in energy.
SPEAKER_0:  at a time of global warming.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  The baseline is so low for this that it's a super bargain.
SPEAKER_0:  We were.
SPEAKER_0:  during the energy crisis, the first energy crisis in the 70s.
SPEAKER_0:  before the current one.
SPEAKER_0:  are.
SPEAKER_0:  annual spending in the United States and constant dollars on.
SPEAKER_0:  R&Ds, research and development for energy.
SPEAKER_0:  was about $5 billion.
SPEAKER_0:  and then it's just dribbled away.
SPEAKER_0:  since then and recently now there's a big burst of new money coming through these new bills that got passed.
SPEAKER_0:  But what I was told over and over again by people in that arena.
SPEAKER_0:  is you.
SPEAKER_0:  Can't just have these little bubbles of...
SPEAKER_0:  investment. You don't get young people.
SPEAKER_0:  away from thinking about Wall Street for jobs towards thinking about energy innovation.
SPEAKER_0:  If there isn't like a.
SPEAKER_0:  future there.
SPEAKER_0:  and a lot of the in the United States and Europe.
SPEAKER_0:  The presumption was the way to that future was.
SPEAKER_0:  Taxing.
SPEAKER_0:  carpet.
SPEAKER_0:  Make that.
SPEAKER_0:  so punitive that
SPEAKER_0:  You're basically leveling even in the landscape for cleaner stuff that's more expensive.
SPEAKER_0:  That has failed completely.
SPEAKER_0:  They're little examples in Europe where.
SPEAKER_0:  Working.
SPEAKER_0:  And what's happened now is...
SPEAKER_0:  well, the United States, this big chunk of money.
SPEAKER_0:  designed to take us over a finish line.
SPEAKER_0:  that was started with
SPEAKER_0:  not just innovation, but with the production efficiency too. This is one thing I got wrong, I think, a little bit in my reporting. I was so fixated on the innovation part.
SPEAKER_0:  just because.
SPEAKER_0:  I love science too.
SPEAKER_0:  I saw this untapped possibility.
SPEAKER_0:  that others were saying, no, no, production efficiency, the more people are.
SPEAKER_0:  producing batteries the cheapest I'll get.
SPEAKER_0:  This is Elon Musk.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, path.
SPEAKER_0:  and many others.
SPEAKER_0:  And it really is both. So when you were talking about purchasing power for governments, for example.
SPEAKER_0:  that can stimulate.
SPEAKER_0:  Production.
SPEAKER_0:  capacity for batteries or whatever the good thing is.
SPEAKER_0:  and take you down faster.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's all about getting that margin.
SPEAKER_0:  of the new thing.
SPEAKER_0:  out competing the old.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's not just innovation. It has so many parts of the pipeline that need to be nurtured.
SPEAKER_0:  So, so.
SPEAKER_0:  And the other thing is relative cost.
SPEAKER_0:  The United States.
SPEAKER_0:  When I was writing about this in 2006.
SPEAKER_0:  our budget for
SPEAKER_0:  DARPA, the Advanced Research Project Agency for the Defense Department.
SPEAKER_0:  just for science, was 80 billion a year.
SPEAKER_0:  for health, for medical.
SPEAKER_0:  frontier research on cancers of 40 billion.
SPEAKER_0:  Energy was two or three.
SPEAKER_0:  So we weren't taking this remotely seriously. So now that if we get that.
SPEAKER_0:  To me, there's like this level.
SPEAKER_0:  You know we're taking something seriously when it's like in the tens of billions.
SPEAKER_0:  for R&D. It's not that R&D will solve the problem, but...
SPEAKER_0:  It's a proxy for what we really care about.
SPEAKER_0:  We care a shitload about defense.
SPEAKER_0:  What's their defense budget in the United States now? Like 800 billion?
SPEAKER_0:  It's some insane number. Who's counting when you're having fun? Yeah, yeah, yeah. And so, um.
SPEAKER_0:  Innovation is not just like for the better.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  Camera.
SPEAKER_0:  better solar panel, the better battery.
SPEAKER_0:  Social innovation actually matters hugely, like the guy in Nairobi I mentioned.
SPEAKER_0:  with a company doing micropayment.
SPEAKER_0:  gas to get people off charcoal.
SPEAKER_0:  We need that.
SPEAKER_0:  as much as this.
SPEAKER_0:  And I actually, I interviewed Bill Gates. We had to spend an hour with him in Seattle.
SPEAKER_0:  in 2016.
SPEAKER_0:  when he was rolling out his breakthrough energy thing. I got to spend...
SPEAKER_0:  It was 45 minutes, me and Bill Gates, which was pretty fun. But I brought this up, I said, you know, because he's all about
SPEAKER_0:  the new nuclear thing that will solve the world's problems. And I, yes, yes, yes, but we also- He brought up nuclear, sorry to interrupt. Oh, he did, oh sure, yes.
SPEAKER_1:  So he's interested in the new.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, he's investing heavily in nuclear, but he invests in everything. He's got a big portfolio.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  But I brought up a guy I met in India.
SPEAKER_0:  who runs a little outfit called Selco, that they do really interesting, cool.
SPEAKER_0:  Village to village.
SPEAKER_0:  They're like.
SPEAKER_0:  An energy analyst will come to your house here in the States.
SPEAKER_0:  tell you how to weatherize your house, so they do it at the village scale.
SPEAKER_0:  and in a village that has...
SPEAKER_0:  Brother Milling Wheat.
SPEAKER_0:  He'll put in a solar powered wheat.
SPEAKER_0:  Wheat milk.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  that's not going to solve the world's problems, but it gives them a way to control their energy.
SPEAKER_0:  They don't have to buy something to grind their wheat.
SPEAKER_0:  and that needs just as much attention as the.
SPEAKER_0:  the things I really like too, the cool technologies.
SPEAKER_0:  And I thought I cornered Bill Gates. I was like.
SPEAKER_0:  Because he really does focus on these big wins.
SPEAKER_0:  big, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, too clear.
SPEAKER_0:  that will make.
SPEAKER_0:  net zero completely doable. And I said, well, you know,
SPEAKER_0:  What about New York City where I was still living at the time?
SPEAKER_0:  I said, it's got a million buildings.
SPEAKER_0:  New York City has one million buildings. And in 2013, the Bloomberg government.
SPEAKER_0:  analyzed this.
SPEAKER_0:  Looking ahead to 2050.
SPEAKER_0:  75% of the buildings in New York City.
SPEAKER_0:  that will exist in 2050.
SPEAKER_0:  already exist.
SPEAKER_0:  Think about these brave new futures, right?
SPEAKER_0:  We're just going to come in.
SPEAKER_0:  have these shiny cool passive house cities.
SPEAKER_0:  And I put this to Bill and I said, so.
SPEAKER_0:  How do you do that? How do you retrofit all those?
SPEAKER_0:  boilers, many of which were coal fired like 20 years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  to get a zero energy in New York City.
SPEAKER_0:  I kind of thought I had him. He kind of sat back and went, well.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you have unlimited clean power coming into that city, it doesn't really matter.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a pretty good Bill Gates impression. It was a good answer. I mean, it was a good answer. He said, oh yeah, it's a leaky bucket, but pour in zero carbon energy, then it doesn't matter.
SPEAKER_0:  But I still think we have to figure out the other part too. That end, how do you, how do you?
SPEAKER_0:  innovate at the household level, at the village level.
SPEAKER_0:  It's much more of a distributed problem, we used to think.
SPEAKER_0:  The one big change I've had in my own thinking too is...
SPEAKER_0:  is.
SPEAKER_0:  from top down.
SPEAKER_0:  to distribute it.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything about the climate problem.
SPEAKER_0:  True.
SPEAKER_0:  The first three decades of my reporting was that the
SPEAKER_0:  The IPCC will come out a new report, the framework convention, the treaty will.
SPEAKER_0:  Get us on board.
SPEAKER_0:  we'll all behave better. It has this like.
SPEAKER_0:  top down, parent to child.
SPEAKER_0:  architecture.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Everything I've learned has gone the other way. It's distributed capacity.
SPEAKER_0:  for improved.
SPEAKER_0:  lives, you know, kids getting through school.
SPEAKER_0:  Women not having to.
SPEAKER_0:  spend three hours collecting firewood. And if it means propane for that household in that context, that's a good thing.
SPEAKER_0:  So stop with all your yammering about any oil, fossil fuel subsidies.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  You know, what's an America look like?
SPEAKER_0:  has some claims.
SPEAKER_0:  climate safe energy future.
SPEAKER_0:  Find your part in that.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't get disempowered by the scale of it. There's just like a thousand things to do. When you start to cut it into pieces.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's very different, it's not a top-down thing.
SPEAKER_0:  No one's going to magically come in and...
SPEAKER_1:  and that's where I think, so I agree that everyone should try to play their
SPEAKER_1:  their part and do.
SPEAKER_1:  whatever they can. But I also think, you know, just
SPEAKER_1:  the sheer incentives, what we saw happening with shale gas.
SPEAKER_1:  is a great example. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  when shale gas becomes so cheap that you just stop using coal.
SPEAKER_1:  that then you don't really have to convince.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, lots and lots of people, you know, coal is really bad. It wasn't labeled a climate.
SPEAKER_0:  No, it wasn't a climate thing. It was an energy thing.
SPEAKER_1:  It was totally, and the point is just, you know, the power of an innovation.
SPEAKER_1:  is that you're almost.
SPEAKER_1:  don't see it anymore, it just happens.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think that's really the only way we're going to fix.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, these big problems, if you think about, you know, the nutrition problem back in the 60s, 70s, we worried a lot about India and other places.
SPEAKER_1:  The solution is not worrying or the solution was not us eating a little bit less and sending it down to India or wherever. The solution was the Green Revolution, right? It was the fact that some scientists made...
SPEAKER_1:  ways to make every seed.
SPEAKER_1:  produce three times as much. So you could grow three times as much food on an acre. And that's what basically made it possible for India to go from a basket case to what.
SPEAKER_1:  the world's leading rice exporter.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's how you do these things. You solve these big problems.
SPEAKER_1:  through innovation.
SPEAKER_1:  And again, I'm not saying that we're actually arcing a carbon tax is a smart thing to do. That's what any economist would tell you to do.
SPEAKER_1:  But it also turns out...
SPEAKER_1:  that it's.
SPEAKER_1:  partly is not going to solve most of the problem and
SPEAKER_1:  it's incredibly politically hard to do. So it may also just be the wrong sort of tree to bark up against. If you can do it, please do.
SPEAKER_1:  But this is not the main thing that's going to solve climate. The main thing is that we get these innovations that basically make greened-ish so cheap everyone will just want.
SPEAKER_1:  We mentioned nuclear quite a few times.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there was a for a long time.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems to have shifted recently. Maybe you can-
SPEAKER_1:  clarify and educate me on this, but they're-
SPEAKER_1:  For the longest time people thought that nuclear is...
SPEAKER_1:  is.
SPEAKER_1:  almost unclean energy.
SPEAKER_1:  or
SPEAKER_1:  dangerous energy or all that kind of stuff. When did that shift?
SPEAKER_1:  What was the source of that alarmism?
SPEAKER_1:  I am woke.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe is that a case study of how?
SPEAKER_1:  alarmism can turn into
SPEAKER_1:  a productive constructive policy.
SPEAKER_0:  Haha.
SPEAKER_0:  Productive from whose standpoint?
SPEAKER_1:  I live- Is it not? Is it not?
SPEAKER_0:  like nuclear. We're not trying to be, do you mean productive in terms of yay we banned it or protective because
SPEAKER_1:  I see, I see what you mean, yes. I meant productive for human.
SPEAKER_0:  No, the alarmism over nuclear power.
SPEAKER_0:  dominated.
SPEAKER_0:  any alarmism over global warming.
SPEAKER_0:  Absolutely.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh really?
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yeah, this in the United States, three mile island, then you turn over there.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  the traditional environmental movement.
SPEAKER_0:  won't.
SPEAKER_0:  still won't go there. Is that a a
SPEAKER_0:  the big groups, NRDC, EDF, that whole alphabet soup of
SPEAKER_0:  the big greens are reluctant to.
SPEAKER_0:  put forward the nuclear.
SPEAKER_0:  option because they know a lot of their aging donors.
SPEAKER_0:  basically grew up in the thinking about nuclear is the problem, not the solution.
SPEAKER_0:  I lived for the last 30 years. I moved to Maine recently.
SPEAKER_0:  But I lived in the Hudson Valley, 10 miles from the Indian Point Nuclear Power Plant.
SPEAKER_0:  which was built in the 60s, 70s.
SPEAKER_0:  and had some problems.
SPEAKER_0:  None of them were.
SPEAKER_0:  to the point of.
SPEAKER_0:  meltdown or the threat of it or even the theoretical possibility of one.
SPEAKER_0:  I was in it twice as a reporter, looking down in the cooling pool. I can send you a fun video.
SPEAKER_0:  bubbles in the cooling pool with the rods.
SPEAKER_0:  Progressively they-
SPEAKER_0:  demonstrated how to handle waste in the United States. Now the waste is.
SPEAKER_0:  because we haven't figured out how to move it across state lines.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a.
SPEAKER_0:  glassified it's put into kind of containers that sit there at the plant.
SPEAKER_0:  We just simply don't have a long term.
SPEAKER_0:  solution.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  the Nevada.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  politicians were successful in saying not here, not here, not Yucca Mountain.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  About my wife?
SPEAKER_0:  I've been married to, well, I met 30 years ago and she lives with me. She's an environmental educator.
SPEAKER_0:  She was very happy when Cuomo...
SPEAKER_0:  Shut it down.
SPEAKER_0:  Said we're going to shut it down.
SPEAKER_0:  three or four years ago, which just happened a year.
SPEAKER_0:  It actually is shut down now.
SPEAKER_0:  I speak Muffball and I was like, that sucks.
SPEAKER_0:  We need... She's happy.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and we still love each other.
SPEAKER_1:  environmentalist so that that just
SPEAKER_1:  speaks to.
SPEAKER_1:  a lot of environmentalists still see nuclear as bad.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh totally.
SPEAKER_0:  and you bring in the weapons proliferation issues and...
SPEAKER_0:  But it's a safety thing, it's a generational thing. I think young people are different, I hope.
SPEAKER_0:  these small modular reactor designs.
SPEAKER_0:  several of which
SPEAKER_0:  There's a couple of.
SPEAKER_0:  PhDs from
SPEAKER_0:  MIT, who did transatomic power.
SPEAKER_0:  They're both like in their early 30s.
SPEAKER_0:  We need so much more of them.
SPEAKER_0:  And just briefly, the one thing I say about nuclear is...
SPEAKER_0:  Like with so many of these things, like subsidies.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't talk to me about.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, no, nuclear.
SPEAKER_0:  Talk to me about what do you want to do with existing nuclear power plants?
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  What do you want to do about the possibility of new ones?
SPEAKER_0:  Let's parse this out in chunks that we can.
SPEAKER_0:  have constructive conversations about the idea of no nuclear.
SPEAKER_0:  drives me crazy.
SPEAKER_0:  just like no fossil fuel subsidies.
SPEAKER_0:  is silly in the world we inhabit that has these pockets of no energy.
SPEAKER_0:  So that.
SPEAKER_0:  That's just my, you know, my sustained what?
SPEAKER_0:  Mantras.
SPEAKER_0:  start with some dividing it and divide and conquer.
SPEAKER_0:  to conquer the dispute.
SPEAKER_0:  over by saying, let's at least get real.
SPEAKER_0:  This power plant has been in the Hudson Valley for 30 years.
SPEAKER_0:  It was the baseload. It was baseload. Baseload is a real thing.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Guesswork has filled the gap since that power plant is turned off.
SPEAKER_0:  Natural gas.
SPEAKER_0:  Natural gas, but.
SPEAKER_0:  And.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't hear that.
SPEAKER_0:  from the environmental community that was so eager to turn off.
SPEAKER_0:  the Indian Point.
SPEAKER_1:  I think both the point of saying.
SPEAKER_1:  People are saying it's the end of the world, but no, I don't want a new clip how it just doesn't make sense. Right. And Andy is absolutely right to talk about so existing nuclear power plants.
SPEAKER_1:  You already paid for them.
SPEAKER_1:  We already have them. We already committed to decommissioning them eventually.
SPEAKER_1:  while they're running.
SPEAKER_1:  pretty much the cheapest power you can possibly have on the planet, because it costs almost nothing.
SPEAKER_1:  to run them.
SPEAKER_1:  day to day.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's basically.
SPEAKER_1:  cheap or almost free CO2.
SPEAKER_1:  baseload power. There's just nothing there that is
SPEAKER_1:  that you should embrace.
SPEAKER_1:  New nuclear power plants.
SPEAKER_1:  turn out to be very expensive currently. So the one they built in Finland, some in the UK and France and several other places turn out to be incredibly expensive. So they're much more expensive than the costliest renewables you can imagine. So they're actually not a solution right now.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's why we need the innovation. That's why we need the potentially fourth generation nuclear power. It's just simply, it's a bad deal.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's why nuclear is never going to win on its third generation. Now it may never.
SPEAKER_1:  Get there. Who knows?
SPEAKER_1:  but it's certainly a-
SPEAKER_1:  a possibility and we should be looking into it. And there are, there are, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  wonky.
SPEAKER_0:  realities.
SPEAKER_0:  that need to be.
SPEAKER_0:  dealt with. I'm the chair of the regulatory commission in the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  their approval process.
SPEAKER_0:  is still locked and designed.
SPEAKER_0:  on this 50-year-old model of big, giant power plants.
SPEAKER_0:  There's an intense discussion right now about.
SPEAKER_0:  evolving a new regulatory scheme for small modular ones because of all these
SPEAKER_0:  implicit advantages they offer.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's so weird.
SPEAKER_0:  along with the innovation, you need to have this.
SPEAKER_0:  get out of the way or you're never going to have the investment.
SPEAKER_0:  So it really is an all of the above thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Looking at these as systems solutions is really important.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask you about it.
SPEAKER_1:  Alex Epstein.
SPEAKER_1:  So he wrote, I'm not sure if you're familiar who he is, but he wrote a couple of books.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just interesting to ask a question about fossil fuels because we're talking about reality.
SPEAKER_1:  and he's somebody that doesn't just talk about the reality of fossil fuels, but
SPEAKER_1:  He wrote a book, Moral Case for Fossil Fuels and Fossil Future.
SPEAKER_1:  or he makes the case.
SPEAKER_1:  that as his subtitle says, global human flourishing requires oil, coal and natural gas.
SPEAKER_1:  or.
SPEAKER_1:  More.
SPEAKER_1:  oil, coal, and natural gas, not less.
SPEAKER_1:  what do you think about the argument he makes? so he pushes
SPEAKER_1:  We've had this kind of speaking of the center.
SPEAKER_1:  of this balanced discussion of the reality of fossil fuels but also investing a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  into renewable energy and then having
SPEAKER_1:  the $1 to $11 return.
SPEAKER_1:  He says like
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not sure exactly how to
SPEAKER_1:  I'll frame it but...
SPEAKER_1:  investing and maintaining investment of fossil fuels.
SPEAKER_1:  also has a positive return because of how efficient the energy is.
SPEAKER_0:  I've read the first book.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I haven't got a second one.
SPEAKER_0:  I've been planning to have them on my webcast, my tiny webcast.
SPEAKER_0:  What's the name of the webcast? Sustain what? Everything I do is sustain what? Cause it's like, don't talk to me about sustainability.
SPEAKER_0:  Sustain what?
SPEAKER_0:  For whom? How? Then we're talking, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  interrogatory approach to things.
SPEAKER_0:  So, um.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  The valuable part of what he has done is to remind people.
SPEAKER_0:  particularly in the West or North of what everyone.
SPEAKER_0:  the developed world.
SPEAKER_0:  that everything we take for granted.
SPEAKER_0:  Low fertilizer, from low fertilizer.
SPEAKER_0:  prices too.
SPEAKER_0:  air conditioning to everything else exists because we had this bounty.
SPEAKER_0:  that we dug out of the ground or pumped out of the ground.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a boon, it's been an amazing boon to society.
SPEAKER_0:  period. So start there.
SPEAKER_0:  which means...
SPEAKER_0:  going forward, what we're talking about is a substitution.
SPEAKER_0:  Or...
SPEAKER_0:  Having your fossil fuels and eating it too, meaning getting rid of the carbon dioxide. If you focus on the carbon dioxide.
SPEAKER_0:  which is the thing warming the planet, not the burning of the fuels.
SPEAKER_0:  then that's another way forward that could sustain fossil fuels.
SPEAKER_0:  As far as I can tell from at least the first book, he makes the moral case.
SPEAKER_0:  fossil fuels are.
SPEAKER_0:  essentially a good.
SPEAKER_0:  overall.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think he adequately.
SPEAKER_0:  accounts for the need.
SPEAKER_0:  to stop global warming. You know, I think that...
SPEAKER_0:  We have to slow, slowing global warming is a fundamental need in this coming, in this century we're in.
SPEAKER_0:  that's just not factored into his math.
SPEAKER_1:  where?
SPEAKER_1:  I've had a few sort of offline conversations with him. I think he said, because I mentioned I'm talking to the two of you, he said that.
SPEAKER_1:  That's probably where he disagrees about the level of threat.
SPEAKER_1:  um, global warming.
SPEAKER_0:  causes.
SPEAKER_0:  Brilliant guy. He lived right close to me in the Hudson Valley.
SPEAKER_0:  He was in the Obama administration energy department.
SPEAKER_0:  It's K-O-O-N-I-N.
SPEAKER_0:  He wrote a bestseller that came out recently on.
SPEAKER_0:  skepticism about climate.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And, um...
SPEAKER_0:  There are other smart people who-
SPEAKER_0:  somehow feel we can literally adapt our way forward without any constraint.
SPEAKER_0:  on the gases changing the climate.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  spent enough time on this. I think I'm a pretty level-headed reporter when it comes to this issue.
SPEAKER_0:  I think having some sense that.
SPEAKER_0:  We can.
SPEAKER_0:  adapt our way into the world we're building through.
SPEAKER_0:  relentless climate change with no new normal. hong imager
SPEAKER_0:  More guests.
SPEAKER_0:  accumulating in the air every year.
SPEAKER_0:  This was not static.
SPEAKER_0:  moments.
SPEAKER_0:  that that's a good thing to do.
SPEAKER_0:  That's it.
SPEAKER_0:  strike me as...
SPEAKER_1:  I'd probably say that I think it's more sort of a, at least the thing that I take away from Alex.
SPEAKER_1:  it's uh i'm
SPEAKER_1:  is the fact as you point out.
SPEAKER_1:  We need to recognise that fossil fuels are basically the backbone of our society today. We get 80% of our energy.
SPEAKER_1:  from fossil fuels to day.
SPEAKER_0:  50 years. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, yeah, yeah. And people have no sense of this, right? So they have the idea because you see so many wind turbines and solar panels and everybody's talking about it, that this is huge big things. But the reality is remember only about a fifth of all energy uses, electricity, the rest is, you know, in processes and heating, industrial processes and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  So actually, solar and wind right now.
SPEAKER_1:  produces 1% of energy from wind and 0.8% from solar.
SPEAKER_1:  This is not a huge thing. It's a fairly tiny bit.
SPEAKER_0:  growing explosively but
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, it's absolutely growing. But actually, it's growing slower than what nuclear was growing in the 70s and 80s, which I thought was a f-
SPEAKER_1:  a fun point not by a little amount, but like two or three times.
SPEAKER_1:  So we're still talking about something which is somewhat boutique, at least.
SPEAKER_1:  And when you then look out into the future, and I think this is the interesting part of it.
SPEAKER_1:  when you look out into the future, if you look at the Biden administration's own estimate of what will happen by 2050.
SPEAKER_1:  We will be at.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, if all countries do all the stuff that they promised and everything, we will be at 70% fossil fuels by 2015.
SPEAKER_1:  Globally.
SPEAKER_1:  This is just, yes, it's a better world. I think it's good that we're now down to 70 instead of 80.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  It is still a world that's fundamentally dependent on fossil fuels for almost everything that we really like about the world.
SPEAKER_1:  and forgetting that, and I think we are doing that.
SPEAKER_1:  in the sense as you also mentioned that people say no fossil fuels and we're in all development organizations, we're now telling the poor countries you can't get any funding for anything that has to do with fossil fuels. We have literally reduced our investment in...
SPEAKER_1:  oil and gas by more than half since 2014.
SPEAKER_1:  And much of this is because of climate concerns.
SPEAKER_1:  This has real world consequences. This is why.
SPEAKER_1:  and that your prices have gone up. It's not the only reason.
SPEAKER_1:  COVID also, certainly the war in Ukraine, but this is an underlying system.
SPEAKER_1:  systemic reason why fossil fuel costs will go up dramatically. Now a lot of greens.
SPEAKER_1:  will sort of tend to say, well, that's great. We want fossil fuels to be expensive. We want people to be forced over to renewables.
SPEAKER_1:  But that's very easy to say.
SPEAKER_1:  if you're rich.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's the kind of thing that New Yorkers will say, you know, when you, when you go to rich, well-meaning, green New Yorkers and say,
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, gasoline should cost $20 a gallon.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, you don't have a car. You just ride the Metro. It's very easy for you to say that.
SPEAKER_1:  lots of people both in the rich world but in poor parts of the US.
SPEAKER_1:  all around the world, their lives have basically depended on fossil fuels. And so the idea that we're going to get people off by making it so expensive that it becomes impossible for them to live good lives.
SPEAKER_1:  is almost morally reprehensible. And I think
SPEAKER_1:  Alex has the right point there.
SPEAKER_1:  We need to get people to realize.
SPEAKER_1:  We're not going to get off fossil fuels anytime soon, so we need
SPEAKER_1:  reasonably affordable fossil fuels for most of the world?
SPEAKER_1:  And that's of course why we need to focus so much more on the innovation so that we can get to the point where we no longer need fossil fuels as soon as possible. But to say to everyone, look, we're going to make fossil fuels expensive way before we have the solution is just terrible.
SPEAKER_0:  And so much is on the rich countries of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I did a conversation recently with Johann Rockstrom who's
SPEAKER_0:  a famed
SPEAKER_0:  sustainability scientist in Stockholm.
SPEAKER_0:  actually potstamp now.
SPEAKER_0:  and he's come up with the idea of planetary boundaries.
SPEAKER_0:  There's lots of things he...
SPEAKER_0:  I said that I.
SPEAKER_0:  As a journalist, I'm still looking into about that. Planetary boundaries. Yeah, that there are limits to what Earth can absorb in human...
SPEAKER_0:  our use of water, phosphorus, our carbon dioxide loading in the atmosphere. There are these tipping
SPEAKER_0:  there are these boundaries if we cross them.
SPEAKER_0:  A hot zone, a danger zone.
SPEAKER_0:  He's an interesting thinker.
SPEAKER_0:  But on this point...
SPEAKER_0:  last year at the Glasgow Climate Talks.
SPEAKER_0:  He gave a very important talk about.
SPEAKER_0:  The equity thing here.
SPEAKER_0:  That you.
SPEAKER_0:  He basically laid out a landscape.
SPEAKER_0:  saying the rich nations of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  need to greatly ramp up their reduction of emissions or what they're going to pay poor countries to do.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  to allow poor countries
SPEAKER_0:  some of which have fossil resources like in Africa.
SPEAKER_0:  to have the carbon space.
SPEAKER_0:  to own whatever space or time is left.
SPEAKER_0:  to be able to develop their
SPEAKER_0:  Fossil fuels.
SPEAKER_0:  as a fundamental right because also they're starting from this little baseline, Ghana.
SPEAKER_0:  hasn't contributed squat to the global warming problem in terms of emissions.
SPEAKER_0:  Ghana has natural gas.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Right now, this month, environmental groups are
SPEAKER_0:  Outside.
SPEAKER_0:  the World Bank.
SPEAKER_0:  Today, actually tonight.
SPEAKER_0:  saying
SPEAKER_0:  This was on their list of dirty projects. World Bank should stop financing Ghana's right to get gas out of the ground.
SPEAKER_0:  to develop its economy.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, it's people less poor.
SPEAKER_0:  make them more productive, innovative parts of humanity.
SPEAKER_0:  to me that's really reprehensible.
SPEAKER_0:  One of the other projects on their list?
SPEAKER_0:  as a World Bank kind of gotcha.
SPEAKER_0:  Like how dare they give money?
SPEAKER_0:  was for a new fertilizer factory in Bangladesh.
SPEAKER_0:  that is designed to get three times as much fertilizer from the same amount of natural gas as the old plants that are not dormant.
SPEAKER_0:  That's...
SPEAKER_0:  This is in a time when we're facing.
SPEAKER_0:  High energy prices, high gas prices, high...
SPEAKER_0:  food prices when food insecurity is spreading rapidly.
SPEAKER_0:  when a country like Bangladesh has millions of rice farmers who need
SPEAKER_0:  Urea.
SPEAKER_0:  tablets to put in their rice fields.
SPEAKER_0:  to say how dare they finance that because there's a fossil fuel involved is immoral. So yes on that point from Alex.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is...
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  2022 poll.
SPEAKER_1:  pulse.
SPEAKER_1:  Just this is a bunch of different ways to look at the same
SPEAKER_1:  basic effect in the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  Democrats, younger Americans identify dealing with climate change as a top.
SPEAKER_1:  priority us adults.
SPEAKER_1:  42% say...
SPEAKER_1:  42% say that dealing with climate change should be a top priority.
SPEAKER_1:  11% of Republicans.
SPEAKER_1:  65% of Democrats.
SPEAKER_1:  and we could see this effect.
SPEAKER_1:  throughout.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  46% of Americans say human activity contributes a great deal to climate change.
SPEAKER_1:  By the way.
SPEAKER_1:  This is a little bit different than what we're discussing. How was uh.
SPEAKER_1:  just look at the different polls.
SPEAKER_1:  In the public, there seems to still be uncertainty about how much humans contribute to climate change.
SPEAKER_1:  More than.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I mean, it would only be 24% that disagree with the UN climate panel, right?
SPEAKER_1:  Three-quarters would agree. Are you uncomfortable about the 29?
SPEAKER_1:  I know 29 is actually, it's exactly right. I mean, the UN doesn't say it's all, well, they say that could be the border case.
SPEAKER_1:  But anyway, this is interesting, but to me, across all these poles, if you look.
SPEAKER_1:  Republican versus
SPEAKER_1:  Democrat.
SPEAKER_1:  Republican.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... it's say that seventy percent say
SPEAKER_1:  It's a great deal. Democrats say 71% says it's a great deal. And you just see this.
SPEAKER_1:  complete division.
SPEAKER_1:  I think you probably.
SPEAKER_1:  or COVID pandemic.
SPEAKER_1:  You can ask a lot of questions like this. Do masks work? Are they an effective method?
SPEAKER_1:  the slow transmission of a pandemic. You'll probably have the same kind of polls about.
SPEAKER_1:  Republicans and Democrats.
SPEAKER_1:  And um...
SPEAKER_1:  while the effectiveness of masks to me is a scientific question.
SPEAKER_1:  but...
SPEAKER_1:  So there's different truths here apparently.
SPEAKER_1:  One is a scientific truth.
SPEAKER_1:  One is the truth.
SPEAKER_1:  which seems to be also different than the scientific truth sometimes. And the other is the public perception that has...
SPEAKER_1:  that's...
SPEAKER_1:  polluted or affected by
SPEAKER_1:  political affiliation.
SPEAKER_1:  And then there's whatever is the.
SPEAKER_1:  narrative that's communicated by the media.
SPEAKER_1:  They will also have a question, the answer to the question of whether masks work or not. And they will also have an answer to the question about.
SPEAKER_1:  all these climate related things.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a long way of asking the question.
SPEAKER_1:  What?
SPEAKER_1:  How is politics mixed into all of this?
SPEAKER_1:  on the communication front on the figuring out what the right policy is front.
SPEAKER_1:  on the friction.
SPEAKER_1:  humanity.
SPEAKER_1:  in the face of the right policies.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I've written a ton on this after I had that conversion about the social science.
SPEAKER_0:  2006.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll begin.
SPEAKER_0:  digging in a lot more on how people hold beliefs.
SPEAKER_0:  what they do as opposed to what they think.
SPEAKER_0:  questions about polling.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's two things that come to me that make me not worry about the basic literacy.
SPEAKER_0:  Is climate change X percent of whatever?
SPEAKER_0:  I don't.
SPEAKER_0:  really care about that.
SPEAKER_0:  and I'll explain why.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  For one thing.
SPEAKER_0:  More.
SPEAKER_0:  science literacy, more basic literacy, like what is a greenhouse gas?
SPEAKER_0:  All that stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  Dan Kahane, K-A-H-A-N at Yale.
SPEAKER_0:  He's actually at Yale Law School.
SPEAKER_0:  The last.
SPEAKER_0:  decade he did all this work in what he calls cultural cognition.
SPEAKER_0:  which is, and he did.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Studies that showed.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, how, what you believe.
SPEAKER_0:  emerges.
SPEAKER_0:  based on.
SPEAKER_0:  culture based on your background, your red blue.
SPEAKER_0:  or where you are in the country.
SPEAKER_0:  And one of the really disturbing findings was
SPEAKER_0:  that the people who have the most basic science literacy, like who know the most about.
SPEAKER_0:  greenhouse effect or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  They're at both ends of the spectrum.
SPEAKER_0:  of views on climate, dismissives and alarmed.
SPEAKER_0:  Steve Kuhnen, as I mentioned, is a good example. He's brilliant physicist.
SPEAKER_0:  and he knows all the science and he's completely at the end of skepticism.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Will Happer.
SPEAKER_0:  who was.
SPEAKER_0:  close to being Trump's science advisor.
SPEAKER_0:  There's even more out there.
SPEAKER_0:  And he's on, they're both on the.
SPEAKER_0:  Jason committee that advises the government on big strategic things.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And people at the...
SPEAKER_0:  who are really alarmed about it also have the same belief. So as a journalist, I was thinking, do I just spend my time writing more explanatory?
SPEAKER_0:  Stories that explain the science better?
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  Do I dig in on this work to understand?
SPEAKER_0:  what brings people together. And then the same.
SPEAKER_0:  Surveys, the same science shows you.
SPEAKER_0:  If you don't make it about climate, among other things, this becomes.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't have to worry about this anymore.
SPEAKER_0:  If you could Google for.
SPEAKER_0:  Google for no red-blue divide.
SPEAKER_0:  climate revkin.
SPEAKER_0:  You'll find a piece I did with some really good graphs.
SPEAKER_0:  Essentially it shows.
SPEAKER_0:  that in America, this is the Yale group again.
SPEAKER_0:  They're a climate communication group.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no red-blue divide on energy innovation.
SPEAKER_0:  None.
SPEAKER_0:  We need more climate, energy, clean energy innovation. There wasn't even a divide.
SPEAKER_0:  country by state by state on.
SPEAKER_0:  whether CO2 should be regulated as a pollutant.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's all like, what are the questions you ask if you ask about-
SPEAKER_0:  innovation if you ask about more incentives for renewable power.
SPEAKER_0:  Oklahoma.
SPEAKER_0:  Iowa.
SPEAKER_0:  you know?
SPEAKER_0:  I did a piece when I was at ProPublica showing that...
SPEAKER_0:  The 17 states that were fighting Obama.
SPEAKER_0:  in court over his.
SPEAKER_0:  Clean Power Plan.
SPEAKER_0:  We're actually.
SPEAKER_0:  The majority of them were actually meeting the targets that the Clean Power Plan had.
SPEAKER_0:  because they're expanding wind power.
SPEAKER_0:  already.
SPEAKER_0:  Not because of the climate, because it...
SPEAKER_0:  Mix.
SPEAKER_0:  money sense and energy sense. So you don't think there's a political divide in this? There is on climate, if you call it climate. If you say it's a climate, do you believe in the climate crisis? You're not asking.
SPEAKER_0:  What kind of energy future do you want?
SPEAKER_0:  And so if you ask that question.
SPEAKER_0:  the polarization goes away.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess what I'm asking is their polarization on policy.
SPEAKER_0:  No, well, well, they're-
SPEAKER_0:  Again.
SPEAKER_0:  bipartisan infrastructure law.
SPEAKER_0:  that was passed last November. That was bipartisan.
SPEAKER_0:  Congress said yes, and that's a trillion dollars.
SPEAKER_0:  several hundred billion of which are for cleaner energy and resilience.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, but that's...
SPEAKER_0:  But it's not a climate pill.
SPEAKER_0:  and it wasn't a tax.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a, it's a.
SPEAKER_0:  It's incentives.
SPEAKER_1:  So the word climate and similar words are just used as part of the signaling, like masks.
SPEAKER_1:  It's, it's- Absolutely.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not.
SPEAKER_0:  As Dan Cahan's work, that guy at Yale.
SPEAKER_0:  he really demonstrated powerfully.
SPEAKER_0:  abortion gun rights.
SPEAKER_0:  climate.
SPEAKER_0:  and a more parsed level of nuclear power.
SPEAKER_0:  has given the answer.
SPEAKER_0:  enduring camps that for and against. What, what, what are the camps for?
SPEAKER_0:  some of its
SPEAKER_0:  cultural cognition. It's how you grew up. It's what you fear.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no common human frame for...
SPEAKER_1:  like folks like certain individuals like Al Gore.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah, like he would make a film.
SPEAKER_1:  He cares about this thing.
SPEAKER_1:  He's a Democrat.
SPEAKER_0:  Therefore I hate this thing. Therefore I don't like this thing, yeah. I'm sure.
SPEAKER_0:  when people get attached to an issue. If that's what pops into your head.
SPEAKER_0:  when you hear climate then. And it got politicized. It became.
SPEAKER_0:  Emblematic
SPEAKER_0:  and the whole vaccine thing.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I'm not American, so I should stay a little bit out of this, but I think it seems to me.
SPEAKER_1:  that a lot of the thing that people believe and talk about.
SPEAKER_1:  is really about what they worried that that.
SPEAKER_1:  will lead to in terms of policy down the line. So a little bit like, do masks work? I'm sort of imagining, I don't know whether this is true, but I think part of it is.
SPEAKER_1:  If I say masks work, they're going to
SPEAKER_1:  forced me to wear it for the next year.
SPEAKER_1:  So it doesn't work because then I don't have to wear it kind of thing. That it's really, you're looking much further down the line. And certainly on climate, it seems to me that a lot of the people who say it's not real.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not because they don't know it's... Of course it's real.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's that they don't want you to then come and regulate it heavily.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Because they don't like.
SPEAKER_1:  top-down government. Yeah, and also because they don't.
SPEAKER_1:  want another tax and you know that there's lots of other so it's it's really it's not a science it's not a straight science question it really is a question
SPEAKER_1:  what do you want to do? And that's where I think Andy, you're much, much more right in saying we should have that discussion.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you want to do?
SPEAKER_1:  because that will be a much easier conversation to say, do you wanna do really smart, cheap stuff, or do you wanna do pretty dumb, expensive stuff? When you put it that way, you can get most people on board. Of course, it's not as simple as that, I know.
SPEAKER_0:  And it gets back to what you said earlier, that again, you talked about collaborative cooperation or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a guy at Columbia, Peter Coleman, who runs this thing called Difficult Conversations Laboratory.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Yeah, that's awesome. And when I first heard about it, I was like, oh man, we need that.
SPEAKER_0:  And his background is psychology and...
SPEAKER_0:  Conflict resolution.
SPEAKER_0:  Mostly at the global scale related to it.
SPEAKER_0:  atrocities that countries are trying to get over.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's a science to how to hold a better conversation, either through experience or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  If you hold a debate, like...
SPEAKER_0:  I wouldn't want to be in a debate with Bjorn. We could find lots of things we disagree on.
SPEAKER_0:  but that takes it back to the win-lose model, right?
SPEAKER_0:  That's not how you make progress.
SPEAKER_0:  And what Peter...
SPEAKER_0:  what I learned absorbed from him, Peter Coleman.
SPEAKER_0:  because I was thinking like.
SPEAKER_0:  We need room for agreement. I need to build a room for agreement. My blog at the Times and then.
SPEAKER_0:  the stuff I do now, you know, it's like, how can we talk?
SPEAKER_0:  and come to agreement. He says, no, no, you don't want agreement. You want cooperation.
SPEAKER_0:  That allows you to hold onto your.
SPEAKER_0:  beliefs.
SPEAKER_0:  But to...
SPEAKER_0:  burger, you know, we.
SPEAKER_0:  We can disagree on all these things, but let's cooperate on that.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's a really valuable.
SPEAKER_0:  Distinction.
SPEAKER_0:  that's needed so much in this arena because...
SPEAKER_0:  As I said earlier, you can parse it right down to.
SPEAKER_0:  the whole menu of things Joe Manchin wanted.
SPEAKER_0:  transmission lines, now we're going to have big fights over transmission lines. We've got billions of dollars to expand expanding America's grid.
SPEAKER_0:  And every community in America is going to say, not here. So how do you?
SPEAKER_0:  Foster a federal local.
SPEAKER_0:  I just dialogued it.
SPEAKER_0:  allows that to happen if you want to have any hope of a better.
SPEAKER_0:  grid.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's like.
SPEAKER_0:  Those insights come from behavioral sciences that I think are completely under.
SPEAKER_0:  undervalued.
SPEAKER_0:  in this.
SPEAKER_0:  area.
SPEAKER_1:  Pilke loves to quote, I think it's Lippert. Oh, Walter Lippman. Yes, that democracy is not about.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, everybody agree?
SPEAKER_1:  but it's about different people disagreeing.
SPEAKER_1:  doing the same thing. Doing one thing together. Yes. I mean, agreeing that we're going to do this thing. So you can disagree, but still do a thing, you know, possibly for very different.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. Red to
SPEAKER_0:  And there's an amazing video clip.
SPEAKER_0:  that shows this so powerfully.
SPEAKER_0:  2015 was the buildup to the Paris talks that led to the Paris agreement.
SPEAKER_0:  and a really talented journalist at CNN at the time, John Sutter.
SPEAKER_0:  who's from Oklahoma originally, he...
SPEAKER_0:  He saw another Yale study that.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a county by county study of American attitudes on global warming.
SPEAKER_0:  right down to the county level. And
SPEAKER_0:  There's this little.
SPEAKER_0:  Glowing.
SPEAKER_0:  data point in Woodward County, West Oklahoma. Woodward County, Oklahoma was ground zero for climate skepticism, climate denial, whatever you want to call it.
SPEAKER_0:  And he thought, oh, I'm going to go there. He went there just as a-
SPEAKER_0:  just to meet people on the street, talk to them about energy and weather.
SPEAKER_0:  And he did these little interviews. And there's this one with this guy who's like, um,
SPEAKER_0:  middle-aged oil company employee.
SPEAKER_0:  like a business, like a administrator, Thai, Thai kind of guy.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's
SPEAKER_0:  He starts out the interview and the guy is saying like, you know, God controls the environment.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you're watching this, you're just going, okay, this is going to be interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  And the backstory, by the way, is the guy, he paid for the local.
SPEAKER_0:  playground.
SPEAKER_0:  to have dinosaurs and people.
SPEAKER_0:  toy dinosaurs and people all the way around because he believes in creation.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, 6,000 year creation. So that's the guy, right?
SPEAKER_0:  And then he gets to energy and the guy says, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  The same guy who believes God controls the environment.
SPEAKER_0:  says, you know, we have half of our roof covered with solar panels and we want to get off the grid entirely.
SPEAKER_0:  And when I show this to audiences, I say, just pause and think about that for a second.
SPEAKER_0:  If you went.
SPEAKER_0:  Why do you think that's happening? And it's because he's independent. He wants to have his own source of power. He's libertarian. He doesn't want the government telling him what to do. He would never vote for Hillary, I guarantee you.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the run 15.
SPEAKER_0:  But he wanted to get off the grid entirely to be his own.
SPEAKER_0:  to be himself.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  So then I say, okay, so if you were going around the country with your climate crisis...
SPEAKER_0:  placard and you go to Woodward County.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think?
SPEAKER_0:  That would be a productive way.
SPEAKER_0:  to go to that place and make your case.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  The answer is pretty obvious, no.
SPEAKER_0:  If you go in there and you listen.
SPEAKER_0:  Like listening is such an important.
SPEAKER_0:  property that we all forget, including journalists.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  you much more apt to find a path to cooperation.
SPEAKER_0:  you could talk to him about.
SPEAKER_0:  I guarantee if I went there today, maybe I should go.
SPEAKER_0:  to talk about this new bill, $370 billion. How do we make that work at the local level?
SPEAKER_0:  How do we answer that guy at the energy department, Jigar Shah? So how do we put this to work?
SPEAKER_0:  to get our buses off.
SPEAKER_0:  electricity to get electrified or.
SPEAKER_0:  transition our street lamps and stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  You could have a good chat with him. If you go in there and say.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm here to debate you to death on global warming.
SPEAKER_0:  forget about.
SPEAKER_1:  Actually, let me ask you a question, given your roots as a journalist.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  So yeah, talking to a guy you disagree with, that's one thing.
SPEAKER_1:  What about talking to people?
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  might be, society might consider.
SPEAKER_1:  bad, unethical, even evil.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the role of a journalist in that context?
SPEAKER_1:  So climate changes.
SPEAKER_1:  large number of people that believe one thing, large number of people that believe another thing.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... it turns out you know people the society deems evil
SPEAKER_1:  there's a large number of people that support them.
SPEAKER_1:  What's your role as a journalist?
SPEAKER_1:  to talk to them.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I have talked to really bad people. When I wrote about the murder of Chico Mendes, a Brazilian...
SPEAKER_0:  Amazon rainforest activist.
SPEAKER_0:  1989, I revealed it.
SPEAKER_0:  The Killers?
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  One was in jail, several of them were.
SPEAKER_0:  ranchers who
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  They had their point of view. They were there in the Amazon rainforest to-
SPEAKER_0:  The word in Brazil and Portuguese is limpar, to clean the land. They're the bandarantes, the pioneers of...
SPEAKER_0:  Brazil, they go into these frontiers and tame them.
SPEAKER_0:  like we had in our West.
SPEAKER_0:  And they would bring that up too. They would say to me.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you did this out, you know. Didn't say you murdered your-
SPEAKER_0:  Native Americans and stuff, but they could easily have said that too, and you deforested all your landscapes.
SPEAKER_0:  So who are you to come down here to?
SPEAKER_0:  But if I didn't.
SPEAKER_0:  Talk to them.
SPEAKER_0:  That would be
SPEAKER_0:  Not a way to do journalism.
SPEAKER_1:  But when you talked to them, did you empathize with them?
SPEAKER_1:  Or did you push back?
SPEAKER_1:  That's the ultimate question.
SPEAKER_1:  Like if you want to understand...
SPEAKER_1:  like if you talk to Hitler in 1941.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you empathize with him?
SPEAKER_1:  Or do you push back?
SPEAKER_1:  because most journalists
SPEAKER_1:  Push.
SPEAKER_1:  because they're trying to signal to fellow journalists and to people back home.
SPEAKER_1:  that this me, the journalist, is on the right side.
SPEAKER_1:  but if you actually want to understand the person.
SPEAKER_1:  You should empathize.
SPEAKER_1:  If you want to be the kind of person that actually understands
SPEAKER_1:  in the-
SPEAKER_1:  fool.
SPEAKER_1:  Arc of History.
SPEAKER_1:  you need to empathize. I find that journalists
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of times, perhaps they're protecting their job.
SPEAKER_1:  their reputation, their sanity.
SPEAKER_1:  are not willing to empathize.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, well, I think this happened with Joe Manchin. I'm not doing any kind of equation here related to Hitler and Joe Manchin. Or Trump, I mean Trump. I interviewed the guy, Will Happer, I mentioned, who was
SPEAKER_0:  physicist at Princeton who thinks carbon dioxide is the greatest thing.
SPEAKER_0:  in the world and we should have more of it in the atmosphere.
SPEAKER_0:  I profoundly disagree on that point.
SPEAKER_0:  But I interviewed him for an hour and...
SPEAKER_0:  And it was so interesting because he was trying to kind of rope-a-dope me.
SPEAKER_0:  into
SPEAKER_0:  making it about CO2 and climate, because he's a super-
SPEAKER_0:  Smart physicist.
SPEAKER_0:  And I kind of said, let's talk about some other things.
SPEAKER_0:  we start talking about education and science education. He went on for like 20 minutes.
SPEAKER_0:  about the vital importance of better.
SPEAKER_0:  science education for Americans he drew on.
SPEAKER_0:  people he knew from Europe, Hungary.
SPEAKER_0:  A bunch of Nobel Prize winners came from some town in Hungary, at least a couple.
SPEAKER_0:  he said that he learned their teachers.
SPEAKER_0:  At any rate, we human did a long exposition on that.
SPEAKER_0:  He then defended climate science. He said, we need more climate science. He says, I love this stuff. I love...
SPEAKER_0:  ocean buoys, there are now thousands of them in the oceans charting.
SPEAKER_0:  clear pictures of ocean circulation.
SPEAKER_0:  Satellites.
SPEAKER_0:  And he said something really important that made people discount, which is
SPEAKER_0:  We need sustained investment in monitoring this planet.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  we neglect our systems.
SPEAKER_0:  Just tell us what's happening in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's happened over and over again.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So if I had left it.
SPEAKER_0:  Define d-
SPEAKER_0:  gone into the terrain of the fight over CO2.
SPEAKER_0:  some
SPEAKER_0:  journalist friends might say, oh, that was good.
SPEAKER_0:  mashup, you know, matchup and.
SPEAKER_0:  but I found these really profound and important things.
SPEAKER_0:  that I wanted the world to know about.
SPEAKER_0:  in the context of whether Trump was going to have him as a science advisor.
SPEAKER_0:  And so if I hadn't gone there.
SPEAKER_0:  And a lot of people, if you look back.
SPEAKER_0:  I got hammered.
SPEAKER_0:  for doing that.
SPEAKER_0:  even from friends.
SPEAKER_0:  and.
SPEAKER_0:  Then later, John Holdren, who had been Obama's
SPEAKER_0:  science advisor for eight years.
SPEAKER_0:  He said.
SPEAKER_0:  I would rather have
SPEAKER_0:  Will Haper.
SPEAKER_0:  as Trump's science advisor than no science advisor. In other words, there's a landscape of things that are important.
SPEAKER_0:  He recognized that Happer is really smart about defense and all kinds of things too.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's like you do have to sort of screw up your.
SPEAKER_0:  Ideally, you screw up your courage, but then not necessarily get into the-
SPEAKER_0:  It's like with the guy in Oklahoma.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  If you go in looking for the differences, you'll find them.
SPEAKER_0:  with us.
SPEAKER_0:  paralyzed sense of.
SPEAKER_0:  nothing having happened that was useful. Or you can find these nuggets, everyone is a human being.
SPEAKER_0:  I can't play the mind game of what I would have said as to Hitler.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  I play that mind game all the time, but that's that's for another conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  and my family.
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhhh
SPEAKER_1:  that have suffered under him.
SPEAKER_1:  Nevertheless, he is a human being.
SPEAKER_1:  And people sometimes caricature.
SPEAKER_1:  Hitler is saying like that's when you mention Hitler is a conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  All right, you've had a certain point, but.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't agree. I think sort of these extremes are useful thought experiments to understand because you're not willing to take your ideals to that extreme.
SPEAKER_1:  Then...
SPEAKER_1:  then maybe your ideals need some rethinking.
SPEAKER_1:  and from a journalist's perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  A number of years ago, my wife and I were with our veterinarian who was German born.
SPEAKER_0:  Dr. Bach.
SPEAKER_0:  PSH.
SPEAKER_0:  We were talking about the dog and stuff, and then we were talking about Trump and-
SPEAKER_0:  And he just mentioned in passing, he said, my mother voted for Hitler.
SPEAKER_0:  That hit me like a brick. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Cause it was so.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  This-
SPEAKER_0:  at the very least understanding how.
SPEAKER_0:  Pathways lead to...
SPEAKER_0:  people doing things like he did in order.
SPEAKER_0:  is essential and the only way to understand that is to.
SPEAKER_0:  dig in and ask questions.
SPEAKER_0:  yet uncomfortable.
SPEAKER_0:  That still makes my hair prickle when I think back to him saying.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, my mom voted for Hitler.
SPEAKER_1:  That somehow makes it super real. Like, oh, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, there's elections, there's...
SPEAKER_1:  real people living their lives.
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly, struggling with a broken economy.
SPEAKER_0:  All kinds of stuff. I hope it will help online.
SPEAKER_1:  littles.
SPEAKER_1:  personal resentments and all that kind of stuff. Let me ask you about presidents, American presidents.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, what?
SPEAKER_1:  Who had a positive or negative impact on climate change efforts?
SPEAKER_1:  in your view, Clinton, Bush, Obama, Trump, Biden.
SPEAKER_1:  Or maybe you could say that they don't have much of an impact. So like they...
SPEAKER_1:  in public discourse.
SPEAKER_1:  presidents have a kind of
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe.
SPEAKER_1:  Disproportional like we imagine they have a huge amount of impact. How much impact do they actually have?
SPEAKER_1:  on climate policy.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if you have comments on this.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a background decarbonization rate that's happened for 150 years.
SPEAKER_0:  We moved from wood to...
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  charcoal too.
SPEAKER_0:  coal to oil and
SPEAKER_0:  gas is cleaner, it's more hydrogen, less carbon.
SPEAKER_0:  I asked recently, I asked-
SPEAKER_0:  some really smart scientists who study these long trajectories of energy.
SPEAKER_0:  When you look at those curves, is there anything in that curve that says, oh,
SPEAKER_0:  Climate Treaty, 1992. World diameter within the next decades ofrge
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Oh, Paris.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It's really hard. Or China, I mean when China came in.
SPEAKER_0:  with his huge growth in emissions that created a.
SPEAKER_0:  bit of a recarbonization.
SPEAKER_0:  blip, but that was this huge growth in their economy that pulled a bunch of people out out group.
SPEAKER_0:  out of poverty.
SPEAKER_0:  So yeah, no, precedents don't really change anything on time scales that we would measure.
SPEAKER_0:  as meaning where you could parse it out.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's not to say that.
SPEAKER_0:  Obama's and the current focus on.
SPEAKER_0:  on the stimulus that's happening.
SPEAKER_0:  which includes a lot more money for research, et cetera, and innovation.
SPEAKER_0:  I do think that will be beneficial in a very, very long run.
SPEAKER_0:  But I have to say...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, when Obama stood up and...
SPEAKER_0:  made credit, took credit for reductions from moving from coal to gas.
SPEAKER_0:  Because of fracking?
SPEAKER_0:  That was actually chainy.
SPEAKER_1:  Who set that in motion? I was thinking, I would say Bush.
SPEAKER_1:  Not because I like him or anything, but he's the guy who inadvertently.
SPEAKER_1:  Start it fracking.
SPEAKER_0:  It goes further back than that. It was a federal investment in fracking in the 60s and 70s, and then this one guy in Texas right here in Texas.
SPEAKER_0:  George Mitchell who
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  to get the technology.
SPEAKER_0:  And that led to this.
SPEAKER_0:  Real dramatic.
SPEAKER_0:  change from gas to coal.
SPEAKER_0:  that mostly played out in the Obama years, but that really was stimulated by Cheney's early.
SPEAKER_0:  Energy Task Force 2001.
SPEAKER_0:  when they were getting in office.
SPEAKER_0:  And also Bush did something interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  in the whole wonky climate.
SPEAKER_0:  3D.
SPEAKER_0:  process.
SPEAKER_0:  It was under Bush that they started to focus on sectors.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's do a, they did a, oh, and also on big emitters. This isn't about 200 countries.
SPEAKER_0:  It's about basically eight or 10 countries.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's get them into a room and let's.
SPEAKER_0:  have these little sub rooms on.
SPEAKER_0:  like electrification on mining on whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  and by parsing it out.
SPEAKER_0:  And Obama picked up the same model. They had different names for it because presidents always name something different than the last president.
SPEAKER_0:  One was the major economies forum and then it was the.
SPEAKER_0:  Major emitters, something or other.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's
SPEAKER_0:  getting away from the treaty dots and dashes toward just sectoral.
SPEAKER_0:  big sectors that matter, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  gas electrification.
SPEAKER_0:  makes a difference. But again, you couldn't ever measure enough.
SPEAKER_0:  It's always the lag time.
SPEAKER_1:  And also, I think...
SPEAKER_1:  One very under.
SPEAKER_1:  Report it.
SPEAKER_1:  fact, so the UNEP, the environment program.
SPEAKER_1:  They come out with what they call a gap report every year where they estimate how much is the world doing compared to what should it or has it promised to do. Emissions gap..
SPEAKER_1:  And in 2019, so just before COVID hit.
SPEAKER_1:  They actually did a survey of the 2010s.
SPEAKER_1:  So the last big sort of report on how well are we doing.
SPEAKER_1:  and their takeaway quote, and I'm not gonna get this right, but it's pretty much what they said was.
SPEAKER_1:  If you take the world...
SPEAKER_1:  as if we hadn't cared about climate change.
SPEAKER_1:  since 2005.
SPEAKER_1:  we can't tell the difference between.
SPEAKER_1:  That world.
SPEAKER_1:  and the world that we're actually living in.
SPEAKER_1:  So despite the fact that we've had 10 years of immense focus on climate and everybody talks about it and the Paris agreement, which is perhaps the biggest global sort of agreement and what we're going to be doing.
SPEAKER_1:  You can't actually tell.
SPEAKER_1:  That, I think, is incredibly important because what it tells you is...
SPEAKER_1:  All that we're doing is not even on the margin, it's sort of smaller than that, and I'm not sure what that is. But yeah, we're basically dealing in, you know, so for instance, the UK loves to point out that they have dramatically reduced their carbon emissions, and they have. They've really dramatically lowered their emissions.
SPEAKER_1:  Mostly because they've deindustrialized.
SPEAKER_1:  They basically said, look, we're just going to be bankers for all of you guys. And then everybody else is going to produce our stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  Which of course is great for Britain, or I don't know if it's great for Britain, but...
SPEAKER_1:  We can't all do that.
SPEAKER_1:  And so most of what we're trying to do right now is sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  this virtue signaling, it makes us feel good. It's sort of, yeah, on the margin or in the very tiny margin. But you know, what we basically, that was Andy, your point with China.
SPEAKER_1:  The reason why we can't tell the difference of course is because China basically became the workshop for everyone.
SPEAKER_1:  And so not only did they lift more than half a billion people out of poverty,
SPEAKER_1:  BUT
SPEAKER_1:  They also.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, basically took over most production in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  And so of course, you know, many rich countries could decarbonize or at least reduce their carbon emissions and feel very virtuous about it.
SPEAKER_1:  But fundamentally, we haven't solved how does the world do this.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's why I think we're also left with this sense of not only are we being told this is a
SPEAKER_1:  unmitigated catastrophe, and that's why this is the only thing we should be focusing on, but also somehow, and we can all fix it. I don't think we have any sense of how hard this is actually going to be. That's of course why I would go back and say, look, the only way you're going to fix this is through innovation, because if you have something that's cheaper than fossil fuels, you fixed it. You have something that's harder and-
SPEAKER_1:  you know, costlier and more inconvenient.
SPEAKER_1:  No, you're just not gonna...
SPEAKER_1:  Make it.
SPEAKER_0:  and getting more.
SPEAKER_0:  time.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  cutting vulnerability. Yes. Vulnerability on the planet.
SPEAKER_0:  are huge and they're identifiable and you know what to do.
SPEAKER_0:  What are the biggest
SPEAKER_1:  pockets of vulnerability. Well,
SPEAKER_0:  Infrastructure of cities? No, it's where people are living and what their capacities are.
SPEAKER_0:  So moving people, how do you...
SPEAKER_1:  How do you decrease the vulnerability in the world?
SPEAKER_0:  of the big affordable housing. One reason so many people moved out of San Francisco and
SPEAKER_0:  adjacent cities into the countryside and then had their houses burned down.
SPEAKER_0:  It's because they can't afford to live in the city anymore.
SPEAKER_0:  So affordable housing in cities can limit exposure to, in that case, wildfire.
SPEAKER_0:  Durban, South Africa that.
SPEAKER_0:  terrible devastating flood they had this year, this year.
SPEAKER_0:  who was washed away, poor people who don't have any place to live, so they settle in a floodplain.
SPEAKER_0:  along the stream bed that's...
SPEAKER_0:  livable when it's not raining buckets and.
SPEAKER_0:  Those are vulnerabilities that are there because of...
SPEAKER_0:  dislocation, housing.
SPEAKER_0:  Tacloban, this typhoon that hit the Philippines terribly.
SPEAKER_0:  ahead of the Paris talks or was it the...
SPEAKER_1:  No, it was in 2013, I believe.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, yeah, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Thousands died.
SPEAKER_0:  Most of the stories that were written were framed around climate change because the Pope made a deal about it. It was just before the climate talks of that year.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  What happened, partially why there were so many losses was...
SPEAKER_0:  Takleban city had quadrupled in population in the last 30 years, and most of the people coming into the city were poor, looking for work and settling in.
SPEAKER_0:  marginal places where a surge, storm surge killed them.
SPEAKER_0:  So those are things we.
SPEAKER_0:  we, whatever the we is in the different places.
SPEAKER_0:  really can work on and that gives more flex for sure and thinking about how...
SPEAKER_0:  this long trajectory that seems so immovable and so hard, the decarbonization part.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no excuse. I wrote a piece.
SPEAKER_0:  not long, I guess a year ago.
SPEAKER_0:  I said there's a vulnerability emergency hiding behind this.
SPEAKER_0:  this climate emergency label.
SPEAKER_0:  That's
SPEAKER_0:  really what needs work.
SPEAKER_1:  And also on the taklaban, I mean the...
SPEAKER_1:  the hurricane that hit in 2013, there was almost a similar hurricane in the early part of 1900s.
SPEAKER_1:  that hit
SPEAKER_1:  Pretty much the same strength.
SPEAKER_1:  And it eradicated half the city. It killed half the city.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, and so what's happened since then is
SPEAKER_1:  People just got much, much richer. You know, from early 1900 to 2013.
SPEAKER_1:  We've just moved a lot of people out of poverty. Now it's a lot bigger. Well, Bangladesh.
SPEAKER_0:  And yeah. Bangladesh is even a bigger example of that. And in the 1970s, they had horrible cyclones, one of which was the Beatles, George Harrison's concert for Bangladesh.
SPEAKER_0:  Great album.
SPEAKER_0:  that I still have somewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  He did a fundraising concert for Bangladesh after this terrible cyclone tragedy.
SPEAKER_0:  hit Bangladesh and I think there were several hundred thousand who were killed.
SPEAKER_0:  and a couple like that around that time.
SPEAKER_0:  Bangladesh has been hit by comparable storms recently.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's terrible. Every death is terrible, but it's like 123 deaths.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's not just because of wealth, it's because people.
SPEAKER_0:  know what to do because there are cell phones.
SPEAKER_0:  because they have elevated platforms in many communities.
SPEAKER_0:  and the floodplains there that you know to get to.
SPEAKER_0:  So they went from hundreds of thousands of deaths.
SPEAKER_0:  in a cyclone to 123.
SPEAKER_1:  When we were working with Bangladesh.
SPEAKER_1:  It's no longer the problem of people dying.
SPEAKER_1:  It's the fact that their cattle die. So they want it. They want it.
SPEAKER_1:  cattle places where you could herd your calf. This, this is their capital and it's not to make fun of it, but you know, it's an amazing progress that you've stopped worrying about your, you know, your parents dying and you worry about your cows dying.
SPEAKER_0:  And when I was talking about social innovation.
SPEAKER_0:  The other hour.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a model emerging in Bangladesh for farmers to move from raising chickens, poultry, to ducks.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's working.
SPEAKER_0:  and ducks actually fetch a higher price at the market.
SPEAKER_0:  And guess what? When you get flooded, you survive. You can still have your income and your future.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask you...
SPEAKER_1:  to give advice.
SPEAKER_1:  Put on your sage.
SPEAKER_1:  wise hat and give advice to young people that are looking into this.
SPEAKER_1:  into this world and see how they can do the most good we talked about.
SPEAKER_1:  What is the one dollar that can do the most positive?
SPEAKER_1:  Improvement
SPEAKER_1:  to lead to $40, $45 and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  What advice would you give to young people in high school and college?
SPEAKER_1:  how to have.
SPEAKER_1:  positive impact on the world. How to have a career they can be proud of.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe ask Bjorn first and how to have a life.
SPEAKER_1:  to be, they can be proud of.
SPEAKER_1:  So I think, and this really.
SPEAKER_1:  pretty well reflects the whole conversation we've had. We've got to sort of take the catastrophism out of the climate conversation. And this really matters because a lot of kids literally think...
SPEAKER_1:  the world is going to end pretty soon. That obviously makes any other kind of plan.
SPEAKER_1:  meaningless.
SPEAKER_1:  So first of all,
SPEAKER_1:  You're not going to die.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, you know, that, that poster that people, that a lot of kids have.
SPEAKER_1:  you're gonna die from old age, but I'm gonna die from climate. No, you're not. You're gonna die from old age and you're gonna die much older, very likely. So the reality is.
SPEAKER_1:  The world has improved dramatically and it's very likely to improve even more.
SPEAKER_1:  Bassline is good.
SPEAKER_1:  This is just, you know, the facts.
SPEAKER_1:  then there's still lots and lots of problems. And what you should do as a young person is stop being.
SPEAKER_1:  paralyzed by fear?
SPEAKER_1:  and then realize what you can do is basically help.
SPEAKER_1:  humanity become even smarter.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot of different places you can do. I mean, the obvious thing when you're talking about climate is-
SPEAKER_1:  What if you could become the guy that develops fourth generation nuclear? It's very likely something that-
SPEAKER_1:  neither of us know anything about right now, but develop the energy source that will basically power the rest of humanity, how cool would that be?
SPEAKER_1:  That's one of the many things you could do. But again, also remember there are lots and lots of other things that need solutions. So-
SPEAKER_1:  What about you become the girl that makes the social innovation in Tanzania or in Kenya?
SPEAKER_1:  Or what about if you become the person who finds a way that is a much cheaper, more effective way to tackle tuberculosis right now? It needs four to six months of medication. One of the big problems is once you pop the pills and you're fresh, it's really hard to get people to do it for the other five and a half months, right? And you need that, otherwise you actually have a big risk of getting multi-drug resistant tuberculosis, which is a real scourge on the earth. So, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  What if you-
SPEAKER_1:  Develop that.
SPEAKER_1:  So the truth is...
SPEAKER_1:  Not only can your life be much better when you sort of-
SPEAKER_1:  ditch that, uh, that doomerism.
SPEAKER_1:  but it also becomes much more possible for you to be a positive part.
SPEAKER_1:  of making sure that you do that progress. Why has the world improved so much?
SPEAKER_1:  because our parents and great grandparents.
SPEAKER_1:  They made all this work. This was all their innovations.
SPEAKER_1:  and a lot of hard work.
SPEAKER_1:  and I'm incredibly grateful that they've done it.
SPEAKER_1:  now it's kind of time to pay back. So you got to do this for our grandkids.
SPEAKER_1:  You've got to make those innovations, make those policy opportunities. They'll make the world an even better place.
SPEAKER_0:  Totally. And to me.
SPEAKER_0:  There's never been a
SPEAKER_0:  Better time.
SPEAKER_0:  be effective.
SPEAKER_0:  as a young person, because the internet.
SPEAKER_0:  connectedness. Neverchcover
SPEAKER_0:  brainstorm with someone in another country just as easily as you can brainstorm with someone down the block when we were kids.
SPEAKER_0:  As I said earlier with my
SPEAKER_0:  My pen pal was letters taking weeks to come.
SPEAKER_0:  And um.
SPEAKER_0:  So the key properties.
SPEAKER_0:  Ideally, that young people.
SPEAKER_0:  would do well to cultivate our...
SPEAKER_0:  Well, certainly adaptability.
SPEAKER_0:  because.
SPEAKER_0:  change is changing.
SPEAKER_0:  Not just, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  The rate of change is changing. These layers of change are all piling up on each other.
SPEAKER_0:  having an ability to understand.
SPEAKER_0:  the information environment.
SPEAKER_0:  is a fundamental need now that wasn't a need when we were growing up.
SPEAKER_0:  We read a few newspapers. My dad would turn on the nightly news.
SPEAKER_0:  And Walter Cronkite would say that's the way it is.
SPEAKER_0:  So I said, that's the way it is.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  That's so not the way the media environment is now.
SPEAKER_0:  So courses in media literacy should be kind of fundamental.
SPEAKER_0:  parts of curricula from like kindergarten on, or parents can do the same thing.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a woman at URI, University of Rhode Island, Renee Hobbs, who teaches a course in propaganda literacy.
SPEAKER_0:  And she said, you know, the history of the word is-
SPEAKER_0:  Not bad, propaganda could be good. It's pro, it's for the-
SPEAKER_0:  for the church.
SPEAKER_0:  She did a wonderful chat with me.
SPEAKER_0:  She laid this out and.
SPEAKER_0:  But understanding...
SPEAKER_0:  when it is propaganda, like the tobacco, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  There is hopefully a difference between that and...
SPEAKER_0:  and that, right, cigarette ads and...
SPEAKER_0:  journalistically acquired.
SPEAKER_0:  information.
SPEAKER_0:  So, Kira, everything Bjorn was talking about too is just understanding how to not be.
SPEAKER_0:  sucked into this information environment and spit out as a paralyzed.
SPEAKER_0:  Dumest Entity.
SPEAKER_0:  Because once you have an ability to step back,
SPEAKER_0:  Then you can use Twitter or whatever you're on.
SPEAKER_0:  to find people who might have a skill set you don't have that.
SPEAKER_0:  is something you need to do.
SPEAKER_0:  to
SPEAKER_0:  incorporate to harness.
SPEAKER_0:  to do the thing you want to do in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  finding your way to make the world better.
SPEAKER_0:  and it can have nothing to do with climate.
SPEAKER_0:  But if it makes.
SPEAKER_0:  few more people's lives better, then overall you're leading toward better capacity for all this stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  So that, and then the climate problem, the prismatic.
SPEAKER_0:  giant nature of it.
SPEAKER_0:  is.
SPEAKER_0:  What they said.
SPEAKER_0:  So daunting, but it's also what gives everybody an opportunity.
SPEAKER_0:  Like there's something for artists, scientists.
SPEAKER_0:  Poets, everybody.
SPEAKER_0:  needs to get into the game.
SPEAKER_0:  I just.
SPEAKER_0:  spent some time with Kim Stanley Robinson who wrote that book Ministry of the Future, which is this sprawling novel that
SPEAKER_0:  a worst case outcome where everyone in India is dying.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  So fiction can help.
SPEAKER_0:  experiment, different kinds of fiction, different kinds of arts can help us sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  experiment with what the future might look like different ways.
SPEAKER_0:  Just get started. And the other thing, unfortunately, that's needed.
SPEAKER_0:  I think I first said this in 2008 when someone asked me something about climate. I said
SPEAKER_0:  Weirdly, you have to sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  Have a sense of urgency, but a sense of patience at the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  Like just roll those words around in your mind. Like what does that mean?
SPEAKER_0:  urgent and patient. How could that possibly be?
SPEAKER_0:  but actually it really is the reality.
SPEAKER_0:  There is an urgency with this building gas that's cumulative, it doesn't go away like smoke when it rains.
SPEAKER_0:  And every year that happens, it's.
SPEAKER_0:  adding to risco.
SPEAKER_0:  and you can kind of wake up completely freaked out urgent.
SPEAKER_0:  But when you realize energy transitions take time, then you have to sort of find patience or whatever your word is for that.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I think you have to oscillate back and forth throughout the day.
SPEAKER_1:  having a sense of urgency when you're trying to...
SPEAKER_1:  actually be productive and have patience.
SPEAKER_1:  so you can have a calm head about you in terms of putting everything into perspective. Yeah and like you said with information.
SPEAKER_1:  That is interesting, especially in the scientific community. I think you've spoken about this before.
SPEAKER_1:  you know that there is some responsibility or at least an opportunity for scientists.
SPEAKER_1:  not just through science, but to understand the dynamics of
SPEAKER_1:  the different mediums in which information is exchanged. So it could be Twitter.
SPEAKER_1:  for a few years, then it could be TikTok.
SPEAKER_1:  that it could be.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I'm a huge believer in the power of YouTube.
SPEAKER_1:  over the next.
SPEAKER_1:  several years, perhaps decades. I mean, it's a very interesting medium for education.
SPEAKER_1:  and communication for.
SPEAKER_1:  debate and
SPEAKER_1:  That's grassroots, that's from like the bottom up.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, that every scientist is able to.
SPEAKER_1:  communicate their work and I personally believe have the responsibility to communicate their work
SPEAKER_1:  If anything, the internet made me realize.
SPEAKER_1:  that science is not just about.
SPEAKER_1:  doing the science, it's about communicating it.
SPEAKER_1:  Like that.
SPEAKER_1:  This is not some kind of virtue signaling on my part.
SPEAKER_1:  No, no, no. Like I feel like.
SPEAKER_1:  If the tree falls in the forest and nobody's around to hear it.
SPEAKER_1:  It really didn't fall.
SPEAKER_1:  Like that's not...
SPEAKER_1:  There should be a culture of.
SPEAKER_1:  We have an MIT.
SPEAKER_1:  is a place called the Media Lab.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, sir.
SPEAKER_1:  where they really emphasize.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you always be able to demo something to show off your work. They really emphasize showing off their work
SPEAKER_1:  And I think that was.
SPEAKER_1:  in some part criticized in the big MIT culture that.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, that's.
SPEAKER_1:  That's like being focusing too much on the PR versus doing the science.
SPEAKER_1:  but I really disagree with that. Of course there's a balance to strike.
SPEAKER_1:  You don't want to be all smoke and mirrors, but there really is a lot of value to communication.
SPEAKER_1:  and not just.
SPEAKER_1:  sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  some broad.
SPEAKER_1:  You almost don't want to teach a course on communication because by the time you teach the course, it's already too late. It's always being on top.
SPEAKER_1:  of.
SPEAKER_1:  how, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  What is the language? What is the culture and the etiquette? What is the technology of communication that is effective?
SPEAKER_1:  I actually had.
SPEAKER_1:  conversation about that in my university because I think, and this is perhaps especially true for social sciences, but I think it's probably true for everyone, just simply communicating what it is you've done in research makes it possible for you to sort of get an outsider's perspective and see, did I just go into an incredibly deep hole that just three other people really care about in the world?
SPEAKER_1:  Or is this actually something that matters to the world and being able to explain what it is that you've done?
SPEAKER_1:  to everyone else.
SPEAKER_1:  makes my sort of senses if you can't say it in a couple of minutes.
SPEAKER_1:  Probably. It's not necessarily true, but it's probably because it wasn't all that important.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a hashtag.
SPEAKER_0:  generated maybe seven years ago by a Caltech.
SPEAKER_0:  PhD candidate, woman.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was fantastic. The hashtag was I am a scientist because.
SPEAKER_0:  And she posted it with a picture of herself with her answer.
SPEAKER_0:  And that, when I talk to scientists, or basically anybody about communicating,
SPEAKER_0:  So start, don't start with I.
SPEAKER_0:  Emma, I'm a.
SPEAKER_0:  phytologist and I use a spectrophotometer to do X.
SPEAKER_0:  Start with.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm a scientist because...
SPEAKER_0:  The world is endlessly interesting and I just found these salamanders.
SPEAKER_0:  which are gonna vanish.
SPEAKER_0:  if we don't stop this fungus from coming to the United States. Utterly interesting. And then you're then you're got people hooked.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's the motivation part, because everyone grew up as a kid.
SPEAKER_0:  And a kid is basically like a scientist. Wow, what the hell is this? How does this work?
SPEAKER_0:  So you can connect with people that way.
SPEAKER_0:  But this other issue you approached is really important. And what I love about MIT particularly.
SPEAKER_0:  I spent a lot of time there over the decades.
SPEAKER_0:  not just talking to the hurricane guy.
SPEAKER_0:  Amy Smith, who's the development lab in the basement there somewhere. Most of them, it looks like.
SPEAKER_1:  it's the basement.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's sort of like your... It's part of the charm....things here. But it's a usability function as part of...
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of that goes on there. It's engineering and science.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It reminds me of 1997.
SPEAKER_0:  these two very different scientists, Dan Kamen at Berkeley and Michael Dove at Yale.
SPEAKER_0:  wrote a manifesto. It was, um...
SPEAKER_0:  the virtues of mundane science.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what they called it.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a prod to the scientific community to.
SPEAKER_0:  Actually, it's about useful utility.
SPEAKER_0:  because the whole arena is set up to advance your career through.
SPEAKER_0:  revealing new knowledge.
SPEAKER_0:  that will get you tenure someday.
SPEAKER_0:  actually doing useful science is disincentivized. Having a conversation, especially if it involves
SPEAKER_0:  more than one discipline.
SPEAKER_0:  Because as a young scientist...
SPEAKER_0:  There were some post-docs at Columbia who wrote this other manifesto paper saying...
SPEAKER_0:  Here are the things universities need to do.
SPEAKER_0:  to foster the collaborative capacity we need to have sustainable development.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was like four or five things that universities don't do.
SPEAKER_0:  give you time to become fluent in.
SPEAKER_0:  for a physicist to talk to an anthropologist.
SPEAKER_0:  and understand how anthropology works for sociology.
SPEAKER_0:  takes time and then building a relationship with a community that has a problem that you want to fix.
SPEAKER_0:  time.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you do these quick turnaround papers.
SPEAKER_0:  that get you toward your little.
SPEAKER_0:  micro career goal, but they're not actually.
SPEAKER_0:  getting you what you want in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Those are really hard problems going forward.
SPEAKER_0:  But starting with that idea of usability.
SPEAKER_0:  What can I do with my skill sets? There are a lot of great physicists I know are.
SPEAKER_0:  dug in on.
SPEAKER_0:  string theory and stuff. Someone has to dig in on that too, but I'd like to have them pull a little bit of their brain power weight.
SPEAKER_0:  to think about.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of the practical things beyond things about too.
SPEAKER_0:  the two of you.
SPEAKER_1:  have been.
SPEAKER_1:  thinking about some of the biggest questions.
SPEAKER_1:  which is.
SPEAKER_1:  life here on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  The history of life here, the future of life here on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  of Earth itself.
SPEAKER_1:  and how to...
SPEAKER_1:  allocate our resources to alleviate suffering in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  So let me ask the big question. What do you think is the why of it all?
SPEAKER_1:  What's the meaning of it?
SPEAKER_1:  the meaning of our life here on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  You waited till the last moment to ask us that question. Yes, in case there's...
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhhh...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, in case in case I can trick you into finding an answer.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, so I mean, again, I'm just going to take a stab in this because
SPEAKER_1:  I think in some ways it's...
SPEAKER_1:  It's the same thing that you were talking about before. It's not about getting everybody sort of in the same track.
SPEAKER_1:  and all agree on something?
SPEAKER_1:  but it's about getting a lot of people with very different.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, goals and targets and
SPEAKER_1:  ways of thinking about the world.
SPEAKER_1:  go in the same direction. So for me,
SPEAKER_1:  The goal of...
SPEAKER_1:  Life.
SPEAKER_1:  certainly my goal, but I think for most people.
SPEAKER_1:  is to make the world a better place.
SPEAKER_1:  It sounds incredibly pedestrian because it's become so overused, but that really and literally is the point.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, your point of your life is to, you know, when, when one of your friends is, is a sad to make sure that they sort of get out of that and, and find out why they're sad and maybe move them a little bit in the right direction. And, you know, and, and all the things that we've talked about, you know, stop people from dying from tuberculosis and live longer lives and fix climate change.
SPEAKER_1:  but fix it in such a way
SPEAKER_1:  that we actually use resources smartest because there are lots of problems. So let's make sure we deal with them adequately. This is very unsexy in some sense.
SPEAKER_1:  But I think it's also very basic and really what.
SPEAKER_1:  It matters.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you know, biologically.
SPEAKER_0:  Evolution.
SPEAKER_0:  has demanded that life is about.
SPEAKER_0:  finding sources of energy.
SPEAKER_0:  and perpetuating yourself, right? So that's the baseline.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  that's led us into a bit of a bollocks because
SPEAKER_0:  we have this easy energy that's come from the ground so far.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  but our brilliance.
SPEAKER_0:  has
SPEAKER_0:  given this larger awareness of.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything about the planet is transitory.
SPEAKER_0:  and.
SPEAKER_0:  So, well, how do you work with that?
SPEAKER_0:  productively is really an important question.
SPEAKER_0:  I could just sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  try to be as rich as possible and use as much energy as possible.
SPEAKER_0:  Have other people.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, Alex Epstein, I think, again, this is one of the constraints on my support for what he says is.
SPEAKER_0:  He's just talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  growth and
SPEAKER_0:  progress in that sense.
SPEAKER_0:  But there are.
SPEAKER_0:  consequences, and there are long-term trajectories here that have to be taken into account too.
SPEAKER_0:  So what do you wake up?
SPEAKER_0:  to do?
SPEAKER_0:  To me, it's finding your-
SPEAKER_0:  part of this.
SPEAKER_0:  And as Bjorn said.
SPEAKER_0:  finding a way to...
SPEAKER_0:  pursue and expand betterment.
SPEAKER_0:  when I taught, I was at Pace University.
SPEAKER_0:  for six years.
SPEAKER_0:  And one of the courses I launched there was called Blogging a Better Planet.
SPEAKER_0:  and it was for grad students mostly in communication. It wasn't an environment.
SPEAKER_0:  It wasn't like better planet, like save the climate.
SPEAKER_0:  But my task for the students was to blog about something they're passionate about.
SPEAKER_0:  First of all, because you can't do this just like you can't do your conversations.
SPEAKER_0:  if you don't wake up in the morning wanting to do what you're doing, right?
SPEAKER_0:  You're doing this.
SPEAKER_0:  I used to call myself a selfish blogger because I was learning every day. I still am.
SPEAKER_0:  I love this. My wife laughs.
SPEAKER_0:  she thinks I work too much.
SPEAKER_0:  But I'm always like asking those questions, like, sustain what? So my charge to the students was-
SPEAKER_0:  harness a passion, build a blog.
SPEAKER_0:  either alone or with others.
SPEAKER_0:  not just the world a little bit towards some better outcome.
SPEAKER_0:  And so there was a musician who did a thing on music, musicians who use their art for...
SPEAKER_0:  their work for.
SPEAKER_0:  making the world better.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of it was like music therapy, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  bands contributing money, whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  Another one did.
SPEAKER_0:  Her blog was on comfort- comfort food.
SPEAKER_0:  all around the world. And I thought it was my favorite. It was a video.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it should be viral actually.
SPEAKER_0:  It was like looking at the world, every different cultures.
SPEAKER_0:  She was in Queens. So every culture, every cuisine is there in Queens, 200 countries.
SPEAKER_0:  But she would go and talk to people's moms and have them cook the food of that country that's their common food.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I just love this because we all need to eat.
SPEAKER_0:  you're getting this expanded sense of what comfort is.
SPEAKER_0:  by thinking about what other cultures choose.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  That felt like a great course because it was not directive. It was just...
SPEAKER_0:  it gave them this potential to go forward. I'd love to think they've all gone on to become superstar.
SPEAKER_0:  Whatever is, I don't know. That's the giving, that's the letting go part.
SPEAKER_0:  Even if one did.
SPEAKER_0:  something special then that makes me feel job done.
SPEAKER_0:  And you know...
SPEAKER_0:  After I'd been writing about climate for 30 years.
SPEAKER_0:  2016ish.
SPEAKER_0:  Did a lot of writing about.
SPEAKER_0:  What did I learn? Unlearn and stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  and I had had a stroke in 2011.
SPEAKER_0:  which was interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the first time I really.
SPEAKER_0:  thought about my brain.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't think about your brain on a day-to-day basis.
SPEAKER_0:  But this is my brain telling me, you know, ding, ding, ding, ding, some weird shit's happening.
SPEAKER_0:  And when I was thinking about...
SPEAKER_0:  climate or confronting climate change, it felt like some of the things I learned about my own.
SPEAKER_0:  existence, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm gonna die.
SPEAKER_0:  but you don't really.
SPEAKER_0:  absorbs out of it.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that the first time you kind of?
SPEAKER_0:  That was like my first like, yeah, this is really the shit, you know, or at least deep disability, if not death.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  that ability is transitory.
SPEAKER_0:  And I thought about the climate problem. We're not gonna solve the global warming problem, at least not in our lifetimes.
SPEAKER_0:  but you work on making.
SPEAKER_0:  those trajectories.
SPEAKER_0:  sustainable, you know, the end of life particularly. You work on
SPEAKER_0:  making sure other people don't get strokes if they can avoid it. In my case.
SPEAKER_0:  I wrote about it, I was blogging about my stroke while I was having it.
SPEAKER_0:  I was tweeting about it. There's a funny tweet that's kind of mistyped.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  Co-F 650....
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, yeah, yeah. Right, right, right. So that's like share your knowledge, share your learning. And everyone can do this now, like on whatever platform.
SPEAKER_0:  And then, um...
SPEAKER_0:  There's also this like giving up part.
SPEAKER_0:  but not in a depressing well.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe you can call it depressing.
SPEAKER_0:  I started to zoom in.
SPEAKER_0:  years ago and the idea of the serenity prayer, the sobriety thing, you know, it's like
SPEAKER_0:  know what you can change, know what you can't.
SPEAKER_1:  Grant me the serenity to accept the things that cannot change, the courage to change the things that can.
SPEAKER_1:  and the wisdom to know the difference.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, see those three properties are really important right now.
SPEAKER_0:  Some aspects of this we know absolutely what we can work on.
SPEAKER_0:  cutting vulnerability.
SPEAKER_0:  Energy transitions take time.
SPEAKER_0:  Science can help.
SPEAKER_0:  us discriminate the difference.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's an iterative changing landscape.
SPEAKER_0:  going forward.
SPEAKER_0:  But at the same time...
SPEAKER_0:  science.
SPEAKER_0:  Like I personally on climate modeling or.
SPEAKER_0:  like narrowing how hot it's gonna get.
SPEAKER_0:  more clarity on.
SPEAKER_0:  when an ice sheet is going to collapse.
SPEAKER_0:  I think those are what I call known unknowable. So being able to-
SPEAKER_0:  I've seen enough evidence.
SPEAKER_0:  That
SPEAKER_0:  Those are deeply complex problems We're not going to get there quickly.
SPEAKER_0:  So then that gives you a landscape to act on.
SPEAKER_0:  And that.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, whether you bring God into the mix is irrelevant. It's really.
SPEAKER_0:  Know what you can change, know what you can't.
SPEAKER_0:  and know what that gives you the quality to work on.
SPEAKER_0:  them and serenity is
SPEAKER_0:  Comfort with...
SPEAKER_0:  that this is transitory.
SPEAKER_0:  The Human Journey.
SPEAKER_0:  like anyone's individual journey.
SPEAKER_0:  will have some end.
SPEAKER_0:  doesn't mean it has to be near. This Anthropocene that I've been writing about for decades is...
SPEAKER_0:  can still be a good.
SPEAKER_0:  Anthropocene.
SPEAKER_0:  or at least a less bad one in terms of how we get through it.
SPEAKER_0:  and you're also.
SPEAKER_1:  musician so in context when
SPEAKER_1:  One of my favorite songs of yours and album.
SPEAKER_1:  A very fine line.
SPEAKER_1:  I should mention that with the stroke.
SPEAKER_1:  Coming close to death.
SPEAKER_1:  The lyrics here are quite brilliant, I have to say.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh well.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a very fine line between winning and losing.
SPEAKER_1:  A very fine line between living and dying. A very fine line. By the way, people should listen to this. I can't play this because YouTube will give me trouble.
SPEAKER_1:  A very fine line between loving and leaving.
SPEAKER_1:  Most of your life you spend walking a very fine line and the rest of the lyrics are just quite brilliant.
SPEAKER_1:  It is a fine line.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm glad you walked it with me today, gentlemen. You're brilliant.
SPEAKER_1:  kind, beautiful human beings. Thank you so much.
SPEAKER_1:  for having this quote unquote debate that was much more about just exploring ideas together.
SPEAKER_1:  Bjorn, thank you so much.
SPEAKER_1:  and uh... andy thank you so much for talking to them
SPEAKER_0:  You know, these kinds of...
SPEAKER_0:  Extended conversations, the more of it, the better.
SPEAKER_0:  and finding ways to.
SPEAKER_0:  Spread that.
SPEAKER_0:  capacity.
SPEAKER_0:  just to get people out of this win-lose thing is really important. So thanks for what you're doing. No.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with Bjorn Lomborg and Andrew Refkin.
SPEAKER_1:  To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now, let me leave you with some words.
SPEAKER_1:  from Henry David Thoreau.
SPEAKER_1:  Heaven is under our feet.
SPEAKER_1:  as well as over our heads.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for listening and hope to see you.
SPEAKER_1:  time.