SPEAKER_1:  Can you imagine possible features?
SPEAKER_1:  that Python 4.0 might have.
SPEAKER_1:  that would.
SPEAKER_1:  necessitate the creation.
SPEAKER_1:  of the new 4.0.
SPEAKER_1:  given the amount of
SPEAKER_1:  Pain and Joy.
SPEAKER_1:  suffering and triumph that was involved in the move between.
SPEAKER_1:  Version 2 and version 3.
SPEAKER_1:  Following is a conversation with Guido Van Rossum.
SPEAKER_1:  his second time on this podcast.
SPEAKER_1:  He is the creator.
SPEAKER_1:  the Python programming language.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's Python's.
SPEAKER_1:  and Merida's BDFO.
SPEAKER_1:  benevolent dictator for life.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the Lex Friedman podcast to support it.
SPEAKER_1:  Please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now...
SPEAKER_1:  difference.
SPEAKER_1:  Que es guido, buen raso.
SPEAKER_1:  Python 3.11 is coming out very soon.
SPEAKER_1:  In it, see Python.
SPEAKER_1:  claimed to be 10 to 60% faster.
SPEAKER_1:  How'd you pull that off?
SPEAKER_1:  And let's see Python.
SPEAKER_0:  CPython is the last Python implementation standing, also the first one that was ever created. The original Python implementation that I started over 30 years ago.
SPEAKER_1:  So what does it mean that Python, the programming language is implemented?
SPEAKER_1:  in another programming language called C.
SPEAKER_0:  What kind of audience do you have in mind here?
SPEAKER_0:  People who know programming?
SPEAKER_1:  No, there's somebody on a boat that's into fishing and I've never heard about programming.
SPEAKER_1:  but also some world-class programmers. You're gonna have to speak to both. Imagine a boat with two people.
SPEAKER_1:  One of them has not heard about programming is really into fishing.
SPEAKER_1:  And the other one is.
SPEAKER_1:  like an incredible Silicon Valley programmer that's programmed in everything.
SPEAKER_1:  C, C++, Python.
SPEAKER_1:  Rust, Java, it knows the entire history of programming languages, so you're going to have to speak.
SPEAKER_0:  I imagine that boat in the middle of the ocean. I'm going to please the guy who knows how to fish first. Yes, please.
SPEAKER_1:  It is.
SPEAKER_1:  He seems like the most useful in the middle of the ocean.
SPEAKER_0:  You gotta make him mad. I'm sure he has a cell phone, so he's probably very suspicious about what goes on in that cell phone, but he must have heard that inside a cell phone is a tiny computer.
SPEAKER_0:  And a programming language is computer code that tells the computer what to do.
SPEAKER_1:  very low level.
SPEAKER_1:  language.
SPEAKER_1:  It's zeros and ones and then there's assembly.
SPEAKER_1:  And then... OHHHH, YET
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, we don't talk about these really low levels because those just confuse people.
SPEAKER_0:  When we're talking about human language, we're not usually talking about vocal tracts and...
SPEAKER_0:  how you position your tongue. I was talking yesterday about how
SPEAKER_0:  when you have a Chinese person.
SPEAKER_0:  and they speak English. This is a bit of a…
SPEAKER_0:  Stereotype they often don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  They can't seem to make the difference well between an L and an R.
SPEAKER_0:  And I have a theory about that and I've never checked this with linguists.
SPEAKER_0:  that it probably has to do with the fact that in Chinese there is not really a difference.
SPEAKER_0:  And it could be that there are regional variations in.
SPEAKER_0:  how Chinese native Chinese speakers pronounce that one sound that's
SPEAKER_0:  Sounds to L to some-
SPEAKER_0:  like L to some of them.
SPEAKER_0:  to others.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's both the sounds you produce.
SPEAKER_1:  with your mouth throughout the history of your life.
SPEAKER_1:  and what you're used to listening to. I mean, every language has that. Russian has, the Slavic languages have sounds like the letters.
SPEAKER_1:  S-s-s-sha-
SPEAKER_1:  like Americans or English speakers don't seem to know the sound.
SPEAKER_1:  Zzzz
SPEAKER_1:  This seemed uncomf-
SPEAKER_0:  That's
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So yes, OK, so we're not we're not going to.
SPEAKER_1:  the shapes of tongues.
SPEAKER_1:  and the sounds that the mouth can make.
SPEAKER_0:  And similarly we're not going into the ones and zeros or machine language.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say a programming language is a list of instructions like...
SPEAKER_0:  A cookbook recipe.
SPEAKER_0:  that sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  tells you how to do a certain thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Like make a sandwich, well...
SPEAKER_0:  Acquire a loaf of bread, cut it in slices.
SPEAKER_0:  Take two slices, put mustard on one.
SPEAKER_0:  Duh.
SPEAKER_0:  jelly on the other or something.
SPEAKER_0:  then add the meat, then add the cheese.
SPEAKER_0:  I've heard that science teachers can actually do great stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  with recipes like that and trying to interpret their students' instructions incorrectly.
SPEAKER_0:  until the students are completely unambiguous about it.
SPEAKER_1:  with language, see that's the difference between.
SPEAKER_1:  natural languages and programming languages.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  ambiguity as a feature, not a bug in human spoken languages.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  That's the dance of communication between humans.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, for lawyers, ambiguity certainly is a feature.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  for plenty of other cases, the ambiguity.
SPEAKER_0:  is not much of a feature, but we work around it, of course.
SPEAKER_0:  What's more important is context.
SPEAKER_1:  So with context, the precision of the statement.
SPEAKER_1:  becomes more and more concrete.
SPEAKER_1:  But, you know, when you say...
SPEAKER_1:  I love you to a person that...
SPEAKER_1:  matters a lot to you.
SPEAKER_1:  The person doesn't
SPEAKER_1:  to compile that statement and return an error saying
SPEAKER_1:  Please define love.
SPEAKER_0:  Right. But I imagine that my wife and my son...
SPEAKER_0:  interpret it very differently.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes. That's the same three words.
SPEAKER_1:  but imprecisely still.
SPEAKER_0:  Lawyers never have a lot of follow-up questions for you. Nevertheless, the context is already different in that case.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, fair enough. So that's...
SPEAKER_1:  That's a programming language.
SPEAKER_1:  is uh...
SPEAKER_1:  ability to unambiguously
SPEAKER_1:  state a recipe.
SPEAKER_1:  Actually, let's go back.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's go to Pepe.
SPEAKER_1:  You go through and pep ate the style guy for Python code.
SPEAKER_1:  some ideas of what this language should look like.
SPEAKER_1:  Feel like, read like.
SPEAKER_1:  And the big idea there is that code readability counts.
SPEAKER_1:  What does that mean to you?
SPEAKER_1:  and how to achieve it.
SPEAKER_1:  So this recipe should be.
SPEAKER_0:  Readable. That's a thing between programs.
SPEAKER_0:  Because on the one hand, we always explain the concept of programming language as...
SPEAKER_0:  computers
SPEAKER_0:  need instructions and computers are very dumb and they need very precise instructions because they don't have much context. In fact they have lots of context but their context is very different.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  what we've seen.
SPEAKER_0:  emerged during the development of software starting in the probably in the late 40s.
SPEAKER_0:  is that.
SPEAKER_0:  Software is a very social activity.
SPEAKER_0:  A software developer is not a mad scientist who sits alone in his lab writing brilliant code.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  software is developed by teams of people.
SPEAKER_0:  Even the mad scientist sitting alone in his lab can type fast enough to produce enough code.
SPEAKER_0:  so that by the time he's done with his coding, he still remembers what's going on.
SPEAKER_0:  the first few lines he wrote mean.
SPEAKER_0:  So even the mad scientist.
SPEAKER_0:  coding alone in his lab would be sort of wise to.
SPEAKER_0:  adopt conventions on how to.
SPEAKER_0:  format.
SPEAKER_0:  the instructions that he gives to the computer so that
SPEAKER_0:  The thing is...
SPEAKER_0:  There is a difference between a cookbook recipe and a computer program.
SPEAKER_0:  The cookbook recipe, the author of the cookbook.
SPEAKER_0:  Write it once.
SPEAKER_0:  and then it's printed in 100,000 copies.
SPEAKER_0:  And then lots of people in their kitchens try to recreate that recipe, that particular...
SPEAKER_0:  pie or dish.
SPEAKER_0:  from the recipe.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  DARE THE-
SPEAKER_0:  The goal of the cookbook author is to make it clear.
SPEAKER_0:  to the human.
SPEAKER_0:  reader of the recipe, the human.
SPEAKER_0:  Amateur.
SPEAKER_0:  chef in most cases.
SPEAKER_0:  when you're writing.
SPEAKER_0:  a computer program, you have two audiences at once.
SPEAKER_0:  It needs to.
SPEAKER_0:  Tell the computer what to do.
SPEAKER_0:  but.
SPEAKER_0:  It also is useful if that program is readable by other programmers.
SPEAKER_0:  because computer software, unlike the typical recipe for...
SPEAKER_0:  a cherry pie.
SPEAKER_0:  is so complex.
SPEAKER_0:  that you don't get all of it right at once.
SPEAKER_0:  you end up with the activity of debugging.
SPEAKER_0:  and you end up with the activity of. So debugging is.
SPEAKER_0:  trying to figure out why your code doesn't run the way you thought it should run.
SPEAKER_1:  That means broadly, it could be stupid little errors or it could be big.
SPEAKER_0:  logical errors, spiritual. It could be anything from a typo to a wrong choice of algorithm to
SPEAKER_0:  building something that does what
SPEAKER_0:  You tell it to do, but that's not useful.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems to work really well 99% of the time.
SPEAKER_1:  does weird things 1% of the time on some edge cases.
SPEAKER_1:  That's pretty much all software nowadays. All good software.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, yeah, for bad software.
SPEAKER_1:  That 99 goes down a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  So, but it's not just about the complexity of the program. It's like you said, it is a social endeavor.
SPEAKER_1:  in that.
SPEAKER_1:  You're constantly improving that recipe for the cherry.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  but you're sort of, you're in a group of people.
SPEAKER_0:  improving that recipe.
SPEAKER_0:  or the mad scientist.
SPEAKER_0:  is improving the recipe that he created a year ago.
SPEAKER_0:  and making it better.
SPEAKER_0:  or adding.
SPEAKER_0:  adding something he decides that he wants to.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, he wants some decoration on his pie or icing or...
SPEAKER_1:  So there's broad philosophical things in their specific advice on style.
SPEAKER_1:  So first of all, the thing that people first experience when they look up Python.
SPEAKER_1:  There is a, it is very readable.
SPEAKER_1:  but there's also like a spatial structure to it.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you explain the indentation style of Python and what is the
SPEAKER_1:  magic to it.
SPEAKER_0:  Spaces are important for readability of any kind of text.
SPEAKER_0:  if you take a cookbook recipe.
SPEAKER_0:  and you remove all the sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  all the bullets and other markup.
SPEAKER_0:  and you just crunch all the text together. Maybe you leave the spaces between the words, but that's all you leave.
SPEAKER_0:  when you're in the kitchen.
SPEAKER_0:  trying to figure out what are the ingredients and what are the steps.
SPEAKER_0:  And where does this step end and the next step begin?
SPEAKER_0:  You're going to have a hard time if it's just one solid block of text.
SPEAKER_0:  On the other hand, what a typical cookbook does if the paper is not too expensive.
SPEAKER_0:  Each recipe starts on its own page. Maybe there's a picture next to it.
SPEAKER_0:  The list of ingredients comes first.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... there's a standard notation
SPEAKER_0:  there's shortcuts so that you don't have to...
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  write two sentences on how you have to cut the onion because there are only three ways that people ever cut onions in the kitchen.
SPEAKER_0:  small, medium, and in slices.
SPEAKER_0:  or something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  Right. None of my examples make any sense to real cooks of-
SPEAKER_1:  We're talking to programmers with the metaphor of cooking. I love it.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, but there is a strictness to the spacing that Python defines.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's some.
SPEAKER_1:  looser things some stricter things but the four spaces for the
SPEAKER_1:  for the indentation is really interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  It's really, um,
SPEAKER_1:  It really defines what language you look some.
SPEAKER_0:  feels like.
SPEAKER_0:  because indentation sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  taking a block of text and then having inside that block of text.
SPEAKER_0:  A smaller block of text that is indented further.
SPEAKER_0:  a sort of a group. It's like.
SPEAKER_0:  You have a bulleted list.
SPEAKER_0:  in a complex business document and inside some of the bullets are other bulleted lists.
SPEAKER_0:  You will indent those too.
SPEAKER_0:  If each bulleted list is indented several inches,
SPEAKER_0:  then at two levels deep, there's no.
SPEAKER_0:  No space left on the page to put any of the words of the text.
SPEAKER_0:  So you can't indent too far. On the other hand, if you don't indent at all,
SPEAKER_0:  You can't tell whether something is a top level bullet or a second level bullet or a third level bullet. So you have to have.
SPEAKER_0:  Some compromise and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Based on
SPEAKER_0:  Ancient conventions.
SPEAKER_0:  and sort of the typical width of a computer screen in the 80s.
SPEAKER_0:  and all sorts of things sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  we came up with sort of forced basis as a compromise.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, there are groups.
SPEAKER_0:  There are large groups of people who code with two spaces.
SPEAKER_0:  indent level, for example the Google Style Guide.
SPEAKER_0:  All the Google Python code and I think also all the Google C++ code is indented with only two spaces.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're not used to that.
SPEAKER_0:  It's harder.
SPEAKER_0:  At a glance.
SPEAKER_0:  understand the code because the sort of the high level structure.
SPEAKER_0:  is determined by the indentation.
SPEAKER_0:  On the other hand, there are other programming languages where the indentation is eight spaces or a whole tap stop.
SPEAKER_0:  in sort of classic unix.
SPEAKER_0:  And to me that looks weird because you sort of after three indent levels you've
SPEAKER_0:  You've got no room left.
SPEAKER_1:  Well there are some languages where the indentation is a recommendation.
SPEAKER_1:  This is a stylistic one. The code compiles even without any indentation.
SPEAKER_1:  And then Python really indentation is a fundamental part of the language.
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't have to be four spaces, so you can...
SPEAKER_0:  code Python with two spaces per block or for or.
SPEAKER_0:  six paces or.
SPEAKER_0:  12 if you really want to go wild but
SPEAKER_0:  sort of everything.
SPEAKER_0:  that belongs to the same block needs to be indented the same way.
SPEAKER_0:  In practice, in most other languages, people recommend doing that anyway. If you look at...
SPEAKER_0:  C or Rust or C++.
SPEAKER_0:  all those languages.
SPEAKER_0:  Jaffa.
SPEAKER_0:  don't have a requirement of indentation.
SPEAKER_0:  but except in extreme cases.
SPEAKER_0:  they're just as anal about.
SPEAKER_0:  having their code properly indented.
SPEAKER_1:  So any IDE that
SPEAKER_1:  the syntax highlighting.
SPEAKER_1:  that works with Java or C++, they will yell at you.
SPEAKER_1:  aggressively if you don't do proper indentation.
SPEAKER_0:  they'd suggest the proper indentation for you.
SPEAKER_0:  Like.
SPEAKER_0:  In C, you type...
SPEAKER_0:  a few words and then you type a curly brace which is their notion of sort of begin an indented block.
SPEAKER_0:  Then you hit return and then it automatically indents four or eight spaces depending on your style preferences or how your editor is configured.
SPEAKER_1:  Was there a possible universe in which you considered having braces in Python?
SPEAKER_0:  Absolutely.
SPEAKER_1:  What was it 6040, 7030?
SPEAKER_1:  in your head.
SPEAKER_1:  What was the trade-off?
SPEAKER_0:  for a long time.
SPEAKER_0:  I was actually
SPEAKER_0:  convinced that the indentation was just
SPEAKER_0:  better.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  without context.
SPEAKER_0:  I would still claim that indentation is better.
SPEAKER_0:  Uhhh...
SPEAKER_0:  It reduces clutter.
SPEAKER_0:  However...
SPEAKER_0:  as I started to say earlier, context is almost everything.
SPEAKER_0:  and in the context of coding.
SPEAKER_0:  Most programmers are familiar with multiple languages, even if they're only good at one or two.
SPEAKER_0:  And apart from Python.
SPEAKER_0:  and maybe Fortron, I don't know how that's written these days anymore but...
SPEAKER_0:  All the other languages, Java, Rust, C, C++, JavaScript, TypeScript.
SPEAKER_0:  Pearl.
SPEAKER_0:  are all using curly braces.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, to-
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  indicate blocks.
SPEAKER_0:  And so Python is the odd one out.
SPEAKER_1:  with a radical idea.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you still?
SPEAKER_1:  as a radical renegade revolutionary, you still stand behind this idea of space, of uh...
SPEAKER_1:  indentation versus braces.
SPEAKER_1:  Like what can you dig into it a little bit more?
SPEAKER_1:  why you still stand behind indentation.
SPEAKER_0:  because context is not.
SPEAKER_0:  The whole story history...
SPEAKER_0:  in a sense provides more context.
SPEAKER_0:  for Python.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no chance.
SPEAKER_0:  that we can switch.
SPEAKER_0:  Python is using curly braces for something else, dictionaries mostly.
SPEAKER_0:  We would get in trouble if we wanted to switch.
SPEAKER_0:  just like you couldn't.
SPEAKER_0:  redefine C to use indentation.
SPEAKER_0:  even
SPEAKER_0:  if you agree that indentation sort of…
SPEAKER_0:  in a greenfield environment would be better.
SPEAKER_0:  You can't change-
SPEAKER_0:  that kind of thing in a language.
SPEAKER_0:  It's hard enough to reach agreement over much more minor details.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean in the past in Python we did have a big debate about teps versus spaces and four spaces versus fewer or more.
SPEAKER_0:  And we sort of came up with.
SPEAKER_0:  a recommended standard and sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  options for people who want to be different.
SPEAKER_0:  But yes.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess the thought experiment I'd like you to consider.
SPEAKER_1:  is if you could travel back.
SPEAKER_1:  through time.
SPEAKER_1:  when the compatibility is not an issue.
SPEAKER_1:  and you start a Python all over again.
SPEAKER_1:  can you make?
SPEAKER_1:  the case.
SPEAKER_1:  for a
SPEAKER_1:  indentations still.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it frees up a pair of matched brackets of which there are never enough in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  for other purposes.
SPEAKER_0:  really makes the language slightly.
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  easier to grasp.
SPEAKER_0:  for people who don't already know.
SPEAKER_0:  programming language.
SPEAKER_0:  Because the sort of-
SPEAKER_0:  One of the things, and I mostly got this from my mentors who were...
SPEAKER_0:  taught me programming language design in the earlier 80s.
SPEAKER_0:  when you're teaching programming.
SPEAKER_0:  for the total newbie who has not.
SPEAKER_0:  code it before, not in any other language.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  A whole bunch of concepts in programming are very alien.
SPEAKER_0:  or.
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  new and maybe very interesting but also distracting and confusing and there are many different things you have to learn you have to
SPEAKER_0:  Sative.
SPEAKER_0:  in a typical.
SPEAKER_0:  13 week programming course you have to
SPEAKER_0:  if it's like really.
SPEAKER_0:  learning to program from scratch.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to cover algorithms, you have to cover data structures, you have to cover
SPEAKER_0:  Syntax, you have to cover variables, loops.
SPEAKER_0:  functions.
SPEAKER_0:  recursion classes.
SPEAKER_0:  expressions operators.
SPEAKER_0:  There are so many concepts if you sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  if you can spend a little less time.
SPEAKER_0:  having to worry about the syntax.
SPEAKER_0:  The classic example was often
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, the compiler complains every time I put a semicolon in the wrong place or I forget to put a semicolon.
SPEAKER_0:  Python doesn't have semicolons in that sense.
SPEAKER_0:  so you can't forget them.
SPEAKER_0:  and you are also not.
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  misled into putting them where they don't belong because
SPEAKER_0:  you don't learn about them in the first place.
SPEAKER_1:  the flip side of that is.
SPEAKER_1:  forcing the strictness onto the beginning programmer.
SPEAKER_1:  to teach them that programming is a...
SPEAKER_1:  values attention to details. You don't get to just.
SPEAKER_1:  write the way you write in English.
SPEAKER_0:  many of other details that they have to pay attention to. I think they'll...
SPEAKER_0:  They'll still get the message about...
SPEAKER_0:  paying attention to detail.
SPEAKER_1:  The interesting design choice, so I still program quite a bit in PHP.
SPEAKER_1:  and I'm sure there's other languages like this, but the dollar sign before a variable.
SPEAKER_1:  That was.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, isn't it annoying?
SPEAKER_1:  thing for me.
SPEAKER_1:  I didn't quite...
SPEAKER_1:  fit into my understanding of why this is good for a programmer.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not sure if you ever thought about that one.
SPEAKER_1:  That is a
SPEAKER_0:  historical thing. There is a whole lineage of programming languages, PHP.
SPEAKER_0:  is one.
SPEAKER_0:  Pearl was one.
SPEAKER_0:  on the Unix Shell.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... is one of the oldest or or all the different shells
SPEAKER_0:  The dollar was invented for that purpose.
SPEAKER_0:  because the very earliest shells had a notion of scripting, but they did not have a notion of parameterizing the scripting.
SPEAKER_0:  And so a script is just a few lines of text.
SPEAKER_0:  where each line of text is a command.
SPEAKER_0:  That is.
SPEAKER_0:  read by a very primitive command processor that then...
SPEAKER_0:  sort of takes the first word on the line as the name of a program and passes all the rest.
SPEAKER_0:  of the
SPEAKER_0:  line as text into the program for the program to figure out what to do with.
SPEAKER_0:  as arguments.
SPEAKER_0:  And so by the time scripting was slightly more mature than the very first script
SPEAKER_0:  there was a convention that...
SPEAKER_0:  just like the first.
SPEAKER_0:  Word of the line is...
SPEAKER_0:  the name of the program.
SPEAKER_0:  The following words.
SPEAKER_0:  could be names of files.
SPEAKER_0:  input.text.
SPEAKER_0:  output.html.
SPEAKER_0:  things like that.
SPEAKER_0:  The next thing that happens is...
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, it would actually be really nice if we could have variables and especially parameters for scripts. Values are usually what starts this process.
SPEAKER_0:  But now you have a problem because you can't just...
SPEAKER_0:  Say the parameters are x, y, and z.
SPEAKER_0:  And so now we call.
SPEAKER_0:  Say, let's say X is the input file and Y is the output file. And let's forget about Z for now.
SPEAKER_0:  I have my program.
SPEAKER_0:  and I write program x, y. Well, that already has a meaning because that presumably means...
SPEAKER_0:  X.
SPEAKER_0:  itself is the file.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a file name. It's not a variable name.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, and so.
SPEAKER_0:  the inventors of things like the Unix shell and I'm sure job command language at IBM before that
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  had to use.
SPEAKER_0:  Something that made it clear to the script processor.
SPEAKER_0:  Here is an X that is not actually the name of a file, which you just pass through.
SPEAKER_0:  to the program you're running.
SPEAKER_0:  Here is an x that is the name of a variable.
SPEAKER_0:  And
SPEAKER_0:  when you're writing a script processor.
SPEAKER_0:  you try to keep it as simple as possible.
SPEAKER_0:  because certainly in the 50s and 60s.
SPEAKER_0:  Uhhh
SPEAKER_0:  The thing that interprets the script had to be a very small program because it had to fit in a very small part of memory.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  saying oh.
SPEAKER_0:  Just look at each character and if you see a dollar sign...
SPEAKER_0:  You jump to another section of the code and then you gobble up characters, say, until the next space or something.
SPEAKER_0:  and you say that's the variable name.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it was sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  invented as
SPEAKER_0:  a clever way to make parsing of things that contain both variable and fixed parts.
SPEAKER_0:  Very easy.
SPEAKER_0:  in a very simple script processor.
SPEAKER_0:  it also helps even then it also helps the human
SPEAKER_0:  author and the human reader of the
SPEAKER_0:  the script.
SPEAKER_0:  quickly see O.
SPEAKER_0:  20 lines down in the script I see a reference to xyz. Oh, it has a dollar in front of it, so now we know that xyz must be one of the parameters of the script.
SPEAKER_1:  But this is fascinating. Several things to say, which is...
SPEAKER_1:  the leftovers from the simple script processor languages.
SPEAKER_1:  are now on code bases like behind Facebook.
SPEAKER_1:  or behind most of the back end. I think PHP probably still runs almost at the back end of the internet.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yeah, I think there's a lot of it in Wikipedia too, for example.
SPEAKER_1:  It's funny that those decisions are not funny. It's fascinating that those decisions...
SPEAKER_1:  permeate through time.
SPEAKER_1:  just like biological.
SPEAKER_0:  systems, right?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, that sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  the inner workings of DNA.
SPEAKER_0:  Have been stable for well i don't know how long it was like three hundred.
SPEAKER_0:  million years, half a billion years.
SPEAKER_0:  And there are all sorts of weird quirks there.
SPEAKER_0:  that don't make a lot of sense if you were to design.
SPEAKER_0:  a system like self-replicating molecules.
SPEAKER_1:  from scratch.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, that system has a lot of interesting resilience.
SPEAKER_1:  as redundancy.
SPEAKER_1:  that results.
SPEAKER_1:  Like it messes up in interesting ways that still is resilient when you look at the system level of the organism code doesn't necessarily.
SPEAKER_1:  have that program, a computer programming code.
SPEAKER_0:  You'd be surprised.
SPEAKER_0:  how much resilience modern code has.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, if you look at the number of bugs per line of code.
SPEAKER_0:  Even in, in very well tested.
SPEAKER_0:  code that in practice works just fine.
SPEAKER_0:  There are actually lots of things that don't work fine.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  There are error correcting or self-correcting mechanisms at many levels.
SPEAKER_1:  including probably the U.
SPEAKER_0:  user of the code.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, in the end, the user who sort of is told, well, you've got to reboot your PC, is part of that system.
SPEAKER_0:  and a slightly...
SPEAKER_0:  last drastic thing is reload the page which we all
SPEAKER_0:  know how to do without thinking about it when...
SPEAKER_0:  something weird happens. You try to reload a few times before you say, oh, there's something really weird.
SPEAKER_1:  Or try to click the button again if the first time didn't work.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, yeah, we should all have learned not to do that, because that's probably just going to turn the light back off.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, true. So do it.
SPEAKER_1:  three times. That's the right lesson.
SPEAKER_1:  So, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  And I wonder how many people actually...
SPEAKER_1:  like the dollar sign.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you said, it is documentation.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  To me, it's...
SPEAKER_1:  whatever the opposite of syntactic sugar is syntactic poison.
SPEAKER_1:  to me.
SPEAKER_1:  It is such a pain in the ass that after typing a dollar sign, also super error prone.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's not self documenting, it's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a bug generating thing.
SPEAKER_1:  It is a kind of documentation that's the pro and the con is it's a source of a lot of bugs.
SPEAKER_1:  But actually I have to ask you, um...
SPEAKER_1:  This is a really interesting idea of bugs per line of code.
SPEAKER_1:  If you look at all the computer systems out there.
SPEAKER_1:  from the code that runs.
SPEAKER_1:  nuclear weapons.
SPEAKER_1:  the code that runs.
SPEAKER_1:  all the amazing companies that you've been involved with.
SPEAKER_1:  and not.
SPEAKER_1:  code that runs Twitter and Facebook and Dropbox and Google and
SPEAKER_1:  Microsoft Windows and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  and we like laid out.
SPEAKER_1:  Wouldn't that be a cool like table?
SPEAKER_1:  bugs per line of code.
SPEAKER_1:  What would the- let's put like actual companies aside.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think we'd be surprised by the number we see there for all these companies?
SPEAKER_0:  that depends on whether you've ever...
SPEAKER_0:  read about.
SPEAKER_0:  research that's been done in this area before.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, the last time I...
SPEAKER_0:  I saw some research like that that was probably in the 90s and the research might have been done in the 80s.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  The conclusion was...
SPEAKER_0:  across.
SPEAKER_0:  a wide range of different software.
SPEAKER_0:  different languages.
SPEAKER_0:  different companies
SPEAKER_0:  different development styles.
SPEAKER_0:  The number of bugs is always...
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's in the order of about one buck per thousand lines in Sertif.
SPEAKER_0:  mature software that is considered.
SPEAKER_0:  Interesting. As good as it gets.
SPEAKER_1:  Can I give you some facts here? There's a lot of papers.
SPEAKER_1:  So you said mature software, right?
SPEAKER_1:  So here's a.
SPEAKER_1:  a report from a, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  like programming analytics company.
SPEAKER_1:  Now this is from a developer perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me just say what it says because this is very weird and surprising.
SPEAKER_1:  On average, a developer creates 70 bugs per 1,000 lines of code.
SPEAKER_1:  15 bugs per 1000 lines of code find their way to the customers.
SPEAKER_1:  This is in software, they've...
SPEAKER_0:  No, I was wrong by an order.
SPEAKER_1:  Fixing a bug takes 30 times longer than writing a line of code.
SPEAKER_1:  That I can believe.
SPEAKER_1:  75% of a developer's time is spent on debugging.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, that's for an average developer that they analyze this 15 argue.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_1:  1500 hours a year.
SPEAKER_1:  in US alone.
SPEAKER_1:  $113 billion to spend annually on identifying and fixing bugs.
SPEAKER_0:  And I imagine this is marketing literature for someone who claims to have a golden bullet or silver bullet that...
SPEAKER_0:  makes all that investment in fixing bugs go away, but that is usually not going to... Yeah. It's not gonna happen.
SPEAKER_0:  Well there are...
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, they're referencing a lot of stuff, of course, but it is a page.
SPEAKER_1:  that is you know there's a contact us button at the bottom
SPEAKER_1:  Presumably if you just...
SPEAKER_1:  spend a little bit less than $100 billion, we're willing to solve the problem for you.
SPEAKER_1:  Right. And there's also a report on stock exchanges that overflow on the exact same topic. But when I open it up at the moment.
SPEAKER_1:  The page says, Stack Overflow is currently offline for me.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, that is ironic. Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... by the way they're air-paid
SPEAKER_1:  is awesome. Anyway.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, can you believe that number of bugs? Oh, absolutely.
SPEAKER_1:  Isn't that scary that 70 bucks per 1000 lines of code?
SPEAKER_1:  So even 10 bucks for a thousand lines of- Well-
SPEAKER_0:  That's about...
SPEAKER_0:  one bug after every 15 lines, and that's when you're first typing it in.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, from a developer, but...
SPEAKER_1:  but like.
SPEAKER_1:  how many bugs are gonna be found.
SPEAKER_0:  if you're typing it in. Well, the development process is extremely iterative.
SPEAKER_0:  Typically you don't make.
SPEAKER_0:  A plan for what software you're going to release a year from now.
SPEAKER_0:  and work out all the details because actually all the details themselves consist.
SPEAKER_0:  sort of compose a program.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's that.
SPEAKER_0:  being a program, all your plans will have bugs in them too.
SPEAKER_0:  and inaccuracies.
SPEAKER_0:  But what you actually do is...
SPEAKER_0:  you do a bunch of typing and I'm actually...
SPEAKER_0:  really, I'm a really bad typist.
SPEAKER_0:  That just.
SPEAKER_0:  I've never learned to type with ten fingers.
SPEAKER_0:  I need to use.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I use all ten of them, but not very well.
SPEAKER_0:  But I never took a typing class and I never sort of corrected that. So the first time I seriously learned...
SPEAKER_0:  I had to learn the layout of it.
SPEAKER_0:  of a QWERTY keyboard.
SPEAKER_0:  was actually in college in my first programming classes.
SPEAKER_0:  where we used punch cards.
SPEAKER_0:  And so...
SPEAKER_0:  with my two fingers, I sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  PECT OUT!
SPEAKER_0:  my code.
SPEAKER_0:  Watch anyone.
SPEAKER_0:  give you a little coding demonstration.
SPEAKER_0:  they'll have to produce like...
SPEAKER_0:  four lines of code.
SPEAKER_0:  and now see how many times they use the backspace key.
SPEAKER_0:  because they made a mistake and
SPEAKER_0:  And some people, especially when someone else is looking.
SPEAKER_0:  Will Backspace over 20, 30, 40 characters?
SPEAKER_0:  to fix a typo earlier in the line. If you're
SPEAKER_0:  If you're slightly more experienced, of course, you use your arrow buttons to go or your mouse to, but the mouse is usually slower than the arrows.
SPEAKER_0:  But a lot of people...
SPEAKER_0:  when they type.
SPEAKER_0:  A 20-character word, which is not unusual.
SPEAKER_0:  and they realized they made a mistake at the start of the word. They backspaced over the whole thing.
SPEAKER_0:  and then retype it. And sometimes it takes three, four times to get it right. So
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know what your definition of bug is.
SPEAKER_0:  Arguably.
SPEAKER_0:  mistyping a word and then correcting it immediately.
SPEAKER_0:  is not a bug on the other hand you
SPEAKER_0:  You already.
SPEAKER_0:  do sort of lose time.
SPEAKER_0:  And every once in a while, there's sort of a typo that you don't get.
SPEAKER_0:  in that process.
SPEAKER_0:  And now you've typed like 10 lines of code.
SPEAKER_0:  and somewhere in the middle of it you don't know where yet is a typo or
SPEAKER_0:  maybe a think-o where you forgot that.
SPEAKER_0:  you had to initialize a variable or something.
SPEAKER_1:  But those are two different things. And I would say, yes, you have to actually run the code.
SPEAKER_1:  to discover that typo.
SPEAKER_1:  but...
SPEAKER_1:  forgetting to initialize a variable is a fundamentally different
SPEAKER_1:  because that thing could go undiscovered.
SPEAKER_0:  that depends on the language in python it will not write in the sort of modern compilers are usually pretty good at
SPEAKER_0:  catching that even.
SPEAKER_0:  even for C.
SPEAKER_1:  for that specific thing, but actually deeper.
SPEAKER_1:  it might, there might be another variable.
SPEAKER_1:  that his initialized but logically speaking.
SPEAKER_1:  The one you meant related. Yup.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like name the same, but it's a different thing and you forgot to initialize.
SPEAKER_1:  whatever some counter or some
SPEAKER_1:  some basic variable there.
SPEAKER_0:  I can tell that you've coded.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  By the way, I should mention that I use a Kinesis keyboard.
SPEAKER_1:  which has the backspace under the thumb.
SPEAKER_1:  and one of the biggest reasons.
SPEAKER_1:  I use that keyboard.
SPEAKER_1:  is because you realize in order to use the backspace on a usual keyboard.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to stretch your pinky out.
SPEAKER_1:  Mm-hmm. I like
SPEAKER_1:  the foremost normal keyboards the back space is under the pinky
SPEAKER_1:  And so I don't know if people realize.
SPEAKER_1:  The pain.
SPEAKER_1:  they go through in their life.
SPEAKER_1:  because of the backspace key being so far away. So with the kinesis, it's right under the.
SPEAKER_1:  so you don't have to actually move your hands.
SPEAKER_0:  the backspace and the delete. What do you do if you're ever not with your own keyboard and you have to use someone else's PC keyboard that has a standard layout?
SPEAKER_1:  So first of all, it turns out.
SPEAKER_1:  that you can actually go your whole life.
SPEAKER_1:  always having a keyboard.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_0:  So this, well, except for that little tablet that you're using, so we're note taking right now, right? You're going.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's very inefficient note taking, but I'm not. I'm just looking stuff up.
SPEAKER_1:  But in most cases I would be actually using the keyboard here.
SPEAKER_1:  right now.
SPEAKER_1:  I just don't anticipate, you have to calculate how much.
SPEAKER_1:  typing do you anticipate? If I anticipate quite a bit then I'll just
SPEAKER_1:  I have a keyboard. extent, vote with me.
SPEAKER_1:  And same with the Hameen.
SPEAKER_1:  The embarrassing...
SPEAKER_1:  I've accepted being the weirder that I am.
SPEAKER_1:  What?
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  when I go on an airplane and I anticipate to do programming or a lot of typing.
SPEAKER_1:  I will have a laptop.
SPEAKER_1:  I will pull out a Kinesis keyboard.
SPEAKER_1:  in addition to the laptop.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's just who I am, you have to...
SPEAKER_1:  You have to accept who you are.
SPEAKER_1:  But also
SPEAKER_1:  It's a, you know, for a lot of people.
SPEAKER_1:  For me, certainly, there's a comfort space.
SPEAKER_1:  wait, there's a certain kind of setups that are maximized productivity.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  It's like some people have a warm.
SPEAKER_1:  blanket that they like.
SPEAKER_1:  when they watch a movie.
SPEAKER_1:  I like the Kinesis keyboard, it takes me to a...
SPEAKER_1:  a place of focus and I still mostly.
SPEAKER_1:  I am trying to make sure I use.
SPEAKER_1:  the state of the art ID's for everything but.
SPEAKER_1:  My comfort place, just like the Kinesis keyboard, is still E-Max.
SPEAKER_1:  So I still use it.
SPEAKER_1:  I still, I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  That's some of the debates I have with myself.
SPEAKER_1:  about everything from a technology perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  is how much to hold on to the tools you're comfortable with.
SPEAKER_1:  versus how much to invest.
SPEAKER_1:  and using modern tools.
SPEAKER_1:  and the signal that the communities provide you with.
SPEAKER_1:  Is the noisy one because a lot of people year to year get excited about new tools.
SPEAKER_1:  and you have to make a prediction.
SPEAKER_1:  are these tools.
SPEAKER_1:  defining a new generation of something that will transform programming.
SPEAKER_1:  Or is this just a fad that will pass?
SPEAKER_1:  certainly with JavaScript frameworks and.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... front and back end of the web
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot of different styles that came and went.
SPEAKER_1:  I remember learning...
SPEAKER_1:  What was it called? What was it called?
SPEAKER_1:  Remember for flash.
SPEAKER_1:  um, you know, learning how to program in flash.
SPEAKER_1:  learning how to design, do graphic animation, all that kind of stuff with Flash.
SPEAKER_1:  Same with Java applets. I remember creating quite a lot of Java applets.
SPEAKER_1:  thinking that this potentially defines the future of the web.
SPEAKER_1:  and did not.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you know...
SPEAKER_0:  In most cases like that.
SPEAKER_0:  the particular technology.
SPEAKER_0:  eventually gets replaced.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  many of the concepts that the technology introduced are made accessible first.
SPEAKER_0:  are preserved.
SPEAKER_0:  because yeah, we're not using Java applets anymore, but the notion of reactive web pages.
SPEAKER_0:  that sort of contain little bits of code.
SPEAKER_0:  that respond directly to
SPEAKER_0:  Something you do like pressing a button or a link or hovering even.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, it has certainly not gone away.
SPEAKER_0:  and that those animations that were.
SPEAKER_0:  made painfully.
SPEAKER_0:  complicated with flash.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  Flash was an innovation when it first came up.
SPEAKER_0:  and when it was replaced by JavaScript equivalents.
SPEAKER_0:  stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a somewhat better way.
SPEAKER_0:  to do animations, but those animations are still there.
SPEAKER_0:  Not all of them?
SPEAKER_0:  But, but...
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, there is an evolution and often, so often with technology.
SPEAKER_0:  that the sort of the technology that was eventually thrown away or replaced.
SPEAKER_0:  was still.
SPEAKER_0:  essential to.
SPEAKER_0:  to sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  get started there wouldn't be jet planes without propeller planes.
SPEAKER_0:  I betcha.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  From a user perspective, yes. From the feature set, yes.
SPEAKER_1:  But I...
SPEAKER_1:  from a programmer perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  It feels like...
SPEAKER_1:  all the time I've spent.
SPEAKER_1:  with ActionScript.
SPEAKER_1:  all the time I spent with.
SPEAKER_1:  Java on the applet side for the GUI development. Well, no, Java I have to push back. That was useful.
SPEAKER_1:  because it transfers, but the flash doesn't transfer. So some things you learn and invest time in.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, what you learned, the skill you picked up learning ActionScript.
SPEAKER_0:  What sort of it was.
SPEAKER_0:  Perhaps?
SPEAKER_0:  a super valuable skill at the time you picked it up.
SPEAKER_0:  If you.
SPEAKER_0:  if you learned ActionScript.
SPEAKER_0:  Early enough?
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  That skill is no longer.
SPEAKER_0:  in demand.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the calculation you have to make when you're learning new things. Like today people start learning programming.
SPEAKER_1:  Today I'm...
SPEAKER_1:  trying to.
SPEAKER_1:  to see what are the new.
SPEAKER_1:  languages to try what are the new systems to try that.
SPEAKER_1:  What are the new ideas to try to keep improving?
SPEAKER_0:  That's why we start when we're young, right?
SPEAKER_0:  When were... but...
SPEAKER_0:  That seems very true to me, that when you're young, you have your whole life ahead of you and you're-
SPEAKER_0:  you're allowed to make mistakes. In fact,
SPEAKER_0:  You should feel encouraged to do a bit of stupid stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  Try not to get yourself killed or seriously maimed, but...
SPEAKER_0:  Try stuff that's-
SPEAKER_0:  deviates from what everybody else is doing.
SPEAKER_0:  and like.
SPEAKER_0:  Nine out of ten times you'll just learn why everybody else is not doing that.
SPEAKER_0:  why everybody else is doing it so moderately.
SPEAKER_0:  And one out of ten times you sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  You discover something that's better or that somehow works. I mean, there are all sorts of crazy things that were invented.
SPEAKER_0:  by accident.
SPEAKER_0:  by people trying.
SPEAKER_0:  trying stuff together.
SPEAKER_1:  That's great advice to try random stuff, make a lot of
SPEAKER_0:  of mistakes.
SPEAKER_0:  some time where you were experimenting with crazy shit.
SPEAKER_0:  I like how I'm marriage-ing.
SPEAKER_1:  kids solidifies your choice of programming language.
SPEAKER_1:  How does that, the Robert Frost poem with the road less taken.
SPEAKER_1:  which I think is misinterpreted by most people. But anyway, I feel like the choices you make early on.
SPEAKER_1:  especially if you go all in.
SPEAKER_1:  they're gonna define the rest of your life's trajectory in a way that
SPEAKER_1:  like you basically are picking a camp. So, um.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there's if you invest a lot in PHP, if you invest a lot in dot net, if you invest a lot in JavaScript.
SPEAKER_1:  You're going to s-
SPEAKER_0:  THICC.
SPEAKER_1:  There.
SPEAKER_1:  That's your life journey.
SPEAKER_0:  It's very hard to tell. Only as far as depth.
SPEAKER_0:  technology remains relevant.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, yes. I mean, if at age 16...
SPEAKER_0:  You'll learn coding in C.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  By the time you're 26, C is like a dead language.
SPEAKER_0:  then...
SPEAKER_0:  there's still time to switch.
SPEAKER_0:  There's probably some kind of survivor bias or whatever it's called in sort of your observation that
SPEAKER_0:  that you pick a camp because there are many...
SPEAKER_0:  different camps to pick and if you picked.NET
SPEAKER_0:  then...
SPEAKER_0:  then you can coast for the rest of your life because that technology is now so ubiquitous, of course, that it's
SPEAKER_0:  even if it's
SPEAKER_0:  If it's bound to die, it's going to take a very long time.
SPEAKER_1:  For me personally.
SPEAKER_1:  I had a very...
SPEAKER_1:  difficult and in my own head.
SPEAKER_1:  brave leap that I had to take.
SPEAKER_1:  relevant to our discussion.
SPEAKER_1:  which is most of my life I programmed in C and C++.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  having that hammer everything look like a nail.
SPEAKER_1:  So I would literally even do scripting in C++.
SPEAKER_1:  Like how great programs that do script like things.
SPEAKER_1:  and uh
SPEAKER_1:  when I first came to Google and before then it became already.
SPEAKER_1:  Before TensorFlow, before all of that, there was a growing...
SPEAKER_1:  Realization that C++ is not the right tool for machine learning.
SPEAKER_1:  We could talk about why that is. It's unclear why that is. A lot of things.
SPEAKER_1:  has to do with...
SPEAKER_1:  community and culture and how it emerges and stuff like that, but
SPEAKER_1:  For me, they decided to take the leap to Python.
SPEAKER_1:  like all out.
SPEAKER_1:  basically switched completely from C++.
SPEAKER_1:  except for.
SPEAKER_1:  highly performant robotics applications. was still
SPEAKER_1:  there's still a culture of C++ in the space of robotics.
SPEAKER_1:  That was a big leap.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I had to, you know, like.
SPEAKER_1:  like people have like existential.
SPEAKER_1:  crises or midlife crises or whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  Get to realize.
SPEAKER_1:  almost like walking away from a person you love.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Because I was sure that C++ would have to be a lifelong companion.
SPEAKER_1:  For a lot of problems I would want to solve C++ would be there.
SPEAKER_1:  And it was a question to say, well.
SPEAKER_1:  That might not be the case, because C++ is still one of the most popular languages in the world, one of the most used.
SPEAKER_1:  one of the most depended on. It's also.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  still evolving.
SPEAKER_0:  white a bit I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  That is not sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  fossilizing community.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, they are doing great innovative work actually.
SPEAKER_0:  But their innovations are hard to follow if you're not already a hardcore C++ user.
SPEAKER_1:  This was the thing. It pulls you in. It's a rabbit hole. I was a hardcore.
SPEAKER_1:  the all meta programming template programming like.
SPEAKER_1:  I would start using the modern.
SPEAKER_1:  C++ as it developed.
SPEAKER_1:  Right, not just the...
SPEAKER_1:  not just the shared pointer and the garbage collection that makes it easier for you to work with some of the flaws.
SPEAKER_1:  but the detail like the meta programming, the crazy stuff that's.
SPEAKER_1:  that's coming out there.
SPEAKER_1:  But then you have to just empirically look.
SPEAKER_1:  and step back.
SPEAKER_1:  and say, what language am I more productive in?
SPEAKER_1:  Sorry to say, what language do I enjoy my life with more?
SPEAKER_1:  and readability and able to think through and all that kind of stuff. Those questions are harder to ask.
SPEAKER_1:  when you already have.
SPEAKER_1:  A loved one.
SPEAKER_1:  which in my case was C++.
SPEAKER_1:  and then there's Python.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... like that mean was is that the the grass greener than the other side in my just infatuated with a new fad
SPEAKER_1:  New cool thing.
SPEAKER_1:  or is this actually going to make my life better? And I think a lot of people face that kind of decision.
SPEAKER_1:  It was a difficult decision for me.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  When I made it at this time, it's an obvious switch if you're into machine learning
SPEAKER_1:  but at that time it wasn't quite yet so obvious.
SPEAKER_1:  So it was a risk and you know, you have the same kind of stuff with them.
SPEAKER_1:  I still, because of my connection to WordPress.
SPEAKER_1:  I still do a lot of back-end programming in PHP.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh.
SPEAKER_1:  And the question is, you know, no JS Python. Do you switch to do you switch back into any of those?
SPEAKER_1:  Programming is it there's the case for no JS for me
SPEAKER_1:  Well...
SPEAKER_1:  More and more and more of the front end it runs in JavaScript
SPEAKER_1:  and fascinating cool stuff is on his JavaScript.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe use the same programming language for the back end as well.
SPEAKER_1:  The case for Python for the back end is, well, you're doing so much.
SPEAKER_1:  programming.
SPEAKER_1:  outside of the web in Python.
SPEAKER_1:  So maybe use Python for the backend.
SPEAKER_1:  And then the case for PHB, well...
SPEAKER_1:  Most of the web still runs in PHP.
SPEAKER_1:  You have a lot of experience with PHP.
SPEAKER_1:  Why fix something that's not broken?
SPEAKER_1:  Those are my own personal struggles, but I think they reflect the struggles of a lot of people.
SPEAKER_1:  with different programming languages different problems are trying to solve
SPEAKER_1:  That's a weird one.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's not a single answer, right? Because...
SPEAKER_0:  depending on how much time you have to learn new stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  where you are in your life.
SPEAKER_0:  what you're currently working on who you want to work with what communities you like.
SPEAKER_0:  There's not one right choice.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe if you, if you sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  If you can look back 20 years, you can say, well, that whole detour through action script was a waste of time.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  Nobody could know that.
SPEAKER_0:  So you can't beat yourself up over that.
SPEAKER_0:  Uhhh
SPEAKER_0:  You just need to accept that not every choice you make.
SPEAKER_0:  is going to be perfect, maybe sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  Keep plan B in the back of your mind.
SPEAKER_0:  But don't don't overthink it.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't try to sort of don't.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't create a spreadsheet with like...
SPEAKER_0:  We're trying to estimate well if I...
SPEAKER_0:  Learn this language I expect to make.
SPEAKER_0:  X million dollars in a lifetime and if I learn that language...
SPEAKER_0:  I expect to make $1 million in a lifetime.
SPEAKER_0:  and which is higher and which has more risk and where is the chance that
SPEAKER_0:  It's like picking a stock.
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  Kind of, but...
SPEAKER_1:  I think with stocks you can do.
SPEAKER_1:  Diversifying your investment is good.
SPEAKER_1:  with productivity in life.
SPEAKER_1:  Boy, that spreadsheet.
SPEAKER_1:  is possible to construct.
SPEAKER_1:  Like if you actually carefully analyze what your interests in life are, where you think you can maximally...
SPEAKER_1:  impact the world.
SPEAKER_1:  There really is better and worse choices for programming language. They're not just about the syntax, but about the community.
SPEAKER_1:  about where you predict the communities headed.
SPEAKER_1:  what large systems are programmed in the...
SPEAKER_0:  But can you create that spreadsheet because that sort of
SPEAKER_0:  You're mentioning a whole bunch of inputs that go into that spreadsheet where you have to estimate things that are very hard to measure and...
SPEAKER_0:  even harder. I mean they're hard to measure.
SPEAKER_0:  retroactively and they're even harder to predict.
SPEAKER_0:  What is the better community?
SPEAKER_0:  Well...
SPEAKER_0:  Better is one of those.
SPEAKER_0:  incredibly difficult words. What's better for you is not better for someone else.
SPEAKER_1:  but we're not doing a public speech about what's better. We're doing.
SPEAKER_1:  personal spiritual journey.
SPEAKER_1:  I can determine a circle of friends.
SPEAKER_1:  Circle one and circle two and I can have a bunch of parties with one and a bunch of parties with two.
SPEAKER_1:  And then.
SPEAKER_1:  Write down.
SPEAKER_1:  or to take a mental note of what made me happier.
SPEAKER_1:  Right?
SPEAKER_1:  and that.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you have.
SPEAKER_1:  If you're a machine learning person, you want to say, okay.
SPEAKER_1:  I want to build a large company that does, that is.
SPEAKER_1:  grounded in machine learning.
SPEAKER_1:  but also has a sexy interface that has a large impact in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  What languages do I use?
SPEAKER_1:  You look at what Facebook is using, you look at what Twitter is using.
SPEAKER_1:  Then you look at performance.
SPEAKER_1:  more newer languages like rust.
SPEAKER_1:  or you look at languages that have taken.
SPEAKER_1:  that most of the community uses in the machine learning space that's Python.
SPEAKER_1:  And you can like think through, you can hang out and think through it. And it's always an invest. And the level of activity of the community is also really interesting. Like you said, C++ and Python are super active.
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of the development of the language itself.
SPEAKER_0:  But do you think that you can make?
SPEAKER_0:  Objective choices there?
SPEAKER_1:  No, no, no.
SPEAKER_1:  but there's a gut you build up. Like don't you believe in that gut feeling?
SPEAKER_0:  Everything is very subjective and yes, you most certainly can have a gut feeling and your gut can also be wrong. That's why there are billions of people because they're not all right.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  Clearly there are more people living in the Bay Area who have plans to...
SPEAKER_0:  sort of create a Google sized company.
SPEAKER_0:  then there's room in the world for Google sized companies.
SPEAKER_0:  and they're gonna have to duke it out in the market.
SPEAKER_0:  the space.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's.
SPEAKER_1:  many more choices than just the programming language.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of which, let's go back to the boat.
SPEAKER_1:  with the, with the fisherman who's tuned out long ago, the programmer, let's jump around and go back to see Python that we tried to define as the reference implementation. And one of the big things that's coming out in.
SPEAKER_1:  3.11.
SPEAKER_0:  We tend to say 3.11 because it really was like...
SPEAKER_0:  We went 3.8, 3.9, 3.10, 3.11, and they're planning to go up to 3.99.
SPEAKER_1:  99
SPEAKER_1:  What happens after 99?
SPEAKER_0:  Probably just 3.100 if I make it there.
SPEAKER_1:  and go all the way to 420. I got it. Forever Python V3. We'll talk about 4, but.
SPEAKER_1:  More for fun.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  3.11 is coming out. One of the big sexy things in it is it'll be much faster. So how
SPEAKER_1:  Did you, beyond hiring a great team or working with a great team?
SPEAKER_1:  Make it faster. What are some ideas?
SPEAKER_1:  that makes it faster.
SPEAKER_0:  It has to do with...
SPEAKER_0:  simplicity of software versus performance.
SPEAKER_0:  And so even though C is known to be a low level language, which is
SPEAKER_0:  great for writing sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  a high-performance language interpreter.
SPEAKER_0:  When I originally started.
SPEAKER_0:  Python or CPython.
SPEAKER_0:  I-
SPEAKER_0:  didn't expect there would be.
SPEAKER_0:  Great.
SPEAKER_0:  success and fame in my future.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, so I-
SPEAKER_0:  I tried to get something.
SPEAKER_0:  working.
SPEAKER_0:  and useful.
SPEAKER_0:  in about three months.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I sort of, I cut corners.
SPEAKER_0:  I-
SPEAKER_0:  borrowed ideas left and right when it comes to language design as well as implementation.
SPEAKER_0:  I also wrote much of the code as simple as it could be.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  They're like.
SPEAKER_0:  There are many things that you can code.
SPEAKER_0:  more efficiently by adding more code.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a bit of a sort of a time space.
SPEAKER_0:  straight off.
SPEAKER_0:  where you can compute a certain thing.
SPEAKER_0:  from a small number of inputs.
SPEAKER_0:  and every time you get presented with new input.
SPEAKER_0:  you do the whole computation from the top.
SPEAKER_0:  That can be simple looking code, it's easy to understand, it's easy to reason about that you can tell quickly that it's correct, at least in the sort of mathematical sense of correct.
SPEAKER_0:  Uhhh
SPEAKER_0:  Because it's implemented in C, maybe it performs.
SPEAKER_0:  relatively well.
SPEAKER_0:  but over time as-
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  as the requirements for that code and the need for performance.
SPEAKER_0:  Go up.
SPEAKER_0:  you might be able to rewrite that same algorithm.
SPEAKER_0:  using
SPEAKER_0:  More memory.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe remember previous results.
SPEAKER_0:  so you don't have to recompute everything from scratch like the
SPEAKER_0:  The classic example is computing prime numbers.
SPEAKER_0:  like
SPEAKER_0:  is 10 a prime number.
SPEAKER_0:  Well.
SPEAKER_0:  You sort of, is it divisible by two? Is it divisible by three? Is it divisible by four?
SPEAKER_0:  and we go all the way to is a divisible by nine.
SPEAKER_0:  And it is not well, actually 10 is divisible by two. So there we stop at say 11.
SPEAKER_0:  is divisible by 10.
SPEAKER_0:  The answer is 9, is no, 10 times in a row, so now we know 11 is a prime number.
SPEAKER_0:  On the other hand, if we already know that 2, 3, 5 and 7 are prime numbers.
SPEAKER_0:  and you know a little bit about the mathematics of...
SPEAKER_0:  how prime numbers work.
SPEAKER_0:  You know that if you have a rough estimate for the square root of 11,
SPEAKER_0:  You don't actually have to check is it divisible by four.
SPEAKER_0:  or is it divisible by 5? All you have to check in the case of 11 is is it divisible by 2, or is it divisible by 3?
SPEAKER_0:  Because take 12.
SPEAKER_0:  If it's divisible by four.
SPEAKER_0:  Well 12 divided by 4 is 3 so you...
SPEAKER_0:  you should have come across the question, is it a fizzle by three first?
SPEAKER_0:  So if you know...
SPEAKER_0:  basically nothing about prime numbers except the definition maybe you go
SPEAKER_0:  for X from two.
SPEAKER_0:  through n-1.
SPEAKER_0:  is indivisible by x.
SPEAKER_0:  And then at the end, if you got a...
SPEAKER_0:  all knows.
SPEAKER_0:  for every single one of those questions.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, oh, it must be a prime number. Well, the first thing is you can stop.
SPEAKER_0:  iterating when you find a yes answer.
SPEAKER_0:  And the second is you can also stop iterating when you have reached.
SPEAKER_0:  the square root.
SPEAKER_0:  of n.
SPEAKER_0:  Because you know that if it has a divisor larger than the square root, it must also have a divisor smaller than the square root.
SPEAKER_0:  Then you say, oh, except for two, we don't need to bother with checking for even numbers because all even numbers are divisible by two. So if it's divisible by four.
SPEAKER_0:  We would already have come across the question, is it divisible by two? And so now you go.
SPEAKER_0:  Special case, check is it divisible by two, and then you just check three, five, seven, eleven.
SPEAKER_0:  And so now you've sort of reduced your search space by 50% again by skipping all the even numbers it kept for two.
SPEAKER_0:  if you think a bit more about it.
SPEAKER_0:  or you just.
SPEAKER_0:  read in your book about the history of math.
SPEAKER_0:  one of the first algorithms ever written down.
SPEAKER_0:  All you have to do is check.
SPEAKER_0:  Is it divisible by any of the previous prime numbers that are smaller than the square root?
SPEAKER_0:  before you get to a better algorithm.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  you have
SPEAKER_0:  to have several PhDs in.
SPEAKER_0:  indiscreet math.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's as much as I know.
SPEAKER_1:  So of course that same story applies to a lot of other algorithms. String matching is a good example.
SPEAKER_1:  of how to come up with an innovation algorithm. And sometimes... yep.
SPEAKER_1:  The more efficient algorithm is not so much more complex than the inefficient one.
SPEAKER_1:  but that's an art.
SPEAKER_1:  It is not.
SPEAKER_1:  always the case in the general cases.
SPEAKER_1:  the more performant the algorithm.
SPEAKER_1:  the more complex it's gonna be.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a kind of trade-off.
SPEAKER_0:  The simpler algorithms are also the ones that people...
SPEAKER_0:  Invent first.
SPEAKER_0:  Because when you're looking for a solution...
SPEAKER_0:  you look at the simplest way to get there first.
SPEAKER_0:  And so if there is a simple.
SPEAKER_0:  Solution.
SPEAKER_0:  Even if it's not the best solution, not the fastest or the most memory efficient or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  A simple solution and simple is...
SPEAKER_0:  Fairly subjective, but mathematicians have also thought about what is a good definition for simple in the case of algorithms.
SPEAKER_0:  But the simpler solutions...
SPEAKER_0:  tend to be...
SPEAKER_0:  easier to follow for.
SPEAKER_0:  other programmers who...
SPEAKER_0:  haven't made a study of a particular field. And when I started with Python, I...
SPEAKER_0:  I was a good programmer in general, I knew sort of basic data structures, I knew the C language pretty well.
SPEAKER_0:  but there were...
SPEAKER_0:  many areas where I was.
SPEAKER_0:  Only.
SPEAKER_0:  somewhat familiar with the state of the art.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I picked...
SPEAKER_0:  in many cases, the simplest way I could solve a particular sub problem, because when you're designing and implementing a language, you have to like...
SPEAKER_0:  You have many hundreds of little problems to solve.
SPEAKER_0:  and...
SPEAKER_0:  You have to have solutions for every one of them.
SPEAKER_0:  before you can.
SPEAKER_0:  can sort of say, I've invented the programming.
SPEAKER_1:  First of all, so CPython.
SPEAKER_1:  What kind of things does it do?
SPEAKER_1:  It's an interpreter.
SPEAKER_1:  it takes in this readable language that we talked about that is Python.
SPEAKER_1:  What is this supposed to do?
SPEAKER_0:  The interpreter basically, it's sort of a recipe for...
SPEAKER_0:  understanding recipes.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  instead of a recipe that says
SPEAKER_0:  Bake me a cake, we have a recipe for...
SPEAKER_0:  Well, given.
SPEAKER_0:  the text of a program.
SPEAKER_0:  how do we run that program and that is sort of the recipe for building a computer.
SPEAKER_1:  The recipe for the baker and the chef. Yeah
SPEAKER_1:  What are the-
SPEAKER_1:  algorithmically tricky things that...
SPEAKER_1:  happen to be law-hanging fruit.
SPEAKER_1:  that could be improved on.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe throughout the history of Python, but also now.
SPEAKER_1:  How is it possible that 3.11 in year 2022
SPEAKER_1:  it's possible to get such a big performance improvement.
SPEAKER_0:  We focused.
SPEAKER_0:  on a few areas.
SPEAKER_0:  where we still felt there was low-hanging fruit.
SPEAKER_0:  The biggest one is actually the interpreter itself.
SPEAKER_0:  And this has to do with details of how Python is defined. So.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if the fisherman is going to follow this story. He already jumped off the boat. He's, he's, he's, he's, he's this.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm bored. Yeah. This is stupid. Is actually even though it's always.
SPEAKER_0:  called an interpreted language, it's...
SPEAKER_0:  There's also a compiler in there. It just doesn't compile to machine code. It compiles to...
SPEAKER_0:  bytecode which is
SPEAKER_0:  Certificate.
SPEAKER_0:  code for an imaginary computer.
SPEAKER_0:  that is called the Python interpreter.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's compiling code that is more easily digestible by the interpreter or is digestible.
SPEAKER_0:  It is the code that is digested by the interpreter. That's the compiler. We tweaked very minor bits of the compiler. Almost all the work was done in the interpreter.
SPEAKER_0:  because
SPEAKER_0:  when you have a program.
SPEAKER_0:  You compile it once and then you run the code a whole bunch of times.
SPEAKER_0:  or maybe there's one function in the code that gets run.
SPEAKER_0:  many times.
SPEAKER_0:  Now I know that that sort of people who...
SPEAKER_0:  who know this field are expecting me to at some point say...
SPEAKER_0:  We built a just-in-time compiler. Actually, we didn't.
SPEAKER_0:  We just made the interpreter a little more efficient.
SPEAKER_1:  What's a just in time comm-
SPEAKER_0:  That is a thing from the Java world, although it's now applied to almost all.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  programming languages, especially interpreted ones.
SPEAKER_1:  So you see the compile inside Python, not like it just in time.
SPEAKER_1:  compiler but is a compiler that creates by code that is then
SPEAKER_1:  fed to the interpreter.
SPEAKER_1:  and the compiler.
SPEAKER_1:  Was there something interesting to say about the compiler? It's interesting that you haven't changed that, tweet that at all.
SPEAKER_1:  or much.
SPEAKER_0:  We changed some.
SPEAKER_0:  parts of the bytecode.
SPEAKER_0:  but not very much.
SPEAKER_0:  And so we only had to change the parts of the compiler where we...
SPEAKER_0:  decided that the breakdown of a Python program in bytecode instructions had to be slightly different.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  That didn't gain us.
SPEAKER_0:  the performance.
SPEAKER_0:  improvements that performance improvements were.
SPEAKER_0:  like making the interpreter faster in part by
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  removing the fat from some internal data structures used by the interpreter but
SPEAKER_0:  Uhhh, duck.
SPEAKER_0:  The key idea is an adaptive specializing interpreter.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's go. What is adaptive about it?
SPEAKER_1:  What is specialized about it? Well
SPEAKER_0:  Let me first talk about the specializing part because the adaptive part is the sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  the second order effect, but they're both important.
SPEAKER_0:  So bytecode.
SPEAKER_0:  is a bunch of
SPEAKER_0:  machine instructions but it's an imaginary machine
SPEAKER_0:  But the machine can do things like...
SPEAKER_0:  Call of function.
SPEAKER_0:  Add two numbers.
SPEAKER_0:  print value.
SPEAKER_0:  Those are sort of typical instructions in Python.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  And if we take the example of adding two numbers.
SPEAKER_0:  Actually in Python the language, there's no such thing as adding two numbers. There's just an...
SPEAKER_0:  The compiler...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  doesn't know that you're adding two numbers. You might as well be adding two strings or two lists.
SPEAKER_0:  or two instances of some user defined class that happen to implement this operator called
SPEAKER_0:  add
SPEAKER_0:  That's a very-
SPEAKER_0:  interesting and fairly powerful mathematical concept.
SPEAKER_0:  It's mostly a user interface trick because it means that
SPEAKER_0:  a certain category of functions.
SPEAKER_0:  can be written using a single symbol the plus sign.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of a bunch of other functions can be written using another single symbol, the multiply sign.
SPEAKER_0:  So if we take...
SPEAKER_0:  Addition the way
SPEAKER_0:  traditionally in python that add bytecode was executed is.
SPEAKER_0:  Pointers, pointers, and more pointers.
SPEAKER_0:  So first we have two objects. An object is basically a pointer to a bunch of memory that contains more pointers. It points all the way down.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, not quite, but there are a lot of them, so...
SPEAKER_0:  To simplify a bit, we look up.
SPEAKER_0:  in one of the objects.
SPEAKER_0:  What is the type of that object and does that object...
SPEAKER_0:  type to find an add operation.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you can imagine that there is a
SPEAKER_0:  sort of a type integer that knows how to add itself to another integer.
SPEAKER_0:  and there is a type floating point number that knows how to add itself.
SPEAKER_0:  to another floating point number.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  integers and floating point.
SPEAKER_0:  numbers are sort of important.
SPEAKER_0:  I think mostly historically because in the first computers...
SPEAKER_0:  Uhhh
SPEAKER_0:  You used-
SPEAKER_0:  This sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  The same bit pattern, when interpreted as a floating point number, had a very different value than when interpreted as an integer.
SPEAKER_1:  Can I ask a dumb question here? Please do. Given the basics of int and float and add.
SPEAKER_1:  Who carries the knowledge of how to add two integers?
SPEAKER_1:  Is it the answer, Jerk?
SPEAKER_1:  It's the type integer.
SPEAKER_0:  versus it's the type integer and the type flow.
SPEAKER_1:  What about the operator is the operator?
SPEAKER_1:  just exist as a platonic form.
SPEAKER_1:  possessed by...
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  The operator is more...
SPEAKER_0:  like
SPEAKER_0:  It's an index in a list of functions.
SPEAKER_0:  that the integer type defines.
SPEAKER_0:  And so the integer type.
SPEAKER_0:  is really a collection of functions and there is an add function and there's a multiply function and there are like 30 other functions for other operations. There's a power function for example.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  You can imagine that...
SPEAKER_0:  In memory, there is a distinct slot for the add operations. Let's say the add operation is the first operation of a type and the multiply is the second operation of a type.
SPEAKER_0:  So now we take the integer type and we take the floating point type.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  in both cases.
SPEAKER_0:  The add operation is the first slot and multiplies the second slot.
SPEAKER_0:  but.
SPEAKER_0:  Each slot contains a function and the functions are different.
SPEAKER_0:  because the
SPEAKER_0:  add to integers function.
SPEAKER_0:  interprets the bit patterns as integers that add to float.
SPEAKER_0:  function.
SPEAKER_0:  interprets the
SPEAKER_0:  the same bit pattern.
SPEAKER_0:  as
SPEAKER_0:  as a floating point number. And then there is the string.
SPEAKER_0:  data type, which again, interprets the
SPEAKER_0:  The bit.
SPEAKER_0:  pattern as a
SPEAKER_0:  the address of a sequence of characters.
SPEAKER_0:  There are lots of lies in that story, but that's...
SPEAKER_0:  That's sort of a basic idea.
SPEAKER_0:  I can tell.
SPEAKER_1:  I could tell the fake news and the fabrication going on here at the table.
SPEAKER_1:  But where's the optimization? Is it on the operator? Is it a different?
SPEAKER_0:  So the optimization is.
SPEAKER_0:  the observation that
SPEAKER_0:  in a particular line of code.
SPEAKER_0:  So now you write your little Python program.
SPEAKER_0:  and you write a function and that function sort of takes a bunch of inputs and at some point
SPEAKER_0:  It adds two of the inputs together.
SPEAKER_0:  Now I bet you even if you call your function a thousand times
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  All those calls are likely all going to be about integers.
SPEAKER_0:  because maybe your program is all about integers.
SPEAKER_0:  Or maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  on that particular line of code where there's that plus operator.
SPEAKER_0:  every time the program hits that line.
SPEAKER_0:  The variables a and b that are being added together happen to be strings.
SPEAKER_0:  And so what we do is instead of having this single byte code that says
SPEAKER_0:  Here's an add operation and the implementation of add is fully generic. It looks at the...
SPEAKER_0:  object from the object it looks at the type.
SPEAKER_0:  then it takes the type and it looks up the function pointer.
SPEAKER_0:  then it calls the function.
SPEAKER_0:  Now the function has to look at the other argument and has to double check that the other argument has the right type.
SPEAKER_0:  And then there's a bunch of error checking before it can actually.
SPEAKER_0:  just go ahead and add the two bit patterns in the right way.
SPEAKER_0:  What we do is...
SPEAKER_0:  every time we execute an add instruction like that.
SPEAKER_0:  We.
SPEAKER_0:  We keep a little note of
SPEAKER_0:  In the end, after-
SPEAKER_0:  after we hit the code that did the addition.
SPEAKER_0:  for a particular type.
SPEAKER_0:  What type was it?
SPEAKER_0:  and then after a few times...
SPEAKER_0:  through that code if it's the same type all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  We say.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  So this add operation, even though it's the generic add operation...
SPEAKER_0:  It might as well be the add integer operation.
SPEAKER_0:  And add integer operation is much more efficient because it just says.
SPEAKER_0:  Assume that a and b are integers.
SPEAKER_0:  Do the addition operation, do it right there inline.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  produce the result.
SPEAKER_0:  The big lie here is that in Python, even if...
SPEAKER_0:  you have.
SPEAKER_0:  great evidence that in the past it was always two integers that you were adding.
SPEAKER_0:  At some point in the future, that same line of code could still be hit with two floating points or two strings, or maybe a string and an integer.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not a great lie, that's just the fact of life.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't account for what should happen in that case.
SPEAKER_0:  in the way I told the story.
SPEAKER_1:  There is some accounting.
SPEAKER_0:  And so...
SPEAKER_0:  What we actually have to do is...
SPEAKER_0:  when we have the add integer operation.
SPEAKER_0:  We still have to check.
SPEAKER_0:  Are the two arguments in fact integers?
SPEAKER_0:  Weep.
SPEAKER_0:  applied some tricks to make those checks efficient.
SPEAKER_0:  And we know statistically that the outcome is almost always, yes, they are both integers.
SPEAKER_0:  And so we quickly make that check and then we proceed with the sort of add integer operation and then there is a fallback mechanism where we say
SPEAKER_0:  Oops, one of them wasn't an integer.
SPEAKER_0:  Now we're going to pretend that it was just the fully generic add operation.
SPEAKER_0:  We wasted a few cycles.
SPEAKER_0:  believing it was
SPEAKER_0:  was going to be two integers, and then we had to back up.
SPEAKER_0:  But we didn't waste that much time and statistically.
SPEAKER_0:  most of the time.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, we're sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  hoping that most of the time we guess right, because if we...
SPEAKER_0:  if it turns out that we guessed wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  too often.
SPEAKER_0:  or we didn't have a good guess at all.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  things might actually end up running a little slower.
SPEAKER_0:  So someone with.
SPEAKER_0:  Armed with this knowledge.
SPEAKER_0:  and a copy of the implementation. Someone could easily construct a counter example where they say,
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, I have a program and now it runs five times as slow in Python 3.11 than it did in Python 3.10.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's a very unrealistic program. That's just like...
SPEAKER_0:  an extreme fluke.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a fun reverse engine.
SPEAKER_1:  engineering task though.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah. So there's a.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... people
SPEAKER_1:  Like fun, yes.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's some...
SPEAKER_1:  Presumably heuristic.
SPEAKER_1:  of what defines a momentum.
SPEAKER_1:  of saying you know you seem to be working adding two integers not two generic types.
SPEAKER_1:  So
SPEAKER_1:  How do you figure out that heuristic?
SPEAKER_0:  I think that the heuristic is actually...
SPEAKER_0:  we assume that the weather tomorrow is going to be the same as the weather today.
SPEAKER_1:  So you don't need two days of the weather?
SPEAKER_1:  I've got the
SPEAKER_0:  That is already so much better than...
SPEAKER_0:  than than guessing randomly that. So how do you
SPEAKER_1:  find this idea.
SPEAKER_1:  Hey, I wonder if instead of adding to generic...
SPEAKER_1:  types.
SPEAKER_1:  we start assuming that the weather tomorrow is the same as the weather today
SPEAKER_1:  Where do you find the idea for that?
SPEAKER_1:  because that ultimately...
SPEAKER_1:  For you to do that, you have to kind of understand how people are using the language, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Python is not the first language to do a thing like this.
SPEAKER_0:  This is a fairly well known trick, especially from...
SPEAKER_0:  other interpreted languages that had reason to be sped up.
SPEAKER_0:  We occasionally look at papers about HHVM, which is for Facebook's...
SPEAKER_0:  efficient compiler for PHP.
SPEAKER_0:  There are tweaks known from the JVM and...
SPEAKER_0:  Sometimes it just comes from academia.
SPEAKER_1:  So the trick here is that the type itself doesn't
SPEAKER_1:  The variable doesn't know what type it is.
SPEAKER_1:  So this is not a statically typed language where you can.
SPEAKER_1:  You can get support to have a shortcut to saying it's in.
SPEAKER_0:  This is a trick that is especially important for...
SPEAKER_0:  for interpreted languages with dynamic typing because
SPEAKER_0:  If.
SPEAKER_0:  If the compiler could read in the source.
SPEAKER_0:  these x and y that we're adding are integers, the compiler can just insert a single add machine code.
SPEAKER_0:  hardware machine instruction that exists.
SPEAKER_0:  on every CPU.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, and ditto for floats.
SPEAKER_0:  But because in Python you don't
SPEAKER_0:  generally declare the types of your variables.
SPEAKER_0:  don't even declare the existence of your variables. They just spring into existence when you first assign them.
SPEAKER_0:  which.
SPEAKER_0:  is really cool and sort of helps those beginners because there is less bookkeeping they have to
SPEAKER_0:  Learn how to do before they can start.
SPEAKER_0:  playing around with code.
SPEAKER_0:  but it makes the...
SPEAKER_0:  day in.
SPEAKER_0:  interpretation of the code.
SPEAKER_0:  less efficient and so we're sort of
SPEAKER_0:  trying to.
SPEAKER_0:  to make the interpretation.
SPEAKER_0:  more efficient without losing the super dynamic nature of the language.
SPEAKER_0:  That's always the challenge.
SPEAKER_1:  3.5.
SPEAKER_1:  Got the pep.
SPEAKER_1:  type hints.
SPEAKER_1:  What is type hinting?
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Is it used?
SPEAKER_1:  by the interpreter, the hints.
SPEAKER_1:  Or is it just syntactic?
SPEAKER_0:  sugar.
SPEAKER_0:  that people can use and it's especially popular with sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  larger companies that have very large code bases written in Python.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think of it as almost like documentation saying these two variables are the same?
SPEAKER_0:  at this time. More than documentation. I mean, so it's
SPEAKER_0:  It is a sub-language of Python where...
SPEAKER_0:  where you can express the types of variables. So here is a variable and it's an integer.
SPEAKER_0:  And here's an argument to this function and it's a string. And here is a function that returns a list of strings.
SPEAKER_1:  but that's not checked when you run the
SPEAKER_0:  But
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly. There is a separate piece of software called a static type checker.
SPEAKER_0:  that reads all your source code without executing it and thinks long and hard about
SPEAKER_0:  what it looks from just reading the code that code might be doing.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  double checks.
SPEAKER_0:  if that makes sense if you take the types.
SPEAKER_0:  as annotated into a count.
SPEAKER_1:  So this is something you're supposed to run as you develop.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like a linter.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that's definitely a development tool, but the type annotations currently are not used for.
SPEAKER_0:  speeding up the interpreter and
SPEAKER_0:  There are a number of reasons...
SPEAKER_0:  Many people don't use them.
SPEAKER_0:  even when they do use them.
SPEAKER_0:  They sometimes contain lies.
SPEAKER_0:  Where?
SPEAKER_0:  The Static Type Checker.
SPEAKER_0:  says everything's fine.
SPEAKER_0:  I cannot prove that this integer is ever not an integer, but at runtime somehow someone
SPEAKER_0:  manages to.
SPEAKER_0:  violate that assumption.
SPEAKER_0:  And the interpreter...
SPEAKER_0:  ends up doing just fine if we
SPEAKER_0:  started enforcing type annotations in Python.
SPEAKER_0:  Many Python programs would no longer work.
SPEAKER_0:  And some Python programs wouldn't even be possible because they're too dynamic.
SPEAKER_0:  So we made a choice of not.
SPEAKER_0:  using the annotations. There is a possible future where eventually
SPEAKER_0:  3, 4...
SPEAKER_0:  Five.
SPEAKER_0:  releases in the future, we could start using those annotations to sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  provide hints?
SPEAKER_0:  because we can still say...
SPEAKER_0:  Well...
SPEAKER_0:  The source code leads us to believe that these x and y are both integers, and so we can generate an add integer instruction.
SPEAKER_0:  but we can still have a fallback that says...
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, if somehow the code.
SPEAKER_0:  encoded runtime.
SPEAKER_0:  provided something else maybe it provided two decimal numbers
SPEAKER_0:  we can still use that generic add operation.
SPEAKER_0:  as a fallback.
SPEAKER_0:  But we're not there.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there currently a mechanism?
SPEAKER_1:  or do you see something like that?
SPEAKER_1:  where you can almost add like an assert.
SPEAKER_1:  inside a function that says
SPEAKER_1:  Please check that my type hints.
SPEAKER_1:  are actually mapping to reality.
SPEAKER_1:  sort of like insert.
SPEAKER_1:  Manual static typing.
SPEAKER_0:  There are third party libraries that...
SPEAKER_0:  are in that business.
SPEAKER_1:  It's possible to do that kind of thing. It's possible for a third party library to take a hint.
SPEAKER_1:  and enforce it.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, well what we actually do is, and I think this is a fairly unique feature in Python.
SPEAKER_0:  The type hints.
SPEAKER_0:  can be introspected at runtime.
SPEAKER_0:  So while the program is running...
SPEAKER_0:  They mean Python is a very introspectable language.
SPEAKER_0:  You can look at the variable and ask yourself, what is the type of this?
SPEAKER_0:  this variable and if that variable happens to
SPEAKER_0:  refer to a function, you can ask.
SPEAKER_0:  What are the arguments to the function?
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Nowadays you can also ask what are the type annotations for the function.
SPEAKER_1:  So the type annotations are there inside the variable local visits.
SPEAKER_1:  at runtime.
SPEAKER_0:  They're mostly associated with the function object, not with each individual variable, but...
SPEAKER_0:  Right. You can sort of map from.
SPEAKER_0:  from the arguments to the variable.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's what a third party li-
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly. And the problem with that is that all that extra runtime type checking...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  is going to slow your code down instead of speed it up.
SPEAKER_1:  I think to reference this.
SPEAKER_1:  a sales pitchy blog post.
SPEAKER_1:  that says 75% of developers' time is spent on debugging.
SPEAKER_1:  I would say that in some cases that might be okay.
SPEAKER_1:  It might be okay to pay the cost of performance.
SPEAKER_1:  for the catching of the types, the type errors.
SPEAKER_0:  And in most cases...
SPEAKER_0:  doing it.
SPEAKER_0:  statically before you ship your code to production.
SPEAKER_0:  is more efficient than doing it at runtime piecemeal.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you tell me about...
SPEAKER_1:  Mypy project.
SPEAKER_1:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_1:  What is it?
SPEAKER_1:  What's the mission?
SPEAKER_1:  And in general, what is the future of static typing in Python?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, so MyPy was started by a Finnish.
SPEAKER_0:  Developer, you can let us know.
SPEAKER_1:  So many cool things out of Finland.
SPEAKER_1:  i guess it
SPEAKER_1:  Just that part of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  I guess people have nothing better to do in those long cold winters.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, I think Yuka lived in England when he invented that stuff actually.
SPEAKER_0:  My pie.
SPEAKER_0:  is the original static type checker for Python and the type annotations that were introduced with PEP 484.
SPEAKER_0:  were sort of developed.
SPEAKER_0:  together.
SPEAKER_0:  with the static type checker.
SPEAKER_0:  And in fact, Yuka had first invented a different syntax that wasn't quite compatible with Python.
SPEAKER_0:  and Yuka and I sort of met at the Python conference.
SPEAKER_0:  in I think in 2013.
SPEAKER_0:  And we.
SPEAKER_0:  We sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  came up with a compromise syntax.
SPEAKER_0:  That's it.
SPEAKER_0:  would not require any changes to Python.
SPEAKER_0:  and that would let
SPEAKER_0:  MyPy sort of be an add-on static type checker for Python.
SPEAKER_1:  Just out of curiosity, was it like double colon or something? What was he proposing that would break python?
SPEAKER_0:  I think he was using angular brackets.
SPEAKER_0:  for types like in C++ or Java generics.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, you can't use angular brackets in Python. That would be too tricky.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, we...
SPEAKER_0:  The key thing is that we already had.
SPEAKER_0:  uh no, a syntax for annotations we just didn't know what to use them for yet.
SPEAKER_0:  So type annotations were just the sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  most logical.
SPEAKER_0:  thing to use that existing dummy syntax for.
SPEAKER_0:  So there was no there was no syntax for.
SPEAKER_0:  defining generics.
SPEAKER_0:  directly syntactically in the language.
SPEAKER_0:  MyPy literally meant my version of Python.
SPEAKER_0:  where mine refers to Yucca.
SPEAKER_0:  He had a-
SPEAKER_0:  parser that translated mypy into python.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  like doing the type checks.
SPEAKER_0:  and then
SPEAKER_0:  removing the annotations and all the angular brackets from the positions where he was using them.
SPEAKER_0:  But a preprocessor model doesn't work very well with the typical workflow of Python development projects.
SPEAKER_1:  That's funny. I mean, that could have been another major split if it became successful.
SPEAKER_1:  Like if you watch...
SPEAKER_1:  TypeScript versus JavaScript.
SPEAKER_1:  is like a split in the community over types, right? That seems to be stabilizing now.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not necessarily a split, there's certainly plenty of people who...
SPEAKER_0:  Don't use TypeScript, but...
SPEAKER_0:  just use the original JavaScript.
SPEAKER_0:  notation just like there are many people in the Python world who don't use type annotations and don't use static type checkers.
SPEAKER_1:  No, you know, but there is a bit of a split between TypeScript and JavaScript, old school JavaScript.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, in the JavaScript world, transpilers are sort of the standard way of working anyway, which is why TypeScript being a transpiler itself is not a big deal.
SPEAKER_1:  And transpires for people who don't know. It's, it's exactly the thing you said with my price. It's the code.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess you call it preprocessing.
SPEAKER_1:  code that translates from one language to the other. And that's part of the culture, part of the-
SPEAKER_1:  workflow of the JavaScript community. So.
SPEAKER_0:  That's right. At the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  An interesting development in the JavaScript slash TypeScript world at the moment is that
SPEAKER_0:  There is a proposal under consideration. It's only a Stage 1 proposal.
SPEAKER_0:  that proposes to add a feature to JavaScript where, just like Python,
SPEAKER_0:  It will.
SPEAKER_0:  Ignore certain syntax.
SPEAKER_0:  when
SPEAKER_0:  running the JavaScript code.
SPEAKER_0:  and what it ignores is more or less.
SPEAKER_0:  a superset of the TypeScript annotation syntax.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  That would mean that eventually, if you wanted to...
SPEAKER_0:  You could take TypeScript.
SPEAKER_0:  and you could shove it directly into a JavaScript interpreter without translation.
SPEAKER_0:  The interesting thing in the JavaScript world, at least the web browser world...
SPEAKER_0:  The web browsers have changed how they deploy and they.
SPEAKER_0:  they sort of update their JavaScript engines.
SPEAKER_0:  much more quickly than they used to in the early days and so there's much less of a need for.
SPEAKER_0:  translation in JavaScript itself.
SPEAKER_0:  because most browsers just support the...
SPEAKER_0:  most recent version of ECMAScript.
SPEAKER_1:  just in a tangent of a tangent, do you see if you would recommend somebody use a thing, would you recommend TypeScript or JavaScript?
SPEAKER_0:  I would recommend TypeScript.
SPEAKER_1:  just because of the strictness of the typing.
SPEAKER_0:  It's.
SPEAKER_0:  an enormously helpful extra tool that helps you sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  Keep your head straight about.
SPEAKER_0:  what your code is actually doing.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean it's it's it.
SPEAKER_0:  It helps with...
SPEAKER_0:  Editing your code, it helps with ensuring that your code.
SPEAKER_0:  is not too incorrect.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's actually...
SPEAKER_0:  Quite compatible with JavaScript, nevermind this syntactic.
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  hack that is still years in the future.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  Any library that is written in pure JavaScript can still be used from TypeScript programs.
SPEAKER_0:  and also the other way around. You can write.
SPEAKER_0:  a library in TypeScript.
SPEAKER_0:  and then export it in a form that is totally consumable by JavaScript.
SPEAKER_0:  That's sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  compatibility is sort of the key to the success of TypeScript.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, just to look at it as almost like a biological system that's evolving. It's fascinating to see JavaScript evolve the way it does.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, maybe we should consider that biological systems are just engineering systems too, right? Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  just very advanced.
SPEAKER_0:  With more history.
SPEAKER_1:  but...
SPEAKER_1:  It's almost like the most visceral.
SPEAKER_1:  in the JavaScript world because
SPEAKER_1:  There's just so much code written in JavaScript.
SPEAKER_1:  that for its history was.
SPEAKER_1:  messy. If you talk about bugs per line of code, I just feel like JavaScript.
SPEAKER_1:  eats the cake or whatever the terminology is. It beats Python by a lot in terms of number of bugs.
SPEAKER_1:  meaning like way more bugs in JavaScript.
SPEAKER_1:  And then the...
SPEAKER_1:  Obviously the browsers are developing. Just there's so much active development. It feels a lot more like evolution.
SPEAKER_1:  where a bunch of stuff is born and dies and there's experimentation.
SPEAKER_1:  Debates versus python is more.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  All that stuff is happening.
SPEAKER_1:  but there's just a longer history of stable working.
SPEAKER_1:  giant software systems written in Python.
SPEAKER_1:  versus JavaScript is just a giant.
SPEAKER_1:  beautiful I would say mess.
SPEAKER_0:  of code. Very different culture and-
SPEAKER_0:  To some extent differences in culture are random but to some extent the differences have to do with the environment.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, and...
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that JavaScript is primarily...
SPEAKER_0:  the language for developing.
SPEAKER_0:  web applications, especially the client side.
SPEAKER_0:  and the fact that it's...
SPEAKER_0:  basically the only language for developing web applications.
SPEAKER_0:  makes that community sort of just have.
SPEAKER_0:  a different nature than the community of other languages.
SPEAKER_1:  Plus the graphical component.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  and the fact that they're deploying it.
SPEAKER_1:  on all kinds of shapes of screens and devices and all that kind of stuff. justpticsmoke
SPEAKER_1:  beautiful chaos.
SPEAKER_1:  Anyway, back to my pipe.
SPEAKER_1:  So what? Okay. You met you talked about
SPEAKER_1:  syntax that could work.
SPEAKER_1:  Where does it currently stand?
SPEAKER_1:  What's the future of static typing in Python?
SPEAKER_0:  It is still controversial, but it is much more accepted than when MyPy and PEP484 were young.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the connection between a pet 44 type hints and my pie?
SPEAKER_0:  My pie.
SPEAKER_0:  was the original static type checker. So it, MyPy quickly evolved from Yucca's
SPEAKER_0:  own variant of Python 2.
SPEAKER_0:  a static type checker for Python and sort of PEP 484 that was it like.
SPEAKER_0:  A very productive year where like many hundreds of messages were exchanged debating the merits.
SPEAKER_0:  of every aspect of that pep.
SPEAKER_0:  And so myPy is a static type checker for Python. It is itself written in Python.
SPEAKER_0:  most.
SPEAKER_0:  Additional
SPEAKER_0:  static typing features that we introduced in the time since 3.6.
SPEAKER_0:  i were also prototype.
SPEAKER_0:  through MyPy.
SPEAKER_0:  MyPy being an open source project with a very small number of maintainers.
SPEAKER_0:  was successful enough.
SPEAKER_0:  that people said this static type checking stuff for Python is actually worth an investment for our company.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  Somehow they chose not to support.
SPEAKER_0:  making my pie faster say or.
SPEAKER_0:  adding new features to myPy, but...
SPEAKER_0:  both Google and Facebook and later Microsoft.
SPEAKER_0:  developed their own static type checker.
SPEAKER_0:  I think Facebook was one of the first.
SPEAKER_0:  date.
SPEAKER_0:  decided that they wanted to use the same technology.
SPEAKER_0:  that they had successfully used for HHVM.
SPEAKER_0:  because they sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  They had a bunch of compiler writers and static type checking experts.
SPEAKER_0:  who had written.
SPEAKER_0:  the HHVM compiler and it was a big success within the company.
SPEAKER_0:  and they had done it in a certain way, sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  They wrote a-
SPEAKER_0:  BIG.
SPEAKER_0:  highly parallel application in an obscure language named OCaml.
SPEAKER_0:  which is apparently mostly very good for writing static type checkers.
SPEAKER_1:  Interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  I have a lot of questions about how to write a static type checker.
SPEAKER_1:  That's very confusing.
SPEAKER_0:  Facebook wrote.
SPEAKER_0:  their version and they worked on it in secret for about a year and then they came clean and went open source.
SPEAKER_0:  Google in the meantime was developing something called PyType which was mostly
SPEAKER_0:  interesting because it
SPEAKER_0:  as you may have heard, they-
SPEAKER_0:  have one gigantic monorepo.
SPEAKER_0:  So all the code is checked into a single repository.
SPEAKER_0:  Facebook has a different approach, so Facebook developed Pyre.
SPEAKER_0:  Which
SPEAKER_0:  which was written in OCaml.
SPEAKER_0:  which worked well with Facebook's.
SPEAKER_0:  development workflow.
SPEAKER_0:  And Google developed something they called PyType.
SPEAKER_0:  which was actually itself written in Python.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  and it was meant to sort of fit well in.
SPEAKER_0:  their static type checking needs in.
SPEAKER_0:  Google's gigantic monorepo.
SPEAKER_0:  So Google has the money.
SPEAKER_1:  giant got it.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  Just to clarify, this static type checker...
SPEAKER_1:  philosophically is a thing that's supposed to exist outside of the language itself.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's just a workflow like a debugger for the program. It's a linter. For people who don't know, a linter, maybe you can correct me.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's a thing that runs through the code continuously.
SPEAKER_1:  preprocessing to find issues.
SPEAKER_1:  based on style.
SPEAKER_1:  documentation and there's all kinds of linters right you can check that.
SPEAKER_1:  What usual things does a linter do? Maybe!
SPEAKER_1:  Check that you haven't.
SPEAKER_1:  too many.
SPEAKER_1:  characters in a single line.
SPEAKER_0:  Linters often do static analysis where they try to point out things that are likely mistakes, but not
SPEAKER_0:  incorrect according to the language specification.
SPEAKER_0:  like.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe you have a variable that you never use.
SPEAKER_0:  for the compiler.
SPEAKER_0:  That is valid. You might be able to keep up with me in more details about the
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of, you might be planning to use it in future version of the code, and the compiler might just optimize it out, but the compiler's not going to tell you, hey, you're never using this variable.
SPEAKER_0:  A linter.
SPEAKER_0:  We'll tell you.
SPEAKER_0:  That variable is not used, maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a typo somewhere else where you meant to use it, but you accidentally used something else, or there are a number of...
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  common scenarios and a linter is often
SPEAKER_0:  a big collection of little heuristics.
SPEAKER_0:  where by looking at the combination of how your code is laid out, maybe how it's indented, maybe...
SPEAKER_0:  Chart pavement structure.
SPEAKER_0:  and but also just
SPEAKER_0:  things like...
SPEAKER_0:  Definition of names, use of names.
SPEAKER_0:  It'll tell you likely things that are wrong. And in some cases, linters are.
SPEAKER_0:  I release style checkers.
SPEAKER_0:  For Python, there are a number of linters that check things like...
SPEAKER_0:  Do you use the PEP8?
SPEAKER_0:  recommended naming scheme for your functions and classes and variables.
SPEAKER_0:  Because classes start with an uppercase and the rest starts with a lowercase.
SPEAKER_0:  There's like...
SPEAKER_0:  differences there and so the linter can tell you hey you have a class that uh who's
SPEAKER_0:  First letter is not.
SPEAKER_0:  an uppercase letter and that's just, I just find it annoying if I wanted that to be an uppercase letter. I would have typed an uppercase letter, but other people find it very comforting that if the linter is an uppercase letter, then I would have typed an uppercase letter.
SPEAKER_0:  is no longer complaining about their code that they have followed all this time.
SPEAKER_1:  rules.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe it's a fast way for a new developer joining a team to learn the style rules, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there's definitely that, but the best use of a linter is probably...
SPEAKER_0:  not so much to sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  and force team uniformity, but to actually help developers.
SPEAKER_0:  catch bugs that the compilers, for whatever reason, don't catch.
SPEAKER_0:  And there is lots of that in Python.
SPEAKER_0:  And so, but the Aesthetic Type Checker.
SPEAKER_0:  focuses on.
SPEAKER_0:  a particular aspect of the linting, which
SPEAKER_0:  I mean it.
SPEAKER_0:  MyPy doesn't care how you name your classes and variables.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  but it is meticulous about...
SPEAKER_0:  When you say that there was an integer here...
SPEAKER_0:  and you're passing a string there.
SPEAKER_0:  it will tell you, hey, that string is not an integer. So something's wrong either.
SPEAKER_0:  Either you were.
SPEAKER_0:  incorrect when you said it was an integer or you're incorrect when you're passing into string.
SPEAKER_1:  If this is a race.
SPEAKER_1:  Static type checkers is somebody winning. As you said, it's interesting that the companies didn't choose to invest in.
SPEAKER_1:  this centralized development.
SPEAKER_1:  of my pie.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there a future for my pie?
SPEAKER_1:  What do you see as the, will one of the companies win out and everybody uses?
SPEAKER_1:  Like, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  type or whatever Google's is called.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, Microsoft is hoping that Microsoft's horse in that race called Pyrite is going to win.
SPEAKER_0:  Pyrite, right.
SPEAKER_1:  like R-I-G-H-T.
SPEAKER_0:  Correct.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, all my word processors tend to...
SPEAKER_0:  typo corrected as pyrite, the name of the...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know what it is.
SPEAKER_0:  some kind of semi-precious metal.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, right.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for watching.
SPEAKER_1:  I love it. Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  So, okay, that's the Microsoft hope, but.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so let me ask the question a different way.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there going to be ever a future where the static type checker gets integrated into the language?
SPEAKER_0:  Nobody is currently excited about.
SPEAKER_0:  doing any work towards that. That doesn't mean that 5 or 10 years from now...
SPEAKER_0:  the situation isn't.
SPEAKER_0:  different.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  At the moment...
SPEAKER_0:  Old aesthetic type checkers.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... still
SPEAKER_0:  evolve at a much higher speed than Python and its annotation syntax evolve.
SPEAKER_0:  you get a new release of Python.
SPEAKER_0:  once a year.
SPEAKER_0:  Those are the only times that you can introduce new
SPEAKER_0:  annotation syntax.
SPEAKER_0:  And there are always people who invent new.
SPEAKER_0:  new annotation syntax that they're trying to push.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  and worse.
SPEAKER_0:  once we've all agreed that we are going to put some new syntax in, we can never take it back.
SPEAKER_0:  at least a sort of
SPEAKER_0:  Deprecating an existing feature takes many releases because
SPEAKER_0:  You have to assume that people started using it as soon as we announced it.
SPEAKER_0:  and then you can't take it away from them right away. You have to start.
SPEAKER_0:  telling them, well, this will go away, but we're not.
SPEAKER_0:  gonna commit.
SPEAKER_0:  tell you that it's an error yet and then later it's going to be a warning and then eventually three releases in the future maybe we remove it
SPEAKER_0:  On the other hand, the typical static type checker.
SPEAKER_0:  still has a release like
SPEAKER_0:  every month.
SPEAKER_0:  every two months.
SPEAKER_0:  certainly many times a year.
SPEAKER_0:  Some type checkers also include a bunch of.
SPEAKER_0:  experimental ideas that aren't official standard.
SPEAKER_0:  Python syntax yet.
SPEAKER_0:  And the static type checkers also just get the same.
SPEAKER_0:  better at discovering.
SPEAKER_0:  things that.
SPEAKER_0:  that are unspecified by the language, but that could make sense.
SPEAKER_0:  Each static type checker actually has
SPEAKER_0:  it's sort of strong and weak points.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's cool. It's like a laboratory of experiments. Yeah. Microsoft Google and all and you get to see.
SPEAKER_0:  And you see that everywhere, right? Because there is not one single JavaScript in...
SPEAKER_0:  engine either there is one in chrome there is one in safari there's one in firefox
SPEAKER_1:  But that said, you said there's not interest, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  There is a lot of interest in type hinting, right?
SPEAKER_1:  in the PEP 484.
SPEAKER_1:  XC they come in people use that give a sense
SPEAKER_1:  How many people use, because it's optional, it's a sugar.
SPEAKER_0:  I can't
SPEAKER_0:  put a number on it but...
SPEAKER_0:  from the number of packages that do interesting things with it at runtime and the fact that there are like
SPEAKER_0:  Now feel for very mature type checkers.
SPEAKER_0:  that each have their own.
SPEAKER_0:  their segment of the market and then there is PyCharm which has a more heuristic based type checker that also supports the same syntax.
SPEAKER_0:  My assumption is that
SPEAKER_0:  many many people developing python software professionally.
SPEAKER_0:  for some kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  production situation.
SPEAKER_0:  are using a static type checker.
SPEAKER_0:  especially anybody who has a continuous integration cycle.
SPEAKER_0:  probably has a
SPEAKER_0:  one of the steps in there.
SPEAKER_0:  their testing routine that happens for basically every.
SPEAKER_0:  every commit.
SPEAKER_0:  is run a static type checker.
SPEAKER_0:  And in most cases, that will be my pie.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think it's a pretty popular topic.
SPEAKER_1:  according to this webpage.
SPEAKER_1:  20 to 30% of Python 3 code bases are using type hints.
SPEAKER_1:  Wow.
SPEAKER_0:  I wonder how they measured that. Did they just scan all of GitHub?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, that's what it looks like. Yeah. They did a quick set, not all of, but like a random sampling.
SPEAKER_1:  So you mentioned PyCharm.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask you the big subjective question.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the best?
SPEAKER_1:  IDE for Python.
SPEAKER_1:  and you're extremely biased now that you're with Microsoft.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it PyCharm VS code Vim or Emacs?
SPEAKER_0:  Historically, I actually started out with using Vim.
SPEAKER_0:  when it was still called VI.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... for very long time i think from the
SPEAKER_0:  early 80s to...
SPEAKER_0:  I'd say...
SPEAKER_0:  Two years ago...
SPEAKER_0:  I was Emacs user?
SPEAKER_1:  Nice.
SPEAKER_0:  between I'd say 2013 and 2018.
SPEAKER_0:  dabbled with pie charm?
SPEAKER_0:  Mostly because it had...
SPEAKER_0:  had a couple of features, I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye charm.
SPEAKER_0:  is.
SPEAKER_0:  like
SPEAKER_0:  It's deriving an 18-wheeler truck, whereas E-MAX is more...
SPEAKER_0:  like.
SPEAKER_0:  driving your comfortable Toyota car.
SPEAKER_0:  That's that's.
SPEAKER_0:  that you've had for a hundred thousand miles and you know what every little rattle of the car means.
SPEAKER_0:  I was very comfortable in Emacs, but there were certain things it couldn't do. It wasn't very good at...
SPEAKER_0:  That's sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  At least.
SPEAKER_0:  the way I had configured it.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't have very good tooling in Emacs for finding the definition of a function.
SPEAKER_0:  Got it.
SPEAKER_0:  when I was at Dropbox.
SPEAKER_0:  Exploring a 5 million line.
SPEAKER_0:  Python code base.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  just grabbing all that code for where is there a class foobar.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, turns out that if you grab all five million lines of code...
SPEAKER_0:  There are many classes with the same name.
SPEAKER_0:  And so PyCharm sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  once.
SPEAKER_0:  once you fired it up and once it's indexed.
SPEAKER_0:  your repository.
SPEAKER_0:  It was very helpful.
SPEAKER_0:  But as soon as I had to edit code...
SPEAKER_0:  jump back to Emacs and do all my editing there because I could type much faster and switch between files.
SPEAKER_0:  when I knew which file I wanted much quicker. I never really got used to that.
SPEAKER_0:  the whole PyCharm user interface.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I feel torn in that same kind of way, because I've used...
SPEAKER_1:  PyCharm off and on exactly in that same way.
SPEAKER_1:  and I feel like I'm just being a-
SPEAKER_1:  an old grumpy man.
SPEAKER_1:  for not learning how to quickly switch between files and all that kind of stuff. I feel like that has to do with shortcuts, has to do with...
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, you just have to get accustomed, just like with touch typing.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, you have to just want to learn that. I mean, if you don't need it much.
SPEAKER_1:  You don't need touch typing either.
SPEAKER_1:  You can type with two fingers just fine in the short term, but in the long term your life will...
SPEAKER_1:  become.
SPEAKER_1:  better.
SPEAKER_1:  psychologically and productivity wise if you learn how to type with 10 fingers.
SPEAKER_0:  if you do a lot of keyboard input.
SPEAKER_1:  but for everyone emails and stuff, right? Like you look at the.
SPEAKER_1:  The next.
SPEAKER_1:  20, 30 years of your life, you have to anticipate where technology is going.
SPEAKER_1:  Um
SPEAKER_1:  Do you want to invest in handwriting notes?
SPEAKER_1:  Probably not.
SPEAKER_1:  more and more people are doing typing versus.
SPEAKER_1:  handwriting notes.
SPEAKER_1:  So you can anticipate that.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's no reason to actually practice handwriting. There's more reason to practice typing.
SPEAKER_1:  you can actually estimate back to the spreadsheet the number of
SPEAKER_1:  paragraphs.
SPEAKER_1:  sentences or words you write.
SPEAKER_1:  for the rest of your life.
SPEAKER_1:  You best-
SPEAKER_0:  Here we go again with the spreadsheet of my life, huh?
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, all of that is not actual like converted to a spreadsheet, but the gut feeling.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I have the same kind of gut feeling about books.
SPEAKER_1:  I've almost exclusively switched to Kindle now for ebook readers.
SPEAKER_1:  even though I still love.
SPEAKER_1:  and probably always will, the smell, the feel of a physical book.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  You, the reason I switched to Kindle is like, all right, well, this is really paving.
SPEAKER_1:  the future is going to be.
SPEAKER_1:  digital in terms of consuming.
SPEAKER_1:  books and content of that nature. So you should get, you know, you should let your brain get accustomed to that experience.
SPEAKER_1:  And that same way...
SPEAKER_1:  It feels like pie charm or VS code. I think by charmers.
SPEAKER_1:  the most sophisticated, featureful.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Python ID.
SPEAKER_1:  It feels like.
SPEAKER_1:  I should probably at some point very soon.
SPEAKER_1:  switch entire like I'm not allowed to use anything else for Python.
SPEAKER_1:  than this ID.
SPEAKER_1:  or VS code, it doesn't matter, but walk away from Emacs for this particular application.
SPEAKER_1:  I think I'm limiting myself.
SPEAKER_1:  in the same way that using two fingers for typing is limiting myself.
SPEAKER_1:  This is a therapy session. This isn't maybe
SPEAKER_0:  But I'm sure a lot of people are thinking of this one, right? I can't stop you, I-
SPEAKER_0:  I think that that sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  Everybody has to decide for themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  which one they want to to invest more time in.
SPEAKER_0:  I actually...
SPEAKER_0:  ended up giving VS Code a very tentative try.
SPEAKER_0:  when I started out at Microsoft and really liking it.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It sort of, it.
SPEAKER_0:  Took me a while before I realized why that was.
SPEAKER_0:  but.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think that actually the founders of VS code may not necessarily agree with me on this.
SPEAKER_0:  to me.
SPEAKER_0:  VS Code is in a sense the spiritual successor of Emacs.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  As you probably know as an old Emacs hack.
SPEAKER_0:  The key part of Emacs is that it's mostly written in Lisp.
SPEAKER_0:  And that sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  New features of Emacs usually.
SPEAKER_0:  Update all the list packages.
SPEAKER_0:  and add new list packages.
SPEAKER_0:  And oh yeah, there's also...
SPEAKER_0:  some very obscure thing improved in the part that's not in Lisp.
SPEAKER_0:  That's usually not why you would upgrade to a new version of Emacs.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a.
SPEAKER_0:  Core implementation.
SPEAKER_0:  That's sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  can read a file and it can put bits on the screen and it can.
SPEAKER_0:  sort of manage memory and buffers.
SPEAKER_0:  and then what makes it
SPEAKER_0:  An editor full of features is all the list packages.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course the design of how the list packages interact with
SPEAKER_0:  each other and with that sort of the base layer.
SPEAKER_0:  of the core immutable engine. But almost everything in that core engine in Emacs case can still be.
SPEAKER_0:  overridden or replaced.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  VS code has a similar architecture where there is like.
SPEAKER_0:  Bass Engine.
SPEAKER_0:  that you have no control over.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean it's open source but nobody...
SPEAKER_0:  except the people who work on that part.
SPEAKER_0:  It changes it much.
SPEAKER_0:  and it has a sort of a package manager.
SPEAKER_0:  and a whole series of interfaces for packages and an additional series of
SPEAKER_0:  conventions for how packages should interact with the lower layers and with each other.
SPEAKER_0:  and powerful primitive operations that let you...
SPEAKER_0:  move the cursor around or select pieces of text or delete pieces of text or
SPEAKER_0:  interact with the keyboard and mouse and whatever peripherals you have.
SPEAKER_0:  And so the sort of the.
SPEAKER_0:  extreme extensibility.
SPEAKER_0:  and the package ecosystem.
SPEAKER_0:  that you see in VS code is a mirror of very similar.
SPEAKER_0:  architectural features in Emacs.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I'll have to give it a serious try.
SPEAKER_1:  Kazoo.
SPEAKER_1:  As far as sort of the hype and the excitement in the general programming community VS code seems to dominate.
SPEAKER_1:  interesting thing about
SPEAKER_1:  Pie Charm and
SPEAKER_1:  What is it? Which should be Storm, which are these jet brains?
SPEAKER_1:  uh... specific ideas that design for one programming language
SPEAKER_1:  It's interesting too.
SPEAKER_1:  when an ID is specialized.
SPEAKER_0:  They're usually...
SPEAKER_0:  actually just specializations of IntelliJ because underneath it's all the same.
SPEAKER_0:  editing engine with.
SPEAKER_0:  different.
SPEAKER_0:  veneer on top.
SPEAKER_0:  where in VS Code
SPEAKER_0:  many things you do.
SPEAKER_0:  REQUIRE
SPEAKER_0:  loading third party extensions.
SPEAKER_0:  In PyCharm, it is possible to have third-party extensions.
SPEAKER_0:  But it is.
SPEAKER_0:  It is a struggle to create one.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, we.
SPEAKER_1:  culture all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, we that I remember that
SPEAKER_0:  might have been five years ago or so we were.
SPEAKER_0:  trying to get some.
SPEAKER_0:  better MyPy integration into PyCharm.
SPEAKER_0:  because my pie is sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  Python tooling and PyCharm.
SPEAKER_0:  had its own.
SPEAKER_0:  type checking heuristic thing that we wanted to replace with something based on MyPy because that was what we were using in the company and it
SPEAKER_0:  for the...
SPEAKER_0:  guy who was writing that.
SPEAKER_0:  by charm extension it was really a struggle to sort of
SPEAKER_0:  find documentation and
SPEAKER_0:  get the development workflow.
SPEAKER_0:  going and debug his code and all that. So that was not a pleasant experience.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me talk to you about.
SPEAKER_1:  Prell-ism.
SPEAKER_1:  in your post titled reasoning about async IO semaphore.
SPEAKER_1:  You talk about a fast food restaurant in Silicon Valley that has only one table. Is this a real thing? I just wanted to ask you about that.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that just like a metaphor you're using or is that an actual restaurant?
SPEAKER_1:  and so it was.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a metaphor, of course.
SPEAKER_1:  I can imagine such a restaurant.
SPEAKER_1:  So for people who don't...
SPEAKER_1:  then read the thing you should.
SPEAKER_1:  But it was a...
SPEAKER_1:  idea of a restaurant where there's only one table and you show up.
SPEAKER_1:  one at a time.
SPEAKER_1:  and they are prepared.
SPEAKER_1:  And I actually looked it up and there is restaurants like this throughout the world.
SPEAKER_1:  And it just seems like a fascinating idea. You stand in line, you show up, there's one table.
SPEAKER_1:  They are...
SPEAKER_1:  They ask you all kinds of questions. They cook just for you.
SPEAKER_1:  That's fascinating. Do you understand what I'm trying to explain?
SPEAKER_0:  like you'd find places like that in Tokyo.
SPEAKER_0:  It sounds like a very Japanese thing. Or in the Bay Area there are pop places that probably more or less work like that. I've never eaten at such a place.
SPEAKER_1:  The fascinating thing is you propose as a fast food. This is off for a br-
SPEAKER_0:  It was one of my rare
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  more literary or
SPEAKER_0:  poetic moments where I thought I'll just...
SPEAKER_0:  Open with a crazy example.
SPEAKER_0:  too.
SPEAKER_0:  catch your attention and the rest is very dry stuff about
SPEAKER_0:  locks and semaphores and how a semaphore is a generalization of the lock.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, it was very poetic and well delivered and it actually made me wonder if it's real or not because you don't make that explicit
SPEAKER_1:  And it feels like it could be true. And in fact, I wouldn't be surprised if somebody like listens to this and knows exactly a restaurant like this in Silicon Valley.
SPEAKER_1:  Anyway.
SPEAKER_1:  Can we step back and...
SPEAKER_1:  Can you just talk about...
SPEAKER_1:  Parallelism.
SPEAKER_1:  concurrency threading.
SPEAKER_1:  asynchronous all these different terms.
SPEAKER_1:  What is it? What is it?
SPEAKER_1:  The fisherman is back on the boat.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, the idea is if the fisherman has two fishing rods...
SPEAKER_0:  Since fishing is mostly a matter of waiting for fish to nibble.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it depends on how you do it actually, but if you had two f-
SPEAKER_0:  If you're doing the style of fishing where you sort of, you throw it out and then...
SPEAKER_0:  You let it sit for a while until maybe you see a nibble.
SPEAKER_0:  One fisherman can easily run two or three or four.
SPEAKER_0:  fishing rods.
SPEAKER_0:  And so as long as you can.
SPEAKER_0:  Afford the equipment you can catch four times as many fish by
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Small investment in for fishing rods and so get since your time.
SPEAKER_0:  You sort of say you have all Saturday to go fishing.
SPEAKER_0:  if you can catch four times as much fish.
SPEAKER_0:  you have a much higher productivity.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's actually, I think, how deep sea fishing is done. You could just have a rod and you put in a hole so you can have many rods.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  What is there an interesting difference between
SPEAKER_1:  Parallelism and concurrency?
SPEAKER_1:  and asynchronous?...
SPEAKER_1:  one is subset of the other to you. Like how do you think about these terms?
SPEAKER_0:  In the computer world there is a
SPEAKER_0:  Big difference.
SPEAKER_0:  when people are talking about
SPEAKER_0:  Parallelism.
SPEAKER_0:  like a parallel computer.
SPEAKER_0:  That's usually really...
SPEAKER_0:  several complete CPUs that are
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  tied together and.
SPEAKER_0:  share something like memory or an IO bus.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, concurrency.
SPEAKER_0:  can be a much more abstract concept.
SPEAKER_0:  where...
SPEAKER_0:  You have the illusion that things happen.
SPEAKER_0:  simultaneously but what the computer actually does is
SPEAKER_0:  It spends a little time running.
SPEAKER_0:  some this program for a while and then it spends some time running that program for a while and then spending some time for the third program.
SPEAKER_1:  for a while.
SPEAKER_1:  So parallelism is the...
SPEAKER_1:  reality and concurrency.
SPEAKER_1:  part reality part o-
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, parallelism typically...
SPEAKER_0:  implies that there is multiple copies of the hardware.
SPEAKER_1:  You write that implementing synchronization primitives is hard in that blog post. You talk about locks and semaphores.
SPEAKER_1:  Why is it hard to implement?
SPEAKER_1:  synchronization primitive.
SPEAKER_0:  because
SPEAKER_0:  At the conscious level our brains are not.
SPEAKER_0:  trained to sort of keep track of multiple things.
SPEAKER_0:  the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, obviously you can walk and chew gum at the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  Because they're both.
SPEAKER_0:  activities that.
SPEAKER_0:  require only a little bit of your conscious
SPEAKER_0:  activity but try balancing your checkbook.
SPEAKER_0:  and watching a murder mystery on TV.
SPEAKER_0:  you'll mix up the digits or you'll miss an essential clue in the TV show.
SPEAKER_1:  So why does it matter that the programmer, the human...
SPEAKER_1:  is bad.
SPEAKER_0:  Because the programmer is...
SPEAKER_0:  at least with the current state of the art, is responsible for...
SPEAKER_0:  writing the code correctly.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's hard enough.
SPEAKER_0:  to keep track of.
SPEAKER_0:  A recipe that you just
SPEAKER_0:  Execute one step at a time.
SPEAKER_0:  Chop the carrots.
SPEAKER_0:  Then peel the potatoes.
SPEAKER_0:  Mix the icing.
SPEAKER_0:  You need your whole brain.
SPEAKER_0:  when you're reading a piece of code.
SPEAKER_0:  What is going on? Okay, we're...
SPEAKER_0:  We're loading.
SPEAKER_0:  The number of mermaids in variable A and the number of mermen in variable B, and now we take the average or whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  I like how we're just jumping from metaphor to metaphor.
SPEAKER_0:  I like it.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to keep in your head what is in A, what is in B.
SPEAKER_0:  What is NC?
SPEAKER_0:  Hopefully you have better names.
SPEAKER_0:  And that is challenging enough.
SPEAKER_0:  If you have two.
SPEAKER_0:  different
SPEAKER_0:  pieces of code that are
SPEAKER_0:  are sort of
SPEAKER_0:  being executed.
SPEAKER_0:  simultaneously, whether it's using the parallel or the concurrent.
SPEAKER_0:  approach.
SPEAKER_0:  if like...
SPEAKER_0:  A is the number of fishermen and B is the number of programmers.
SPEAKER_0:  But in another part of the code, A is the number of mermaids and B is the number of merman.
SPEAKER_0:  and somehow...
SPEAKER_0:  that's the same variable if you do it sequentially if first you do your mermaid
SPEAKER_0:  More people computation and then you do your people in the boat computation.
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't matter that-
SPEAKER_0:  the variables are called A and B and that is literally the same variable because you're done with one use of that variable but
SPEAKER_0:  When you mix them together.
SPEAKER_0:  Suddenly.
SPEAKER_0:  The number of merpeople replaces the number of fishermen and your computation goes...
SPEAKER_0:  dramatically wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  and there's all kinds of ordering.
SPEAKER_1:  operations that could result in the assignment of those variables and so you have to anticipate all possible orders
SPEAKER_0:  And you think you're smart and you'll put a lock around it.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  In practice.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of bugs per line of per thousand lines of code.
SPEAKER_0:  This is an area where everything is worse.
SPEAKER_1:  So a lock is a...
SPEAKER_1:  mechanism by which
SPEAKER_1:  You forbid only one.
SPEAKER_1:  Chef can access the oven at a time.
SPEAKER_1:  Something like that.
SPEAKER_1:  And then semaphores allow you to do what? Multiple ovens?
SPEAKER_0:  That's not a bad idea because if you're sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  If you're preparing, if you're baking cakes and you have multiple people all...
SPEAKER_0:  baking cakes but there's only one oven.
SPEAKER_0:  then maybe you can tell that the oven is in use, but maybe it's preheating. And so you have to, maybe you make a sign that says oven in use.
SPEAKER_0:  And you flip the sign over and it says often is free when you're done baking your cake.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's a lock that sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  and what do you do?
SPEAKER_0:  when...
SPEAKER_0:  You have two ovens, or maybe you have ten ovens.
SPEAKER_0:  You can put a separate sign on each oven or maybe you can...
SPEAKER_0:  sort of someone who comes in wants to see at a glance.
SPEAKER_0:  and maybe there's an electronic sign that says there are still five ovens available.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... or maybe they're already
SPEAKER_0:  three people waiting for an oven so you can't...
SPEAKER_0:  If you see an oven that's not in use, it's already reserved for someone else who got in line first.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's sort of what the restaurant metaphor was trying to explain.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. And so you're now tasks you sitting as a designer of Python.
SPEAKER_1:  with a team of brilliant core developers have to try to figure out
SPEAKER_1:  To what degree can any of these ideas be integrated and not?
SPEAKER_1:  So maybe this is a good time to ask what is async IO?
SPEAKER_1:  and how has it evolved since Python 3.4?
SPEAKER_0:  Wow, yeah, so we had this really old library for
SPEAKER_0:  for doing things.
SPEAKER_0:  Concurrently, especially things that had to do with I.O. and networking I.O. was especially a sort of a popular topic.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  In the Python standard library, we had a...
SPEAKER_0:  someone breathe
SPEAKER_0:  period where there was lots of development.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think it was late 90s, maybe early 2000s and like...
SPEAKER_0:  Two little modules were added that were the state of the art of doing asynchronous IO or sort of non-blocking IO, which means that you can keep multiple network connections open and sort of service them.
SPEAKER_0:  all in parallel like a typical web server does.
SPEAKER_1:  So I always input an output so you're writing either to.
SPEAKER_1:  the network and re-establishment network connection.
SPEAKER_1:  or reading and writing to a hard drive, storage. Also possible. And you can do.
SPEAKER_1:  the ideas you could do to multiple
SPEAKER_1:  while also doing computation.
SPEAKER_1:  running some code that does some fancy stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, like when you're writing a web server.
SPEAKER_0:  when a request comes in a user.
SPEAKER_0:  Assertive.
SPEAKER_0:  needs to see a particular webpage.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to find that page maybe in the database and format it properly and send it back to the client.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a lot of waiting, waiting for the database, waiting for the network. And so you can handle hundreds or thousands or millions of requests.
SPEAKER_0:  concurrently on Lawn Machine anyway.
SPEAKER_0:  Ways of doing that in Python were kind of stagnated and, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I forget they might have been around.
SPEAKER_0:  20
SPEAKER_0:  2012-2014.
SPEAKER_0:  Uhhh
SPEAKER_0:  when someone for the umpteenth time actually said
SPEAKER_0:  these async chats.
SPEAKER_0:  And async core modules that you have in a standard library are not quite enough to solve my particular problem.
SPEAKER_0:  Can we add one tiny little feature?
SPEAKER_0:  And everybody said...
SPEAKER_0:  No, that stuff is not to be, you're not supposed to use that stuff. Write your own using a third party library. And then everybody started the debate about what the right third party library was.
SPEAKER_0:  And somehow I-
SPEAKER_0:  I-
SPEAKER_0:  felt that.
SPEAKER_0:  that was actually...
SPEAKER_0:  a cue for well maybe we need a
SPEAKER_0:  better state of the art.
SPEAKER_0:  module in the standard library for multiplexing input output from different sources.
SPEAKER_0:  You could say that it spiraled out of control a little bit. It was at the time it was the largest.
SPEAKER_0:  Python enhancement proposal that was ever proposed.
SPEAKER_1:  and you were deeply involved with that.
SPEAKER_0:  At the time I was very much involved with that. I was like the lead architect.
SPEAKER_0:  I ended up
SPEAKER_0:  talking to people who had already developed serious third party
SPEAKER_0:  libraries that did similar things and sort of taking ideas from them.
SPEAKER_0:  getting their feedback on my design and eventually we...
SPEAKER_0:  put it in the standard library and after a few years I got distracted. I think the big thing that distracted me was actually type annotations.
SPEAKER_0:  But other people kept it alive and kicking and it's been quite successful actually.
SPEAKER_0:  in the world of Python web clients.
SPEAKER_1:  So initially, what are some of the...
SPEAKER_1:  the sign challenges there in that debate for the pep.
SPEAKER_1:  And what are some things that got rejected? What are some things that got accepted that stand out to you?
SPEAKER_0:  There are a couple of different ways you can...
SPEAKER_0:  handle parallel I O and this happened sort of at an architectural level in operating systems as well like windows
SPEAKER_0:  prefers to do it one way and unix prefers to do it the other way.
SPEAKER_0:  You sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  You have an object that represents a network endpoint.
SPEAKER_0:  say, a connection with a web browser that your client.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Say you're waiting for an incoming request.
SPEAKER_0:  Two fundamental approaches are...
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, I'm waiting for an incoming request. I'm doing something else.
SPEAKER_0:  Come wake me up or come tell me when something interesting happened, like a packet came in on that network connection.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  D.
SPEAKER_0:  Other
SPEAKER_0:  paradigm is
SPEAKER_0:  We're on a team of a whole bunch of...
SPEAKER_0:  people with maybe a little mind and we can only manage one web connection at a time.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm just sitting.
SPEAKER_0:  looking at this
SPEAKER_0:  this web connection and I'm just blocked.
SPEAKER_0:  until...
SPEAKER_0:  something comes in and then.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm already waiting for it.
SPEAKER_0:  I get the data, I process the data, and then I go back to the top and say no.
SPEAKER_0:  sort of, I'm waiting for the next packet.
SPEAKER_0:  Those are about the two paradigms. The one is...
SPEAKER_0:  a paradigm where there is sort of notionally a thread of control, whether it's an actual operating system thread or more an abstraction in async IO we call them tasks.
SPEAKER_0:  But a task in async.io or a thread in other contexts is devoted to one thing.
SPEAKER_0:  and it has logic.
SPEAKER_0:  for all the stages, like when it's a web request, like.
SPEAKER_0:  First wait for the first line of the web request, parse it because then you know if it's a get or a post or a put or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  or an error.
SPEAKER_0:  Then wait until you have a bunch of lines until there's a blank line, then parse that as headers and then
SPEAKER_0:  interpret that and then wait for the rest of the...
SPEAKER_0:  data to come in if there is any more that you expect. That's sort of standard web.
SPEAKER_0:  stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  And the other thing is, and there's always endless debate about which approach is more efficient and which approach is more error prone.
SPEAKER_0:  where I just have a whole bunch of stacks in front of me and whenever
SPEAKER_0:  A packet comes in, I sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  look at the number of the pack that there's some number on the packet and I say oh that packet goes on this
SPEAKER_0:  file.
SPEAKER_0:  And then I can do a little bit and then sort of that pile provides my context.
SPEAKER_0:  And as soon as I'm done with the processing, I sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  I can't forget everything about what's going on because the next packet will come in from some random other client and it's that pile or this pile.
SPEAKER_0:  And every time a pile is maybe empty or full or whatever the criteria is, I can toss it away or...
SPEAKER_0:  use it for a new space but
SPEAKER_0:  several traditional
SPEAKER_0:  Third-party libraries for asynchronous I-O processing in Python chose the model of a callback.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's the idea where you have a bunch of different...
SPEAKER_0:  stacks of paper in front of you and every time someone gives you a piece
SPEAKER_0:  gives you new sheet.
SPEAKER_0:  you decide which stack it belongs to.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  leads to a certain style of spaghetti code that.
SPEAKER_0:  I find sort of aesthetically.
SPEAKER_0:  not pleasing and I was sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  never very successful and I had heard many stories about people who were also
SPEAKER_0:  sort of complaining about that style of coding.
SPEAKER_0:  It was very prevalent in javascript at the time at least because it was like.
SPEAKER_0:  How did JavaScript event loop?
SPEAKER_0:  basically works.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I thought.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, the task-based model where...
SPEAKER_0:  Each task has a bunch of logic.
SPEAKER_0:  We had mechanisms in the Python language that we could easily reuse.
SPEAKER_0:  for that. And I thought, I want to build a whole-
SPEAKER_0:  Library for Asynchronous Networking I.O.
SPEAKER_0:  and all the other things that may need to be done asynchronously.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, based on that paradigm.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I just chose a paradigm and.
SPEAKER_0:  try to see how far I could get with that. And it turns out that it's a pretty good paradigm.
SPEAKER_0:  So people enjoy that.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of paradigm programming for asynchronous.
SPEAKER_1:  I.O.
SPEAKER_1:  relative to callbacks.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, beautiful. So how does that all interplay with.
SPEAKER_1:  the infamous Gill, the global interpreter Locke.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe can you say what the gil is and how does it dance?
SPEAKER_1:  beautifully with Ace and Kaio.
SPEAKER_0:  The global interpreter luck.
SPEAKER_0:  solves the problem that Python originally was not written with either asynchronous or
SPEAKER_0:  or.
SPEAKER_0:  parallelism in mind at all there was no concurrency in the language there was no parallelism there were no
SPEAKER_0:  threads.
SPEAKER_0:  only a small number of years into Python's initial development.
SPEAKER_0:  all the new cool operating systems like SunOS and Silicon Graphics, IRIX and then
SPEAKER_0:  Eventually POSIX and Windows all came with threading libraries.
SPEAKER_0:  that lets you do multiple things in parallel. And there is a certain...
SPEAKER_0:  Certain sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  principle which is
SPEAKER_0:  The operating system handles the threads for you.
SPEAKER_0:  and the program
SPEAKER_0:  can pretend that there are as many CPUs as...
SPEAKER_0:  as there are threads in the program.
SPEAKER_0:  and those CPUs work completely independently.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you don't have enough CPUs to...
SPEAKER_0:  operating system sort of simulates.
SPEAKER_0:  those extra CPUs. On the other hand, if you have enough CPUs...
SPEAKER_0:  you can get a lot of work done.
SPEAKER_0:  by deploying those multiple CPUs.
SPEAKER_0:  But Python wasn't written.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  to do that.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  S
SPEAKER_0:  libraries for for multi threading were added to see.
SPEAKER_0:  but every operating system vendor was adding their own version of that.
SPEAKER_0:  we thought, and maybe we were wrong, but at the time we thought, well, we quickly want to be able to support these multiple threads.
SPEAKER_0:  because they seemed at the time in the early 90s when they were new at least to me.
SPEAKER_0:  they seemed a cool interesting programming paradigm.
SPEAKER_0:  And one of the things that Python, at least at the time...
SPEAKER_0:  felt was nice about the language was that we could give a
SPEAKER_0:  safe version of all kinds of...
SPEAKER_0:  cool new operating system toys.
SPEAKER_0:  to the Python programmer, like I remember.
SPEAKER_0:  one or two years.
SPEAKER_0:  Before threading, I had spent some time adding networking sockets.
SPEAKER_0:  to Python and they were very literal translation of the networking sockets that were in the BSD operating system so Unix BSD.
SPEAKER_0:  But the nice thing was if you're using sockets from Python...
SPEAKER_0:  then all the things you can do wrong with sockets in C would automatically give you a clear error message instead of just ending up with a malfunctioning hanging program.
SPEAKER_0:  And so we thought, well, we'll do the same thing with threading.
SPEAKER_0:  But we didn't really want to rewrite the interpreter.
SPEAKER_0:  to be thread safe because that was...
SPEAKER_0:  bus like.
SPEAKER_0:  That would be a very complex refactoring of all the interpreter code and all the runtime code.
SPEAKER_0:  because all the objects were written with the assumption that there's only one.
SPEAKER_0:  And so we said, okay, well.
SPEAKER_0:  We'll take our losses, we'll provide...
SPEAKER_0:  something that looks like threads.
SPEAKER_0:  And as long as you only have a single CPU on your computer, which most computers at the time did.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  It feels just like threads because...
SPEAKER_0:  The whole idea of multiple threads in the OS was that even if your computer only had one CPU you could still fire up as many threads as you wanted.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, within reason, maybe 10 or 12, not 5000.
SPEAKER_0:  And so
SPEAKER_0:  we thought we had conquered the
SPEAKER_0:  the abstraction of threads pretty well because multi.
SPEAKER_0:  core CPUs were not in.
SPEAKER_0:  in most Python programmers' hands anyway.
SPEAKER_0:  And then of course, a couple of more iterations of Moore's Law and the computer is getting faster and at some point...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Duh.
SPEAKER_0:  Chip designers decided that they...
SPEAKER_0:  couldn't make the CPUs faster but they could still make them smaller and so they could put multiple CPUs on one chip.
SPEAKER_0:  And suddenly there was all this pressure.
SPEAKER_0:  about.
SPEAKER_0:  do things in parallel and that's where the
SPEAKER_0:  the solution we had in Python didn't work.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's sort of the moment that the gill became...
SPEAKER_0:  became infamous.
SPEAKER_0:  Because the guilt was the solution we used to sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  take this single interpreter and share it between all the different operating system traps that you could create.
SPEAKER_0:  And so as long as the...
SPEAKER_0:  Hardware physically only had one CPU, that was all fine.
SPEAKER_0:  and then S.
SPEAKER_0:  hardware vendors were suddenly telling us all, oh you gotta paralyze.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything's gotta be paralyzed.
SPEAKER_0:  people started saying, oh.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, but...
SPEAKER_0:  We can use multiple threads in Python and then they discovered, oh, but actually all threads run on a single core.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, is there a way...
SPEAKER_1:  Is there ideas in the future to remove?
SPEAKER_1:  the global interpreter log Gil.
SPEAKER_1:  like maybe multiple sub interpreters.
SPEAKER_1:  Some tricky.
SPEAKER_1:  interpreters on top of interpreters kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there are a couple of...
SPEAKER_0:  possible futures there.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  The most likely future is that we'll get multiple sub-interpreters.
SPEAKER_0:  which each run a completely independent Python program.
SPEAKER_0:  Nice. But there there's still some benefit of
SPEAKER_0:  of Surtuf.
SPEAKER_0:  faster communication between
SPEAKER_1:  those programs. But it's also managing for you this.
SPEAKER_1:  running on multiple Python programs.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so it's hidden from you, right?
SPEAKER_0:  It's hidden from you, but you have to spend more time communicating between those programs, because this sort of-
SPEAKER_0:  The attractive.
SPEAKER_0:  thing about the multi-threaded model is that the threads can share objects.
SPEAKER_0:  At the same time, that's also the downfall of the multithreaded programming model.
SPEAKER_0:  because when you do, share objects.
SPEAKER_0:  you weren't and you didn't necessarily intend to share them or.
SPEAKER_0:  There were aspects of those objects that
SPEAKER_0:  were not reusable, you get all kinds of concurrency bugs.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  The reason I wrote that little blog post about semaphores was that
SPEAKER_0:  concurrency bugs are just harder.
SPEAKER_0:  It would be nice if Python had
SPEAKER_0:  No global interpreter lock and it had so-called free threading.
SPEAKER_0:  but it would also cause a lot more software bugs.
SPEAKER_0:  The interesting thing is that there is still a possible future where we are actually going to or where we could experiment at least with that.
SPEAKER_0:  because there is a...
SPEAKER_0:  Guy working for Facebook.
SPEAKER_0:  who has developed a fork of CPython.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  he called the no-gill.
SPEAKER_0:  interpreter.
SPEAKER_0:  where he removed the gill.
SPEAKER_0:  and made a whole bunch of optimizations so that the single threaded case doesn't run too much slower.
SPEAKER_0:  and multi-threaded case will actually use all the cores that you have.
SPEAKER_0:  And so that would be an interesting possibility.
SPEAKER_0:  If we...
SPEAKER_0:  would be willing as a
SPEAKER_0:  Python Core developers to actually.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... maintain that code indefinitely
SPEAKER_0:  And if we're willing to put up with the...
SPEAKER_0:  additional complexity of the interpreter and the additional sort of overhead for the single threaded case and
SPEAKER_0:  I'm personally not convinced.
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  There are enough people.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, kneading.
SPEAKER_0:  the speed of multiple threads.
SPEAKER_0:  with their Python programs.
SPEAKER_0:  that it's worth to sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  take that performance hit and that complexity hit.
SPEAKER_0:  And I feel that the gill actually is pretty nice.
SPEAKER_0:  Goldilocks point between no threads and all threads all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  But not everybody agrees on that, so...
SPEAKER_0:  that is definitely a possible future. What do sub-interpreters look like?
SPEAKER_0:  a fairly safe bet for 312, so...
SPEAKER_0:  say a year from now.
SPEAKER_1:  year so the goal is to do a new version every year.
SPEAKER_1:  for Python.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask you perhaps a fun question but-
SPEAKER_1:  There's a philosophy to it too.
SPEAKER_1:  Will there ever be a Python 4.0?
SPEAKER_1:  Now.
SPEAKER_1:  Before you say, it's currently a joke.
SPEAKER_1:  and probably not.
SPEAKER_1:  So we're gonna go to 3.99.
SPEAKER_1:  or 3.9999.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you imagine possible features?
SPEAKER_1:  that Python 4.0 might have.
SPEAKER_1:  that would.
SPEAKER_1:  and necessitate the creation.
SPEAKER_1:  of the new 4.0.
SPEAKER_1:  given the amount of
SPEAKER_1:  Pain and Joy.
SPEAKER_1:  suffering and triumph that was involved in the move between.
SPEAKER_1:  Version 2 and version 3.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, well worked.
SPEAKER_0:  We.
SPEAKER_0:  As a community and as a core development team, we have a large amount of
SPEAKER_0:  painful memories about the Python 3 transition.
SPEAKER_0:  which is one reason that sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  Everybody is happy that we've decided.
SPEAKER_0:  There's not going to be a 4.0 at least.
SPEAKER_0:  not anytime soon and if there is going to be one that will sort of plan the transition very differently.
SPEAKER_0:  because clearly we underestimated...
SPEAKER_0:  the pain, the transition.
SPEAKER_0:  caused for our users in the Python 3 case.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  had we known we could have
SPEAKER_0:  sort of designed.
SPEAKER_0:  Python 3 somewhat differently without making it any worse.
SPEAKER_0:  We just.
SPEAKER_0:  thought that we had a good plan but we
SPEAKER_0:  We underestimated where.
SPEAKER_0:  But what sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  the users were capable of when it comes to that kind of transition.
SPEAKER_1:  By the way, I think we talked.
SPEAKER_1:  way before, like a year and a half before.
SPEAKER_1:  the Python 2 officially.
SPEAKER_1:  End of life. End of life. End of life.
SPEAKER_1:  What was that? What was your memory of the end of life? Did you shed a tear on January 1st, 2020?
SPEAKER_1:  It was there.
SPEAKER_1:  Everyone
SPEAKER_0:  The core team had basically moved on years before.
SPEAKER_0:  It was purely, it was a little symbolic moment.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... to signal to the the remaining users
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  There was no longer going to
SPEAKER_0:  be any new releases or support for Python 2.7.
SPEAKER_1:  Did you shed a single tear while looking out over the horizon?
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not a very poetic person and I don't shed tears like that, but no.
SPEAKER_0:  We actually had planned a party, but the party was planned for the US Python conference that year, which would never happen, of course, because of the pandemic.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, was it like in March? It was 20. The conference was going to be, I think, late April that year.
SPEAKER_1:  out
SPEAKER_1:  So that was a...
SPEAKER_0:  It's a very difficult decision to cancel it, but...
SPEAKER_0:  They did. Anyway, if we're going to have a Python four, we're going to have to have both a different reason for.
SPEAKER_0:  for having that.
SPEAKER_0:  and a different process for managing the transition.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you imagine a possible process?
SPEAKER_1:  that so.
SPEAKER_1:  So I think you're implying that if there's a 4.0 in some ways it would break.
SPEAKER_1:  back compatibility.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, so...
SPEAKER_0:  Here is a concrete thought I've had.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm not unique, but not everyone agrees.
SPEAKER_0:  with this, so this is definitely a personal opinion.
SPEAKER_0:  If we were to try something...
SPEAKER_0:  like that no-gill python?
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  My expectation is that...
SPEAKER_0:  It would feel...
SPEAKER_0:  Just
SPEAKER_0:  Different enough.
SPEAKER_0:  at least for the part of the Python ecosystem that...
SPEAKER_0:  is heavily based on C extensions.
SPEAKER_0:  And that is like the entire machine learning data science scientific Python.
SPEAKER_0:  World is all based on C extensions for Python.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  Those people would likely feel the pain.
SPEAKER_0:  the most.
SPEAKER_0:  Because they-
SPEAKER_0:  even if we don't change.
SPEAKER_0:  Anything about the syntax of the language and the semantics of the language when you're writing Python code
SPEAKER_0:  We could even say, suppose that after Python, say, 3.19 instead of 3.20, we'll have 4.0.
SPEAKER_0:  Suppose that's the time when we.
SPEAKER_0:  Flip the switch to 4.0 will not have a gil.
SPEAKER_0:  Imagine it was like that.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I would probably say...
SPEAKER_0:  That particular year, the release that we name 4.0 will be syntactically
SPEAKER_0:  it will not have any new syntactical features.
SPEAKER_0:  No new modules in the standard library, no new built-in functions.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything will be.
SPEAKER_0:  at the Python level will be purely compatible.
SPEAKER_0:  with Python 3.19.
SPEAKER_0:  However,
SPEAKER_0:  Extension modules
SPEAKER_0:  We'll have to.
SPEAKER_0:  make a change. They will have to be recompiled. They will not have the same.
SPEAKER_0:  Binary.
SPEAKER_0:  interface.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  the semantics and APIs for some.
SPEAKER_0:  things that are frequently accessed by C extensions will be different.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  for a pure Python user.
SPEAKER_0:  4.0 would be a breeze.
SPEAKER_0:  except that there are very few pure Python users left because everybody who is using Python for something significant is using
SPEAKER_0:  third party extensions there are like I don't know
SPEAKER_0:  several hundreds of thousands of third party extensions on the
SPEAKER_0:  the PyPI service.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm not saying they're all good, but...
SPEAKER_0:  there is a large list of extensions that would have to do work. And some of those extensions are
SPEAKER_0:  currently already low on maintainers.
SPEAKER_0:  and they're struggling to work.
SPEAKER_1:  Keep afloat.
SPEAKER_1:  So there you can give a huge heads up to them if you go to 4.0.
SPEAKER_1:  to really keep developing it.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, we probably have to do something like.
SPEAKER_0:  several years before, who knows, maybe five years earlier, like 3.15.
SPEAKER_0:  we would have to say...
SPEAKER_0:  and and i'm just making that that specific numbers up but we did at some point we have to say
SPEAKER_0:  the Nogil Python could be an option.
SPEAKER_0:  It might be a compile time option.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  If you want to.
SPEAKER_0:  Use Nogil, Python.
SPEAKER_0:  you have to recompile Python from source for your platform using your toolset.
SPEAKER_0:  All you have to do is change one configuration variable, and then you just run make.
SPEAKER_0:  or configure and make and it will build it for you.
SPEAKER_0:  but now you also have to use the
SPEAKER_0:  the no-gill compatible versions of all extension modules you want to use.
SPEAKER_0:  And so as long as many extension modules don't have fully functional
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of variants.
SPEAKER_0:  that work in the no-gill world.
SPEAKER_0:  That's not a very practical thing for Python users, but it would allow.
SPEAKER_0:  Extension developers.
SPEAKER_0:  to test the waters.
SPEAKER_0:  see what they need to syntactically...
SPEAKER_0:  to be able to compile it all maybe they're using.
SPEAKER_0:  Functions that are defined by the Python 3 runtime that won't be in the Python 4 runtime, those functions will not work.
SPEAKER_0:  Find an alternative.
SPEAKER_0:  But they can experiment with that and sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  write test applications and that would be a way to transition and that
SPEAKER_0:  that could be...
SPEAKER_0:  a series of
SPEAKER_0:  releases where the
SPEAKER_0:  Python 4 is more and more imminent. Uh, we-
SPEAKER_0:  have supported more and more third-party extension modules to
SPEAKER_0:  have solid support that works for No-Gill Python for that new API.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  then sort of Python 4.0 is like.
SPEAKER_0:  the official moment that the mayor comes out and cuts the ribbon and now Python.
SPEAKER_0:  Now the sort of no-gill mode is the default and maybe the only mode there is.
SPEAKER_1:  The internet wants to know from Reddit.
SPEAKER_1:  Alright.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a small and fun question. There's many fun questions, but...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  out of the PyPy packages.
SPEAKER_1:  API packages.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, do you have, uh, do you have ones you like, do you, in your opinion, are there must have pi pi libraries or ones you use all the time constantly.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh my.
SPEAKER_0:  I should really have a standard answer for that question, but.
SPEAKER_0:  like a positive standard answer, but my current standard answer is that I'm not a big user of third-party packages.
SPEAKER_0:  When I write Python code, I'm usually...
SPEAKER_0:  developing some tooling around building Python itself.
SPEAKER_0:  And the last thing we want is dependencies on third-party packages. So I tend to just use the standard library. That's where your focus is. That's where you buy this.
SPEAKER_1:  But you...
SPEAKER_1:  Do you keep an eye on what's out there to understand?
SPEAKER_1:  Where to stand the library?
SPEAKER_1:  could be moving, should be moving. It's a good kind of landscape of what's.
SPEAKER_1:  missing from the Santa library.
SPEAKER_0:  Usually when something's missing from the standard library nowadays...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  is a relatively new idea.
SPEAKER_0:  and there is a third party.
SPEAKER_0:  implementation or maybe possibly multiple third party implementations but
SPEAKER_0:  they evolve at a much higher rate than they could when they're in the standard library. So they, it would.
SPEAKER_0:  be a big.
SPEAKER_0:  reduction in in activity to
SPEAKER_0:  incorporate things like that in the standard library. So I like that there is a lively package ecosystem and that sort of
SPEAKER_0:  recent trends in the standard library are actually that we're doing the occasional spring cleaning where we're just
SPEAKER_0:  We're
SPEAKER_0:  choosing some
SPEAKER_0:  modules that have not had a lot of change.
SPEAKER_0:  in a long time and
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  would be better off not existing at all at this point because there might be a better third party
SPEAKER_0:  alternative anyway and we're sort of slowly removing those that often those are things that I sort of
SPEAKER_0:  I spiked somewhere in 1992 or 1993.
SPEAKER_0:  If you look through the commit history, it's very sad.
SPEAKER_0:  All cosmetic changes like changes in the indentation style or the name of this other standard library module got changed or...
SPEAKER_0:  Nothing of any substance, the API is identical to what it was 20 years ago.
SPEAKER_1:  So speaking of packages, they have a...
SPEAKER_1:  a lot of impact on a lot of people's lives.
SPEAKER_1:  Does it make sense to you why Python?
SPEAKER_1:  has become the primary, the dominant language for the machine learning community.
SPEAKER_1:  So packages like.
SPEAKER_1:  PyTorch, TensorFlow.
SPEAKER_1:  second learn and even like the lower level stuff like non-pi sci-pi pandas.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm at Platte Lab with the visualization.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you like?
SPEAKER_1:  Does it make sense to you why it...
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh...
SPEAKER_1:  permeated the entire data science machine learning AI community.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it's...
SPEAKER_0:  Part of it is an effect that's as simple as.
SPEAKER_0:  We're all driving on the right side of the road, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  It's compatibility.
SPEAKER_0:  It's it's an end.
SPEAKER_0:  and part of it is...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Not- not quite as- as- as-
SPEAKER_0:  fundamental as driving on the right side of the road, which you have to do for safety reasons. Agree on something.
SPEAKER_0:  They could have picked JavaScript or Perl.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a time in the early 2000s that it really looked like Pearl was.
SPEAKER_0:  going to dominate like biosciences.
SPEAKER_0:  because DNA search was all based on regular expressions and Pearl has the fastest and most comprehensive regular expression engine still does.
SPEAKER_1:  I spent quite a long time with Pearl. That was another letting go.
SPEAKER_1:  Letting go of this kind of data processing.
SPEAKER_1:  system.
SPEAKER_0:  The reasons why Python.
SPEAKER_0:  became the lingua franca of
SPEAKER_0:  The scientific.
SPEAKER_0:  code and and
SPEAKER_0:  machine learning in particular.
SPEAKER_0:  and data science.
SPEAKER_0:  it really had a lot to do with.
SPEAKER_0:  anything was better than C or C++.
SPEAKER_0:  Recently, a guy who worked at Lawrence Livermore National Laboratories in the
SPEAKER_0:  the sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  computing.
SPEAKER_0:  Division.
SPEAKER_0:  wrote me his memoirs and he had his own view of
SPEAKER_0:  How he helped.
SPEAKER_0:  something he called computational steering into existence.
SPEAKER_0:  And...
SPEAKER_0:  This was the idea that you take libraries that in his days were written in Fortran.
SPEAKER_0:  that solve universal mathematical problems.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... and those libraries still work but
SPEAKER_0:  uh... the scientists that use the libraries
SPEAKER_0:  Use them to solve continuously.
SPEAKER_0:  different.
SPEAKER_0:  specific applications and answer different questions.
SPEAKER_0:  And so those poor scientists.
SPEAKER_0:  Word.
SPEAKER_0:  were required to use, say, Fortran, because Fortran was the language that...
SPEAKER_0:  the library was written in.
SPEAKER_0:  and then the scientist would have to write.
SPEAKER_0:  an application that sort of uses the library.
SPEAKER_0:  to solve a particular equation or set of.
SPEAKER_0:  of answer a set of questions and the safer same for C++.
SPEAKER_0:  because there's interoperability, so the dusty decks are written either in C++ or Fortran.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  And so Paul Dubois was one of the people who...
SPEAKER_0:  I think in the mid 90s.
SPEAKER_0:  saw that.
SPEAKER_0:  you need a higher level language.
SPEAKER_0:  for the scientists.
SPEAKER_0:  to sort of tie together.
SPEAKER_0:  the fundamental mathematical algorithms of linear algebra and
SPEAKER_0:  and other stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  Gradually.
SPEAKER_0:  some libraries started appearing that did very fundamental.
SPEAKER_0:  stuffed with arrays of numbers in Python.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  When I first created Python, I was not expecting it to be used for arrays of numbers much. I thought that was like an outdated data type.
SPEAKER_0:  and everything was like objects and strings and like Python was
SPEAKER_0:  good and fast at string manipulation in objects obviously but arrays of numbers
SPEAKER_0:  were not very efficient and the multidimensional arrays didn't even exist in the language at all.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  But there were people who realized that Python had.
SPEAKER_0:  extensibility.
SPEAKER_0:  that was flexible enough that they could.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  Third party.
SPEAKER_0:  packages that did support large arrays of numbers and operations on them very efficiently.
SPEAKER_0:  and somehow they got a foothold.
SPEAKER_0:  through sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  different.
SPEAKER_0:  parts of the scientific community, I remembered that the Hubble Space Telescope people in Baltimore were somehow big Python fans in the late 90s.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  at various.
SPEAKER_0:  points.
SPEAKER_0:  small improvements were made and more people.
SPEAKER_0:  got in touch with using Python to derive these libraries.
SPEAKER_0:  interesting uh
SPEAKER_0:  algorithms and
SPEAKER_0:  like once once you have a bunch of scientists who are working on similar problems say they're all working on stuff that
SPEAKER_0:  that come data that comes in from the Hubble Space Telescope but they're looking at different things some some are looking at stars in this galaxy the other are looking at
SPEAKER_0:  galaxies. The math is completely different.
SPEAKER_0:  the underlying.
SPEAKER_0:  libraries are still the same.
SPEAKER_0:  And so they exchange.
SPEAKER_0:  code they say well I wrote this Python program or I wrote a Python library to solve this class of problems
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  The other guys either say, oh, I can use that library too. Or if you make a few changes, I can use that library too.
SPEAKER_0:  Why start from scratch?
SPEAKER_0:  in Perl or JavaScript.
SPEAKER_0:  where there's not that infrastructure.
SPEAKER_0:  for arrays of numbers yet where is in python you have it
SPEAKER_0:  And so more and more scientists at different places doing different.
SPEAKER_0:  different work.
SPEAKER_0:  discovered Python and then
SPEAKER_0:  Then people who had an idea for an important new fundamental library decided, oh, Python is actually.
SPEAKER_0:  already known to our users, so...
SPEAKER_0:  let's use Python as the user interface. I imagine at least that's how TensorFlow ended up with Python as the user interface.
SPEAKER_0:  But with TensorFlow.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a...
SPEAKER_1:  deeper.
SPEAKER_1:  History of what the communities, it's not just like what packages and needs.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like what the community leans on for programming language.
SPEAKER_1:  TensorFlow.
SPEAKER_1:  I had a prior library that was internal to Google.
SPEAKER_1:  but there's also competing.
SPEAKER_1:  machine learning.
SPEAKER_1:  frameworks like the piano.
SPEAKER_1:  Cafe, they were in Python, there was some Scala.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, some other languages, but Python was really dominating it.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's interesting because there's other languages from the engineering space.
SPEAKER_1:  MATLAB.
SPEAKER_1:  that a lot of people use.
SPEAKER_1:  but...
SPEAKER_1:  different design choices by the company, by the core developers.
SPEAKER_1:  led to it not.
SPEAKER_1:  spreading and one of the choices of my lab.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, by math works is to not make it open source, right? Or not, you know, having people.
SPEAKER_0:  Hey, it was very expensive product and so.
SPEAKER_0:  universities especially dislike it because it was a price per seat.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember hearing.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that's not why it's.
SPEAKER_1:  Failed.
SPEAKER_1:  or a failed spread.
SPEAKER_1:  I think the universities didn't like it, but they would still pay for it.
SPEAKER_1:  The thing is it didn't feed into that GitHub open source.
SPEAKER_1:  packages culture.
SPEAKER_1:  So like and that's somehow a precondition for
SPEAKER_1:  for viral spreading.
SPEAKER_1:  The hacker culture, like the tinkerer culture.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... the with with python it feels like you can build a package from scratch to solve a particular problem
SPEAKER_1:  and get excited about sharing that package with others.
SPEAKER_1:  and that creates an excitement.
SPEAKER_0:  in a bottle language.
SPEAKER_0:  I tend to like Python's approach to open source in particular because it's sort of
SPEAKER_0:  It's almost egalitarian.
SPEAKER_0:  There's little hierarchy.
SPEAKER_0:  There's obviously some because you all need to decide whether you drive on the left or the right side of the road sometimes.
SPEAKER_0:  but there is a lot of...
SPEAKER_0:  access for people with little power. You don't have to work for a big tech company to make a difference in the Python world.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, we have.
SPEAKER_0:  affordable events that really care about community and support people.
SPEAKER_0:  and sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  Community is is
SPEAKER_0:  It's like.
SPEAKER_0:  big deal at our conferences and in the PSF.
SPEAKER_0:  When the PSF funds events, it's always about.
SPEAKER_0:  growing the community.
SPEAKER_0:  The PSF.
SPEAKER_0:  funds very little development.
SPEAKER_0:  date.
SPEAKER_0:  They do some, but most of the money that the PSF...
SPEAKER_0:  Forks out.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... is to community
SPEAKER_0:  fostering things.
SPEAKER_1:  So speaking of egalitarian, last time we talked four years ago.
SPEAKER_1:  It was just after you stepped down from your roll.
SPEAKER_1:  as the benevolent dictator for life, BDFL.
SPEAKER_1:  Looking back
SPEAKER_1:  What are your insights and lessons?
SPEAKER_1:  You learn from that experience about Python developer community, about human nature, about human civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  life itself.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh my.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I probably held onto the position too long.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember being just...
SPEAKER_0:  extremely stressed for a long time.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It wasn't very clear to me.
SPEAKER_0:  what was leading, what was causing the stress.
SPEAKER_0:  and looking back.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I should have sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  relinquished.
SPEAKER_0:  My central role.
SPEAKER_0:  as BDFL sooner.
SPEAKER_1:  What were the pros and cons of the BDFL roll?
SPEAKER_1:  Like what were the-
SPEAKER_1:  You not relinquishing it. What are the benefits of that for the community?
SPEAKER_1:  and what are the drawbacks?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, the-
SPEAKER_0:  The benefits for the community would be things like...
SPEAKER_0:  Uhhh
SPEAKER_0:  clarity of vision and sort of
SPEAKER_0:  clear direction because I
SPEAKER_0:  I had certain ideas in...
SPEAKER_0:  in mind when I created Python and while I sort of let myself be influenced by many other ideas as Python evolved and became.
SPEAKER_0:  more successful and more complex and more.
SPEAKER_0:  used.
SPEAKER_0:  I also stuck to certain principles and it's still hard to say what are Python's core principles.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that...
SPEAKER_0:  I was
SPEAKER_0:  playing that role and sort of always...
SPEAKER_0:  Very active.
SPEAKER_0:  through the community in a certain way.
SPEAKER_0:  It modeled.
SPEAKER_0:  the community how to think about.
SPEAKER_0:  How to solve a certain problem? Well...
SPEAKER_1:  That was a source of stress, but it was also benefit.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a source of stress for me personally, but it was beneficial for the community because
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  People. People sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  over time had.
SPEAKER_0:  learned how I was thinking and could predict.
SPEAKER_0:  but how I would decide about a particular issue. not always perfectly of course but there was like
SPEAKER_0:  There wasn't a lot of jerking around like this year, we're all, but this year the Democrats are in power and we're doing these kinds of things and now the Republicans are in power and they roll all that back and do those kind of things.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a clear.
SPEAKER_0:  fairly straight path ahead.
SPEAKER_0:  And so fortunately the successor structure with the steering console.
SPEAKER_0:  has sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  found a similar way of
SPEAKER_0:  of leading the community.
SPEAKER_0:  in a fairly steady direction without
SPEAKER_0:  Stagnating.
SPEAKER_0:  And for me personally, it's more fun because there are...
SPEAKER_0:  There are things I can just ignore.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yeah, there's a bug in multiprocessing.
SPEAKER_0:  Let someone else decide whether that's important to solve or not.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll stick to typing in the async I.O. and the faster interpreter.
SPEAKER_1:  It allows you to focus a little bit more. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  What are interesting differences in culture if you can comment on between Google Dropbox and Microsoft from a Python programming perspective?
SPEAKER_1:  all places you've been to, the positive.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there a difference or is it just about people and there's?
SPEAKER_1:  Great people everywhere.
SPEAKER_1:  Or is there a culture differences?
SPEAKER_0:  So Dropbox is much smaller than the other two in your list.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. So-
SPEAKER_0:  DUT.
SPEAKER_0:  That is a big difference.
SPEAKER_1:  the set of products they provide is narrower so they're more focused
SPEAKER_0:  and yeah and and dropbox sort of at least during the time i was there
SPEAKER_0:  had the tendency of sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  Making a big plan.
SPEAKER_0:  putting the whole company behind that plan for a year.
SPEAKER_0:  and then evaluate and then suddenly find that.
SPEAKER_0:  everything was wrong about the plan and then they had to do something completely different.
SPEAKER_0:  So there was like...
SPEAKER_0:  The annual engineering reorg was sort of an unpleasant tradition at Dropbox because like, oh, there's a new VP of engineering and so now all the directors are being reshuffled and
SPEAKER_0:  This guy was in charge of.
SPEAKER_0:  infrastructure one year and the next year he was made in charge of, I don't know, product development.
SPEAKER_1:  It's fascinating because you don't think about these companies internally.
SPEAKER_1:  But Dropbox to me from the very beginning was one of my favorite.
SPEAKER_1:  services. There's certain like programs and online services that
SPEAKER_1:  Make me happy.
SPEAKER_1:  make me more efficient and all that kind of stuff, but.
SPEAKER_1:  one of the powers of those kinds of services, they disappear. You're not supposed to think about how it all works.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's incredible to me that you can sync.
SPEAKER_1:  stuff effortlessly.
SPEAKER_1:  across so many machines.
SPEAKER_1:  so quickly.
SPEAKER_1:  and don't have to worry about conflicts. They take care of the-
SPEAKER_1:  you know, as a person that comes from.
SPEAKER_1:  version repositories and all that kind of stuff or merge.
SPEAKER_1:  is super difficult and.
SPEAKER_1:  Just keeping different versions of different files is very tricky. The fact that they could take care of that is just, I don't know. The engineering behind the scenes must be super difficult, both on the computer infrastructure and the software.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of internal sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  hand-wringing about things like that.
SPEAKER_0:  but that's it.
SPEAKER_0:  the product itself always worked very smoothly.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  But there's probably a lot of lessons to that. You can have a lot of turmoil inside on the engineering side, but...
SPEAKER_1:  If the product is good, the product is good. And maybe don't mess with that either, because you don't want it to be good.
SPEAKER_1:  Keep it's like with Google focus on the search and the ads.
SPEAKER_1:  And the money will come.
SPEAKER_1:  and make sure that's done extremely well. And don't forget.
SPEAKER_1:  what you do extremely well.
SPEAKER_1:  In what ways do you provide?
SPEAKER_1:  Value and happiness to the world. Make sure you do that well.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there something else to say about Google and Microsoft?
SPEAKER_1:  Microsoft has had a very fascinating shift recently.
SPEAKER_1:  Within you see how.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... what
SPEAKER_1:  you know, recent CEO.
SPEAKER_1:  with purchasing GitHub.
SPEAKER_1:  embracing open source culture, embracing the developer culture. It's pretty interesting to see.
SPEAKER_0:  That's like why I joined Microsoft.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, after retiring and thinking that I would.
SPEAKER_0:  stay retired for the rest of my life, which of course was a ridiculous thought.
SPEAKER_0:  I was
SPEAKER_0:  I was done working for a bit and then the pandemic made me realize that work can also provide a
SPEAKER_0:  a source of fulfillment.
SPEAKER_0:  keep you out of trouble.
SPEAKER_0:  Microsoft is a very interesting company because it has this in-
SPEAKER_0:  God
SPEAKER_0:  very long and
SPEAKER_0:  varied history.
SPEAKER_0:  and this amazing catalog of products that
SPEAKER_0:  many of which also
SPEAKER_0:  date way back.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  I've been talking to a bunch of Excel people lately, and Excel is like 35 years old.
SPEAKER_0:  and they can still read spreadsheets that they might find.
SPEAKER_1:  on an old floppy drive.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, there's so many incredible tools through the years.
SPEAKER_1:  Excel, one of the great.
SPEAKER_1:  shames of my life.
SPEAKER_1:  is that I've never learned how to use Excel well.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, it just always felt like so many features are there.
SPEAKER_1:  It's similar with ADEs like PyCharm.
SPEAKER_1:  It feels like I converge quickly to the dumbest way to use a thing to get the job done.
SPEAKER_1:  when clearly there's so much more power in your fingertips.
SPEAKER_1:  but I do think there's probably expert users of Excel.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh...
SPEAKER_1:  Excel is a cash cow.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, it actually brings in money.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of the engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  sort of if you look deep inside Excel.
SPEAKER_0:  There's some very good engineering, very.
SPEAKER_0:  Very impressive stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, now I need to definitely learn Excel a little better.
SPEAKER_1:  I had issues because I'm a keyboard person, so I...
SPEAKER_1:  and issues coming up with shortcuts and Microsoft sometimes.
SPEAKER_1:  It's changed over the years, but sometimes they kind of want to make things easier for you on the surface.
SPEAKER_1:  And therefore...
SPEAKER_1:  make it harder for like a
SPEAKER_1:  people that like to have shortcuts and all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  to optimize their workflow.
SPEAKER_1:  Now, people are probably yelling at me, it's like, no, Excel probably has a lot of ways to optimize work.
SPEAKER_0:  In fact, I keep discovering that there are many features in Excel that only exists at keyboard.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, that's the sense I have. Now, like I'm embarrassed that it's just.
SPEAKER_0:  You just have to know what they are.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no logic or-
SPEAKER_0:  or reason to the assignment of the keyboard shortcuts because they go back even longer than 35 years.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you maybe comment about such in a Della?
SPEAKER_1:  and how hard it is for a CEO to sort of pivot a company.
SPEAKER_1:  towards open source or developer culture? Is there something you could see about like,
SPEAKER_1:  What's the role of leadership?
SPEAKER_1:  in such a...
SPEAKER_1:  Pivot and definition of a new vision.
SPEAKER_1:  I've never met him.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I hear...
SPEAKER_0:  He's just a really...
SPEAKER_0:  sharp.
SPEAKER_0:  Thinker.
SPEAKER_0:  but he also has an incredible business sense.
SPEAKER_0:  He took the organization that had very solid pieces, but that was also
SPEAKER_0:  struggling.
SPEAKER_0:  with all sorts of shameful things.
SPEAKER_0:  Especially to Steve Ballmer time.
SPEAKER_0:  I imagine in part through his personal charm and thinking and of course that
SPEAKER_0:  The great trust that...
SPEAKER_0:  that the rest of the leadership has in him. He managed to.
SPEAKER_0:  really turn the company around and sort of
SPEAKER_0:  change it from from openly hostile to open source.
SPEAKER_0:  to actively embracing open source.
SPEAKER_0:  And that doesn't mean that suddenly Excel is going to go open source.
SPEAKER_0:  But that means that there's room for a product like VS Code, which is open source.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, that's fascinating.
SPEAKER_1:  gives me faith that large companies with good leadership can.
SPEAKER_1:  grow, can expand, can change and pivot and so on and develop.
SPEAKER_1:  It gets harder and harder as the company gets large.
SPEAKER_1:  You wrote a blog post in response to a person looking for advice about whether with a CS degree to choose a 9 to 5 job.
SPEAKER_1:  or to become an entrepreneur.
SPEAKER_1:  That's an interesting question.
SPEAKER_1:  If you just think from first principles right now.
SPEAKER_1:  somebody.
SPEAKER_1:  as took a few years in programming, has loved software engineering.
SPEAKER_1:  in some sense.
SPEAKER_1:  Creating Python is an
SPEAKER_1:  entrepreneurial endeavor.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a choice that a lot of people.
SPEAKER_1:  that are good programmers have to make? What do I work for?
SPEAKER_1:  a big company or do I create something new?
SPEAKER_0:  Or you can work for a big company and create something new there.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, inside the...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean big companies.
SPEAKER_0:  have individuals who create new stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  that eventually grows big all the time.
SPEAKER_1:  And if you're the person that creates a new thing, and you're the person that creates a new thing,
SPEAKER_1:  you'll have a chance to move up quickly in the company.
SPEAKER_1:  to run that thing.
SPEAKER_0:  if that's your aspiration, but what can also happen is that.
SPEAKER_0:  Someone is a brilliant engineer and...
SPEAKER_0:  assertive.
SPEAKER_0:  builds a great first version of a product.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  has no aspirations.
SPEAKER_0:  then become a manager and grow the team from five people to 20 people to a hundred people to a thousand people and
SPEAKER_0:  be in charge of hiring and meetings and
SPEAKER_0:  They move on to.
SPEAKER_0:  inventing another crazy thing inside the same company or sometimes they
SPEAKER_0:  they found a startup or they moved to a different grade.
SPEAKER_0:  large or small company there's all sorts of models
SPEAKER_0:  And sometimes people sort of do have this.
SPEAKER_0:  whole trajectory from engineer buckling down.
SPEAKER_0:  writing code.
SPEAKER_0:  Not 9 to 5, but more like...
SPEAKER_0:  Noon till midnight.
SPEAKER_0:  Seven days a week.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Coming up with a product and sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  staying in charge. I mean, if you take Drew Houston...
SPEAKER_0:  Dropbox's founder.
SPEAKER_0:  He is still the CEO.
SPEAKER_0:  And at least when I was there, he had not checked out or anything. He was s-
SPEAKER_0:  He was good.
SPEAKER_0:  CEO.
SPEAKER_0:  but he had started out as the technical inventor or co-inventor.
SPEAKER_0:  And so he was someone who...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if he always aspired that. I think when he was 16, he already started a company. So maybe, maybe he did, but he sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  It turned out that he did have the...
SPEAKER_0:  The personal sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  skill set.
SPEAKER_0:  needed to grow and stay on top and other people.
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  are brilliant engineers and horrible at management. I count myself.
SPEAKER_0:  at least in the second category.
SPEAKER_1:  So your first love and still your love is to be the quote-unquote individual contributor.
SPEAKER_1:  to the programmer.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you have advice for a?
SPEAKER_1:  programming beginner on how to learn Python.
SPEAKER_1:  the right way.
SPEAKER_0:  Find something you-
SPEAKER_0:  actually want to do.
SPEAKER_0:  with it.
SPEAKER_0:  If you say...
SPEAKER_0:  I wanna learn skill X.
SPEAKER_0:  That's not enough motivation.
SPEAKER_0:  You need to pick something!
SPEAKER_0:  and it can be a crazy problem you want to solve. It can be completely unrealistic.
SPEAKER_0:  but something that challenges you into actually.
SPEAKER_0:  Learning.
SPEAKER_0:  coding in some language.
SPEAKER_1:  And there are so many projects out there you can look for like that. That doesn't have to be some big ambitious thing. It could be writing a small bot.
SPEAKER_1:  If you're into social media, you can write a Reddit bot or a Twitter bot or...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  or some aspect of automating something that you do every single day.
SPEAKER_1:  processing files all that kind of stuff
SPEAKER_0:  Nowadays you can take machine learning.
SPEAKER_0:  opponents and sort of
SPEAKER_0:  plug those things together.
SPEAKER_0:  So cool stuff with them.
SPEAKER_1:  a good really good example. So if you're interested in machine learning, the state of machine learning is such.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  Like a-
SPEAKER_1:  a tutorial that takes an hour.
SPEAKER_1:  can get you to start using.
SPEAKER_1:  pre-trained models to do something super cool.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's a good way to learn Python because you learn just enough to run this model and that's like a sneaky way to get get in there.
SPEAKER_1:  to figure out.
SPEAKER_1:  how to import stuff, how to...
SPEAKER_1:  write basic IO.
SPEAKER_1:  how to run functions.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not sure if it's the best way to learn the basics in Python, but it could be nice to just fall in love first and then figure out the basics, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, you can't expect to learn Python.
SPEAKER_0:  from a one hour video.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm blanking out on the name of...
SPEAKER_0:  of someone who...
SPEAKER_0:  who wrote very...
SPEAKER_0:  funny blog post where he said
SPEAKER_0:  I see all these ads for things like...
SPEAKER_0:  Learn Python in 10 days or so.
SPEAKER_0:  And he said...
SPEAKER_0:  The goal should be learn Python in 10 years.
SPEAKER_1:  That's hilarious, but...
SPEAKER_1:  I completely disagree with that.
SPEAKER_1:  I think the criticism behind that is that...
SPEAKER_1:  the the places just like the blog post from earlier, the places that tell you learn Python five minutes or ten minutes.
SPEAKER_1:  They're actually usually really bad tutorials. So the thing is, I do.
SPEAKER_0:  believe.
SPEAKER_1:  that you can learn a thing.
SPEAKER_1:  in an hour.
SPEAKER_1:  to get some interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  quick.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, it hooks you.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, this, but it just takes a tremendous amount of skill to be that kind of educator.
SPEAKER_1:  Richard Feynman was able to condense a lot of ideas in physics in a very short amount of time.
SPEAKER_1:  but that takes a deep, deep understanding. So yes, of course, the actual
SPEAKER_1:  I think the 10.
SPEAKER_1:  the 10 years is about the experience.
SPEAKER_1:  the pain along the way and there's something
SPEAKER_0:  You have to practice. You can memorize the syntax.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I couldn't, but maybe maybe someone else can, but that doesn't make you a coder.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Actually, coding has changed in fascinating ways.
SPEAKER_1:  So much of coding is copying and pasting from Stack Overflow and then adjusting.
SPEAKER_1:  Which is another way of coding and I don't want to talk down to that kind of style of coding because.
SPEAKER_1:  It's kind of nicely efficient.
SPEAKER_0:  But you know where that is going?
SPEAKER_0:  Code generation. No, seriously get up coke
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, copilot.
SPEAKER_0:  I use it every day and it... Really? It writes...
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of code for me, and usually it's slightly wrong, but it still saves me typing.
SPEAKER_0:  because all I have to do is like.
SPEAKER_0:  Change.
SPEAKER_0:  one word in a line of text that otherwise it generated perfectly and like
SPEAKER_0:  How many times?
SPEAKER_0:  Are you looking for like, oh, what was I doing this morning? I was looking for a begin marker and I look at, we're looking for an end marker. And so.
SPEAKER_0:  Begin is.
SPEAKER_0:  Blah blah blah, search for...
SPEAKER_0:  Begin!
SPEAKER_0:  This is the begin token.
SPEAKER_0:  And then the next line I type E.
SPEAKER_0:  and it.
SPEAKER_0:  It's.
SPEAKER_0:  completes the whole line with end instead of begin.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a very simple example. Sometimes it sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  If I name my function right, it writes a 5 or 10 line function.
SPEAKER_1:  and you know...
SPEAKER_1:  Python enough.
SPEAKER_1:  very quickly than detect the issues.
SPEAKER_1:  So it becomes a really good demo.
SPEAKER_0:  partner then. It doesn't save me a lot of thinking, but since I'm a poor typist, I'm very much appreciative of
SPEAKER_0:  All the-
SPEAKER_0:  all the typing it does for me.
SPEAKER_0:  much better actually than the previous generation of suggestions that are also still built in VS code.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, where, when you hit like a dot.
SPEAKER_0:  tries to guess what the...
SPEAKER_0:  type is of the variable to the left of the dot and then it gives you a list of welcome
SPEAKER_0:  what the attributes of that object are, but Copilot is much, much smoother than that.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, it's fascinating to hear.
SPEAKER_1:  that you use GitHub co-pilot.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think, do you worry about the future of that?
SPEAKER_1:  to the...
SPEAKER_1:  Automatic code generation.
SPEAKER_1:  the increasing amount of
SPEAKER_1:  that kind of capability our programmers.
SPEAKER_1:  jobs threatened.
SPEAKER_1:  or is there still a significant role for humans?
SPEAKER_0:  Are programmers jobs threatened by the existence of Stack Overflow?
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think so.
SPEAKER_0:  It helps you take care of the boring stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  You shouldn't try to...
SPEAKER_0:  use it to do something that you have no way of understanding what you're doing yet.
SPEAKER_0:  A tool like that is always best when...
SPEAKER_0:  The question you're asking is, please remind me of how I do this.
SPEAKER_0:  which I-
SPEAKER_0:  I could do, I could look up how to do it.
SPEAKER_0:  but.
SPEAKER_0:  Right now I've forgotten whether the method is called foo or bar.
SPEAKER_0:  or how you.
SPEAKER_0:  What the shape of the API is, does it use a builder object or a constructor or a factory or?
SPEAKER_0:  uh, something else.
SPEAKER_0:  and what are the parameters.
SPEAKER_0:  it serves that role, it's like a great assistant.
SPEAKER_0:  but the creative work of.
SPEAKER_0:  sort of deciding what you want the code to do.
SPEAKER_0:  is totally yours.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think is the future of Python in the next 10, 20, 50 years, you look forward....
SPEAKER_1:  You ever think about, you ever imagine a future?
SPEAKER_1:  of human civilization while living inside the metaverse.
SPEAKER_1:  on Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  humanoid robots everywhere. What part does Python play in that?
SPEAKER_0:  It'll eventually become sort of a legacy language that plays an important role, but that's that most people have never heard of. And, uh,
SPEAKER_0:  don't need to know about just like.
SPEAKER_0:  all kinds of
SPEAKER_0:  basic structures in.
SPEAKER_0:  biology like mitochondria.
SPEAKER_1:  so it permeates all of life.
SPEAKER_1:  all of digital life but...
SPEAKER_1:  People just build on top of it.
SPEAKER_1:  And they only know the stuff that's on top of it.
SPEAKER_0:  You guys, you build layers of abstractions, I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  Most programmers nowadays.
SPEAKER_0:  rarely need to.
SPEAKER_0:  do binary arithmetic, right?
SPEAKER_1:  Yep, or even think about it or even learn about it, or they can go quite far without knowing.
SPEAKER_0:  I started.
SPEAKER_0:  building little digital circuits out of NAND gates that I built myself with transistors and resistors.
SPEAKER_0:  So I sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel very blessed that
SPEAKER_0:  with that start when I was a teenager.
SPEAKER_0:  I-
SPEAKER_0:  I learned some of the basic, at least concepts.
SPEAKER_0:  that go into building a computer.
SPEAKER_0:  And I sort of every.
SPEAKER_0:  heart.
SPEAKER_0:  I have some understanding what
SPEAKER_0:  what it's for and why it's there and how it works.
SPEAKER_0:  And I can forget about all that most of the time, but I sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  I enjoy knowing, oh, if you go deeper, at some point you get to...
SPEAKER_0:  NAND gates and half adders and shift registers and
SPEAKER_0:  When it comes to the point of how do you actually make a chip out of silicon, I have no idea.
SPEAKER_0:  That's just magic to me.
SPEAKER_1:  but you enjoy knowing that you can walk a while towards the lower and lower layers, but you don't need to.
SPEAKER_0:  It's nice. The other day as a sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  A mental exercise I was trying to figure out if I could...
SPEAKER_0:  build a-
SPEAKER_0:  a flip-flop circuit out of relays.
SPEAKER_0:  I was just sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  trying to remember how does a relay work, yeah there's like this electromagnetic
SPEAKER_0:  that pulls a switch open or shut.
SPEAKER_0:  And you can have like, you can open one switch in another.
SPEAKER_0:  shut another and
SPEAKER_0:  You can have multiple contacts that go at once, and how many relays do I really need to sort of represent one bit of information? Can the relay just feed on itself? And it was…
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think I got to the final solution, but it was fun that I
SPEAKER_0:  I could still.
SPEAKER_0:  do a little bit of problem solving and thinking at that level.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's cool how we build on top of each other.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's people that are just...
SPEAKER_1:  You stood on the shoulders of giants and there's others who stand on your shoulders and it's
SPEAKER_1:  It's a giant.
SPEAKER_1:  Beautiful higher. Yeah
SPEAKER_0:  feel I sort of cover this middle layer of the technology stack where
SPEAKER_0:  and sort of Peters out below the.
SPEAKER_0:  the level of Nan Gates.
SPEAKER_0:  And at the top, I lose track when it gets to machine learning.
SPEAKER_1:  And then eventually the machine learning will build higher and higher layers.
SPEAKER_1:  that will help us understand the lowest layer of the physics.
SPEAKER_1:  and thereby the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  figures out how.
SPEAKER_1:  It itself works.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe, maybe not.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I did. I mean, it's possible. I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  if you think of human consciousness if that's even the right concept.
SPEAKER_0:  It's interesting that sort of we have this.
SPEAKER_0:  Super parallel brain that does all these...
SPEAKER_0:  incredible parallel operations like image recognition.
SPEAKER_0:  I recognize your face.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a huge amount of processing that goes on.
SPEAKER_0:  In parallel, there's lots of nerves between my eyes and my brain.
SPEAKER_0:  and the brain does a whole bunch of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  all at once because it's actually really slow.
SPEAKER_0:  circuits but there are many of them that all work together.
SPEAKER_0:  On the other hand...
SPEAKER_0:  When I'm speaking, everything is completely sequential.
SPEAKER_0:  I have to sort of string words together one at a time.
SPEAKER_0:  and when I'm thinking about stuff, when I'm understanding the world.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm also thinking of everything, like, one step at a time.
SPEAKER_0:  And so we've sort of, we've got all this incredible.
SPEAKER_0:  parallel
SPEAKER_0:  circuitry in our brains and eventually we use that to simulate
SPEAKER_0:  a single threaded.
SPEAKER_0:  Much, much.
SPEAKER_0:  higher level interpreter.
SPEAKER_1:  It's exactly I mean, that's the illusion of it. That's the illusion
SPEAKER_1:  of it for us that is a single sequential.
SPEAKER_1:  set of thoughts and all of that came from a single cell.
SPEAKER_1:  through the process of embryogenesis. So DNA is the code.
SPEAKER_1:  DNA holds the entirety of the code.
SPEAKER_1:  the information and how to use that information to build up an organism the entire like
SPEAKER_1:  The arms, the legs.
SPEAKER_0:  built. Yeah, the brain.
SPEAKER_1:  So you don't buy a computer.
SPEAKER_1:  You buy like a...
SPEAKER_0:  You buy a seed, a diagram.
SPEAKER_1:  and then you plant the computer.
SPEAKER_1:  and it builds itself.
SPEAKER_1:  in almost the same way.
SPEAKER_1:  and then does the computation.
SPEAKER_1:  And then.
SPEAKER_1:  is eventually dies.
SPEAKER_1:  It gets stale, but gives birth to young computers.
SPEAKER_1:  more and more and gives them lessons, but they figure stuff out on their own and over time.
SPEAKER_1:  It goes on that way.
SPEAKER_1:  And those computers, when they go to college, tried to figure out how to program and they built their own little computers.
SPEAKER_1:  they're increasingly more intelligent, increasingly...
SPEAKER_1:  higher and higher levels of abstractions.
SPEAKER_0:  Isn't it interesting that you sort of, you see the same thing appearing at different levels though, because you have like...
SPEAKER_0:  cells that that
SPEAKER_0:  create new cells.
SPEAKER_0:  and eventually that builds a whole organism, but then the animal or the plant or the human
SPEAKER_0:  has its own.
SPEAKER_0:  mechanism of replication.
SPEAKER_0:  That is.
SPEAKER_0:  is sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  connected in a very complicated way to the mechanism of replication of the cells. And then if you-
SPEAKER_0:  If you look inside the cell, if you see how DNA and proteins are...
SPEAKER_0:  are connected, then there is yet another completely different mechanism whereby
SPEAKER_0:  Proteins are mass produced.
SPEAKER_0:  using enzymes and a little bit of...
SPEAKER_0:  code from DNA and of course viruses.
SPEAKER_0:  break into it at that level.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  While the mechanisms might be different, it seems like the nature of the mechanism.
SPEAKER_1:  is the same.
SPEAKER_1:  cares across.
SPEAKER_1:  natural languages and
SPEAKER_1:  programming languages.
SPEAKER_1:  humans.
SPEAKER_1:  maybe even human civilizations or intelligent civilizations.
SPEAKER_1:  and then all the way down to...
SPEAKER_1:  uh... single cell organ
SPEAKER_0:  It is fascinating to see what abstraction levels.
SPEAKER_0:  are built on top of individual humans.
SPEAKER_0:  and how you have like whole societies.
SPEAKER_0:  That's sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  have a similar self-preservation.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know what it is, instinct, nature, abstraction.
SPEAKER_0:  as the individuals have and the cells have.
SPEAKER_1:  and they self replicate and breed in different ways.
SPEAKER_1:  It's hard for us humans to introspect it because we were very focused on our particular layer of abstraction.
SPEAKER_1:  but.
SPEAKER_1:  from an alien perspective looking on Earth, they'll...
SPEAKER_1:  they'll probably see.
SPEAKER_1:  the higher level organism.
SPEAKER_1:  of human civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  as part of this bigger organism of life on Earth itself. In fact, that could be an organism just alone, just life, life.
SPEAKER_1:  Life on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  This is...
SPEAKER_1:  been a wild
SPEAKER_1:  both philosophical and technical conversation. thanks for watching
SPEAKER_1:  You're an amazing human being, you're-
SPEAKER_1:  You were gracious enough to talk to me when I was first doing this podcast. You were one of the earliest first people.
SPEAKER_1:  I've talked to somebody I admired for a long time. It's just a huge honor that you did it at that time and you do it again. You're awesome. Thank you, Lex.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with Guido Benrassam.
SPEAKER_1:  To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me leave you with some words from Oscar Wilde.
SPEAKER_1:  Experience is the name that everyone gives to their mistakes.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for listening and hope to see you.
SPEAKER_1:  next time.