SPEAKER_0:  A lot of people were saying like, oh, this whole idea of game theory, it's just nonsense.soft? chewing rotating phone
SPEAKER_0:  If you really want to make money, you've got to look into the other person's eyes and read their soul and figure out...
SPEAKER_0:  what cards they have.
SPEAKER_0:  But what happened was where we played our bot against four top heads up no limit hold'em
SPEAKER_0:  Poker players.
SPEAKER_0:  and the bot.
SPEAKER_0:  wasn't trying to adapt to them, it wasn't trying to exploit them, it wasn't trying to do these mind games, it was just trying to approximate the Nash equilibrium.
SPEAKER_0:  and it crushed them.
SPEAKER_1:  The following is a conversation with No Brown.
SPEAKER_1:  Research scientists at FAIR.
SPEAKER_1:  Facebook AI research group at MetaAI.
SPEAKER_1:  He co-created the first AI system.
SPEAKER_1:  that achieved superhuman level performance in no limit Texas hold them.
SPEAKER_1:  both heads up and multiplayer.
SPEAKER_1:  And now...
SPEAKER_1:  recently.
SPEAKER_1:  He co-created an AI system that can strategically out-negotiate humans.
SPEAKER_1:  using natural language.
SPEAKER_1:  in a popular board game called Diplomacy.
SPEAKER_1:  which is a war game.
SPEAKER_1:  that emphasizes negotiation.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the Lex Friedman podcast.
SPEAKER_1:  to support it.
SPEAKER_1:  Please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now...
SPEAKER_1:  Dear friends.
SPEAKER_1:  Here's Gnome.
SPEAKER_1:  crowd.
SPEAKER_1:  You've been a lead on three amazing AI projects. So we've got Labratus that's solved.
SPEAKER_1:  or at least achieved human level performance on No Limit Texas Hold'em poker with two players. Heads up!
SPEAKER_1:  You got it.
SPEAKER_1:  Pluribus.
SPEAKER_1:  That's solved No Limit Texas Hold'em poker with.
SPEAKER_1:  Six players.
SPEAKER_1:  And just now you have Cicero, these are all names of systems.
SPEAKER_1:  that solved or achieved human level.
SPEAKER_1:  Performance on the Game of Diplomacy.
SPEAKER_1:  which for people who don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  is a popular strategy board game.
SPEAKER_1:  It was loved by JFK, John F. Kennedy.
SPEAKER_1:  and Henry Kissinger.
SPEAKER_1:  and many other.
SPEAKER_1:  Big.
SPEAKER_1:  famous people.
SPEAKER_1:  in the decade since.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's talk about poker and diplomacy today.
SPEAKER_1:  First poker. What?
SPEAKER_1:  is the game of no limit Texas Hold'em.
SPEAKER_1:  and how's it different from chess?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, no limit to Texas Hold'em Poker.
SPEAKER_0:  is the most popular variant of poker in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  So you go to a casino, you sit down at the poker table, the game that you're playing is No Limit Texas Hold'em.
SPEAKER_0:  If you watch movies about poker like Casino Royale or Rounders.
SPEAKER_0:  The game that they're playing is No Limit Texas Hold'em Poker.
SPEAKER_0:  Now, it's very different from limit hold them in that you can bet any amount of chips that you want. The stakes escalate really quickly.
SPEAKER_0:  You start out with like one or two dollars in the pot.
SPEAKER_0:  And then by the end of the hand, you've got like...
SPEAKER_0:  Thousand dollars in there maybe.
SPEAKER_1:  to the option to increase the number very aggressively very quickly as always there.
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_0:  The no limit aspect is there's no limit to how much you can bet.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you can...
SPEAKER_0:  In limit hold on.
SPEAKER_0:  there's like $2 in the potty, you can only bet like $2. But if you got $10,000 in front of you, you're always welcome to it.
SPEAKER_0:  put $10,000 into the...
SPEAKER_1:  So I got a chance to hang out with Phil Hellmuth who plays all these different variants of poker?
SPEAKER_1:  and correct me if I'm wrong, but.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like No Limit Rewards crazy.
SPEAKER_1:  versus the other ones rewards more kind of calculated strategy.
SPEAKER_1:  or no, because you're sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  Looking from an.
SPEAKER_1:  from an analytic perspective is.
SPEAKER_1:  is strategy also rewarded in no limit taxes hold them.
SPEAKER_0:  I think both variants reward strategy, but I think what's different about NoLimit Hold'em
SPEAKER_0:  is it's much easier to get jumpy. You go in there thinking you're going to lose, you're going to...
SPEAKER_0:  Play for like.
SPEAKER_0:  a hundred dollars or something and suddenly there's like you know a thousand dollars in the pot a lot of people can't handle that
SPEAKER_0:  Can you define jumpy?
SPEAKER_0:  When you're playing poker, you always want to choose the action that's going to maximize your expected value.
SPEAKER_0:  It's kind of like with investing, right? If you're ever in a situation where you're...
SPEAKER_0:  the amount of money that's at stake.
SPEAKER_0:  is.
SPEAKER_0:  is going to have a material impact on your life?
SPEAKER_0:  then you're going to play in a more risk averse style.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, if somebody makes a huge bet...
SPEAKER_0:  You're gonna if you're playing element hold them and somebody makes a huge bet
SPEAKER_0:  there might come a point where you're like, this is too much money for me to handle. Like I can't.
SPEAKER_0:  risk this amount.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's what throws a lot of people off.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the big difference I think between no limit and limit.
SPEAKER_1:  What about on the action side when you're actually making that big bet?
SPEAKER_1:  That's what I mean by crazy. I was trying to refer to the technical.
SPEAKER_1:  the technical term of crazy, meaning use the.
SPEAKER_1:  Big jump in the bet.
SPEAKER_1:  to completely throw off the other person in terms of...
SPEAKER_1:  their ability to reason.
SPEAKER_1:  optimally.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's right. I think that's right.
SPEAKER_0:  one of the key strategies in poker.
SPEAKER_0:  is to
SPEAKER_0:  put the other person into an uncomfortable position.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you're doing that, then you're playing poker.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's a lot of opportunities to do that at No Limit Hold'em.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you can have like...
SPEAKER_0:  $50 in there, you throw in a $1,000 bet.
SPEAKER_0:  And um...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, that's sometimes if you do it right.
SPEAKER_0:  it puts the other person in a really tough spot.
SPEAKER_0:  Now it's also possible that you make huge mistakes that way.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it's really easy to lose a lot of money and no limit hold them if you don't know what you're doing.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  But there's a lot of upside potential to.
SPEAKER_1:  So when you build systems, AI systems that play these games, we'll talk about poker, we'll talk about diplomacy.
SPEAKER_1:  Are you, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Are you drawn in in part by the beauty of the game itself, AI aside?
SPEAKER_1:  or is it to you primarily a fascinating?
SPEAKER_1:  problem set for the AI to solve.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm drawn in by the beauty of the game. Goodnight
SPEAKER_0:  I started playing poker when I was in high school and
SPEAKER_0:  The idea to me that there is...
SPEAKER_0:  a correct, an objectively correct way of playing poker.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you could figure out what that is, then you're...
SPEAKER_0:  You're making unlimited money basically.
SPEAKER_0:  That's like a really fascinating concept to me.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I was fascinated by the strategy of poker.
SPEAKER_0:  even when I was like 16 years old.
SPEAKER_0:  It wasn't until much later that I actually worked on poker AIs.
SPEAKER_1:  So there was a sense that you can solve poker.
SPEAKER_1:  In the way you can solve chess, for example, or checkers.
SPEAKER_1:  I believe checkers got sold, right?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, checkers, checkers.
SPEAKER_0:  completely solved. Optimal strategy. Optimal strategy.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and so in that same way you could technically solve chess.
SPEAKER_0:  You could solve chess, you could solve poker. You could solve poker.
SPEAKER_0:  So this gets into the concept of an Nash equilibrium.
SPEAKER_0:  So it is a Nash equilibrium.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  in any finite 2-player zero-sum game.
SPEAKER_0:  There is an optimal strategy.
SPEAKER_0:  that if you play it, you are guaranteed to not lose an expectation no matter what your opponent does.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of a radical concept to a lot of people.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's true in chess. It's true in poker. It's true in any finite two-player zero-sum game
SPEAKER_0:  And to give some intuition for this, you can think of rock, paper, scissors.
SPEAKER_0:  and rock, paper, scissors.
SPEAKER_0:  If you randomly choose between throwing rock, paper, and scissors with equal probability,
SPEAKER_0:  then no matter what your opponent does...
SPEAKER_0:  you are not going to lose an expectation. you are not going to lose an expectation in the long run.
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  The same is true for poker. There exists some strategy, some really complicated strategy.
SPEAKER_0:  that if you play that, you are guaranteed to not lose money.
SPEAKER_0:  in the long run. And I should say this is for two player.
SPEAKER_0:  Six player poker is a different story.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's a beautiful giant mess.
SPEAKER_1:  when you say in expectation.
SPEAKER_1:  You're guaranteed not to lose in expectation. What does in expectation mean?
SPEAKER_0:  Poker is a very high variance game, so you're gonna have hands where you win, you're gonna have hands where you lose, even if you're playing the perfect strategy, you can't guarantee you're gonna win every single hand.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you play for long enough...
SPEAKER_0:  then you are guaranteed to at least break even and.
SPEAKER_0:  in practice probably one.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's an expectation. The size of your stack.
SPEAKER_1:  generally speaking.
SPEAKER_1:  Now that doesn't include anything about
SPEAKER_1:  the fact that you can go broke, it doesn't include any of those kinds of normal, real world limitations. You're talking in a theoretical world.
SPEAKER_1:  What about the zero sum aspect? How big of a constraint is that? How big of a constraint is finite?
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Finites in-
SPEAKER_0:  not a huge constraint. So I mean most games that you play are finite in size.
SPEAKER_0:  It's also true actually that there exists this like perfect strategy in many infinite games as well.
SPEAKER_0:  Technically the game has to be compact.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  There are like some edge cases where you don't have a Nash Equilibrium in a two player zero sum game.
SPEAKER_0:  So you can think of a game where you're like.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, if we're playing a game where whoever names the bigger number...
SPEAKER_0:  is the winner.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no Nash equilibrium to that game. 17. Yeah, exactly. 18.
SPEAKER_1:  You win again.
SPEAKER_1:  You're good at this.
SPEAKER_1:  I played a lot of games.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so that's and then the zero sum aspect.
SPEAKER_0:  Zero sum aspects.
SPEAKER_0:  So there exists a Nash equilibrium.
SPEAKER_0:  in non-two-player zero-sum games as well. And by the way, just to clarify what I mean by two-player zero-sum.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, there's two players, and whatever one player wins, the other player loses.
SPEAKER_0:  So if we're playing poker and I win $50, that means that you're losing $50.
SPEAKER_0:  Now
SPEAKER_0:  Outside of two-player zero-sum games.
SPEAKER_0:  there still exists dash equilibria.
SPEAKER_0:  but they're not as meaningful.
SPEAKER_0:  because you can think of a game like Risk.
SPEAKER_0:  If everybody else on the board decides to team up against you and take you out.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no perfect strategy you can play that's gonna...
SPEAKER_0:  guarantee that you win there. There's just nothing you can do.
SPEAKER_0:  So outside of two-player zero-sum games, there's no guarantee.
SPEAKER_0:  You're going to win by playing a Nash Equilibrium.
SPEAKER_1:  Have you ever tried to model in?
SPEAKER_1:  the other aspects of the game.
SPEAKER_1:  Which is like...
SPEAKER_1:  the pleasure you draw from playing the game.
SPEAKER_1:  And then if you're a professional poker player.
SPEAKER_1:  if you're exciting even if you lose.
SPEAKER_1:  the money you would get from the attention you get to the sponsors and all that kind of stuff
SPEAKER_1:  Z
SPEAKER_1:  That'd be a fun thing to model.
SPEAKER_1:  to model in.
SPEAKER_1:  I was like, make it sort of super complex to include the human factor.
SPEAKER_1:  in its full complexity.
SPEAKER_0:  I think you bring up a couple good points there, so I think...
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of professional poker players, I mean, they get a huge amount of money, not from actually playing poker, but from the sponsorships and...
SPEAKER_0:  having a personality that people want to tune in and watch.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a big way to make a name for yourself in poker.
SPEAKER_1:  I just wonder from an AI perspective if you create and we'll talk about this more maybe
SPEAKER_1:  AI.
SPEAKER_1:  system that also.
SPEAKER_1:  talks trash and all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  that becomes part of the function to maximize. It's not just.
SPEAKER_1:  optimal poker play maybe sometimes you want to be chaotic maybe sometimes you want to be suboptimal you lose
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  the chaos and maybe sometimes you want to be overly aggressive.
SPEAKER_1:  because people.
SPEAKER_1:  the audience.
SPEAKER_1:  Loves that.
SPEAKER_1:  That'd be fascinating.
SPEAKER_0:  I think what you're getting at here is that there's a difference between making an AI that wins a game and an AI that's fun to play with.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. And fun to watch. So those are all different things. Fun to play with and fun to watch.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and I think, you know, I've...
SPEAKER_0:  I've heard talks from game designers and they say people that work on AI for actual recreational games that people play.
SPEAKER_0:  And they say, yeah, there's a big difference between trying to make an AI that actually wins. And you look at a game like Civilization.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  The way that the AIs play is not...
SPEAKER_0:  optimal for trying to win. They're playing a different game. They're trying to have personalities. They're trying to.
SPEAKER_0:  Be fun and engaging.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and
SPEAKER_0:  That makes for a better game.
SPEAKER_1:  And we also talk about NPCs. I just talked to Todd Howard, who is the creator of Fallout and the Elder Scrolls series.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Starfield, the new game coming out.
SPEAKER_1:  creator what I think is the greatest game of all time, which is skyrim.
SPEAKER_1:  and the NPCs there, the AI that governs that whole game is very interesting, but the NPCs also are super interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  considering what language models might do.
SPEAKER_1:  NPCs in an open world.
SPEAKER_1:  RPG, Role Playing Game.
SPEAKER_1:  It's super exciting.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, honestly, I'm...
SPEAKER_0:  I think this is one of the first applications where we're going to see real...
SPEAKER_0:  consumer interaction with large language models.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I guess Elder Scrolls 6 is in development now. They're probably like pretty close to finishing it.
SPEAKER_0:  I would not be surprised at all if Elder Scrolls 7
SPEAKER_0:  was using large language models for their NPS.
SPEAKER_1:  They're not there. I mean, I'm not saying anything. I'm not saying anything.
SPEAKER_0:  This is me speculating, not you.
SPEAKER_1:  No, but there's the just releasing the star feel good. They do one game at a time. Yeah. and so.
SPEAKER_1:  Whatever it is.
SPEAKER_1:  Whenever the date is, I don't know what the date is, calm down, but it would be, I don't know, like 2024, 25, 26. So it's actually very possible that it would include language models.
SPEAKER_0:  I was listening to this.
SPEAKER_0:  this talk by a gaming executive.
SPEAKER_0:  when I was in grad school.
SPEAKER_0:  And one of the questions that
SPEAKER_0:  A person in the audience asked is, why are all these games so focused on fighting and killing?
SPEAKER_0:  And the person responded that it's just so much harder to make an AI that can
SPEAKER_0:  talk with you and cooperate with you than it is to make an AI that can fight you.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I think once this technology develops further and you can have a, you can reach a point where like not every single line of dialogue has to be scripted.
SPEAKER_0:  It unlocks a lot of potential for new kinds of games, like much more.
SPEAKER_0:  interactions that are not so focused on fighting and I'm really looking forward to that.
SPEAKER_1:  It might not be positive, it might be just drama. So you'll be in like a Call of Duty game instead of doing the shooting. You'll just be hanging out.
SPEAKER_1:  and like arguing with an AI about like.
SPEAKER_1:  Like passive aggressive and then you won't be able to sleep that night. You have to return and continue the argument
SPEAKER_1:  that you were emotionally hurt.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, yeah, I think that's actually an exciting world.
SPEAKER_1:  Whatever is the drama, the chaos that we love, the push and pull of human connection, I think it's possible to do that in the video game world.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think you could be messier and make more mistakes in a video game world, which is why it would be a nice place.
SPEAKER_1:  And also it doesn't have.
SPEAKER_1:  as deep of a real psychological impact because inside video games it's kind of understood that you're in a not a real world.
SPEAKER_1:  So whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  crazy stuff he does.
SPEAKER_1:  we have some flexibility to play.
SPEAKER_1:  Just like with the game of diplomacy, it's a game.
SPEAKER_1:  This is not real geopolitics, not real war. It's a game, so you can have a little bit of fun.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... a little bit of chaos okay back to the secret uh... how do we find the Nash Equilibrium
SPEAKER_0:  Alright, so there's different ways to find a Nash Equilibrium.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  The way that we do it is with this process called self-play.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, we have this algorithm.
SPEAKER_0:  that starts by playing totally randomly.
SPEAKER_0:  and it learns.
SPEAKER_0:  how to play the game by playing against itself.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  It will
SPEAKER_0:  start playing the game totally randomly and then it you know if it's playing poker it'll eventually like
SPEAKER_0:  get to the end of the game and make $50.
SPEAKER_0:  and then it will like review all the decisions that it made along the way.
SPEAKER_0:  and say it.
SPEAKER_0:  What would have happened if I had chosen this other action instead?
SPEAKER_0:  you know, if I had raised here instead of called.
SPEAKER_0:  What would the other player have done?
SPEAKER_0:  And because it's playing against a copy of itself, it's able to do that counterfactual reasoning.
SPEAKER_0:  So I can say, okay, well.
SPEAKER_0:  If I took this action and the other person takes this action and then I take this action.
SPEAKER_0:  and eventually I make $150 instead of 50.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  It updates.
SPEAKER_0:  the regret value for that action.
SPEAKER_0:  Regret is basically like how much does it regret having not played that action in the past?
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  when it encounters that same situation again.
SPEAKER_0:  it's going to pick actions that have higher regret with higher probability.
SPEAKER_0:  Now
SPEAKER_0:  It'll just keep simulating the games this way. It'll keep, you know, accumulating regrets for different situations.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and in the long run.
SPEAKER_0:  If you pick actions that have higher probability in the correct way,
SPEAKER_0:  proven to converge to a Nash equilibrium.
SPEAKER_1:  even for super complex games, even for imperfect information games.
SPEAKER_0:  It's true for all games. It's true for chess, it's true for poker. It's particularly useful for poker.
SPEAKER_1:  So this is the method of counterfactual regret minimization.
SPEAKER_0:  This is counterfactual regret.
SPEAKER_1:  That doesn't have to do with self-play, it has to do with just...
SPEAKER_1:  and if you follow this kind of process, hopefully or not.
SPEAKER_1:  you'll be able to...
SPEAKER_1:  arrive at an optimal set of actions.
SPEAKER_0:  So this counterfactual regret minimization is a kind of self-play.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a.
SPEAKER_0:  principled kind of self-play that's proven to converge to Nash Equilibria.
SPEAKER_0:  even in in-private information games.
SPEAKER_0:  Now you can have other forms of self-play and people use other forms of self-play for perfect information games.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  where you have more flexibility the algorithm doesn't have to be as theoretically sound.
SPEAKER_0:  in order to converge to that class of games because there's
SPEAKER_0:  It's a simpler setting.
SPEAKER_1:  Sure. So I kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  In my brain, the word self-play has mapped to neural networks, but we're speaking something bigger than just neural networks. It could be anything.
SPEAKER_1:  The self-playing mechanism is just the mechanism of a system playing itself.
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly, yeah. Self-play is not tied specifically to neural nets. It's a...
SPEAKER_0:  kind of reinforcement learning basically.
SPEAKER_0:  And I would also say.
SPEAKER_0:  this process of like.
SPEAKER_0:  trying to reason, oh, what would the value have been if I had
SPEAKER_0:  taking this other action instead.
SPEAKER_0:  This is very similar to how humans learn to play a game like poker.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Like, you probably played poker before and...
SPEAKER_0:  With your friends you probably ask like, oh.
SPEAKER_0:  Would you have called me if I raised there?
SPEAKER_0:  You know, and that's, that's.
SPEAKER_0:  a person trying to do the same kind of like learning from a counterfactual that the AI is doing.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, and if you do that at scale, you're gonna be able to learn.
SPEAKER_1:  an optimal policy.
SPEAKER_0:  Now where the neural nets come in...
SPEAKER_0:  I said like, okay, if it's in that situation again.
SPEAKER_0:  then it will choose the action that has high regret.
SPEAKER_0:  Now the problem is that poker is such a huge game.
SPEAKER_0:  I think at No Limits Texas Hold'em, the version that we were playing has 10 to the 161 different decision points.
SPEAKER_0:  which is more than the number of atoms in the universe squared. That's heads up.
SPEAKER_0:  That's heads up.
SPEAKER_1:  turn to the 161
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean it depends on the number of chips that you have, the stacks and everything, but like the version that we were playing.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's test the 161.
SPEAKER_1:  which I assume would be a somewhat simplified version anyway.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  I bet there's some like step function you had for like bets.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh no no no that's that's I'm saying like we played the full game you can bet whatever amount you
SPEAKER_0:  The bot maybe was constrained in what it considered for bed sizes.
SPEAKER_0:  the person on the other side can bet whatever they wanted.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean.
SPEAKER_1:  161 plus or minus 10 doesn't matter.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and so the way neural nets help out here is.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you don't have to run into the same exact situation because that's never going to happen again. The odds of you running into the same exact situation are pretty slim.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you run into a similar situation, then you can generalize from other states that you've been in that kind of look like that one.
SPEAKER_0:  And you can say like, well...
SPEAKER_0:  These other situations, I had high regret for this action. So maybe I should play that action here.
SPEAKER_0:  as well.
SPEAKER_1:  which is the more complex game.
SPEAKER_1:  Cheers.
SPEAKER_1:  or poker.
SPEAKER_1:  or go or poker, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  That is a-
SPEAKER_0:  controversial question. Okay. I'm gonna.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like somebody screaming on reddit right now. It depends on which subreddit you're on. Is it chess or is it poker?
SPEAKER_0:  I'm sure David Silver is going to get really angry at me. I'm going to say poker actually, and I think for a couple reasons.
SPEAKER_0:  um... they're not here to defend
SPEAKER_1:  themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  First of all, you have the imperfect information aspect. And so,
SPEAKER_0:  It's um...
SPEAKER_0:  We can go into that, but once you introduce him to have
SPEAKER_0:  Uh
SPEAKER_0:  things get much more complicated.
SPEAKER_1:  So we should say.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe you can describe.
SPEAKER_1:  what is seen to the players, what is not seen.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... in the game of Texas Hold'em
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so Texas Fold-Um, you get two cards face down.
SPEAKER_0:  that only you see.
SPEAKER_0:  And so that's the hidden information of the game. The other players also all get two cards facedown that only they see.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you have to kind of, as you're playing, reason about like, okay, what do they think I have?
SPEAKER_0:  What do they have?
SPEAKER_0:  What do they think I think they have? That kind of stuff and-
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  That's kind of where bluffing comes into play, right? Because...
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that you can bluff.
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that you can bet with a bad hand and still win.
SPEAKER_0:  is because they don't know what your cards are.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's the key difference between a perfect information game like poker, sorry, like chess and go.
SPEAKER_0:  and in preparation games like
SPEAKER_1:  This is what.
SPEAKER_1:  trash talk looks like.
SPEAKER_1:  The implied statement is.
SPEAKER_1:  The game I solved is much tougher. But yeah, so when you're playing, I'm just gonna do random questions here. So what?
SPEAKER_1:  when you're playing your opponent.
SPEAKER_1:  under imperfect information.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there some degree to which you're trying to estimate the range of hands that they have?
SPEAKER_1:  or is that not part of the algorithm? What are the different approaches?
SPEAKER_1:  to the imperfect information game.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  The key thing to understand about why imperfect information makes things difficult.
SPEAKER_0:  is that you have to worry not just about which actions to play.
SPEAKER_0:  but the probability that you're going to play those actions.
SPEAKER_0:  So you think about...
SPEAKER_0:  Rock, paper, scissors for example. Rock, paper, scissors is an improved information game.
SPEAKER_0:  because you don't know what I'm about to.
SPEAKER_1:  I do, but yeah, usually not.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you can't just say like, I'm just going to throw a rock every single time.
SPEAKER_0:  because the other person's gonna figure that out.
SPEAKER_0:  and notice a pattern and then suddenly you're going to start losing.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you don't just have to figure out which action to play, you have to figure out the probability that you play it.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  really importantly.
SPEAKER_0:  the value of an action.
SPEAKER_0:  on the probability that you're going to play it.
SPEAKER_0:  So if you're playing...
SPEAKER_0:  rock every single time, that value is really low.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you're
SPEAKER_0:  Never playing rock. You play rock like 1% of the time and suddenly the
SPEAKER_0:  The other person's probably gonna be throwing...
SPEAKER_0:  Scissors.
SPEAKER_0:  And when you throw a rock, the value of that action is going to be really high.
SPEAKER_0:  Now you take that to poker, what that means is...
SPEAKER_0:  the value of bluffing, for example.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're the kind of person that never bluffs and you have this reputation as somebody that never bluffs
SPEAKER_0:  and suddenly you bluff?
SPEAKER_0:  there's a really good chance that that bluff is gonna work.
SPEAKER_0:  and you're gonna make a lot of money.
SPEAKER_0:  On the other hand, if you got a reputation, like if they've seen you play for a long time and they see, oh, you're the kind of person that's bluffing all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  When you bluff, they're not gonna buy it and they're gonna call you down, you're gonna lose a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  And that.
SPEAKER_0:  finding that balance of how often you should be bluffing.
SPEAKER_0:  is
SPEAKER_0:  the key challenge of a game of poker.
SPEAKER_0:  And you contrast that with a game like chess.
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't matter if you're opening with the Queen's Gambit.
SPEAKER_0:  10% of the time or 100% of the time.
SPEAKER_0:  the value, the expected value is the same.
SPEAKER_0:  So, um.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's why we need these algorithms.
SPEAKER_0:  that understand.
SPEAKER_0:  Not just we have to figure out what actions are good, but the probabilities. We need to get the exact probabilities correct.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's actually when we created the bot, Lebratis.
SPEAKER_0:  Lebrotis means balanced because the algorithm that we designed
SPEAKER_0:  was designed to find that right balance of.
SPEAKER_0:  how often it should play each action.
SPEAKER_1:  the balance of how often in the key sort of branching is the bluff or not the bluff.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that a good crude simplification of the major decision in poker?
SPEAKER_0:  It's a good simplification. I think that's like the main tension.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's not just.
SPEAKER_0:  how often to bluff or not to bluff. It's like, how often should you bet in general? How often should you...
SPEAKER_0:  What kind of bet should you make?
SPEAKER_0:  Should you bet big or should you bet small?
SPEAKER_0:  And with which hands?
SPEAKER_0:  And so this is where the idea of a range comes from.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  when you're bluffing with a particular hand in a particular spot.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't want there to be a pattern for the other person to pick up on. You don't want them to figure out, oh, whenever this person is in this spot.
SPEAKER_0:  They're always bluffing.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you have to reason about.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Would I also?
SPEAKER_0:  bet with a good hand in this spot.
SPEAKER_0:  You want to be unpredictable.
SPEAKER_0:  So you have to think about.
SPEAKER_0:  What would I do if I had this different set of cards?
SPEAKER_1:  Is there explicit estimation of like a theory of mind that the other person has about you or is that just a emergent thing that happens?
SPEAKER_0:  The way that the...
SPEAKER_0:  bots.
SPEAKER_0:  handle it that are really successful, they have an explicit theory of mind. So they're explicitly reasoning.
SPEAKER_0:  about.
SPEAKER_0:  What are?
SPEAKER_0:  What's the common knowledge belief? What is-
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think I have? What do I think you have?
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think? I think you have.
SPEAKER_0:  It's explicitly reasoning about that.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there multiple U's there? So,
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe that's jumping ahead to six players, but is there a stickiness to the person?
SPEAKER_1:  to certain iterative game you're playing the same person
SPEAKER_1:  There is a s-
SPEAKER_1:  There's a stickiness to that, right? You're gathering information as you play.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not every, every, uh,
SPEAKER_1:  Every hand is a new hand. Is there, um...
SPEAKER_1:  a continuation in terms of.
SPEAKER_1:  estimating what kind of player I'm facing here.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a good question. so
SPEAKER_0:  You could approach the game that way. The way that the bots do it, they don't, and the way that humans approach it also, experts human players.
SPEAKER_0:  The way they approach it is to basically assume...
SPEAKER_0:  that you know.
SPEAKER_0:  My strategy.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm going to try to pick a strategy where even if I were to play it for 10,000 hands and you could figure out exactly what it was.
SPEAKER_0:  you still wouldn't be able to beat it. Basically what that means is I'm trying to approximate the Nash Equilibrium.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm trying to be perfectly balanced because if I'm playing the Nash Equilibrium...
SPEAKER_0:  even if you know what my strategy is.
SPEAKER_0:  Like I said, I'm still unbeatable in expectation.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's what the bot aims for.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's actually what a lot of expert poker players aim for as well. To start by playing...
SPEAKER_0:  The Nash Equilibrium.
SPEAKER_0:  and then maybe if they spot weaknesses in the way you're playing.
SPEAKER_0:  then they can deviate a little bit to take advantage of that.
SPEAKER_1:  They aim to be unbeatable in expectation. OK.
SPEAKER_1:  So who's the greatest poker player of all time and why is it Phil Hellmuth? So this is for Phil.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... so he's known uh...
SPEAKER_1:  at least in part for.
SPEAKER_1:  maybe playing suboptimally.
SPEAKER_1:  and he still wins a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a bit chaotic.
SPEAKER_1:  So maybe...
SPEAKER_1:  Can you speak from an AI perspective about the genius of his madness, or the madness of his genius?
SPEAKER_1:  So playing suboptimally, playing chaotically.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  as a way to make you hard to.
SPEAKER_1:  down about what your strategy is.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  The thing that I should explain first of all with like...
SPEAKER_0:  Nash Equilibrium.
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't mean that it's predictable.
SPEAKER_0:  The whole point of it is that you're trying to be unpredictable.
SPEAKER_0:  Now
SPEAKER_0:  I think when somebody like Phil Helmuth might be really successful.
SPEAKER_0:  is not in being unpredictable, but in being able to...
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  take advantage of the other player and figure out where they're being predictable.
SPEAKER_0:  or
SPEAKER_0:  guiding the other player into thinking.
SPEAKER_0:  that you have certain weaknesses.
SPEAKER_0:  and then understanding how they're going to change their behavior, they're going to deviate from
SPEAKER_0:  Nash equilibrium style of play.
SPEAKER_0:  to try to take advantage of those perceived weaknesses and then counter exploit them.
SPEAKER_0:  So you kind of get into the mind games there.
SPEAKER_1:  So you think about.
SPEAKER_1:  at least has a poker as a dance between two agents.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess you're playing the cards or you're playing the player.
SPEAKER_0:  So this gets down to a big argument.
SPEAKER_0:  in the poker community and the academic community. For a long time there was this debate of like
SPEAKER_0:  What's called GTO, Game Theory Optimal Poker.
SPEAKER_0:  or exploitative play.
SPEAKER_0:  And um
SPEAKER_0:  up until about like 2017 when we did the Lebronis match.
SPEAKER_0:  I think actually exploitative play had the advantage. A lot of people were saying like...
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, this whole idea of game theory, it's just nonsense and-
SPEAKER_0:  If you really want to make money, you've got to look into the other person's eyes and read their soul and figure out...
SPEAKER_0:  what cards they have.
SPEAKER_0:  But what happened was people started adopting the Game Theory Optimal Strategy.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  and they were making good money.
SPEAKER_0:  and they weren't trying to.
SPEAKER_0:  adapt so much to the other player, they were just trying to play...
SPEAKER_0:  the Nash Equilibrium.
SPEAKER_0:  And then what really solidified it, I think, was the Labrador's match.
SPEAKER_0:  where we played our bot against four top heads up, no limit. Hold em.
SPEAKER_0:  Poker players.
SPEAKER_0:  and the bot.
SPEAKER_0:  wasn't trying to adapt to them, it wasn't trying to exploit them, it wasn't trying to do these mind games, it was just trying to approximate the Nash equilibrium.
SPEAKER_0:  and it crushed them.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  We were playing for $50, $100 blinds.
SPEAKER_0:  And over the course of about 120,000 hands, it made...
SPEAKER_0:  close to $2 million.
SPEAKER_1:  120,000 hands.
SPEAKER_0:  20,000 hands. Against humans. Yeah. And this was fake money to be clear. So there was real money at stake. There was $200,000.
SPEAKER_1:  All money is fake, but um.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a different conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  we give it meaning.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a phenomena that gets meaning from our complex psychology as a human civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  It's emerging from the collective intelligence of the human species, but that's not what you mean. You mean like there's literally, you can't buy stuff with it. Okay. Can you actually step back and-
SPEAKER_1:  take me through that.
SPEAKER_1:  competition.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, okay, so.
SPEAKER_0:  When I was in grad school, there was this thing called the annual computer poker competition.
SPEAKER_0:  where every year.
SPEAKER_0:  All the different research labs that were working on AI for poker would get together, they would make a bot, they would play them against each other.
SPEAKER_0:  And we made a bot that actually won the
SPEAKER_0:  the 2014 competition, the 2016 competition.
SPEAKER_0:  And so we decided we're going to take this bot, build on it.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  play against real top professional, heads up, no limit, Texas Hold'em poker players.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  We invited four of the world's best.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... players in this specialty
SPEAKER_0:  and we challenge them to 120,000 hands of poker over the course of 20 days.
SPEAKER_0:  And we had $200,000.
SPEAKER_0:  $200,000 in prize money at stake.
SPEAKER_0:  where it would basically be divided among them depending on how well they did relative to each other.
SPEAKER_0:  So we wanted to have some incentive for them to play their best.
SPEAKER_1:  Did you have a confidence?
SPEAKER_1:  2014, 16, that this is even possible.
SPEAKER_1:  How much doubt was there?
SPEAKER_0:  So we did a competition actually in 2015 where we also played against professional poker players and the bot lost by a pretty sizable margin actually.
SPEAKER_0:  Now there were some big improvements from 2015 to 2017.
SPEAKER_1:  And so can you speak to the improvements? Is it computational nature? Or is it the algorithm, the methods?
SPEAKER_0:  It was really an algorithmic approach.
SPEAKER_0:  that was the difference. So we go
SPEAKER_0:  2015 it was much more focused on
SPEAKER_0:  trying to
SPEAKER_0:  come up with a strategy upfront, like trying to solve the entire game of poker, like, and then just have
SPEAKER_0:  a lookup table where you're saying like, oh, I'm in this situation.
SPEAKER_0:  What's the strategy?
SPEAKER_0:  The approach that we took in 2017 was much more search-based.
SPEAKER_0:  It was trying to say, okay, well...
SPEAKER_0:  Let me in real time.
SPEAKER_0:  try to compute.
SPEAKER_0:  a much better strategy than what I had precomputed.
SPEAKER_0:  by playing against myself during self-play.
SPEAKER_1:  What is the search space?
SPEAKER_1:  for watching.
SPEAKER_1:  Poker.
SPEAKER_1:  What are you searching over?
SPEAKER_1:  What's that look like? There's different actions like raising.
SPEAKER_1:  Calling.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, what are the actions?
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Is it just a search over actions?
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  In a game like Chess, the search is like, okay, I'm in this.
SPEAKER_0:  position and I can like, you know, move these different pieces and see where things end up.
SPEAKER_0:  In poker, what you're searching over is...
SPEAKER_0:  the actions you can take for your hand.
SPEAKER_0:  the probabilities that you take those actions.
SPEAKER_0:  And then also the probabilities that you take other actions with other hands that you might have.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's kind of like a
SPEAKER_0:  to wrap your head around like why are you searching over
SPEAKER_0:  These like other.
SPEAKER_0:  Hands that you-
SPEAKER_0:  might have and like trying to figure out what you would do with those hands.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  And the idea is, again, you want to...
SPEAKER_0:  You want to always be balanced and unpredictable.
SPEAKER_0:  And so if you're a search algorithm is saying like.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, I want to raise with this hand.
SPEAKER_0:  Well,
SPEAKER_0:  in order to know whether that's a good action. Like let's say it's a bluff. You know, let's say you have a bad hand and you're saying like, oh, I think I should.
SPEAKER_0:  be betting here with this really bad hand and bluffing.
SPEAKER_0:  Well that's only a good action if you're also...
SPEAKER_0:  betting with a strong hand. Otherwise, it's an obvious bluff.
SPEAKER_1:  So if your action...
SPEAKER_1:  in some sense maximizes your own break.
SPEAKER_1:  unpredictability.
SPEAKER_1:  So that action could be mapped by your opponent to a lot of different hands, then that's a good action.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically what you wanna do is...
SPEAKER_0:  put your opponent into a tough spot.
SPEAKER_0:  So you want them to always have some doubt, like should I call here? Should I fold here?
SPEAKER_0:  And if you are...
SPEAKER_0:  raising in the appropriate balance between bluffs and good hands, then you're putting them into that tough spot. And so that's what we're trying to do. We're always trying to search for a strategy that would put the opponent into a difficult position.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you?
SPEAKER_1:  give a metric that you're trying to maximize or minimize. Does this have to do with the regret thing that we're talking about?
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of.
SPEAKER_1:  putting your opponent in a maximally tough spot.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, ultimately what you're trying to maximize is your expected
SPEAKER_0:  winning, so like your expected value, the amount of money that you're going to walk away from assuming that your opponent's
SPEAKER_0:  was playing optimally in response.
SPEAKER_0:  So you're gonna assume that your opponent is...
SPEAKER_0:  is also playing like.
SPEAKER_0:  as well as possible a Nash equilibrium approach.
SPEAKER_0:  Because if they're not, then you're just gonna make more money, right? You know.
SPEAKER_0:  anything that deviates, like by definition, the Nash equilibrium is.
SPEAKER_0:  the strategy that
SPEAKER_0:  does the best in expectation.
SPEAKER_0:  And so if you're deviating from that, then you're just.
SPEAKER_0:  they're gonna lose money and since it's a two-player zero-sum game, that means you're gonna make money.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's not an explicit like objective function that.
SPEAKER_1:  maximizes the toughness of the spot they're put in. You're always.
SPEAKER_1:  This is from a self-play reinforcement learning perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  You're just trying to maximize winnings.
SPEAKER_1:  and the rest is implicit.
SPEAKER_0:  That's right, yeah. So what we're actually trying to maximize is the expected value.
SPEAKER_0:  given that the opponent is playing optimally in response to us.
SPEAKER_0:  Now in practice what that ends up looking like.
SPEAKER_0:  is it's putting the opponent into difficult situations where there's no obvious decision to be made.
SPEAKER_1:  So the system doesn't know.
SPEAKER_1:  anything about the difficulty of the situation? Not at all, doesn't care. Okay, all right. My head was getting excited whenever I was making the opponent sweat. Okay, so you're in 2015, you didn't do as well.
SPEAKER_1:  So what's the journey from that to a system that...
SPEAKER_1:  and your mind could have a chance.
SPEAKER_0:  So 2015 we...
SPEAKER_0:  God, we beat pretty badly.
SPEAKER_0:  And we actually learned a lot from that competition. In particular,
SPEAKER_0:  You know, what became clear to me is that the way the humans were approaching the game was very different from how
SPEAKER_0:  The bot was approaching the game.
SPEAKER_0:  The bot would
SPEAKER_0:  not be doing search, it would just be trying to compute, you know, it would do like months of self play. It would just be playing against itself for months.
SPEAKER_0:  But then when it's actually playing the game, it would just act instantly.
SPEAKER_0:  And the humans when they're in a tough spot, they would sit there and think
SPEAKER_0:  sometimes even like five minutes about.
SPEAKER_0:  whether they're going to call or fold a hand.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and it became clear to me
SPEAKER_0:  That's
SPEAKER_0:  there's a good chance that that's what's missing from our bot. So I actually did some.
SPEAKER_0:  initial experiments to try to figure out how much of a difference this is actually make.
SPEAKER_0:  and the difference was huge.
SPEAKER_1:  as a signal to the human player how long you took.
SPEAKER_0:  No, no, no. I'm not saying that there were any timing tells. I was saying when the human.
SPEAKER_0:  Like the bot would always act instantly. It wouldn't-
SPEAKER_0:  try to come up with a better strategy in real time.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  over what it had pre-computed during training.
SPEAKER_0:  Whereas the human, like they have all this intuition about how to play.
SPEAKER_0:  but they're also in real time.
SPEAKER_0:  Leveraging.
SPEAKER_0:  their ability to think, to search, to plan.
SPEAKER_0:  and coming up with an even better strategy than what their intuition would say.
SPEAKER_1:  So you're saying that there's.
SPEAKER_1:  you're doing that's what you mean by you're doing search also.
SPEAKER_1:  You have a- You have a-
SPEAKER_1:  Intuition.
SPEAKER_1:  and search on top of that looking for a better solution.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what I mean by search.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  instead of acting instantly, you know, a neural net.
SPEAKER_0:  usually gives you a response in like 100 milliseconds or something, depends on the size of the net.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you can leverage extra computational resources...
SPEAKER_0:  you can possibly get a much better.
SPEAKER_0:  outcome.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  So we did some experiments in small-scale versions of Poker.
SPEAKER_0:  What we found was that...
SPEAKER_0:  If you
SPEAKER_0:  do a little bit of search, even just a little bit.
SPEAKER_0:  It was the equivalent of making.
SPEAKER_0:  your
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  your pre computed strategy like you can kind of think it as your neural net.
SPEAKER_0:  a thousand times bigger.
SPEAKER_0:  with just a little bit of search.
SPEAKER_0:  and it just like blew away.
SPEAKER_0:  all of the research that we had been working on and trying to like scale up.
SPEAKER_0:  this like pre-computed solution.
SPEAKER_0:  It was.
SPEAKER_0:  by the benefit that we got from search.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you just linger on what you mean by search here? You're searching over a space of...
SPEAKER_1:  actions
SPEAKER_1:  for your hand and for other hands.
SPEAKER_1:  How are you selecting the other hands to search over?
SPEAKER_1:  So
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Randomly.
SPEAKER_0:  No, it's all the other hands that you could have. So when you're playing No Limit Text, just hold on.
SPEAKER_0:  you've got two face down cards. And so that's 52 choose 2.
SPEAKER_0:  1326 different combinations. Now that's actually a little bit lower because there's face-up cards in the middle and so you can eliminate those as well.
SPEAKER_0:  But you're looking at like around a thousand different possible hands that you can have.
SPEAKER_0:  And so when we're doing, when the bot's doing search.
SPEAKER_0:  It's thinking explicitly.
SPEAKER_0:  There are these.
SPEAKER_0:  thousand different hands that I could have. There are these thousand different hands that you could have.
SPEAKER_0:  Let me try to figure out what would be a better strategy than what I've precomputed.
SPEAKER_0:  for.
SPEAKER_0:  these hands and your hands.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so.
SPEAKER_1:  That's search.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you fuse that?
SPEAKER_1:  with what the neural net is telling you or what the train system is telling you
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so.
SPEAKER_0:  You kind of like...
SPEAKER_0:  where the train system comes in is the value.
SPEAKER_0:  at the end. There's
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  You only look so far ahead.
SPEAKER_0:  you look like maybe one round ahead. So if you're on the flop, looking to the start of the turn.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And at that point you can use.
SPEAKER_0:  the pre-computed solution to figure out.
SPEAKER_0:  what are what's the value here of like of this strategy
SPEAKER_1:  Is it of a single action essentially in that spot?
SPEAKER_1:  you're getting a value or is it?
SPEAKER_1:  the value of the entire series of actions.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it's kind of both.
SPEAKER_0:  because you're trying to maximize the value for.
SPEAKER_0:  hand that you have, but in the process in order to maximize the value of the hand that you have.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to figure out.
SPEAKER_0:  What would I be doing with all these other hands as well?
SPEAKER_1:  But are you in the search or was going to the end?
SPEAKER_1:  the game.
SPEAKER_0:  In Labrador's we did.
SPEAKER_0:  So we only use search starting on the turn
SPEAKER_0:  and then we searched all the way to the end of the game.
SPEAKER_1:  to turn the river.
SPEAKER_1:  Can we take it?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there's four rounds of poker. So there's the preflop.
SPEAKER_0:  flop the turn in the river.
SPEAKER_0:  And so we would start doing search.
SPEAKER_0:  halfway through the game.
SPEAKER_0:  Now the first half of the game, that was all precomputed, it would just act instantly.
SPEAKER_0:  And then when it got to the halfway point.
SPEAKER_0:  then it would always search to the end of the game.
SPEAKER_0:  Now we later improved this so it wouldn't have to search all the way to the end of the game. It would actually search.
SPEAKER_0:  Just a few moves ahead.
SPEAKER_0:  But that came later and that drastically reduced the amount of computational resources that we needed.
SPEAKER_1:  But the moves, because you can keep betting on top of each other. That's what you mean by moves. So like that's where.
SPEAKER_1:  You don't just get one bet.
SPEAKER_1:  per turner poker. You can have multiple arbitrary number of bets.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, right. I'm trying to think like...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm gonna bet and then what are you gonna do in response? Are you gonna raise me? Are you gonna call?
SPEAKER_0:  And then if you raise, what should I do?
SPEAKER_0:  So it's.
SPEAKER_0:  reasoning about that whole process up until the end of the game in the case of Labrador's.
SPEAKER_1:  So for the broadest, what's the most number of re-raises have you ever seen?
SPEAKER_0:  You probably cap out at like five or something because at that point you're basically all in.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, is there like a...
SPEAKER_1:  interesting patterns like that that you've seen.
SPEAKER_1:  that the game does like you'll have like AlphaZero doing way more sacrifices than
SPEAKER_1:  humans usually do.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there something like...
SPEAKER_1:  The Brattice was constantly re-raising or something like that that you noticed.
SPEAKER_0:  There was something really interesting that we observed with Labradorus.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Humans when they're playing poker.
SPEAKER_0:  they usually size their bets relative to the size of the pot.
SPEAKER_0:  So, you know, if the pot has a hundred dollars in there.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe you bet like $75 or somewhere around that, somewhere between like $50 and $100.
SPEAKER_0:  And with Lebronis, we gave it the option to basically bet whatever it wanted. It was actually...
SPEAKER_0:  really easy for us to say like, oh, if you want, you can bet like 10 times the pot.
SPEAKER_0:  And we didn't think it would actually do that. It was just like...
SPEAKER_0:  Why not give it the option?
SPEAKER_0:  And then during the competition, it actually started doing this.
SPEAKER_0:  And by the way, this is like a very last minute decision on our part to add this option. And so we.
SPEAKER_0:  did not, we did not think the bot would do this and.
SPEAKER_0:  I was actually kind of worried when it did start to do this. Like, oh, is this a problem? Like humans don't do this. Like, is it screwing up?
SPEAKER_0:  But it would put the humans into really difficult spots when it would do that.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you can imagine like you have the second best hand that's possible given the board.
SPEAKER_0:  and you're thinking like, oh, you're in a really great spot here. And suddenly the bot.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's $20,000 into a $1,000 pot.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's basically saying like.
SPEAKER_0:  I have the best hand.
SPEAKER_0:  Or I'm bluffing.
SPEAKER_0:  and you having the second best hand like.
SPEAKER_0:  Now you get a really tough choice to make.
SPEAKER_0:  And so the humans would sometimes think like five or 10 minutes about like.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you do? Should I call? Should I fold?
SPEAKER_0:  And um
SPEAKER_0:  And when I saw the humans really struggling with that decision, that's when I realized, oh, actually, this is maybe a good thing to do after all.
SPEAKER_1:  And of course, the system is a no.
SPEAKER_1:  making.
SPEAKER_1:  Again, like we said, that is putting them in a tough spot.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just that's part of the game theory optimal.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, from the bots perspective, it's just doing the thing that's going to make it the most money.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and the fact that it's putting the humans in a difficult spot, like that's just, um, you know, a side effect of that.
SPEAKER_0:  And this was, I think...
SPEAKER_0:  The one thing, I mean, there were a few things that the humans walked away from, but this was-
SPEAKER_0:  day.
SPEAKER_0:  The number one thing that the humans walked away from the competition saying like
SPEAKER_0:  We need to start doing this.
SPEAKER_0:  And now these over bets, what are called over bets.
SPEAKER_0:  have become really common in high level poker play.
SPEAKER_1:  Have you ever talked to like...
SPEAKER_1:  somebody like Danny on the ground know about this.
SPEAKER_1:  He seems to be a student of the game.
SPEAKER_0:  I did actually have a conversation with Daniel DeGrawne once.
SPEAKER_0:  I was visiting the Isle of Man.
SPEAKER_0:  to talk to PokerStars about AI.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And Daniel and Grandi was there. We had dinner together with some other people.
SPEAKER_0:  And yeah, he was really interested in it. He mentioned that he was like.
SPEAKER_0:  excited about learning from these AIs.
SPEAKER_1:  So he wasn't scared, he was excited.
SPEAKER_0:  He was excited and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  And he honestly, he wanted to play against the bot. He thought he had a decent chance of beating it.
SPEAKER_0:  I think he, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  This is like several years ago when I think it was like.
SPEAKER_0:  not as clear to everybody that the AIs were taking over.
SPEAKER_0:  I think now people recognize that if you're playing against...
SPEAKER_0:  a bot, there's like no chance that you have in a game.
SPEAKER_1:  So consistently the bots will win.
SPEAKER_1:  The bots have heads up.
SPEAKER_1:  and in other variants too, so multi six player.
SPEAKER_1:  Texas Hold'em.
SPEAKER_1:  No limit access hold, don't miss the bots win.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that's the case. So I think there is some debate about like, is it true for every single variant of poker? I think...
SPEAKER_0:  I think for every single variant of poker, if somebody really put in the effort, they could make an AI that would beat all humans at it.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Weave.
SPEAKER_0:  focused on the most popular variants. So heads up, no limit, Texas hold them.
SPEAKER_0:  And then we followed that up with...
SPEAKER_0:  with a six player poker as well.
SPEAKER_0:  where he managed to make about that beat.
SPEAKER_0:  expert human players. And I think even there now.
SPEAKER_0:  it's pretty clear that humans don't stand a chance.
SPEAKER_1:  I would love to hook up an AI system that...
SPEAKER_1:  looks at EEG.
SPEAKER_1:  Like how, like actually.
SPEAKER_1:  tries to optimize the toughness of the spot, it puts a human in.
SPEAKER_1:  I would love to see how different is that from the Game Theory optimal.
SPEAKER_1:  So you try to maximize the heart rate of the human player.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, the freaking out.
SPEAKER_1:  over a long period of time. I wonder if there's going to be...
SPEAKER_1:  different strategies that emerge.
SPEAKER_1:  they're close in terms of effectiveness because something tells me
SPEAKER_1:  You could still.
SPEAKER_1:  B.
SPEAKER_1:  achieve superhuman level performance by just making people sweat.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like that
SPEAKER_0:  There's a good chance that that is the case, yeah. If you're-
SPEAKER_0:  able to see like.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like a decent proxy for score, right? And this is actually like the common poker wisdom where they're teaching.
SPEAKER_0:  players before they're robots.
SPEAKER_0:  and they were trying to teach people how to play poker. They would say like,
SPEAKER_0:  The key to the game is to put your opponent to difficult spots.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a good estimate for if you're making the right decision.
SPEAKER_1:  What else can you say about the fundamental role of search?
SPEAKER_1:  in poker.
SPEAKER_1:  and maybe if you can also relate it to chess and go.
SPEAKER_1:  in these games.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the role of search to solve in these games?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think a lot of people under... This is true for the general public, and I think it's true for the AI community. A lot of people underestimate the importance of search for these kinds of game AI results.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  An example of this is.
SPEAKER_0:  TD Gammon that came out in 1992. This was the first review of external
SPEAKER_0:  the first real instance of a neural net being used in a game AI.
SPEAKER_0:  landmark achievement. It was actually the inspiration for AlphaZero.
SPEAKER_0:  and it used search, it used to apply search to figure out its next move.
SPEAKER_0:  You got
SPEAKER_0:  Deep Blue there.
SPEAKER_0:  It was very heavily focused on search.
SPEAKER_0:  looking many, many moves ahead, farther than any human could.
SPEAKER_0:  And that was key for Wyatt1.
SPEAKER_0:  and then even with something like AlphaGo.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, AlphaGo is.
SPEAKER_0:  commonly hailed as
SPEAKER_0:  a landmark achievement for neural nets, and it is.
SPEAKER_0:  But there's also this huge component of search, Monte Carlo tree search to AlphaGo.
SPEAKER_0:  that was key, absolutely essential.
SPEAKER_0:  for the AI to be able to beat top humans.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I think a good example of this is you look at.
SPEAKER_0:  the latest versions of AlphaGo, like it was called AlphaZero.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And there's this metric called Elo rating where you can.
SPEAKER_0:  compare different humans and you can compare bots to humans.
SPEAKER_0:  Now.
SPEAKER_0:  A top human player is around 3600 elo, maybe a little bit higher now.
SPEAKER_0:  Alpha Zero, the strongest version.
SPEAKER_0:  is around 5200 ELO.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you take out the search that's being done.
SPEAKER_0:  test time and but by the way what I mean by search is
SPEAKER_0:  The planning ahead, the thinking of like, oh, if I move my...
SPEAKER_0:  If I place this stone here and then he does this.
SPEAKER_0:  And then you look like five moves ahead and you see like what the board state looks like.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  That's what I mean by search.
SPEAKER_0:  If you take out the search that's done during the game...
SPEAKER_0:  The ELO rating drops to around 3000.
SPEAKER_0:  So even today.
SPEAKER_0:  what, seven years after AlphaGo.
SPEAKER_0:  If you take out the Monte Carlo tree search that's being done.
SPEAKER_0:  at.
SPEAKER_0:  when playing against a human.
SPEAKER_0:  The bots are not superhuman.
SPEAKER_0:  Nobody
SPEAKER_0:  has made a raw neural net.
SPEAKER_0:  that is superhuman in Go.
SPEAKER_1:  It's worth lingering on, that's quite profound.
SPEAKER_1:  So without search that just means looking at the next move.
SPEAKER_1:  and saying...
SPEAKER_1:  this is the best move. so having a function that estimates accurately.
SPEAKER_1:  what the best move is.
SPEAKER_0:  That's right. Without search.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and all these bots, they have the, what's called a policy network where it will tell you, this is what the neural net thinks is the next best move.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It's kind of like the intuition that a human has. You know, the human looks at the board and...
SPEAKER_0:  and any
SPEAKER_0:  uh go or chess master will be able to tell you like oh instantly here's what i think the right move is
SPEAKER_0:  And the bot is able to do the same thing.
SPEAKER_0:  But just like.
SPEAKER_0:  How a human...
SPEAKER_0:  Grandmaster can make a better decision if they have more time to think.
SPEAKER_0:  when you add on this Monte Carlo tree search.
SPEAKER_0:  the bot is able to make a better decision.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean, of course a human is doing something like searching their brain, but it's not.
SPEAKER_1:  I hesitate to draw a hard line, but it's not like Monte Carlo tree search.
SPEAKER_1:  It's more like...
SPEAKER_1:  sequential language model.
SPEAKER_1:  generation.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's like a different, it's a.
SPEAKER_1:  The neural network is doing the searching.
SPEAKER_1:  I wonder what the human brain is doing in terms of searching.
SPEAKER_1:  because you're doing that computation, like humanist computing.
SPEAKER_1:  They have intuition, they've got-
SPEAKER_1:  They have a really strong ability to estimate, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  amongst the top players of what is good and not position without calculating all the details.
SPEAKER_1:  but they're still doing search in their head.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's a different kind of search. Have you ever thought about like, what is the difference between the human and the animal?
SPEAKER_1:  the search that the human is.
SPEAKER_1:  Performing versus what?
SPEAKER_1:  computers are doing.
SPEAKER_0:  I have thought a lot about that and I think it's a really important question.
SPEAKER_0:  So the AI in Alpha and Alpha's in AlphaGo or any of these Go AIs.
SPEAKER_0:  they're all doing Monte Carlo tree search, which is a particular kind of search.
SPEAKER_0:  It's actually a symbolic tabular search. It uses the neural net to guide its search, but it isn't actually like...
SPEAKER_0:  full on neural net.
SPEAKER_0:  Now.
SPEAKER_0:  That kind of search is.
SPEAKER_0:  very successful in these kinds of like perfect information board games like chess and go.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you take it to a game like poker, for example, it doesn't work.
SPEAKER_0:  It can't.
SPEAKER_0:  It can't understand the concept of hidden information.
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't understand the balance that you have to strike between like
SPEAKER_0:  the amount that you're raising versus the amount that you're calling.
SPEAKER_0:  and in every one of these games.
SPEAKER_0:  you see a different kind of search.
SPEAKER_0:  And the human brain is able to plan for all these different games in a very general way.
SPEAKER_0:  Now, I think that's one thing that we're missing from AI today, and I think it's a really important missing piece.
SPEAKER_0:  the ability to
SPEAKER_0:  plan and reason more generally.
SPEAKER_0:  across a wide variety of different settings.
SPEAKER_1:  in a way worth general reasoning.
SPEAKER_1:  makes you better at each one of the games.
SPEAKER_0:  Not worse. Yeah, so you can kind of think of it as like neural nets today.
SPEAKER_0:  They'll give you like transformers for example, or super general.
SPEAKER_0:  but you know, they'll give you...
SPEAKER_0:  It'll output an answer.
SPEAKER_0:  in like 100 milliseconds. And if you tell it like, oh, you've got five minutes to give me a decision, feel free to take more time to make a better decision.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not gonna know what to do with that.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  But a human, if you're playing a game like chess, they're gonna give you a very different answer depending on if-
SPEAKER_0:  you say, oh, you've got 100 milliseconds or you've got five minutes.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, there, I mean, people have started using the right transformers, the language models, like the, in an iterative way that does improve the answer or like showing the work.
SPEAKER_1:  This
SPEAKER_0:  kind of idea.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, they got this thing called chain of thought reasoning. And that's, I think, super promising, right? Yeah. And I think, I think it's a good step in the right direction.
SPEAKER_0:  I would kind of like say it's similar to Monte Carlo rollouts in a game like chess. There's a kind of search that you can do.
SPEAKER_0:  where you're saying like, I'm gonna roll out my intuition and see like,
SPEAKER_0:  without really thinking.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, what are the better decisions I can make farther down the path?
SPEAKER_0:  What would I do if I just acted according to intuition for the next 10 moves?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And that.
SPEAKER_0:  gets you an improvement but I think that there's much
SPEAKER_0:  uh... much richer kinds of of
SPEAKER_0:  planning that we could do.
SPEAKER_1:  So when the broadest actually beat the poker players, what did that feel like?
SPEAKER_1:  What was that? I mean, actually on that day.
SPEAKER_1:  What were you feeling like? Were you nervous?
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, poker was one of the games that you thought like is not going to be solvable because of the human factor, so...
SPEAKER_1:  at least in the narratives we tell ourselves.
SPEAKER_1:  the human factor is so fundamental to the game of poker.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, the Lebronis competition was super stressful for me.
SPEAKER_0:  Also, I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  I was working on this basically continuously for a year leading up to the competition.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, for me, it became like very clear, like, okay, this is the search technique. This is the approach that we need.
SPEAKER_0:  And then I spent a year working on this pretty much like nonstop.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, can we actually get into details like what programming languages is it written in?
SPEAKER_1:  What's some interesting-
SPEAKER_1:  implementation details that are like...
SPEAKER_1:  fun slash painful.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so one of the interesting things about.
SPEAKER_0:  Lebron is that we had no idea what the bar was to actually beat top humans Yeah, we could play against like our prior bots and that kind of gives us some sense of like are we making progress? Are we going in the right direction?
SPEAKER_0:  But we had no idea what the bar actually was. And so we threw a huge amount of resources.
SPEAKER_0:  at trying to make the strongest bot possible.
SPEAKER_0:  So we used C++, it was parallelized, we were using I think like a thousand CPUs.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe more, actually.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, today that sounds like nothing, but for a grad student back in 2016, that was a huge amount of resources.
SPEAKER_1:  still a lot for even any grad student today. It's still tough to get.
SPEAKER_1:  or even to allow yourself to think in that.
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of scale at CMU at MIT, anything like that.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and you know talking about terabytes of memory.
SPEAKER_0:  So it was a very parallelized and it had to be very fast too because
SPEAKER_0:  the more games that you could simulate.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... the stronger the bot would be
SPEAKER_1:  So is there some like John Carmack style?
SPEAKER_1:  Like.
SPEAKER_1:  Efficiencies yet to come up with like an efficient way to represent the hand.
SPEAKER_1:  all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  There are all sorts of optimizations that I had to make to try to get this thing to run as fast as possible. They were like.
SPEAKER_0:  How do you minimize the latency? How do you package things together so that you minimize the amount of communication between the different nodes?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  How do you optimize the algorithm so that you can...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, try to squeeze out more and more from the game that you're actually playing.
SPEAKER_0:  all these kinds of different decisions that I...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, had to make.
SPEAKER_1:  Just a fun question. What ID did you use?
SPEAKER_1:  What for C++?
SPEAKER_1:  I think I used...
SPEAKER_0:  It's a visual studio actually.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay. Is that still carried through to today?
SPEAKER_0:  VS Code is what I use today.
SPEAKER_1:  It's the community basically conversion on. Okay, cool. You got this.
SPEAKER_1:  super optimized C++ system.
SPEAKER_1:  and then you show up to the day of competition.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1: ...humans versus machine.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  How did it feel throughout the day?
SPEAKER_0:  super stressful.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  I thought going into it that we had like a 50-50 chance. Basically, I thought if they play...
SPEAKER_0:  In a totally normal style, I think we'll squeak out a win.
SPEAKER_0:  but.
SPEAKER_0:  there's always a chance that they can find some weakness in the bot.
SPEAKER_0:  and if they do and we're playing like for 20 days 120 000 hands of poker they have a lot of time to find weaknesses in the system
SPEAKER_0:  And if they do...
SPEAKER_0:  we're gonna get crushed. And that's actually what happened in the previous competition.
SPEAKER_0:  The humans, you know, they started out it wasn't like a they were winning from the start
SPEAKER_0:  but then they found these weaknesses that they could take advantage of.
SPEAKER_0:  And for the next, you know, like 10 days, they were just...
SPEAKER_0:  crushing the bots, stealing money from it.
SPEAKER_1:  What were the weaknesses they found?
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe over betting was effective, that kind of stuff. So certain betting strategies worked.
SPEAKER_0:  What they found is, yeah, overbetting, like betting certain amounts, the bot would have a lot of trouble dealing with those sizes.
SPEAKER_0:  And then also.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  when the bot
SPEAKER_0:  got into really difficult all-in situations.
SPEAKER_0:  It wasn't able to because it wasn't doing search. It had to
SPEAKER_0:  clump different hands together and it wouldn't it would treat them identically.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it wouldn't be able to distinguish.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, like...
SPEAKER_0:  having a king high flush versus an ace high flush. And in some situations that really matters a lot. And so they could put the bot into those situations and then the bot would just bleed money.
SPEAKER_1:  Clever humans. Okay, so I didn't realize it was over 20 days.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  What were the humans like over those 20 days?
SPEAKER_1:  And what was the bot like?
SPEAKER_0:  So we had set up the competition, you know, like I said, there was $200,000 in prize money.
SPEAKER_0:  and they would get paid.
SPEAKER_0:  a fraction of that depending on how well they did relative to each other.
SPEAKER_0:  So I was kind of hoping that they wouldn't work together to try to find weaknesses in the bot.
SPEAKER_0:  they enter the competition with their like number one objective being to beat the bot
SPEAKER_0:  and they didn't care about like individual glory. They were like, we're all going to work as a team.
SPEAKER_0:  to try to take down this bot. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  they immediately started comparing notes. what they would do.
SPEAKER_0:  is they would coordinate.
SPEAKER_0:  looking at different parts of the strategy to try to find out weaknesses.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And then at the end of the day...
SPEAKER_0:  We actually sent them a log of all the hands that were played and what
SPEAKER_0:  cards the bot had on each of those hands. Oh wow.
SPEAKER_0:  That's gutsy. Yeah, it was honestly, I'm not sure why we did that in retrospect, but um.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I'm glad we did it because we ended up winning anyway, but...
SPEAKER_0:  That if you've ever played poker before like that is golden information. I mean to know
SPEAKER_0:  Usually when you play poker, you see about a third of the hands to showdown.
SPEAKER_0:  and to just hand them.
SPEAKER_0:  all the cards that the bot had on every single hand.
SPEAKER_0:  That was, um...
SPEAKER_0:  just a gold mine for them. And so then they would review the hands.
SPEAKER_0:  and try to see like, okay, could they find patterns in the bot? The weakness is, and could they then?
SPEAKER_0:  then they would coordinate and study together and try to figure out okay now
SPEAKER_0:  This person's gonna explore this part of the strategy for weaknesses. This person's gonna explore this part of the strategy for weaknesses.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a kind of psychological warfare showing in the hands. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I'm sure you didn't think of it that way, but like
SPEAKER_1:  Doing that means you're confident in the possibility to win.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, that's one way of putting it. I wasn't super confident. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, going in, like I said, I think I had like 50, 50 odds on us winning the-
SPEAKER_0:  When we actually when we announced the competition
SPEAKER_0:  the poker community decided to gamble on who would win and their initial odds against us were like four to one. They were really convinced that the humans were gonna-
SPEAKER_0:  lot of win.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  The bot ended up winning for three days straight.
SPEAKER_0:  And even then after three days, the betting odds were still just 50-50.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And then at that point...
SPEAKER_0:  It started to look like the humans.
SPEAKER_0:  were coming back, they started to like, you know, but poker is a very high variance game.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I think what happened is like they thought that they spotted some weaknesses that weren't actually there.
SPEAKER_0:  And then around day eight, it was just very clear that they were getting absolutely crushed.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And from that point, for a while there, I was super stressed out.
SPEAKER_0:  thinking like, oh my God, the humans are coming back and they've found weaknesses and now we're just gonna lose the whole thing. But no, it ended up going in the other direction and the bot ended up crushing them in the long-
SPEAKER_1:  How did it feel at the end?
SPEAKER_1:  As a human being, what did-
SPEAKER_1:  as a person who loves.
SPEAKER_1:  appreciates the beauty of the game of poker.
SPEAKER_1:  and the person who appreciates
SPEAKER_1:  The beauty of AI.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there?
SPEAKER_1:  Did you feel a certain kind of way about it?
SPEAKER_0:  I felt a lot of things, man.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, at that point in my life, I had spent five years working on this project.
SPEAKER_0:  and um
SPEAKER_0:  It was a huge sense of accomplishment. I mean, to spend five years working on something and finally see it succeed.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I wouldn't trade that for anything in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, because that's a real benchmark. It's not like a-
SPEAKER_1:  getting some percent accuracy in a data set.
SPEAKER_1:  This is like real.
SPEAKER_1:  This is real world.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just a game, but it's also a game that means a lot to a lot of people.
SPEAKER_1:  and this is humans doing their best to beat the machine. So this is a real benchmark.
SPEAKER_1:  unlike anything else.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and I mean this is...
SPEAKER_0:  This is what I had been dreaming about since I was like 16 playing poker, you know, with my friends in high school.
SPEAKER_0:  the idea that you could find a strategy.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... uh... you know approximately the national will be able to beat
SPEAKER_0:  all the poker players in the world with it.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, so to actually see that.
SPEAKER_0:  come to fruition and be realized?
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, that was...
SPEAKER_0:  It's kind of magical.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, especially money is on the line too. It's different than chess.
SPEAKER_1:  And that aspect, like people get.
SPEAKER_1:  That's why you want to look at betting Marcus.
SPEAKER_1:  if you want to actually understand.
SPEAKER_1:  what people really think. In the same sense, poker, it's really high stakes because it's money.
SPEAKER_1:  to solve that game. That's an amazing accomplishment.
SPEAKER_1:  So the leap from that to...
SPEAKER_1:  Multiway 6 player poker
SPEAKER_1:  What's...
SPEAKER_1:  How difficult is that jump?
SPEAKER_1:  And what are some interesting differences between heads up poker and-
SPEAKER_1:  and multiway poker.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so I mentioned.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, Nash equilibrium in two-player zero-sum games.
SPEAKER_0:  If you play that strategy, you are guaranteed to not lose an expectation no matter what your opponent does.
SPEAKER_0:  Now once you go to 6 player poker, you're no longer playing a 2 player zero sum game.
SPEAKER_0:  And so there was a lot of debate among the academic community and among the poker community.
SPEAKER_0:  about how well these techniques would extend.
SPEAKER_0:  beyond just two player heads up poker.
SPEAKER_0:  Now
SPEAKER_0:  What I had come to realize is that...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  the techniques actually I thought really would extend to six-player poker because even though in theory
SPEAKER_0:  They don't.
SPEAKER_0:  give you these guarantees outside of two players, here are some of the games!
SPEAKER_0:  In practice, it still gives you a really strong strategy.
SPEAKER_0:  Now.
SPEAKER_0:  There were a lot of complications that would come up with 6-player poker, besides the game theoretic aspect, I mean for one...
SPEAKER_0:  The game is just.
SPEAKER_0:  exponentially larger.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  So the main thing that allowed us.
SPEAKER_0:  go from two player to six player?
SPEAKER_0:  was the idea of Deaf Limited Search.
SPEAKER_0:  So I said before, like, you know, we would do search, we would plan out.
SPEAKER_0:  The bot would plan out what it's going to do next and for the next several moves.
SPEAKER_0:  And in the broadest that search was done.
SPEAKER_0:  extending all the way to the end of the game.
SPEAKER_0:  So we have to start.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  It from from the.
SPEAKER_0:  turn onwards, like looking maybe 10 moves ahead.
SPEAKER_0:  it would have to figure out.
SPEAKER_0:  what it was doing for all those moves.
SPEAKER_0:  Now when you get to six player poker, it can't do that exhaustive search anymore because the game is just way too large.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, but by only
SPEAKER_0:  having to look a few moves ahead and then stopping there.
SPEAKER_0:  and substituting a value estimate of like...
SPEAKER_0:  How good is that strategy at that point?
SPEAKER_0:  then we're able to...
SPEAKER_0:  do a much more scalable form of search.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there something cool we're looking at the paper right now?
SPEAKER_1:  Is there something cool in the paper in terms of graphics?
SPEAKER_1:  a GameTree Traversal via Monte Carlo.
SPEAKER_0:  i think if you go down a bit uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Figure 1, an example of equilibrium selection problem.
SPEAKER_1:  Ooh, so yeah, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  What do we know about equilibria?
SPEAKER_1:  when there's multiple players.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  When you go outside of two players, you're a sum.
SPEAKER_0:  So a Nash equilibrium is a set of strategies, like one strategy for each player.
SPEAKER_0:  where no player has an incentive to switch to a different strategy.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you can kind of think of it as like imagine
SPEAKER_0:  you have a game where there's a ring.
SPEAKER_0:  That's actually the visual here. You got a ring.
SPEAKER_0:  and the object of the game is to be as far away from the other players as possible.
SPEAKER_0:  There's.
SPEAKER_0:  A Nash equilibrium is for all the players to be spaced equally apart around this ring.
SPEAKER_0:  But there's infinitely many different Nash equilibria, right? There's infinitely many ways.
SPEAKER_0:  to space four dots along a ring.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  if every single player independently computes a Nash Equilibrium
SPEAKER_0:  then there's no guarantee that the joint strategy they're all playing
SPEAKER_0:  is going to be a Nash equilibrium.
SPEAKER_0:  DERP
SPEAKER_0:  They're just gonna be like random dots scattered along this ring rather than...
SPEAKER_0:  four coordinated dots being equally spaced apart.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it possible to sort of optimally do this kind of selection?
SPEAKER_1:  to do the selection of.
SPEAKER_1:  of the equilibrium you're chasing.
SPEAKER_1:  So is there like a meta problem to be solved here?
SPEAKER_0:  So the meta problem is in some sense, how do you...
SPEAKER_0:  How do you understand the Nash equilibria that the other players are going to play?
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  And even if you do that, again, there's no guarantee that you're going to win.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, if you're playing...
SPEAKER_0:  If you're
SPEAKER_0:  playing risk like I said and all the other players side team up against you
SPEAKER_0:  You're gonna lose. Mass equilibrium doesn't help you there.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  So there is this big debate about whether Nash equilibrium and all these techniques that compute it
SPEAKER_0:  are even useful once you go outside of two players' in-game
SPEAKER_0:  Now.
SPEAKER_0:  I think for many games, there is a valid criticism here.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think when we talk about, when we got to something like diplomacy.
SPEAKER_0:  We run into this issue.
SPEAKER_0:  The
SPEAKER_0:  approach of trying to approximate a Nash equilibrium.
SPEAKER_0:  doesn't really work anymore.
SPEAKER_0:  But it turns out that in 6 player poker...
SPEAKER_0:  Because six player poker is such an adversarial game
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  where.
SPEAKER_0:  none of the players really try to work with each other.
SPEAKER_0:  the techniques that were used into Player Poker to try to approximate an equilibrium.
SPEAKER_0:  those still end up working in practice in six player poker as well.
SPEAKER_1:  There's some.
SPEAKER_1:  Deep way in which six player poker is just a bunch of heads up poker like games in one.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like embedded in it. So the competitiveness.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  is more fundamental to poker than the cooperation.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, yeah, poker is just such an adversarial game, there's no real cooperation. In fact, you're not even allowed to cooperate in poker. It's considered collusion, it's against the rules.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And so for that reason, the techniques end up working really well. And I think that's true more broadly.
SPEAKER_0:  and extremely adverse serial games in general.
SPEAKER_1:  but that's sort of in practice versus being able to prove something.
SPEAKER_0:  That's right, nobody has a proof that that's the case. And it could be that six player poker belongs to some class of games.
SPEAKER_0:  where
SPEAKER_0:  Approximating an ash equilibrium through self play
SPEAKER_0:  Proveably works well.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And you know, there are other classes of games beyond just two players, where this is proven to work well.
SPEAKER_0:  So there are these kinds of games called potential games, which...
SPEAKER_0:  I won't go into, it's kind of like a complicated concept, but...
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  There are...
SPEAKER_0:  classes of games where...
SPEAKER_0:  this approach to approximating an Nash equilibrium is proven to work well.
SPEAKER_0:  Now, 6-player poker is not known to belong to one of those classes, but it is possible that there is some classic games where it's not.
SPEAKER_0:  It either provably performs well or provably performs not that badly.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  What are some interesting things about player bus that was.
SPEAKER_1:  able to achieve human level performance on this.
SPEAKER_1:  or superhuman level performance.
SPEAKER_1:  on the 6 player version of poker.
SPEAKER_0:  Personally, I think the most interesting thing about Pluribus is that it was so much cheaper.
SPEAKER_0:  than Labrador. I mean, Labrador.
SPEAKER_0:  If you had to put a price tag on the computational resources that went into it, I would say the final training run took about $100,000.
SPEAKER_0:  You go to Pluribus.
SPEAKER_0:  The final training run.
SPEAKER_0:  would cost like less than $150 on AWS.
SPEAKER_1:  Is this normalized to computational inflation?
SPEAKER_1:  So meaning, is this just, does this.
SPEAKER_1:  just have to do with the fact that.
SPEAKER_1:  Pluribus was trained like a year later.
SPEAKER_0:  No, no, no. It's not. It's, I mean, first of all, like, yeah, computing resources are getting cheaper every day and like
SPEAKER_0:  You're not going to see a thousand-fold decrease in the computational resources over two years.
SPEAKER_0:  or even anywhere close to that. The real improvement was algorithmic improvements.
SPEAKER_0:  And in particular...
SPEAKER_0:  the ability to do depth-limited search.
SPEAKER_1:  So does depth limited search also work for Lebrados?
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, so.
SPEAKER_0:  Where this depth limited search came from is, you know, I developed this technique and
SPEAKER_0:  um, ran it on to player poker first.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's it.
SPEAKER_0:  Reduce the computational resources needed to make an AI that was superhuman.
SPEAKER_0:  from, you know, $100,000 for Labratus.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  something you could train on your laptop.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you learn from that?
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  from that discovery.
SPEAKER_0:  What I would take away from that is that algorithmic improvements really do matter.
SPEAKER_1:  How would you describe the more general?
SPEAKER_1:  case of limited dev search.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's basically constraining the scale, temporal, or in some other way.
SPEAKER_1:  the computation you're doing in some clever way.
SPEAKER_1:  like with
SPEAKER_1:  Like how else can you significantly constrain computation?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I think the idea is that...
SPEAKER_0:  We want to be able to leverage search as much as possible. And the way that we were doing it in Labradus required us to search all the way to the end of the game.
SPEAKER_0:  Now if you're playing a game like chess, the idea that you're gonna search always to the end of the game
SPEAKER_0:  is kind of unimaginable, right? Like there's just so many situations where you just won't be able to use search in that
SPEAKER_0:  or the cost would be prohibitive.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  This technique allowed us to leverage search.
SPEAKER_0:  and without having to pay such a huge computational cost for it.
SPEAKER_0:  and be able to apply it.
SPEAKER_0:  more broadly.
SPEAKER_1:  So to what degree did you use neural nets for Lebrados and Pleuribus?
SPEAKER_1:  and more generally what role do you need that's have to play
SPEAKER_1:  in, um...
SPEAKER_1:  and superhuman level performance in poker.
SPEAKER_0:  So we actually did not use neural nets at all for Lebrotis.
SPEAKER_0:  or Pluribus.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of people found this surprising.
SPEAKER_0:  Back in 2017, I think they found it surprising today.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  that we were able to do this.
SPEAKER_0:  without using any neural nets.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think the reason for that, I mean, I think neural nets are...
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  incredibly powerful.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  the techniques that are used today, even for poker AIs.
SPEAKER_0:  Do rely.
SPEAKER_0:  quite heavily on neural nets.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, but it wasn't the main challenge for poker. Like I think what neural nets.
SPEAKER_0:  are really good for?
SPEAKER_0:  If you're in a situation where
SPEAKER_0:  Finding features.
SPEAKER_0:  for a value function.
SPEAKER_0:  is really difficult, then neural nets are really powerful. And this was the problem in Go.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, like the problem in Go...
SPEAKER_0:  was that.
SPEAKER_0:  Or the final problem in Go at least.
SPEAKER_0:  was that nobody had a good way of
SPEAKER_0:  Looking at a board?
SPEAKER_0:  and figuring out who was winning or losing and describing.
SPEAKER_0:  through a simple algorithm.
SPEAKER_0:  who was winning or losing.
SPEAKER_0:  And so they are neural nets.
SPEAKER_0:  were super helpful because you could just feed in a ton of different board positions into this neural net.
SPEAKER_0:  and it would be able to predict then who was winning or losing.
SPEAKER_0:  But in poker...
SPEAKER_0:  The features weren't the challenge. The challenge was...
SPEAKER_0:  How do you?
SPEAKER_0:  design a scalable algorithm?
SPEAKER_0:  that would allow you to find this balance strategy.
SPEAKER_0:  that would understand that you have to bluff with the right probability.
SPEAKER_1:  Can that be somehow incorporated into the value function?
SPEAKER_1:  this.
SPEAKER_1:  the complexity of poker that you've described.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so the way the value functions work in poker, like the latest and greatest poker AIs, they do use neural nets for the value function.
SPEAKER_0:  The way it's done is very different from how it's done in a game like Chess or Go because
SPEAKER_0:  In poker, you have to reason about beliefs.
SPEAKER_0:  And so the value.
SPEAKER_0:  of a state.
SPEAKER_0:  depends on the beliefs that players have.
SPEAKER_0:  about.
SPEAKER_0:  what the different cards are.
SPEAKER_0:  Like if you have pocket aces...
SPEAKER_0:  Then...
SPEAKER_0:  Whether that's a really, really good hand or just an okay hand.
SPEAKER_0:  depends on whether you know I have pocket aces.
SPEAKER_0:  where like if you know that I have pocket aces.
SPEAKER_0:  then.
SPEAKER_0:  if I bet you're gonna fold immediately.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you think that I have a really bad hand...
SPEAKER_0:  then I could bet with pocket aces and make a ton of money.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  the value function in poker these days.
SPEAKER_0:  takes the beliefs as an input.
SPEAKER_0:  which is very different from how chess and Go AIs work.
SPEAKER_1:  So as a person who appreciates the game...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Who do you think is the greatest poker player of all time?
SPEAKER_1:  That's a tough question.
SPEAKER_1:  Can AI help answer that question? Can you actually analyze the quality of play?
SPEAKER_1:  so the air chest engines can.
SPEAKER_1:  in.
SPEAKER_1:  Give estimates of the quality of play.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I wonder if there's a, is there an Elo rating type of system for poker?
SPEAKER_1:  I suppose you could, but there's just not enough.
SPEAKER_1:  You would have to play a lot of games, right?
SPEAKER_1:  a very large number of games, like more than you would in chess. The deterministic game makes it easier to estimate ELO.
SPEAKER_0:  I think. Is much harder to estimate.
SPEAKER_0:  Something like Elo rating in poker. I think it's doable.
SPEAKER_0:  The problem is that the game is very high variance.
SPEAKER_0:  So you could.
SPEAKER_0:  play.
SPEAKER_0:  You could be profitable in poker.
SPEAKER_0:  for a year.
SPEAKER_0:  and you can actually be a bad player, just because the variance is so high.
SPEAKER_0:  when you've got.
SPEAKER_0:  professional poker players that would lose for a year.
SPEAKER_0:  just because they're on a really bad.
SPEAKER_0:  Bad streak.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so for ELO you have to have a nice clean way of saying
SPEAKER_1:  Player A played Player B.
SPEAKER_1:  and A beats B that says something, that's a signal.
SPEAKER_1:  In poker, that's a very noisy signal.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a very noisy signal. There is a signal there, and so you could do this calculation.
SPEAKER_0:  it would just be much harder.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, but the same way that AIs have now taken over chess and
SPEAKER_0:  You know, all the top professional chess players train with, with AIs.
SPEAKER_0:  The same is true for poker.
SPEAKER_0:  The game has become
SPEAKER_0:  a very computational
SPEAKER_0:  people train with AIs to try to find out where they're making mistakes.
SPEAKER_0:  try to learn from the AIs to improve their strategy.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, so.
SPEAKER_0:  Now
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so the game has been revolutionized in the past five years by the development of AI in this sport.
SPEAKER_1:  The skill with which you avoided the question of the greatest of all time was impressive.
SPEAKER_0:  So my feeling is that it's a difficult it's a difficult question because
SPEAKER_0:  just like in chess.
SPEAKER_0:  where you can't really compare Magnus Carlsen today to Garry Kasparov.
SPEAKER_0:  because the game has evolved so much.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  the poker players today.
SPEAKER_0:  so far beyond the skills of like...
SPEAKER_0:  people that were playing even.
SPEAKER_0:  10 or 20 years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  So you look at the kinds of all-stars that were on ESPN at the height of the poker boom.
SPEAKER_0:  Pretty much all those players are actually not that good at the game.
SPEAKER_0:  today. At least the
SPEAKER_0:  strategy aspect. I mean, they might still be good at like reading the player at the other side of the table and trying to figure out like are they bluffing or not.
SPEAKER_0:  but in terms of the actual like.
SPEAKER_0:  computational strategy of the game.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of them have really struggled to keep up with that development.
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  So for that reason, I'll give an answer and I'm gonna say Daniel Lagranio.
SPEAKER_0:  who you actually had on the podcast recently. So it was a great episode.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  and Phil's gonna hate it.
SPEAKER_0:  this so much. And I'm going to give him credit.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  He is one of the few like old school really strong players that have kept up.
SPEAKER_0:  with the development of AI.
SPEAKER_1:  he is trying to.
SPEAKER_1:  he's constantly studying the game theory optimal.
SPEAKER_0:  way of playing. Exactly.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think a lot of the old school poker players have just kind of given up on that aspect, and I gotta give them a grand new credit.
SPEAKER_0:  for keeping up.
SPEAKER_0:  with all the developments that are happening in the sport.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's fascinating to watch. It's fascinating to watch where it's headed.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so there you go. Some love for Daniel.
SPEAKER_1:  Quick pause, bath and break? Yep, let's do it.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's go from poker to diplomacy.
SPEAKER_1:  what is at a high level the game of diplomacy.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so I talked a lot about two players, zero-sum games. And what's interesting about diplomacy is that it's very different from...
SPEAKER_0:  These like adversarial.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... games like chess go poker even starcraft and do it up
SPEAKER_0:  Diplomacy has a much bigger cooperative element to it.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a seven player game.
SPEAKER_0:  It was actually created in the 50s.
SPEAKER_0:  and it takes place.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... before world war one it's like a map of europe with seven great powers
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and they're all trying to.
SPEAKER_0:  form alliances with each other. There's a lot of negotiation going on.
SPEAKER_0:  And so the whole focus of the game is on
SPEAKER_0:  Forming alliances with the other players to take on the other players.
SPEAKER_1:  England, Germany, Russia, Turkey.
SPEAKER_1:  Austria, Hungary, Italy and France.
SPEAKER_0:  That's right.
SPEAKER_0:  So the way the game works...
SPEAKER_0:  is
SPEAKER_0:  On each turn, you spend about, you know, five to 15 minutes.
SPEAKER_0:  talking to the other players in privates.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  You make all sorts of deals with them. You say, like, hey, let's work together.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, let's team up against this other player, because the only way that you can make progress is by working with somebody else against the others.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  And then after that negotiation period is done.
SPEAKER_0:  All the players simultaneously submit their
SPEAKER_0:  Moves?
SPEAKER_0:  and they're all executed at the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you can tell people like, Hey, I'm going to support you this turn.
SPEAKER_0:  But then you don't follow through with it.
SPEAKER_0:  And they're only going to figure that out once they see the moves being read off.
SPEAKER_1:  How much of it is natural language, like written?
SPEAKER_1:  actual text how much is like a
SPEAKER_1:  you're actually saying phrases that are structured.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's different ways to play the game.
SPEAKER_0:  You can play it in person, and in that case, it's all natural language.
SPEAKER_0:  Free forum communication. There's no constraints on the kinds of deals that you can make the kinds of things that you can discuss
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  You can also play it online so you can.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, send long emails back and forth.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, you can play it like.
SPEAKER_0:  live online or over voice chat.
SPEAKER_0:  But the focus, the important thing to understand is that
SPEAKER_0:  This is unstructured communication. You can say whatever you want.
SPEAKER_0:  You can make any sorts of deals that you want.
SPEAKER_0:  and everything is done.
SPEAKER_0:  privately so it's not like you're all around the board together having a conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  You're grabbing somebody going off into a corner and conspiring behind everybody else's back about what you're planning.
SPEAKER_1:  And uh...
SPEAKER_1:  There's no limit in theory to the conversation you can have directly with one person.
SPEAKER_0:  That's right. You can make all sorts of... You can talk about anything. You can say like, hey, let's have a long-term alliance against this guy. You can say like, hey, can you support me this turn in return? I'll do this other thing for you next turn.
SPEAKER_0:  or you know, yeah, just.
SPEAKER_0:  You can talk about like what you talked about with somebody else and gossip about like what they're planning.
SPEAKER_0:  The way that I would describe the game is that it's kind of like a mix between risk
SPEAKER_0:  poker and the tv show survivor
SPEAKER_0:  There's like this big element of like trying to.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there's a big social element.
SPEAKER_0:  And the best way that I would describe the game is that it's really a game about people rather than the pieces.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  risk because it is a map it's kind of
SPEAKER_1:  Wargame-like.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... poker because there's a game theory component that's very kind of strategic
SPEAKER_1:  So you could convert it into an artificial intelligence problem.
SPEAKER_1:  and then survivor because of the social component. Strong social component.
SPEAKER_1:  I saw that somebody said online that...
SPEAKER_1:  the internet version of the game.
SPEAKER_1:  has this quality of...
SPEAKER_1:  that it's easier to almost to do like role playing.
SPEAKER_1:  as opposed to being yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  You can actually like be the, like really imagine yourself as the leader of France or Russia and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  Like really.
SPEAKER_1:  pretend to be that person. It's actually fun to really lean into being that.
SPEAKER_1:  that leader.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so some players do go this route where they just like...
SPEAKER_0:  of view it as a strategy game but also a role-playing game where they can like act out like
SPEAKER_0:  What would I be like if I was, you know, a leader of France in 1900?
SPEAKER_1:  forfeit right away. No, I'm just kidding. I'm just kidding.
SPEAKER_1:  Heh!
SPEAKER_1:  And they sometimes use like the old timey language.
SPEAKER_1:  to like...
SPEAKER_1:  or how they imagine the elites would talk at that time. Anyway, so what are the different turns of the game? Like what are the rounds?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so on every turn you got like...
SPEAKER_0:  a bunch of different units that you start out with. So you start out controlling like.
SPEAKER_0:  just a few units and the object of the game is to gain control of the majority of the map. If you're able to do that, then you've won the game.
SPEAKER_0:  But like I said, the only way that you're able to do that is by working with other players.
SPEAKER_0:  So on every turn, you can issue a move order. So for each of your units, you can move.
SPEAKER_0:  them to an adjacent territory.
SPEAKER_0:  or you can keep them where they are.
SPEAKER_0:  or you can support a move.
SPEAKER_0:  or a hold.
SPEAKER_0:  of different units.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  What are the territories? How is the map divided up?
SPEAKER_0:  It's kind of like risk where the map is divided up into like 50 different territories.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Now-
SPEAKER_0:  You can enter a territory if you're moving into that territory with more supports than the person that's in there or the person that's trying to move in there.
SPEAKER_0:  So if you're moving in and there's somebody already there.
SPEAKER_0:  then
SPEAKER_0:  If neither of you have support, it's a one versus one and you'll bounce back and neither of you will make progress.
SPEAKER_0:  if you have a unit that's supporting that move into the territory.
SPEAKER_0:  then it's a two versus one and you'll kick them out and they'll have to retreat somewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  What does support mean? Support is like, it's an action that you can issue in the game. So you can say...
SPEAKER_0:  this unit, you get you right down, this unit is supporting this other unit into this territory.
SPEAKER_1:  Are these units from opposing forces?
SPEAKER_0:  It could be, they could be. And this is where the interesting aspect of the game comes in because you can support your own units into territory.
SPEAKER_0:  but you can also support other people's units into territories. And so that's what the negotiations.
SPEAKER_0:  really revolve around.
SPEAKER_1:  but you don't have to do the thing you say you're going to do.
SPEAKER_1:  And this, yeah. So you can say I'm going to support you, but then.
SPEAKER_1:  backstab the person.
SPEAKER_1:  That's absolutely right. And that tension is, is core to the game.
SPEAKER_0:  That tension is absolutely core to the game.
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that you can make all sorts of...
SPEAKER_0:  promises but you have to reason about the fact that like they might not trust you if you say you're gonna do something
SPEAKER_0:  or they might be lying to you.
SPEAKER_0:  when they say they're going to support you.
SPEAKER_1:  So maybe just.
SPEAKER_1:  to jump back, what's the history of the game in general?
SPEAKER_1:  Is it true that Henry Kissinger loved the game?
SPEAKER_1:  and JFK and all those, I've heard like a bunch of different people that, or is that just one of those things that the cool kids say they do, but they don't actually play.
SPEAKER_0:  So the game was created in the 50s.
SPEAKER_0:  And from what I understand, it was JFK's, it was played in like the JFK White House, Henry Kissinger's favorite game.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if it's true, but that's definitely what I've heard. Since their
SPEAKER_1:  they went with World War I.
SPEAKER_1:  when it was created after World War II.
SPEAKER_0:  The story that I've heard for the creation of the game.
SPEAKER_0:  is it was created by
SPEAKER_0:  um... somebody that had looked at the history of
SPEAKER_0:  of the twentieth century and they saw
SPEAKER_0:  World War I as a failure of diplomacy.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, they saw the fact that this war broke out as like...
SPEAKER_0:  the diplomats of all these countries really failed to prevent a war, and he wanted to create a game that would basically teach people about diplomacy.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It's really fascinating that in his ideal version of the game of diplomacy, nobody actually wins the game.
SPEAKER_0:  because the whole point is that if somebody is about to win, then the other players should be able to work together.
SPEAKER_0:  to stop that person from winning.
SPEAKER_0:  And so the ideal version of the game is just one where nobody actually wins.
SPEAKER_0:  It kind of has a nice, wholesome take home message then that...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, war is ultimately futile.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_1:  and that optimal.
SPEAKER_1:  that feudal optimal could be achieved through great diplomacy.
SPEAKER_1:  So is there some asymmetry in terms of which is more powerful, Russia versus Germany versus
SPEAKER_1:  of France and so on.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think the general consensus is that France is the strongest power in the game. But the beautiful thing about diplomacy is that it's self-balancing, right? So it's the fact that France has an inherited advantage from the beginning.
SPEAKER_0:  means that the other.
SPEAKER_0:  players.
SPEAKER_0:  are less likely to work with it.
SPEAKER_1:  I saw that Russia has four units or four of something that the others have three of something.
SPEAKER_0:  That's true, yeah, so Russia starts off with four units while all the other players start with three.
SPEAKER_0:  But Russia is also in a much more vulnerable position because they have to like...
SPEAKER_0:  They have a lot more neighbors as well
SPEAKER_1:  Got it, larger territory, more, yeah, right, more border to defend.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... what else is
SPEAKER_1:  What else is important to know about the rules?
SPEAKER_1:  So there's how many rounds are there like is this iterative game?
SPEAKER_1:  Is a finite, you just keep going indefinitely?
SPEAKER_0:  Usually the game lasts, uh, I would say about
SPEAKER_0:  15 or 20 turns.
SPEAKER_0:  There's in theory no limit, it could last longer.
SPEAKER_0:  But at some point, I mean, if you're playing a house game with friends, at some point, you just get tired and you all agree like, okay, we're going to end the game here and call it a draw.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  If you're playing online, there's usually set limits on when the game will actually end.
SPEAKER_1:  And what's the end? What's the termination condition?
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_1:  This one.
SPEAKER_1:  country have to conquer everything else?
SPEAKER_0:  So if somebody is able to actually gain control of a majority of the map, then they've won the game, and that is a solo victory as it's called.
SPEAKER_0:  Now that pretty rarely happens, especially with strong players, because like I said, the game is designed.
SPEAKER_0:  to incentivize the other players to put a stop to that and all work together to stop the superpower.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Usually what ends up happening is that
SPEAKER_0:  you know, all the players agreed to a draw.
SPEAKER_0:  and then the the score the the win is divided among the the remaining players.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a lot of different scoring systems, the one that we used in our research.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically,
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  gives a score relative to how much control you have of the map. So the more that you control, the higher your score.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the history of using this game?
SPEAKER_1:  as a benchmark for AI research.
SPEAKER_1:  Do people use it?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so-
SPEAKER_0:  People have been working on AI for diplomacy since about the 80s.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  There was some really exciting research back then, but...
SPEAKER_0:  The approach that was taken was very different from what we see today. I mean, the research in the 80s was a very rule-based approach, kind of a heuristic approach. It was very in line with the kind of research that was being done in the 80s.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, basically trying to encode human knowledge into the strategy of the AI.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it's understandable. I mean, the game is so incredibly...
SPEAKER_0:  different and
SPEAKER_0:  so much more complicated.
SPEAKER_0:  than the kinds of games that
SPEAKER_0:  people working on like chess and go.
SPEAKER_0:  and poker that
SPEAKER_0:  It was honestly even hard to like.
SPEAKER_0:  Start.
SPEAKER_0:  getting making any progress in diplomacy. Can you just.
SPEAKER_1:  formulate.
SPEAKER_1:  What is the problem from an AI perspective?
SPEAKER_1:  And why is it hard? Why is it a challenging game to solve?
SPEAKER_0:  So there's a lot of aspects in diplomacy that make it a huge challenge. First of all,
SPEAKER_0:  you have the natural language components. And I think this really is what makes it.
SPEAKER_0:  are really the most difficult.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... game among the major benchmarks
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to, it's not about.
SPEAKER_0:  Moving pieces on the board?
SPEAKER_0:  your action space is basically all the different
SPEAKER_0:  sentences that you could communicate to somebody else in this game.
SPEAKER_0:  and um
SPEAKER_1:  Is there, can we just like link on that? So
SPEAKER_1:  is part of it.
SPEAKER_1:  Like the ambiguity in the language?
SPEAKER_1:  If it was like very strict.
SPEAKER_1:  If you narrowed the set of possible sentences, it could do it. Would that simplify the game significantly?
SPEAKER_0:  The real-
SPEAKER_0:  Difficulty is the-
SPEAKER_0:  of things that you can talk about.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  You could have natural language in other games, like Settlers of Catan, for example. You could have a natural language, Settlers of Catan AI.
SPEAKER_0:  But the things that you're gonna talk about are basically like, am I trading you?
SPEAKER_0:  Two sheep for a wood or three sheep for a wood?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Whereas in a game like Diplomacy...
SPEAKER_0:  the breadth of conversations that you're going to have are like
SPEAKER_0:  you know, am I going to support you? Are you going to support me in return? Which units are going to do what?
SPEAKER_0:  What did this other person say promise you?
SPEAKER_0:  They're lying because they told this other person that they're going to do this instead.
SPEAKER_0:  If you help me out this turn then in the future I'll...
SPEAKER_0:  do these things that will help you out.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  the
SPEAKER_0:  depth and breadth of these conversations is really...
SPEAKER_0:  complicated.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's all being done in natural language.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Now you could approach it, and we actually consider doing this, like having a simplified language.
SPEAKER_0:  to make this complexity smaller.
SPEAKER_0:  Ultimately we thought
SPEAKER_0:  the most impactful way of doing this research would be to.
SPEAKER_0:  head on.
SPEAKER_0:  and just try to go for the full game upfront.
SPEAKER_1:  Just looking at sample games and with the conversations.
SPEAKER_1:  look like greetings England this should prove to be a fun game since all the
SPEAKER_1:  private press is going to be made public at the end.
SPEAKER_1:  At the least, it will be interesting to see if the press changes because of that. Anyway, good. So there's like a-
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that's just kind of like the generic greetings at the beginning of the game I think that the meat comes a little bit later when you're starting to talk about like
SPEAKER_0:  specific strategy and stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  I agree there are a lot of advantages to the two of us keeping in touch.
SPEAKER_1:  and our nation's.
SPEAKER_1:  make strong natural allies in the middle game. So that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  making friends making enemies
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, or like if you look at the next line, so the person's saying like, I've heard...
SPEAKER_0:  Bits about a lapanto and an octopus opening and basically telling Austria like hey just a heads up
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I've heard these whispers about like what might be going on behind your back.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  That's it, basalt.
SPEAKER_1:  There's all kinds of complexities in that.
SPEAKER_1:  in the language of that.
SPEAKER_1:  Like to interpret what the heck that means. It's hard for us humans, but for AI it's even harder.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to understand at every level the semantics of that.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, I mean, there's the complexity and understanding. When somebody is saying this to me, what does that mean?
SPEAKER_0:  And then there's also the complexity of like.
SPEAKER_0:  Should I be telling this person this? Like, I've overheard these whispers. Should I be telling this person that, like, hey, you might be getting attacked by this other power?
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so...
SPEAKER_1:  What? How are we supposed to think about? Okay, so that's the natural language.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you even begin trying to solve this game? It seems like.
SPEAKER_1:  This seems like the touring test on steroids.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and I mean, there's the natural language aspect. And then even besides the natural language aspect, you also have.
SPEAKER_0:  the the cooperative elements of the game and i think this is actually
SPEAKER_0:  Something that I find really interesting if you look at all the previous game AI
SPEAKER_0:  Breakthroughs?
SPEAKER_0:  They've all happened in these purely adversarial games where you don't actually need to understand how humans play the game.
SPEAKER_0:  It's all just AI versus AI.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, like you look at.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  Checkers, chess, go, poker.
SPEAKER_0:  Starcraft Dota 2
SPEAKER_0:  Like in some of those cases, they leveraged human data, but they never needed to.
SPEAKER_0:  They were always.
SPEAKER_0:  just trying to...
SPEAKER_0:  have a scalable algorithm.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  then they could throw a lot of computational resources out, a lot of memory out.
SPEAKER_0:  and then eventually it would converge.
SPEAKER_0:  to an approximation of a Nash equilibrium.
SPEAKER_0:  perfect strategy.
SPEAKER_0:  that in the two players, your some game guarantees that they're going to be able to not lose to any opponents.
SPEAKER_1:  so you can't leverage self-play.
SPEAKER_1:  to solve this game.
SPEAKER_0:  You can leverage self-play, but it's no longer sufficient.
SPEAKER_0:  to beat humans.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you integrate the human into the loop of this?
SPEAKER_0:  So what you have to do...
SPEAKER_0:  is incorporate human data.
SPEAKER_0:  And to kind of give you some intuition for why this is the case, like imagine you're playing a negotiation game like like diplomacy
SPEAKER_0:  but you're training completely from scratch.
SPEAKER_0:  without any human data. The AI is not going to suddenly like-
SPEAKER_0:  figure out how to communicate in English. It's going to figure out some weird robot language.
SPEAKER_0:  that only it will understand.
SPEAKER_0:  And then when you stick that in a game with six other humans
SPEAKER_0:  They're gonna.
SPEAKER_0:  this person's talking gibberish and they're just going to ally with each other and team up against the bot.
SPEAKER_0:  or not even team up against the bot, but just not work with the bot.
SPEAKER_0:  And so in order to be able to play this game.
SPEAKER_0:  With humans, it has to understand the human way of playing the game.
SPEAKER_0:  not this machine way of playing the game.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, that's fascinating.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a nuanced thing to understand because the
SPEAKER_1:  A chess playing program doesn't need to play like a human to be a human. Exactly.
SPEAKER_1:  But here you have to play like a human in order to beat them.
SPEAKER_0:  Or at least you have to understand how humans play the game so that you can understand how to work with them.
SPEAKER_0:  if they have certain expectations about
SPEAKER_0:  What does it mean to be a good ally?
SPEAKER_0:  What does it mean to have a reciprocal relationship when we're working together?
SPEAKER_0:  You have to abide by those conventions.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you don't, they're just going to work with somebody else instead.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think of this?
SPEAKER_1:  as a clean.
SPEAKER_1:  in some deep sense of the spirit of the touring test as formulated by Alan Turing.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it?
SPEAKER_1:  In some sense, this is what the Turing test actually looks like.
SPEAKER_1:  So because of...
SPEAKER_1:  Open ended natural language conversation seems like.
SPEAKER_1:  very difficult to evaluate.
SPEAKER_1:  Like here.
SPEAKER_1:  at a high stakes where humans are trying to win a game. That seems like how you actually.
SPEAKER_1:  perform the towing test.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's different from the Turing test. Like the way that the Turing test is formulated, it's about trying to distinguish a human from a machine.
SPEAKER_0:  and seeing, oh, could the machine...
SPEAKER_0:  successfully pass as a human in this adversarial setting where the
SPEAKER_0:  player is trying to figure out whether it's a machine or a human.
SPEAKER_0:  Whereas in diplomacy...
SPEAKER_0:  It's not about trying to figure out whether this player is a human or a machine.
SPEAKER_0:  It's ultimately about whether I can work with this.
SPEAKER_0:  player, regardless of whether they are a human or machine.
SPEAKER_0:  and can the machine.
SPEAKER_0:  do that better than a human can.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  think about that but that just feels like
SPEAKER_1:  the implied.
SPEAKER_1:  Requirement for that is for the machine to be human-like.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's true, that if you're going to play in this human game...
SPEAKER_0:  you have to somehow adapt to the...
SPEAKER_0:  to the human surroundings.
SPEAKER_0:  and the human play style.
SPEAKER_1:  and to when you have to adapt.
SPEAKER_1:  So you can't, if you're the outsider.
SPEAKER_1:  If you're not human-like, I feel like that's a losing strategy.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's correct, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  So, okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  What what are the complexities here? What was your approach to it?
SPEAKER_0:  Before I get to that, one thing I should explain, like why we decided to work on diplomacy.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically what happened is in 2019,
SPEAKER_0:  I was wrapping up the work on six player poker on Fluribus.
SPEAKER_0:  and was trying to think about what to work on next.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I had been seeing like all these other breakthroughs happening in AI. I mean like 2019.
SPEAKER_0:  You have StarCraft, you have AlphaStar beating humans in StarCraft, you've got
SPEAKER_0:  the Dota 2 stuff happening at OpenAI.
SPEAKER_0:  You have GPT.
SPEAKER_0:  or gpd3 come i think it was gpd2 at the time
SPEAKER_0:  And it became clear that AI was progressing really, really rapidly.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  People were throwing out these other games about what should be the next
SPEAKER_0:  challenge for multi-agent AI.
SPEAKER_0:  and I just felt like we had to aim bigger.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  If you look at a game like
SPEAKER_0:  chess or a game like Go.
SPEAKER_0:  They took decades for researchers to...
SPEAKER_0:  to ultimately reach superhuman performance at. I mean, like, chess took four years of AI research.
SPEAKER_0:  Go take another 20 years.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  We thought that diplomacy.
SPEAKER_0:  would be this incredibly difficult challenge that could easily take a decade.
SPEAKER_0:  to make an AI that could play competently.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, but we felt like that was, that was a goal worth aiming for.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And so honestly, I was kind of reluctant to work on it first because I thought it was like
SPEAKER_0:  too far out of the realm of possibility, but...
SPEAKER_0:  I was talking to a coworker of mine, Adam Lerner, and he was basically saying, like, eh, why not aim for it? We'll learn some interesting things along the way, and maybe it'll be possible.
SPEAKER_0:  And so we decided to go for it.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it was the right choice considering.
SPEAKER_0:  just how much progress there was.
SPEAKER_0:  in AI and that progress has continued in the years since.
SPEAKER_1:  Winning in diplomacy.
SPEAKER_1:  What does that really look like?
SPEAKER_1:  It means...
SPEAKER_1:  talking to...
SPEAKER_1:  six other players.
SPEAKER_1:  six other entities.
SPEAKER_1:  agents.
SPEAKER_1:  and convincing.
SPEAKER_1:  and convincing them of stuff that you want them to be convinced of.
SPEAKER_1:  Like what exactly I'm trying to get like.
SPEAKER_1:  to deeply understand what the problem is.
SPEAKER_0:  Ultimately
SPEAKER_0:  The problem is...
SPEAKER_0:  It's simple to quantify, right? So you're going to play this game with humans and-
SPEAKER_0:  You want your score on average to be as high as possible. You know, if you can say like, I am winning more than any human alive.
SPEAKER_0:  then you're a champion diplomacy player.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Now ultimately we didn't reach that, we got to human level performance, we actually, so we played about 40 games.
SPEAKER_0:  with real humans.
SPEAKER_0:  Online.
SPEAKER_0:  The bot came in second out of all players that played five or more games.
SPEAKER_0:  And, um...
SPEAKER_0:  So not like number one, but...
SPEAKER_0:  way way higher than- slowly i just
SPEAKER_1:  What was the expertise level? Are they beginners? Are they intermediate players, advanced players?
SPEAKER_0:  Give a sense. That's a great question. And so I think.
SPEAKER_0:  This kind of goes into how do you measure.
SPEAKER_0:  performance in diplomacy and I would argue that when you're measuring performance in a game like this
SPEAKER_0:  You don't actually want to measure it.
SPEAKER_0:  in games with all expert players.
SPEAKER_0:  It's kind of like if you're developing a self-driving car.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't want to measure that car.
SPEAKER_0:  on the road with a bunch of expert stunt drivers.
SPEAKER_0:  You want to put it on a road of like an actual American city and see
SPEAKER_0:  Is this car?
SPEAKER_0:  crashing less often than an expert driver.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's the metric that we've used.
SPEAKER_0:  We're saying like, we're gonna stick this game.
SPEAKER_0:  We're gonna stick this bot in games with.
SPEAKER_0:  a wide variety of skill levels.
SPEAKER_0:  And then are we doing better?
SPEAKER_0:  than a strong or expert human player would in the same situation.
SPEAKER_1:  That's quite brilliant, because I played a lot of sports in my life, like as a tennis judo, whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's.
SPEAKER_1:  Somehow almost easier to go against experts almost always.
SPEAKER_1:  I think they're more predictable.
SPEAKER_1:  and the quality of play.
SPEAKER_1:  that the space of strategies you're operating under is narrower against experts.
SPEAKER_1:  It's more fun. It's really frustrating to go against beginners. Also, because beginners talk trash to you.
SPEAKER_1:  when they somehow do beat you. So that's a human thing that AI doesn't have to be worried about that. They have the variance in strategies.
SPEAKER_1:  It's greater, especially with natural language. It's just all over the place then.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and honestly when you look
SPEAKER_0:  at
SPEAKER_0:  what makes a good human diplomacy player.
SPEAKER_0:  Obviously they're able to handle themselves in games with other expert humans, but where they really shine is when they're playing with these weak players.
SPEAKER_0:  and they know how to take advantage.
SPEAKER_0:  of the fact that they're a weak player, that they won't be able to pull off a stab as well.
SPEAKER_0:  or that.
SPEAKER_0:  They have certain tendencies and they can take them under their wing and persuade them to do things that might not even be in their interest.
SPEAKER_0:  the really good diplomacy players are able to.
SPEAKER_0:  to take advantage of the fact that.
SPEAKER_0:  there is that there are some weak players in the game
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so if you have to incorporate human play data.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you do that?
SPEAKER_1:  How do you do that in order to train in the AI system to play diplomacy?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so that's...
SPEAKER_0:  That's really the crux of the problem. How do we-
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Leverage the benefits of self-play that have been so successful
SPEAKER_0:  in all these other previous games.
SPEAKER_0:  while
SPEAKER_0:  keeping the strategy as human compatible as possible.
SPEAKER_0:  And so what we did is we first trained a language model.
SPEAKER_0:  And then we made that language model controllable.
SPEAKER_0:  on a set of intents, what we call intents, which are basically like an action that we want to play.
SPEAKER_0:  and an action that
SPEAKER_0:  we would like the other player to play.
SPEAKER_0:  And so this gives us a way to generate dialogue that's not just trying to imitate the human style.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  whatever human was saying the situation but to actually give it up uh... an intent of purpose
SPEAKER_0:  in its communication.
SPEAKER_0:  we can talk about a specific move or we can make a specific request.
SPEAKER_0:  and the determination of what that move is.
SPEAKER_0:  that we're discussing.
SPEAKER_0:  comes from.
SPEAKER_0:  strategic reasoning model that uses reinforcement learning and planning.
SPEAKER_1:  So, the...
SPEAKER_1:  computing the intents for all the players.
SPEAKER_1:  How's that done?
SPEAKER_1:  Just sub-
SPEAKER_1:  as a starting point. Is that with reinforcement learning or is that just optimal, determining what the optimal is for intents?
SPEAKER_0:  It's a combination of reinforcement learning and.
SPEAKER_0:  planning.
SPEAKER_0:  Actually very similar to how we approached poker and
SPEAKER_0:  Help.
SPEAKER_0:  people have approached chess and Go as well.
SPEAKER_0:  We're using Self-Play.
SPEAKER_0:  and and search.
SPEAKER_0:  to try to figure out what is an optimal move for us.
SPEAKER_0:  And what is a desirable move that we would like this other player to play?
SPEAKER_0:  Now.
SPEAKER_0:  the difference between.
SPEAKER_0:  the way that we approached reinforcement learning search in this game
SPEAKER_0:  versus those previous games.
SPEAKER_0:  is that we have to keep it human compatible. We have to understand.
SPEAKER_0:  Hell.
SPEAKER_0:  the other person is likely to play rather than just assuming that they're going to play like a machine.
SPEAKER_1:  and how language.
SPEAKER_1:  Get some to play.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  in a way that maximizes the chance of following the intent you want them to follow.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, how do you do that? How do you connect language?
SPEAKER_1:  to intent.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  The way that RL and planning is done is actually not using language. So we're...
SPEAKER_0:  Coming up with this like plan for the action.
SPEAKER_0:  that we're going to play and the other person is going to play and then we feed that action into the dialogue model.
SPEAKER_0:  that will then send a message according to those plans.
SPEAKER_1:  to the language model there.
SPEAKER_1:  is mapping.
SPEAKER_1:  Action 2.
SPEAKER_1:  to message.
SPEAKER_1:  One word at a time.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically one message at a time. So we'll feed into the dialogue model. Like here are the actions that you should be discussing. Here's the message. Here's like the-
SPEAKER_0:  The...
SPEAKER_0:  content of the message that we would like you to send.
SPEAKER_0:  and then it will actually generate a message.
SPEAKER_0:  that corresponds to that.
SPEAKER_1:  Does this actually work?
SPEAKER_1:  It works surprisingly well.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, how?
SPEAKER_1:  Oh man, the number of ways it probably goes horribly. I would have imagined it goes horribly wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... so how the heck is it effective at all
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, there are a lot of ways that this could fail. So for example, I mean,
SPEAKER_0:  you could have a situation where you're basically like...
SPEAKER_0:  We don't tell the language model, like, here are the pieces of...
SPEAKER_0:  our action or the other person's action that you should be communicating. And so like, let's say you're about to attack somebody.
SPEAKER_0:  You probably don't want to tell them that you're going to attack them.
SPEAKER_0:  but there's nothing in the language, like the language model's not very smart at the end of the day.
SPEAKER_0:  So it doesn't really have a way of knowing.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, what should I be talking about? Should I tell this person that I'm about to attack them or not?
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  So we have to develop a lot of other techniques that deal with that.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Like one of the things we do, for example, is we try to calculate.
SPEAKER_0:  If I'm going to send this message.
SPEAKER_0:  what would I expect the other person to do in response?
SPEAKER_0:  So if it's a message like, Hey, I'm going to attack you this turn.
SPEAKER_0:  they're probably gonna, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  attack us or defend against that attack.
SPEAKER_0:  And so we have a way of.
SPEAKER_0:  recognizing like, hey, sending this message.
SPEAKER_0:  is
SPEAKER_0:  a negative expected value action.
SPEAKER_0:  and we should not send this message.
SPEAKER_1:  So yes, for particular kinds of messages, you have like an extra.
SPEAKER_1:  function that does the...
SPEAKER_1:  estimates the value of that message.
SPEAKER_0:  So we have these kinds of filters that like.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's a filter. So there's a good.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that a folder in your network or is it rule-based?
SPEAKER_0:  That's a neural network. Well, it's a combination. It's a neural network, but it's also using planning.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, it's
SPEAKER_0:  trying to compute like what is.
SPEAKER_0:  the policy that the other players are going to play, given that this message has been sent. And then KRP Dogs channel,
SPEAKER_0:  Is that better than not sending the message or not?
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like that's how my brain works too, like there's a-
SPEAKER_1:  language model that generates random crap and then there's these
SPEAKER_1:  Other
SPEAKER_1:  neural nets that are essentially filters.
SPEAKER_1:  At least that's what I tweet.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll use you my-
SPEAKER_1:  process of tweeting I'll think of something.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's hilarious to me. And then about five seconds later, the filter network comes in and says no.
SPEAKER_1:  No, that's not funny at all. I mean, there's something interesting to that kind of process.
SPEAKER_1:  So you have a set of actions that you.
SPEAKER_1:  You want, you have an intent.
SPEAKER_1:  you want to achieve.
SPEAKER_1:  an intent that you want your opponent to achieve then you generate messages.
SPEAKER_1:  And then you evaluated those messages will.
SPEAKER_1:  achieve the...
SPEAKER_1:  Call you on.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, we're filtering for several things. We're filtering like, is this a sensible message? So sometimes language models will generate messages that are just like.
SPEAKER_0:  Totally nonsense. And we try to filter those out.
SPEAKER_0:  We also.
SPEAKER_0:  to filter out messages that are basically lies. So...
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  Diplomacy has its reputation as a game that's really about...
SPEAKER_0:  deception and lying, but
SPEAKER_0:  we try to actually minimize the amount that the bot would lie.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, this was.
SPEAKER_0:  Actually mostly a-
SPEAKER_1:  Or are you?
SPEAKER_1:  No, I'm just kidding.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, like, part of the reason for this is that...
SPEAKER_0:  we actually found that lying
SPEAKER_0:  would make the bot perform worse in the long run. It would end up with a lower score.
SPEAKER_0:  Because once the bot lies...
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  People would never trust it again.
SPEAKER_0:  and and trust is a huge aspect of the game of the plucking
SPEAKER_1:  notes here because I think this applies to
SPEAKER_1:  Life lessons too.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a really, yeah, really strong. So like.
SPEAKER_1:  lying is a dangerous thing to do.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you want to avoid.
SPEAKER_1:  obvious lying.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, I think when people play diplomacy for the first time...
SPEAKER_0:  they approach it as a game of deception and lying and
SPEAKER_0:  and they...
SPEAKER_0:  Ultimately, if you talk to top diplomacy players, they'll tell you.
SPEAKER_0:  is that diplomacy is a game about trust.
SPEAKER_0:  and being able to build trust in an environment that encourages people to not trust anyone.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's the ultimate tension in diplomacy.
SPEAKER_0:  How can this AI
SPEAKER_0:  reason about whether you are being honest in your communication.
SPEAKER_0:  And how can the AI...
SPEAKER_0:  persuade you that it is being honest when it is telling you that hey I'm actually going to support you this turn.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there some sense, I don't know if you step back and think, that this process
SPEAKER_1:  Well...
SPEAKER_1:  indirectly.
SPEAKER_1:  help us study human psychology.
SPEAKER_1:  like if trust is the ultimate goal.
SPEAKER_1:  Wouldn't that help us understand what are the fundamental aspects of forming trust?
SPEAKER_1:  between humans and between humans and AI.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, that's a really, really important question that's much bigger than-
SPEAKER_1:  and strategy games.
SPEAKER_1:  is how can this fundamental to the human-robot interaction problem.
SPEAKER_1:  How do we form trust?
SPEAKER_1:  between intelligent entities.
SPEAKER_0:  So one of the things I'm really excited about with diplomacy.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, there's never really been.
SPEAKER_0:  a good domain to investigate these kinds of questions.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and diplomacy gives us a domain where
SPEAKER_0:  trust is really at the center of it. And it's not just like you've hired a bunch of mechanical turkers that
SPEAKER_0:  you know, are being paid and trying to...
SPEAKER_0:  get through the task as quickly as possible.
SPEAKER_0:  You have these people that are really invested in the outcome of the game and they're really trying to do the best that they can.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I'm really excited that we're able to.
SPEAKER_0:  We actually have...
SPEAKER_0:  put together this.
SPEAKER_0:  We're open sourcing all of our models. We're open sourcing.
SPEAKER_0:  all of the code.
SPEAKER_0:  and we're making the data that we've used available to researchers.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... so that they can investigate these kinds of questions
SPEAKER_1:  So the data of the different, the human and the AI play of diplomacy and the models that you use for
SPEAKER_1:  the generation of the messages and the filtering.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, not just even the data of the AI playing with the humans, but...
SPEAKER_0:  all the training data that we had that we used to train the AI to understand how humans play the game.
SPEAKER_0:  We're setting up a system where researchers will be able to apply.
SPEAKER_0:  to be able to gain access to that data and be able to use it in their own research.
SPEAKER_1:  You should say, what is the name of the system?
SPEAKER_0:  We're calling the bots this room.
SPEAKER_1:  sister.
SPEAKER_1:  And what's the name?
SPEAKER_1:  Like you're open sourcing, what's the name of the repository?
SPEAKER_1:  and the project, is it also just called Cicero the Big Project?
SPEAKER_1:  Are you still coming up with a name?
SPEAKER_0:  The dataset comes from this website, WebDiplomacy.net.
SPEAKER_0:  is this site that's been online for like 20 years now. And it's one of the main sites that people use to play diplomacy on it.
SPEAKER_0:  We've got like...
SPEAKER_0:  50,000 games of diplomacy with natural language communication.
SPEAKER_0:  um... over ten million messages
SPEAKER_0:  So it's a pretty massive data set that people can use to, we're hoping that the academic community and the research community is able to use it for all sorts of interesting research questions.
SPEAKER_1:  So do you.
SPEAKER_1:  from having studied this game is this.
SPEAKER_1:  a sufficiently rich problem space to explore this kind of
SPEAKER_1:  human AI interaction.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, absolutely. And I think it's
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's maybe the best data set that I can think of out there.
SPEAKER_0:  to investigate these kinds of questions of negotiation, trust.
SPEAKER_0:  persuasion.
SPEAKER_0:  I wouldn't say it's the best dataset in the world for
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  human AI interaction that's a very broad field, but I think that it's definitely up there is like.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, if you're really interested in...
SPEAKER_0:  language models interacting with humans in.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, a setting where.
SPEAKER_0:  their incentives are not fully aligned. This seems like an ideal data set for investigating that.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  You have, um...
SPEAKER_1:  You have a paper with some impressive results and just an impressive paper that taking this problem on.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the most exciting thing to you in terms of the results from the paper?
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I think there's ideas or results.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think there's a few aspects of the results.
SPEAKER_0:  and that I think are really exciting. So first of all, the fact that we were able to achieve.
SPEAKER_0:  such strong performance.
SPEAKER_0:  I was
SPEAKER_0:  surprised by and pleasantly surprised by.
SPEAKER_0:  So we played 40 games of diplomacy.
SPEAKER_0:  with real humans.
SPEAKER_0:  and the bot placed second.
SPEAKER_0:  out of all players that have played five or more games. So it's about 80 players total.
SPEAKER_0:  19 of whom played five or more games and the bot was ranked second out of those players.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  The bot was really good in two dimensions. One, being able to establish strong connections with the other players on the board, being able to like...
SPEAKER_0:  persuade them to work with it.
SPEAKER_0:  Being able to coordinate with them about like how it's going to work with them.
SPEAKER_0:  And then also the raw.
SPEAKER_0:  tactical and strategic aspects of the game.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, being able to...
SPEAKER_0:  Understand.
SPEAKER_0:  what the other players are likely to do, being able to model their behavior,
SPEAKER_0:  and respond appropriately to that.
SPEAKER_0:  The bot also really excelled at.
SPEAKER_1:  What are some interesting things that the bot said?
SPEAKER_1:  By the way, you're allowed to swear in the...
SPEAKER_1:  Are there rules to what you're allowed to say and not in diplomacy?
SPEAKER_0:  You can say whatever you want. I think the site will get very angry at you if you start threatening somebody.
SPEAKER_1:  We actually... Like if you're threatened somewhere, you're supposed to do it, pull it.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, politely. You know, keep it in character.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  The bot, we actually had a researcher watching the bot 24 seven for, well, whenever we play a game, we have a bot watching it to make sure that it wouldn't.
SPEAKER_0:  go off the rails and start threatening somebody or something like that.
SPEAKER_1:  I would just love it if the boss started mocking.
SPEAKER_1:  Mocking everybody like some weird quirky strategies would emerge.
SPEAKER_1:  Have you seen anything interesting that you huh that's a weird.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a W-
SPEAKER_1:  That's a weird behavior, either of the filter or the language model.
SPEAKER_1:  That was weird to you.
SPEAKER_0:  That was, yeah, there were definitely like.
SPEAKER_0:  Things that the bot would.
SPEAKER_0:  would do that were not in line with how humans would approach the game.
SPEAKER_0:  and that
SPEAKER_0:  In a good way, the humans actually, you know, we've talked to some expert diplomacy players about these results and their takeaway is that, well, maybe humans are approaching this the wrong way and this is actually like the right way to play the game.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  So what's required to win?
SPEAKER_1:  Like what um...
SPEAKER_1:  What does it mean to mess up or to exploit the suboptimal behavior of a player?
SPEAKER_1:  Like, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Is there optimally rational behavior and irrational behavior that you need to...
SPEAKER_1:  Estimate that kind of stuff like what what stands out to you? Like is there a crack that you can exploit?
SPEAKER_1:  Is there like...
SPEAKER_1:  uh... a weakness the you can exploit in the game
SPEAKER_1:  that everybody's looking for.
SPEAKER_0:  Well-
SPEAKER_0:  I think...
SPEAKER_0:  You're asking kind of two questions there. So one, like modeling the.
SPEAKER_0:  irrationality and the suboptimality of humans.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  you can't, in diplomacy, you can't treat all the other players like they're machines. And if you do that,
SPEAKER_0:  You're going to end up...
SPEAKER_0:  playing really poorly. And so we actually ran this experiment. So we.
SPEAKER_0:  We trained a bot.
SPEAKER_0:  in a two-player zero-sum version of diplomacy.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... the same way that you might approach a game like
SPEAKER_0:  Chester Poker.
SPEAKER_0:  and the bot was superhuman. It would crush any competitor.
SPEAKER_0:  And then we took that same training approach and we trained a bot for the full seven player version of the game.
SPEAKER_0:  through self play.
SPEAKER_0:  without any human data.
SPEAKER_0:  and we stuck it in a game with six humans.
SPEAKER_0:  and it got destroyed.
SPEAKER_0:  Even in the version of the game where there's no explicit natural language communication.
SPEAKER_0:  It still got destroyed.
SPEAKER_0:  Because it just wouldn't be able to understand how the other players were approaching the game and be able to work with that.
SPEAKER_1:  calm
SPEAKER_1:  Lingering around that meeting like there's an individual.
SPEAKER_1:  There's an individual personality to each player and then you're supposed to remember that. But what do you mean it's not able to understand?
SPEAKER_1:  the players.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it would, for example, expect the human to support it in a certain way.
SPEAKER_0:  when the human would simply like...
SPEAKER_0:  Think it like, no, I'm not supposed to support you here.
SPEAKER_0:  It's kind of like, you know, if you
SPEAKER_0:  develop a self-driving car.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's trained completely from scratch with other self-driving cars.
SPEAKER_0:  it might learn to drive on the left side of the road.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a totally reasonable thing to do if you're...
SPEAKER_0:  with these other self-driving cars that are also driving on the left side of the road.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you put it in American City...
SPEAKER_0:  It's gonna crash.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess the intuition I'm trying to build up is why does it then crush a human player?
SPEAKER_1:  Heads up.
SPEAKER_1:  This is multiple
SPEAKER_0:  This is an aspect of two players zero song versus games that involve cooperation
SPEAKER_0:  So in a two-player zero-sum game.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  You can do self play from scratch and you will arrive at the Nash Equilibrium.
SPEAKER_0:  where you don't have to worry about.
SPEAKER_0:  the other player.
SPEAKER_0:  playing in a very human suboptimal style. That's just going to be the only way that.
SPEAKER_0:  deviating from Nash equilibrium.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  would change things as if it helped you.
SPEAKER_1:  So I.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the dynamic of cooperation that's effective in diplomacy?
SPEAKER_1:  Do you always have to?
SPEAKER_1:  to have one friend in the game.
SPEAKER_0:  You always
SPEAKER_0:  want to maximize your friends and minimize your enemies.
SPEAKER_1:  Got it.
SPEAKER_1:  and...
SPEAKER_1:  Boy.
SPEAKER_1:  And the, the line comes into play there.
SPEAKER_1:  So the more friends you have, the better.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, I guess you have to attack somebody or else you're not going to make progress.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the tension.
SPEAKER_1:  Man, this is too real. This is too real. This is too close to geopolitics of actual.
SPEAKER_1:  military conflict in the world. Ok.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... that's passing so that cooperation element is what makes the game really really
SPEAKER_0:  And to give you an example of how this suboptimality and irrationality comes into play.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a really common situation.
SPEAKER_0:  in the game of diplomacy.
SPEAKER_0:  where one player starts to win and they're like at the point where they're controlling about half the map.
SPEAKER_0:  And the remaining players who have all been fighting each other the whole game.
SPEAKER_0:  all have to like work together now to stop this other player from winning or else everybody's gonna lose.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And it's kind of like, you know, Game of Thrones, like I don't know if you've seen the show, where like, you know, you got the others coming from the North and like all the people have to start, work out their differences and stop them from taking over.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And the bot will do this. The bot will work with the other players to stop the superpower from winning.
SPEAKER_0:  but...
SPEAKER_0:  If it doesn't really, if it's trained from scratch, or it doesn't really have a good grounding in how humans approach it,
SPEAKER_0:  It will also at the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  attack the other players with its extra units.
SPEAKER_0:  So all the units that are not necessary to stop the super power from winning, it will use those to grab as many centers as possible from the other players.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  In totally rational play
SPEAKER_0:  The other players should just live with that. You know, they have to understand like, hey-
SPEAKER_0:  A score of 1 is better than a score of 0.
SPEAKER_0:  So, so.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, he's grabbed my centers.
SPEAKER_0:  but I'll just deal with it.
SPEAKER_0:  but humans don't act that way, right? the human
SPEAKER_0:  gets really angry at the bot.
SPEAKER_0:  and ends up throwing the game.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  I'm gonna screw you over because you did something that's not fair to me.
SPEAKER_1:  Got it. And are you supposed to model that? Is the boss supposed to model that kind of...
SPEAKER_1:  human
SPEAKER_1:  Frustration.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, exactly. And so.
SPEAKER_0:  That is something that seems almost impossible to model.
SPEAKER_0:  purely from scratch without any human data. It's a very cultural thing.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you need
SPEAKER_0:  human data to be able to understand that, hey, that's how humans behave.
SPEAKER_0:  and you have to work around that. It might be suboptimal, it might be irrational.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's an aspect of humanity that you have to deal with.
SPEAKER_1:  So how difficult is it to train on human data, given that human data is very limited versus what the us.
SPEAKER_1:  a purely self-playing mechanism can generate.
SPEAKER_0:  That's actually one of the major challenges that we faced in the research that
SPEAKER_0:  We had a good amount of human data. We had about 50,000 games. What we try to do is
SPEAKER_0:  Leverage as much self-play as possible.
SPEAKER_0:  while still leveraging the human data.
SPEAKER_0:  So what we do is we do self play.
SPEAKER_0:  Very similar to how it's been done in Poker and Go.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  we try to regularize the self-play towards the human data. basically the way to think about it is
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  We-
SPEAKER_0:  penalize.
SPEAKER_0:  the bot.
SPEAKER_0:  for
SPEAKER_0:  Choosing actions that are very unlikely.
SPEAKER_0:  under the human data set.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_1:  there is some kind of function that says
SPEAKER_1:  This is Human Like and Not.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so we train a bot through supervised learning.
SPEAKER_0:  to model the human play as much as possible. So we basically like train a neural net.
SPEAKER_0:  on those 50,000 games and that gives us an approximate, that gives us a policy that.
SPEAKER_0:  resembles to some extent how humans actually play the game.
SPEAKER_0:  Now this isn't a perfect...
SPEAKER_0:  model of human play.
SPEAKER_0:  because we don't have unlimited data. We don't have unlimited neural net capacity.
SPEAKER_0:  but it gives us some approximation.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there some data on the internet that's useful besides just diplomacy?
SPEAKER_1:  So on the language side of things, is there some...
SPEAKER_1:  Can you go to it like Reddit?
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  So sort of background model formulation that's useful for the game of diplomacy.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, absolutely. And so for the language model, which
SPEAKER_0:  It's kind of like a separate question. We didn't use the language model during self play training.
SPEAKER_0:  but we...
SPEAKER_0:  pre-trains the language model.
SPEAKER_0:  on tons of internet data.
SPEAKER_0:  as much as possible.
SPEAKER_0:  and then we fine tuned it specifically on the diplomacy games.
SPEAKER_0:  So we are able to leverage the wider data set in order to fill in.
SPEAKER_0:  some of the gaps in how communication happens more broadly, besides just specifically in these diplomacy games.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, cool. So what's some?
SPEAKER_1:  What are some interesting things that came to life from this work?
SPEAKER_1:  to you, like what are some insights?
SPEAKER_1:  about
SPEAKER_1:  about games where natural language is involved and cooperation, deep cooperation is involved.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I think there's a few insights. So first of all.
SPEAKER_0:  the fact that you can't rely.
SPEAKER_0:  purely or even largely on self-play, that you really have to have an understanding of how humans approach the game.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  I think that that's one of the major conclusions that I'm drawing from this work.
SPEAKER_0:  and that
SPEAKER_0:  is I think applicable more broadly to a lot of different games.
SPEAKER_0:  So we've actually already taken the approaches that we've used in diplomacy and tried them.
SPEAKER_0:  on a cooperative card game called Hanabi.
SPEAKER_0:  And we've had a lot of success in that game as well.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, on the language side.
SPEAKER_0:  I think
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that we were able to control
SPEAKER_0:  The language model.
SPEAKER_0:  through this intense approach.
SPEAKER_0:  was very effective and it allowed us.
SPEAKER_0:  Instead of just imitating how humans would communicate, we're able to go beyond that and-
SPEAKER_0:  able to
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  feed into its superhuman strategies.
SPEAKER_0:  that it can then...
SPEAKER_0:  generate messages corresponding to.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there something you could say about detecting whether a person or AI is lying or not?
SPEAKER_0:  The butt.
SPEAKER_0:  doesn't explicitly try to
SPEAKER_0:  calculate whether somebody is lying or not.
SPEAKER_0:  But what it will do is...
SPEAKER_0:  to predict what actions they're going to take given the communications, given the messages that they've sent to us.
SPEAKER_0:  So given our conversation, what do I think you're going to do? And implicitly-
SPEAKER_0:  There is a calculation about whether you're lying to me in that.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, if, if you're
SPEAKER_0:  based on your messages if I think you're going to attack me this turn.
SPEAKER_0:  Even though your messages say that you're not
SPEAKER_0:  then essentially the bot is predicting that you're lying.
SPEAKER_0:  but it doesn't view it.
SPEAKER_0:  as lying the same way that we would view it as lying.
SPEAKER_1:  But you could probably reformulate with all the same data.
SPEAKER_1:  and.
SPEAKER_1:  make a classifier lying or not.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think you could do that. That was not something that we were focused on, but I think that it is possible that-
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  if you came up with some measurements of like, what does it mean to tell a lie? Because there's a spectrum, right? Like...
SPEAKER_0:  If you're
SPEAKER_0:  Withholding some information is that a lie?
SPEAKER_0:  If you mostly telling the truth but you forgot to mention this like one action out of like 10
SPEAKER_0:  Is that a lie?
SPEAKER_0:  It's hard to draw the line, but you know if you're willing to do that
SPEAKER_0:  and then you could possibly use it to...
SPEAKER_1:  This feels like an argument inside a relationship now.
SPEAKER_1:  so
SPEAKER_1:  What constitutes a lie?
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Depends what you mean by the definition of the word is. OK.
SPEAKER_1:  Still, it's fascinating because trust and lying is all intermixed into this.
SPEAKER_1:  and its language models.
SPEAKER_1:  that are becoming more and more sophisticated. It's just a fascinating space to explore.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you see as the future of this?
SPEAKER_1:  is inspired by the breakthrough performance to you getting here with diplomacy.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I think there's a few different directions to take this work.
SPEAKER_0:  I think really what it's showing us is...
SPEAKER_0:  The potential that language models have, I mean, I think a lot of people didn't think that this kind of result was possible even today.
SPEAKER_0:  despite all the progress that's been made in language models.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it shows us how we can.
SPEAKER_0:  leverage
SPEAKER_0:  the power of things like self play.
SPEAKER_0:  on top of language models to get.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Increasingly better performance.
SPEAKER_0:  And the ceiling is really...
SPEAKER_0:  much higher than what we have right now.
SPEAKER_1:  Is this transferable somehow to?
SPEAKER_1:  to chatbots.
SPEAKER_1:  for the more general task of dialogue.
SPEAKER_1:  because there is a kind of negotiation here, between
SPEAKER_1:  entities that are trying to cooperate and at the same time a little bit adversarial.
SPEAKER_1:  which I think maps...
SPEAKER_1:  somewhat to the general.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  the entire process of.
SPEAKER_1:  Reddit.
SPEAKER_1:  Or like internet communication, you're cooperating, you're
SPEAKER_1:  adversarial, you're having debates, you're having uh...
SPEAKER_1:  camaraderie all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  I think one of the things that's really useful about diplomacy is that we have a well-defined value function.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a well-defined score that the bot is trying to optimize.
SPEAKER_0:  in a setting like a general chat bot setting.
SPEAKER_0:  It needs, it would need that kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  objective in order to fully leverage the techniques that we've developed.
SPEAKER_1:  What about like what we talked about earlier with NPCs inside video games?
SPEAKER_1:  How can it be used to create?
SPEAKER_1:  for Elder Scrolls 6 more compelling
SPEAKER_1:  and PCs.
SPEAKER_1:  that you could talk to instead of committing all kinds of violence with a sword.
SPEAKER_1:  and fighting dragons.
SPEAKER_1:  just sitting in a tavern and drink all day and talk to the chat bot.
SPEAKER_0:  The way that we've approached AI and diplomacy is you condition the language on an intent.
SPEAKER_0:  Now that intent in diplomacy is an action.
SPEAKER_0:  but it doesn't have to be and you can imagine.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  You could have NPCs.
SPEAKER_0:  in video games or the metaverse or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  where
SPEAKER_0:  there's some intent or there's some objective that they're trying to maximize and you can specify what that is.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and then the language.
SPEAKER_0:  can correspond to that intent.
SPEAKER_0:  Now, I'm not saying that this is happening imminently, but I'm saying that this is like a future application potentially of
SPEAKER_0:  this direction of research.
SPEAKER_1:  So what's the more general formulation of this?
SPEAKER_1:  making self-play be able to scale the way self-play does and still maintain human-like.
SPEAKER_1:  behavior.
SPEAKER_0:  The way that we've...
SPEAKER_0:  approach self-play in diplomacy is like.
SPEAKER_0:  We're trying to...
SPEAKER_0:  come up with good intents to condition the language model on. In the space of intents.
SPEAKER_0:  is actions that can be played in the game.
SPEAKER_0:  Now there is like the potential to have a broader set of intents.
SPEAKER_0:  Things like.
SPEAKER_0:  you know long-term cooperation or long-term objectives or
SPEAKER_0:  you know gossip about what another player was saying
SPEAKER_0:  These are things that we're currently not conditioning the language model on and so it's not able
SPEAKER_0:  we're not able to control it to say like, Oh, you should be talking about this thing right now.
SPEAKER_0:  it's quite possible that you could expand the scope of intents.
SPEAKER_0:  to be able to allow it to talk about those things.
SPEAKER_0:  Now in the process of doing that.
SPEAKER_0:  the self-play would become much more complicated.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And so that is a potential for future work.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, they're increasing the number of intents. I still am not quite clear.
SPEAKER_1:  how you keep.
SPEAKER_1:  the self-play.
SPEAKER_1:  integrated into the human world.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm a little bit loose on the...
SPEAKER_1:  on understanding how you do that.
SPEAKER_0:  So we train a neural nets to.
SPEAKER_0:  imitate the human data as closely as possible.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's what we call the anchor policy.
SPEAKER_0:  And now we're doing self play.
SPEAKER_0:  The problem with the anchor policy is that...
SPEAKER_0:  It's not.
SPEAKER_0:  perfect approximation of how humans actually play. Because we don't have infinite data, because we don't have
SPEAKER_0:  and limited neural network capacity.
SPEAKER_0:  It's actually a relatively suboptimal approximation of how humans actually play.
SPEAKER_0:  and we can improve that approximation.
SPEAKER_0:  by adding planning.
SPEAKER_0:  and RL.
SPEAKER_0:  And so what we do is...
SPEAKER_0:  We get a better approximation, a better model of human play.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  during the self play process.
SPEAKER_0:  We say...
SPEAKER_0:  you can deviate from this.
SPEAKER_0:  human anchor policy.
SPEAKER_0:  if there is an action that has
SPEAKER_0:  you know, particularly high expected value.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  it would have to be a really high expected value in order to deviate from this human-like policy.
SPEAKER_0:  So you basically say, try to maximize your expected value while at the same time,
SPEAKER_0:  stay as close as possible to the human policy.
SPEAKER_0:  and there is a parameter.
SPEAKER_0:  that controls.
SPEAKER_0:  Those
SPEAKER_0:  the relative weighting of those competing objectives.
SPEAKER_1:  So the question I have.
SPEAKER_1:  is how sophisticated can the anchor policy get?
SPEAKER_1:  So have a policy that approximates human behavior.
SPEAKER_1:  Right?
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  as you increase the number of intents, as you generalize.
SPEAKER_1:  the space in which this is applicable.
SPEAKER_1:  And given that the human data is limited, try to anticipate.
SPEAKER_1:  A policy that works for in much larger number of cases.
SPEAKER_1:  Like how difficult is the process of forming a damn good anchor policy?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it really comes down to how much human data you have.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's all bar scaling the human data.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the more human data you have, the better. And I think that that's going to be the major bottleneck in scaling to
SPEAKER_0:  more complicated domains. With that said, I hope you enjoyed this video.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there might be the potential, just like in the language model where we leveraged.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, tons of data on the internet and then specialized it for diplomacy.
SPEAKER_0:  There is the future potential that you can leverage huge amounts of data across the board.
SPEAKER_0:  And then...
SPEAKER_0:  Specialize it.
SPEAKER_0:  in the data set that you have for diplomacy. And that way you're essentially augmenting the amount of data that you have.
SPEAKER_1:  To what degree does this apply?
SPEAKER_1:  Shoo!
SPEAKER_1:  The General.
SPEAKER_1:  the real world.
SPEAKER_1:  diplomacy.
SPEAKER_1:  the geopolitics.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there's a game theory has a history of being applied to understand.
SPEAKER_1:  and to give us hope about nuclear weapons, for example, the mutually assured destruction.
SPEAKER_1:  is a game theoretic concept that you can formulate.
SPEAKER_1:  Some people say it's oversimplified, but nevertheless, here we are.
SPEAKER_1:  and we somehow haven't blown ourselves up.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you see a future where...
SPEAKER_1:  this kind of
SPEAKER_1:  this kind of system.
SPEAKER_1:  can be used to help us make.
SPEAKER_1:  geopolitical decisions in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, like I said, the original motivation for the game of diplomacy was the failures of World War I. The diplomatic failures that led to war.
SPEAKER_0:  And the real take-home message of diplomacy is that
SPEAKER_0:  You know, if...
SPEAKER_0:  people approach diplomacy the right way.
SPEAKER_0:  then
SPEAKER_0:  war is ultimately unsuccessful.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  The way that I see it war is...
SPEAKER_0:  an inherently negative sum game, right? There's always a better outcome.
SPEAKER_0:  than war for all the parties involved.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  My hope is that...
SPEAKER_0:  you know as a i progresses then maybe this technology could be used
SPEAKER_0:  to help.
SPEAKER_0:  People make better decisions.
SPEAKER_0:  across the board.
SPEAKER_0:  and hopefully avoid...
SPEAKER_0:  negative some outcomes like war.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I would look, I mean, I just came back from Ukraine. I'm going back there.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  deep personal levels.
SPEAKER_1:  think a lot about.
SPEAKER_1:  how peace can be achieved. And I'm a big believer in conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  leaders getting together and having conversations and trying to understand each other.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's fascinating to think, um...
SPEAKER_1:  whether each one of those leaders can run a simulation ahead of time.
SPEAKER_1:  Like if I'm an asshole.
SPEAKER_1:  What are the possible consequences? If I'm nice, what are the possible consequences?
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  My guess.
SPEAKER_1:  is that if the president of the United States got together with
SPEAKER_1:  Vladimir Zelensky and Vladimir Putin.
SPEAKER_1:  that there will be significant benefits.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  Um
SPEAKER_1:  the president of the United States not having the ego.
SPEAKER_1:  of kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  playing down of giving away a lot of chips.
SPEAKER_1:  for the future success of the world.
SPEAKER_1:  So giving a lot of power to the two presidents of the competing nations.
SPEAKER_1:  to achieve peace.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, that's my guess, but it'd be nice to run a bunch of simulations.
SPEAKER_1:  but then you have to have human data, right? You really, because it's like the game with diplomacy is fundamentally different than geopolitics. You need data.
SPEAKER_1:  Any like.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess that's the question I have, like how transferable is this to uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Like, I don't know, any kind of negotiation.
SPEAKER_1:  like to any kind of local, some local.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, a bunch of lawyers.
SPEAKER_1:  like arguing, like at a divorce.
SPEAKER_1:  like divorce lawyers, like how transferable this all kinds of human negotiation.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I feel like this isn't a question that's unique to diplomacy. I mean, I think you look at-
SPEAKER_0:  RL breakthroughs, reinforcement learning breakthroughs in previous games as well, like AI for StarCraft, AI for Atari.
SPEAKER_0:  You haven't really seen it deployed in the real world.
SPEAKER_0:  because you have these problems of it's really hard to collect a lot of data.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and you don't have.
SPEAKER_0:  And...
SPEAKER_0:  You don't have a well-defined action space. You don't have a well-defined reward function.
SPEAKER_0:  These are all things that you really need.
SPEAKER_0:  for reinforcement learning and planning to be really successful today.
SPEAKER_0:  Now there are some domains where you do have that.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, code generation is one example.
SPEAKER_0:  Theorem proving mathematics, that's another example where you have a well defined action space, you have a well defined reward function.
SPEAKER_0:  And.
SPEAKER_0:  Those are the kinds of domains where I can see.
SPEAKER_0:  RL in the short term.
SPEAKER_0:  being incredibly powerful.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think that those are the barriers to deploying this at scale in the real world, but
SPEAKER_0:  The hope is that in the long run we'll be able to get there.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, but see diplomacy feels like.
SPEAKER_1:  closer to the real world than does StarCraft.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, because it's natural language, right? You're operating in the space of intents and in the space of natural language. That feels very close to the real world. It also feels like you could get data on that.
SPEAKER_1:  from the internet.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and that's why I do think that diplomacy...
SPEAKER_0:  is taking a big step.
SPEAKER_0:  closer to the real world than anything that's came before in terms of game AI breakthroughs.
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that
SPEAKER_0:  You know, we're...
SPEAKER_0:  communicating in natural language we've
SPEAKER_0:  we're leveraging the fact that we have this like general dataset of dialogue and communication.
SPEAKER_0:  from a breadth of the internet.
SPEAKER_0:  That is a big step in that direction. We're not 100% there.
SPEAKER_0:  but we're getting closer at least.
SPEAKER_1:  So if we actually return back to poker and chess...
SPEAKER_1:  are some of the ideas that you're learning here with diplomacy.
SPEAKER_1:  Could you construct AI systems that play like humans?
SPEAKER_1:  Like, um...
SPEAKER_1:  Make for a fun opponent.
SPEAKER_1:  in a game of chess.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, absolutely. We've already started looking into this direction a bit, so we tried to use the techniques that we've developed for diplomacy.
SPEAKER_0:  to make Chess and Go AIs. And what we found is that it led to
SPEAKER_0:  much more human-like.
SPEAKER_0:  strong
SPEAKER_0:  Chess and Go players.
SPEAKER_0:  The way that...
SPEAKER_0:  AIs like stockfish today.
SPEAKER_0:  is in a very inhuman style. It's very strong, but it's very different from how humans play.
SPEAKER_0:  And so we can take the techniques that we've developed for diplomacy, we do something similar.
SPEAKER_0:  And, um.
SPEAKER_0:  and chess and go.
SPEAKER_0:  and we end up with a bot that's both strong and human-like.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  To elaborate on this a bit, like...
SPEAKER_0:  One way to approach
SPEAKER_0:  Making a human-like AI for chess?
SPEAKER_0:  is
SPEAKER_0:  to collect a bunch of human games, like a bunch of human grand master games.
SPEAKER_0:  and just to supervise learning on those games.
SPEAKER_0:  But the problem is that if you do that, what you end up with is an AI that's substantially weaker.
SPEAKER_0:  than the human grandmasters that you trained on.
SPEAKER_0:  because the neural net.
SPEAKER_0:  is not able to approximate.
SPEAKER_0:  the nuance of the strategy. This goes back to the planning thing that I mentioned, the search thing that I talked about before.
SPEAKER_0:  These human grandmasters when they're playing, they're using search and they're using.
SPEAKER_0:  planning.
SPEAKER_0:  And the neural net alone, unless you have a massive neural net that's like a thousand times bigger than what we have right now.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not able to...
SPEAKER_0:  approximate those details very effectively.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  On the other hand, you can leverage.
SPEAKER_0:  search and planning very heavily.
SPEAKER_0:  But then what you end up with is an AI that plays in a very different style from how humans play the game.
SPEAKER_0:  Now if you strike this intermediate balance by setting...
SPEAKER_0:  the regularization parameters correctly and say you can do planning but try to keep it close to the human policy.
SPEAKER_0:  Then you end up...
SPEAKER_0:  with.
SPEAKER_0:  an AI that plays in both a very human-like style
SPEAKER_0:  and a very strong.
SPEAKER_0:  style.
SPEAKER_0:  and you can actually even tune it.
SPEAKER_0:  have a certain ELO rating.
SPEAKER_0:  So you can say, playing the style of like a 2800 ELO human.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  I wonder if you could do specific type of humans or categories of humans.
SPEAKER_1:  Not just skill, but style.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think so. And so this is this is where the
SPEAKER_0:  the research gets interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, one of the things that I was thinking about is...
SPEAKER_0:  And this is actually already being done. There's a researcher at the University of Toronto that's working on this.
SPEAKER_0:  is to make an AI that plays in the style of a particular
SPEAKER_0:  player.
SPEAKER_0:  like Magnus Carlsen for example, you can make an AI that plays like Magnus Carlsen.
SPEAKER_0:  And then where I think this gets interesting is like, maybe you're up against Magnus Carlsen in the World Championship or something.
SPEAKER_0:  You can.
SPEAKER_0:  against this Magnus Carlsen bot to prepare.
SPEAKER_0:  against the real Magnus Carlsen and you can try to explore strategies.
SPEAKER_0:  he might struggle with.
SPEAKER_0:  and try to figure out how do you beat this player in particular.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, on the other hand, you can also have Mac is Carlson working with this spot to try to figure out where he's weak.
SPEAKER_0:  and where he needs to improve his strategy.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And so I can envision this future.
SPEAKER_0:  where
SPEAKER_0:  Data on specific chess and Go players becomes extremely valuable because you can use that data.
SPEAKER_0:  to create.
SPEAKER_0:  specific models of how these particular players play.
SPEAKER_1:  So increasingly human-like behavior in bots, however,
SPEAKER_1:  as you've mentioned, makes cheating.
SPEAKER_1:  cheat detection much harder.
SPEAKER_0:  It does, yeah. The way that sheet detection works.
SPEAKER_0:  in a game like poker and a game like...
SPEAKER_0:  chess and go from what I understand is.
SPEAKER_0:  trying to see like is this person making...
SPEAKER_0:  moves that
SPEAKER_0:  are very common among chess AIs, or AIs in general.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  but very.
SPEAKER_0:  uncommon among top human players.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  If you have...
SPEAKER_0:  development of these AIs that play
SPEAKER_0:  in a very strong style, but also a very human-like style.
SPEAKER_0:  then that poses serious challenges for cheat detection.
SPEAKER_1:  and it makes you...
SPEAKER_1:  Now ask yourself a hard question about what is the role of AI systems.
SPEAKER_1:  as they become more and more integrated in our society.
SPEAKER_1:  and this kind of human AI.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  integration.
SPEAKER_1:  has some.
SPEAKER_1:  deep ethical issues.
SPEAKER_1:  that we should be aware of.
SPEAKER_1:  And also it's a kind of cybersecurity challenge, right?
SPEAKER_1:  to make one of the assumptions we have when we play games.
SPEAKER_1:  is that there's a trust that it's only humans involved.
SPEAKER_1:  and there.
SPEAKER_1:  The better AI systems to create, which makes it super exciting. Human like AI systems with different styles of humans is really exciting, but then we have to have the defenses.
SPEAKER_1:  better and better and better.
SPEAKER_1:  if we're to trust that we are.
SPEAKER_1:  can enjoy human versus human game.
SPEAKER_1:  deeply fair way. It's fascinating. It's just.
SPEAKER_1:  It's humbling.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think there is a lot of negative potential for this kind of technology, but...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, at the same time, there's a lot of upside for it as well.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, for example, right now it's really hard to learn how to get better in games like chess and poker and go because
SPEAKER_0:  The way that the AI plays is so foreign and incomprehensible.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you have these AIs that are playing...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you can say like, I'm a 2000 Elo human, how do I get to 2200?
SPEAKER_0:  Now you can have an AI that plays in the style of a 2200 ELO human.
SPEAKER_0:  and that will help you get better.
SPEAKER_0:  or
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you mentioned this problem of like, how do you know that you're actually playing with humans when you're playing like online and in video games?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, now we have the potential of populating.
SPEAKER_0:  these like virtual worlds.
SPEAKER_0:  with
SPEAKER_0:  uh... agents the agents that are actually fun to play with you don't have to
SPEAKER_0:  always be playing with other humans to have a fun time.
SPEAKER_0:  So yeah, a lot of upside potential too. And I think, you know, with any sort of tool, there's the-
SPEAKER_0:  potential for a lot of greatness and a lot of downsides as well.
SPEAKER_1:  So in the paper that I got a chance to look at, there's a section on
SPEAKER_1:  ethical considerations. What's in that section? What are some ethical considerations here?
SPEAKER_1:  Is it some of the stuff we already talked about?
SPEAKER_0:  There's some things that we've already talked about, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  specific to...
SPEAKER_0:  Diplomacy, you know, there's also the...
SPEAKER_0:  the challenge that the game is.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there is a deception aspect to the game.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  have developing language models that
SPEAKER_0:  are capable of deception is I think a dicey issue and something that
SPEAKER_0:  you know, makes research on diplomacy particularly challenging.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  You know, so those kinds of issues of like...
SPEAKER_0:  Should we even be developing AIs that are capable of lying to people? That's something that we have to think carefully about.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, that's so cool. I mean, you have to do that kind of stuff in order to figure out where the ethical lines are, but I can see in the future it being illegal to have a
SPEAKER_1:  consumer product that.
SPEAKER_1:  Lies.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. Yeah. Like your personal assistant AI system is not a lot is always have to tell the truth. But if, if I ask it, do I, do I look, did I get fatter over the past month?
SPEAKER_1:  I sure as hell want that AI system to lie to me.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's a trade-off between lying and being nice.
SPEAKER_1:  I have to somehow find.
SPEAKER_1:  What is the ethics in that? And we're back to discussions inside relationships. Anyway, what were you saying?
SPEAKER_0:  I was thinking like, yeah, that's kind of going to the question of like, what is a lie? You know, is a white lie a bad lie? Is it an ethical lie? You know, those kinds of questions.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Boy, we return time and time again to deep human questions as we design AI systems. That's exactly what they do. They put a mirror to humanity.
SPEAKER_1:  to help us understand ourselves.
SPEAKER_0:  There's also the issue of like, you know, in these diplomacy experiments in order to do...
SPEAKER_0:  a fair comparison. What we found is that
SPEAKER_0:  there's an inherent anti-AI bias in these kinds of games. So we actually played.
SPEAKER_0:  tournaments in a non-language version of the game.
SPEAKER_0:  where you know we we told the participants like hey every single game is going to be an AI.
SPEAKER_0:  And what we found is that the humans...
SPEAKER_0:  would spend basically the entire game like trying to figure out who the bot was. And then as soon as they thought they figured it out, they would all team up and try to kill it.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  You know, overcoming that inherent anti-AI bias is a challenge.
SPEAKER_1:  On the flip side.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  when robots become the enemy.
SPEAKER_1:  That's when we get to heal our human divisions.
SPEAKER_1:  and we can become one.
SPEAKER_1:  As long as we have one enemy, it's that Reagan thing when the aliens show up. That's when we put our side, our divisions will become one.
SPEAKER_1:  one human species.
SPEAKER_0:  We might have our differences, but we're at least all human.
SPEAKER_1:  At least we all hate the robots. No.
SPEAKER_1:  No, no, no. I think there will be actually in the future something like a civil rights movement for robots. I think that's the fascinating thing about AI systems is they ask.
SPEAKER_1:  they force us to ask about.
SPEAKER_1:  ethical questions about what is sentience, what is, how do we feel about systems that are capable of suffering, are capable of displaying suffering.
SPEAKER_1:  and how do we design products that show emotion and not?
SPEAKER_1:  How do we feel about that? Lying is another topic.
SPEAKER_1:  Awee.
SPEAKER_1:  going to allow bots to lie and not...
SPEAKER_1:  and where's the balance between being nice and telling the truth? I mean these are all fascinating human questions.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like so exciting to be in the century with
SPEAKER_1:  We create systems that...
SPEAKER_1:  Take this.
SPEAKER_1:  philosophical questions that have been asked for.
SPEAKER_1:  centuries and now we can engineer them inside systems where like you really have to answer them because you'll have
SPEAKER_1:  transformational impact on human society, depending on what you design inside those systems. It's fascinating.
SPEAKER_1:  And like you said, I feel like diplomacy is a step towards the direction of the real world.
SPEAKER_1:  applying these RL methods towards the real world.
SPEAKER_1:  from.
SPEAKER_1:  from all the breakthrough performances.
SPEAKER_1:  in Go and Chess and StarCraft and Dota.
SPEAKER_1:  This is, this feels like the real world.
SPEAKER_1:  Especially now my mind's been on war.
SPEAKER_1:  military conflict. This feels like it can give us some deep insights about human behavior at the large geopolitical scale.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think?
SPEAKER_1:  is the...
SPEAKER_1:  breakthrough.
SPEAKER_1:  or
SPEAKER_1:  the directions of work that will take us towards solving intelligence.
SPEAKER_1:  towards creating AGI systems.
SPEAKER_1:  You've been a part of.
SPEAKER_1:  creating
SPEAKER_1:  By the way, we should say part of.
SPEAKER_1:  great teams that do this.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  of creating.
SPEAKER_1:  systems that achieve breakthrough performances on before.
SPEAKER_1:  thought unsolvable problems like poker.
SPEAKER_1:  multiplayer poker, diplomacy.
SPEAKER_1:  We're taking steps towards that direction.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think it takes to go all the way to create superhuman level intelligence?
SPEAKER_0:  There's a lot of people trying to figure that out right now.
SPEAKER_0:  I should say the amount of progress that's been made, especially in the past few years is truly phenomenal.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, you look at where AI was.
SPEAKER_0:  10 years ago and the idea that you can have AIs that can generate language and generate images the way they're doing today and able to play a game like diplomacy was just
SPEAKER_0:  Like, unthinkable.
SPEAKER_0:  Even five years ago, let alone 10 years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Now, there are aspects.
SPEAKER_0:  of AI that I think are still.
SPEAKER_0:  Lacking, um...
SPEAKER_0:  I think...
SPEAKER_0:  There's general agreements.
SPEAKER_0:  that one of the major issues with AI today is that it's very data inefficient. It requires
SPEAKER_0:  a huge number of samples of training examples.
SPEAKER_0:  to be able to train.
SPEAKER_0:  and you look at it and the other place go
SPEAKER_0:  and it needs millions of games of go.
SPEAKER_0:  to learn how to play the game well.
SPEAKER_0:  whereas a human can pick it up and like, you know, I don't know how many games as a human go player, go, go grand master playing their lifetime.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  in the thousands or tens of thousands, I guess.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  So that's one issue, overcoming this challenge of data efficiency. This is particularly important if we want to.
SPEAKER_0:  deploy AI systems in.
SPEAKER_0:  real world settings where they're interacting with humans because you know for example with robotics
SPEAKER_0:  it's really hard to generate a huge number of samples.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a different story when you're working in these, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Totally virtual games where you can play a million games and it's no big deal.
SPEAKER_1:  I was planning on just launching like a thousand of these robots in Austin.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't think it's illegal for legged robots to roam the streets and just collect data.
SPEAKER_1:  That's not a crazy idea.
SPEAKER_0:  happened. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, that's one way to overcome the data efficiency problem, is scale it.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I actually tried to see if there's a law against robots, like legged robots, which is.
SPEAKER_1:  operating.
SPEAKER_1:  in the streets of a major city and there isn't.
SPEAKER_1:  couldn't find any.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll take it all the way to the Supreme Court.
SPEAKER_1:  Robot rights. Okay, anyway, sorry, you were saying. So this is the.
SPEAKER_1:  So what are the ideas for becoming more data efficient?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, that's the trillion dollar question in AI today. I mean, if you can figure out how to make AI systems more data efficient, then...
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  A huge breakthrough.
SPEAKER_0:  So nobody really knows right now. It could be just.
SPEAKER_1:  just a gigantic background language model.
SPEAKER_1:  And then you do.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  the training becomes like prompting that model.
SPEAKER_1:  to, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  to essentially do a kind of querying, a search into the space of the things that's learned.
SPEAKER_1:  to customize that to whatever problem you're trying to solve. So maybe if you form a large enough language model, you can go quite a long way.
SPEAKER_0:  That.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I think there's some truth to that. I mean, you look at the way humans approach a game like poker, they're not coming at it from scratch. They're coming at it with a huge amount of background knowledge about.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, how humans work, how the world works.
SPEAKER_0:  um, the idea of money.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  they're able to leverage that kind of information to pick up the game faster.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's not really a fair comparison to then compare it to an AI that's like learning from scratch. And maybe one of the ways that we address this.
SPEAKER_0:  sample complexity problem.
SPEAKER_0:  is by allowing AIs to leverage that general knowledge across a ton of different domains.
SPEAKER_1:  So like I said you did uh
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of incredible work in the space of research.
SPEAKER_1:  and actually building systems, what advice would you give to, let's start with beginners.
SPEAKER_1:  What advice would you give to beginners interested in machine learning?
SPEAKER_1:  Just, they're at the very start of their journey there in high school and college.
SPEAKER_1:  thinking like this seems like a fascinating world.
SPEAKER_1:  What advice would you give them?
SPEAKER_0:  Um, I would say...
SPEAKER_0:  that there are a lot of
SPEAKER_0:  people working on similar.
SPEAKER_0:  aspects of machine learning and to not be afraid to try something.
SPEAKER_0:  a bit different. My own path.
SPEAKER_0:  in AI.
SPEAKER_0:  is pretty atypical for a machine learning researcher today.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I started out working on game theory and...
SPEAKER_0:  and then shifting more towards reinforcement learning as time went on.
SPEAKER_0:  And that actually had a lot of benefits, I think, because it allowed me to...
SPEAKER_0:  look at these problems in a very different way from the way a lot of machine learning researchers view it.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and.
SPEAKER_0:  that
SPEAKER_0:  comes with drawbacks in some respects. I think there's definitely aspects of machine learning.
SPEAKER_0:  where
SPEAKER_0:  No, I'm weaker than-
SPEAKER_0:  most of the researchers out there.
SPEAKER_0:  But I think that diversity of perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, when I'm working with.
SPEAKER_0:  My teammates.
SPEAKER_0:  They're saying that I'm bringing to the table and something that they're bringing to the table.
SPEAKER_0:  And that kind of collaboration becomes very fruitful for that reason.
SPEAKER_1:  So there could be problems like...
SPEAKER_1:  like poker lucky.
SPEAKER_1:  you've chosen diplomacy, there could be problems like that still out there that you can just tackle.
SPEAKER_1:  even if it seems extremely difficult.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, I think that there's a lot of challenges, challenges left. And I think having a diversity.
SPEAKER_0:  of viewpoints.
SPEAKER_0:  and backgrounds is really helpful for.
SPEAKER_0:  working together to figure out how to.
SPEAKER_0:  tackle those kinds of challenges.
SPEAKER_1:  as a beginner. So that I would say that's
SPEAKER_1:  That's more for like a grad student.
SPEAKER_1:  They already built up a bass like a complete beginner.
SPEAKER_1:  What's a good journey? So for you that was doing some more on the math side of things to game theory.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's basically build up a foundation in something. So programming, mathematics.
SPEAKER_1:  even be physics.
SPEAKER_1:  but build that foundation.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I would say build a strong foundation in math and computer science and statistics and these kinds of areas. But don't be afraid to
SPEAKER_0:  try something that's different and learn something that's different from, you know, the
SPEAKER_0:  the thing that everybody else is doing to get into machine learning.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there's there's value.
SPEAKER_0:  in having a different background than everybody else.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so.
SPEAKER_0:  But certainly having a strong math background, especially in things like linear algebra and statistics and probability,
SPEAKER_0:  are incredibly helpful today for learning about.
SPEAKER_0:  understanding machine learning.
SPEAKER_1:  You think one day we'll be able to, since you're taking steps from poker to diplomacy, one day we'll be able to, uh,
SPEAKER_1:  figure out how to live life optimally.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, what is it like in poker and diplomacy, you need a value function, you need to have a reward system. And so
SPEAKER_0:  What does it mean to live a life that's optimal?
SPEAKER_1:  So, okay, so then you can.
SPEAKER_1:  Exactly, like lay down a reward function being like, I want to be rich.
SPEAKER_1:  or I want to be...
SPEAKER_1:  I want to be in a happy relationship.
SPEAKER_1:  and then you'll say well
SPEAKER_1:  Do X.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there's a lot of talk today about, in AI safety circles about like misspecification of.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, reward functions. So you...
SPEAKER_0:  You say like, okay, my objective is to be rich. And maybe the AI tells you like, okay, well, if you want to maximize the probability that you're rich, go rob a bank.
SPEAKER_0:  Sure. So you want to.
SPEAKER_0:  Is that really what you want? Is your objective really to be rich at all costs, or is it more nuanced than that?
SPEAKER_1:  So the unintended consequences.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  That's...
SPEAKER_1:  So maybe life is more about defining the reward function that minimizes the unintended consequences.
SPEAKER_1:  then it is about the actual policy that gets you to the reward function.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe life is just about.
SPEAKER_1:  constantly updating the reward function.
SPEAKER_0:  I think one of the challenges in life is...
SPEAKER_0:  figuring out exactly what that reward function is. Sometimes
SPEAKER_0:  it's pretty hard to specify. The same way that.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, trying to handcraft the optimal policy in a game like chess is really difficult.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not so clear-cut what the reward function is for.
SPEAKER_0:  life.
SPEAKER_1:  I think one day AI will figure it out.
SPEAKER_1:  And I wonder what that would be.
SPEAKER_1:  Until then.
SPEAKER_1:  I just really appreciate the kind of work you're doing.
SPEAKER_1:  It's really fascinating taking a leap into a more and more real world like.
SPEAKER_1:  problem space.
SPEAKER_1:  and just achieving incredible.
SPEAKER_1:  Results.
SPEAKER_1:  by applying reinforcement learning. Since I saw your work on poker, you've been a constant inspiration.
SPEAKER_1:  It's an honor to get to finally talk to you and this is really fun.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for having me.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with No Brown.
SPEAKER_1:  To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me leave you with some words from Sun Tzu.
SPEAKER_1:  and the art of war.
SPEAKER_1:  The whole secret lies in confusing the enemy.
SPEAKER_1:  so that he cannot fathom.
SPEAKER_1:  our real intent.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for listening.
SPEAKER_1:  Hope to see you.
SPEAKER_1:  next time.