SPEAKER_1:  Do you think he is incompetent, insane, or evil?
SPEAKER_1:  The following is a conversation with Coffeezilla.
SPEAKER_1:  an investigator and journalist exposing frauds, scams, and fake gurus.
SPEAKER_1:  He's one of the most important journalistic voices we have working today.
SPEAKER_1:  both in terms of his integrity and fearlessness in the pursuit of truth.
SPEAKER_1:  Please follow, watch, and support his work.
SPEAKER_1:  at youtube.com slash coffeezilla.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the Lex Friedman Podcast. Thanks for watching.
SPEAKER_1:  please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now, dear friends.
SPEAKER_1:  Here's coffee.
SPEAKER_1:  So long.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you like your coffee?
SPEAKER_1:  Dark and soul crushing.
SPEAKER_1:  That was the number one question on the internet.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you like your coffee to reverberate deeply through the worst of human nature? Is that how you drink your coffee?
SPEAKER_0:  I've gone through a lot of phases on coffee. I used to...
SPEAKER_0:  In college I would go.
SPEAKER_0:  super deep into, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Grinding fresh beans all of that kind of stuff water temperature exactly right
SPEAKER_0:  And then I hit a phase where I was just, it was the maintenance dose.
SPEAKER_0:  Then I went to like espresso because I could get a lot more in.
SPEAKER_0:  And now I go through phases of like, sometimes I like it with a little oat milk.
SPEAKER_0:  Sometimes a little half and half in sugar. Have you got some candle ready just don quantity one minute a day for the
SPEAKER_1:  soft in your old age.
SPEAKER_0:  I've gone a little- I- I have.
SPEAKER_0:  But hey, if I'm doing a SBF interview, it's black that day, nothing less. Yeah. The lights go down.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you actually do in those situations, like leading up to a show, do you get...
SPEAKER_1:  hyped up.
SPEAKER_1:  Like how do you put yourself in the right mind space to explore some of these really difficult topics?
SPEAKER_0:  I think a lot of it's preparation and then once it happens, it's mostly fueled by
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of adrenaline, I would say.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I really deeply care about getting to like.
SPEAKER_0:  the root cause of some of these issues because I think
SPEAKER_0:  So often people in positions of power are led off the hook.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I really care about holding their feet to the fire and it translates into like...
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of energy the day of. So I never find myself like funny enough.
SPEAKER_0:  I usually drink a lot of caffeine leading up to the interview.
SPEAKER_0:  And then I try to drink like minimum the day of because I have so much adrenaline, I don't want to be like.
SPEAKER_0:  hyper stimulated. I have to say.
SPEAKER_1:  of all the recent guests I've had, the energy you had when you walked into the door.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm excited! Are people not excited to be here?
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know. I think they're scared. I think they're scared. I don't know if you know.
SPEAKER_1:  down the door or something you were very excited.
SPEAKER_1:  Like that just energy.
SPEAKER_1:  It was terrifying because I'm terrified of social interaction anyway
SPEAKER_1:  uh... speaking of terry
SPEAKER_0:  You chose a good living of interviewing people.
SPEAKER_1:  Face your fears, my friend.
SPEAKER_1:  So let's talk about SPF and FTX, who is...
SPEAKER_1:  Sam Banquinfried. Can you tell a story?
SPEAKER_1:  from the beginning as you understand it.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so Sam Beckman Fried is...
SPEAKER_0:  A kid who grew up.
SPEAKER_0:  sort of from a position of huge privilege.
SPEAKER_0:  both his parents.
SPEAKER_0:  Our lawyers, I believe both of them were from Harvard.
SPEAKER_0:  He went to MIT, went to like, or sorry, backing up a bit more, went to like this top prep high school.
SPEAKER_0:  then to MIT.
SPEAKER_0:  Then he went to Jane Street. And after that, he started a trading firm in I think 2017 called Alameda Research.
SPEAKER_0:  with a few friends, some of them were from Jane Street, some of them worked at Google.
SPEAKER_0:  and they were sort of the smartest kids on the block.
SPEAKER_0:  or that's what everyone thought.
SPEAKER_0:  They made a lot of their money on something called the kimchi premium, or at least the story goes, which just to explain that.
SPEAKER_0:  The price of Bitcoin in Korea was substantially higher than in the rest of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you could arbitrage that by buying Bitcoin elsewhere and selling it on a Korean exchange.
SPEAKER_0:  They made their money early.
SPEAKER_0:  doing kind of smart trades like that.
SPEAKER_0:  they flipped that into market making, which they were.
SPEAKER_0:  pretty early on that.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  just providing liquidity to an exchange. And it's a strategy that is
SPEAKER_0:  considered delta neutral, which means.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically...
SPEAKER_0:  If you take kind of both sides of the trade.
SPEAKER_0:  and you're making a spread, like a fee on that, you make money whether it goes up or down.
SPEAKER_0:  So in theory, there shouldn't be that much risk associated with it.
SPEAKER_0:  So Alameda kind of blew up.
SPEAKER_0:  because they would offer these people.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, people who are giving out loans, they say, hey, we'll give you this really attractive rate of return and we're doing strategies that seemingly are low risk. So we're a low risk bet.
SPEAKER_0:  We're these smart kids from Jane Street and you can kind of trust us to be.
SPEAKER_0:  smarter than everyone else.
SPEAKER_0:  around 2019.
SPEAKER_0:  Sam started FTX.
SPEAKER_0:  which is...
SPEAKER_0:  and exchange.
SPEAKER_0:  Specifically, it specialized in derivatives, so like margins.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of more sophisticated crypto products.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It got in with Binance early on. So Binance actually has a prior relationship to FTX, which we'll explore in a second because they're gonna play a role in FTX's collapse actually. Binance is the number one crypto exchange.
SPEAKER_0:  And they're led by, uh, he's called CZ on Twitter. I don't want to butcher his full name.
SPEAKER_0:  But really smart guy has.
SPEAKER_0:  played his hand really well and built up a...
SPEAKER_0:  quite large exchange.
SPEAKER_0:  And Binance was funding a bunch of different like startups. So they funded, they helped invest into.
SPEAKER_0:  FTX, early on they invested 100 million.
SPEAKER_0:  So these guys were kind of like teammates early on, SBF and CZ.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  FTX quickly grew. They got like, especially in 2020, 2020.
SPEAKER_0:  21.
SPEAKER_0:  They got a lot of endorsements. They got a lot of credibility in the space.
SPEAKER_0:  And eventually FTX actually bought out Binance. They gave him $2 billion, so...
SPEAKER_0:  pretty good investment for CZ in a couple of years.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And now lead that up to 2022, what happens.
SPEAKER_0:  Luna Collapse.
SPEAKER_0:  three hours capital collapse.
SPEAKER_0:  which if you don't know, there's just these kind of cataclysmic events in crypto.
SPEAKER_0:  led by some pretty risky behavior whether Luna was a token that promised really attractive returns that were unsustainable ultimately and it just kind of spiraled
SPEAKER_0:  It did what's called a stable coin death spiral, which we can talk about if we need to.
SPEAKER_1:  stable coin death spiral. I can't wait.
SPEAKER_1:  till that actually enters the lexicon, like a Wikipedia page on it, like economic students are learning in a school, that's like a chapter in a book. Anyway, I mean, this is the reality of our world, because this is a really big part of our...
SPEAKER_1:  of the economic system.
SPEAKER_1:  is cryptocurrency and stablecoin is part of that.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's weird because on the one hand, cryptocurrency is supposed to somewhat
SPEAKER_0:  simplify or add transparency to the financial markets.
SPEAKER_0:  The idea is for the first time, you don't have to wait for an SEC filing from some corporate business. You can look at what they're doing on chain, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So that's good because a lot of big financial problems are caused by lack of transparency and lack of understanding risk.
SPEAKER_0:  But ironically...
SPEAKER_0:  you get some people creating these arbitrarily complicated.
SPEAKER_0:  financial products like algorithmic stablecoins, which then introduce more risk and blow everything up. So.
SPEAKER_0:  Anyways, Three Arrows Capital blew up.
SPEAKER_0:  and all of a sudden this crypto industry, which everyone thought was going to the moon, went from $100,000 to $100,000.
SPEAKER_0:  is in some trouble.
SPEAKER_0:  and FTX seems like the only people who
SPEAKER_0:  besides like Binance, who's also really big and stable.
SPEAKER_0:  Coinbase. They seemed like they were doing fine. In fact, they were bailing out companies.
SPEAKER_0:  in the summer.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if you remember that. SBF was likened to like Jamie Diamond.
SPEAKER_0:  who's the CEO of Chase.
SPEAKER_0:  who like kind of was like the buck stops here.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... you know
SPEAKER_0:  I'm like the backstop.
SPEAKER_0:  So SPF was supporting the industry. He was like the stable guy.
SPEAKER_0:  So come to like around October and November, there's all this talk about regulation. Everything's been blowing up.
SPEAKER_0:  SBF's leading the charge on regulation.
SPEAKER_0:  And CZ, the CEO of Binance gets word that maybe SBF is kind of like.
SPEAKER_0:  cutting them out or making regulation that would maybe impact this business.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh... he doesn't like that too much
SPEAKER_0:  they start kind of feuding a little bit on Twitter.
SPEAKER_0:  So when it comes out, a CoinDesk report came out that...
SPEAKER_0:  FTX's balance sheet wasn't looking that good. Like it looked pretty weak.
SPEAKER_0:  They had a lot of.
SPEAKER_0:  coins.
SPEAKER_0:  that in theory had value if you looked at their market price.
SPEAKER_0:  but for a
SPEAKER_0:  variety of reasons if you tried to sell them they'd collapse in value. So it's sort of like this thing, a house built on sand.
SPEAKER_0:  and a friend of mine.
SPEAKER_0:  On Twitter, he goes by Dirty Bubble Media. He released a report.
SPEAKER_0:  And he basically said, I think these guys are insolvent.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, CZ saw that.
SPEAKER_0:  and he retweeted it and started adding fuel to the fire of like the speculation.
SPEAKER_0:  Cause up to this point, everyone thought FTX is super safe, super secure. There's no reason to not keep your money there. Tom Brady keeps his money there, whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  And...
SPEAKER_0:  CZ kind of adds fuel to the fire by saying not only.
SPEAKER_0:  Am I retweeting this adding kind of like validity to this speculation?
SPEAKER_0:  but also I'm going to take the FTT that I got.
SPEAKER_0:  which part of their balance sheet was this FTT token, which is
SPEAKER_0:  FTX is like proprietary token.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Alameda and FTX control a lot of it.
SPEAKER_0:  They were using this token to basically be a large amount of collateral for their whole
SPEAKER_0:  balance sheet.
SPEAKER_0:  So it accounted for this huge amount.
SPEAKER_0:  of their value?
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  The CEO of Binance had a huge chunk of it as well, and he said, I'm going to sell all of it.
SPEAKER_0:  and the fuel that that introduced to the market is.
SPEAKER_0:  if he sells all this FTT.
SPEAKER_0:  And this FTT is underwriting a lot of the value of FTX. This FT-
SPEAKER_1:  See you next time.
SPEAKER_1:  almost approximate like similar things if you were to buy a stock
SPEAKER_1:  in a public company.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that kind of like a stock in FTX?
SPEAKER_0:  It sort of was this-
SPEAKER_0:  proxy because
SPEAKER_0:  what FTX was committed to doing was sort of like.
SPEAKER_0:  buying back.
SPEAKER_0:  FTT tokens, they would do this thing called the buy and burn. I think there was some amount of sharing in the
SPEAKER_0:  revenue fees of FTX.
SPEAKER_0:  It was kind of this convoluted thing.
SPEAKER_0:  In my opinion, the exact value of FTT was speculated from the beginning, and it was clear that it was
SPEAKER_0:  Very tied.
SPEAKER_0:  to the performance of FTX.
SPEAKER_0:  which is important because...
SPEAKER_0:  we'll get to later.
SPEAKER_0:  FTX sort of built their whole scaffold.
SPEAKER_0:  on FTT, which meant that this scaffold was very wobbly.
SPEAKER_0:  because.
SPEAKER_0:  FTX loses a little bit of confidence.
SPEAKER_0:  then your value goes down. i parents
SPEAKER_0:  you lose more confidence.
SPEAKER_0:  and this goes down. So it was kind of like this thing that this flywheel that when it was going well.
SPEAKER_0:  You got huge amounts of growth when it's going bad.
SPEAKER_0:  you get a exchange death spiral, so to speak.
SPEAKER_1:  Actually, this structure.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a pretty non-standard structure.
SPEAKER_1:  did the architects of its initial design.
SPEAKER_1:  anticipate the wobbliness of the whole.
SPEAKER_1:  system.
SPEAKER_1:  So putting fraud and all those things that happen later aside, do you think it was?
SPEAKER_1:  difficult to anticipate.
SPEAKER_1:  this kind of FTT, FTX, Alameda research.
SPEAKER_1:  weird dynamic.
SPEAKER_0:  No, because I think...
SPEAKER_0:  sophisticated traders.
SPEAKER_0:  Always think in terms of diversification and correlation.
SPEAKER_0:  So if you're trying to, the way to think about risk in investing is like.
SPEAKER_0:  If I invest in...
SPEAKER_0:  you Lex Friedman and then I also invest in
SPEAKER_0:  some product you produce. The performance of those two things will be pretty correlated.
SPEAKER_0:  So whether I invest in you or I invest in this product that you like are completely behind
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not de-risking, I'm basically counting all on you doing well, right? And if you do bad, my investments do very bad.
SPEAKER_0:  So if I'm trying to build a stable thing, I shouldn't put all my eggs in the Lex Friedman basket.
SPEAKER_0:  unless I'm positive that you're gonna do well, right? And these people...
SPEAKER_1:  financial advisor would definitely recommend you do not put all your eggs in this basket.
SPEAKER_0:  Right. And so you can think about it like if I know that these people were trained to think like this and so the idea that you could start this exchange you're worth billions of dollars.
SPEAKER_0:  and you underwrite your whole system by betting.
SPEAKER_0:  putting most of it on your own token is.
SPEAKER_0:  is insane. And what's crazy-
SPEAKER_0:  is we'll later find out that they were basically taking customer assets, which were real things.
SPEAKER_0:  Bitcoin and Ethereum with
SPEAKER_0:  with risks that were not so correlated to FDX.
SPEAKER_0:  and they were swapping them out. They were using to go basically gamble those.
SPEAKER_0:  and putting FTT.
SPEAKER_0:  in its place as, quote, value.
SPEAKER_0:  So they were increasing the risk of the system in order to bet big.
SPEAKER_0:  with the idea that if they bet big and won, we'd all be singing their praises.
SPEAKER_0:  if we bet big and lost.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if they had a plan, but I think they were being extremely risky and there's no way to avoid.
SPEAKER_0:  their knowledge of that.
SPEAKER_1:  So when you say customer assets is.
SPEAKER_1:  I come to this crypto exchange.
SPEAKER_1:  I have Bitcoin or some other cryptocurrency.
SPEAKER_1:  And this is a.
SPEAKER_1:  A thing that has...
SPEAKER_1:  pretty stable value.
SPEAKER_1:  Over time. I mean, yeah, relatively relatively so. And I'm going to store it.
SPEAKER_1:  on this crypto exchange.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's the whole point. This is a
SPEAKER_1:  So this thing to the degree that crypto holds value.
SPEAKER_1:  is supposed to continue holding value.
SPEAKER_1:  There's not any.
SPEAKER_1:  there's not supposed to be an extra risk inserted into the thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Right. And FTX was pretty clear from the beginning that they wouldn't invest your
SPEAKER_0:  assets and anything else. They wouldn't do anything else with it. They wouldn't trade it.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what made FTX.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  such like a horror story for investor confidence is basically they made every
SPEAKER_0:  Signal.
SPEAKER_0:  that they would not do anything nefarious with your tokens.
SPEAKER_0:  They would just.
SPEAKER_0:  put them into the side, put them in a separate account that they don't have access to, and they just kind of wait there until the day that you're ready to withdraw them.
SPEAKER_0:  That's explicitly what they told their customers.
SPEAKER_0:  So going back to the story a little bit.
SPEAKER_0:  CZ then says, hey, I'm selling this token that underwrites the value of FTX.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a total panic.
SPEAKER_0:  SPF during this time makes set says several lies such as.
SPEAKER_0:  FTX assets are fine.
SPEAKER_0:  We have enough money to cover all withdrawals.
SPEAKER_0:  And a day later, he basically admits that that wasn't the case. They don't have the money, they're shutting down. And then a few days later after that...
SPEAKER_0:  They declared bankruptcy.
SPEAKER_0:  There's, I should be clear, there's Alameda research.
SPEAKER_0:  FTX International and FTX US, which is the US side of things.
SPEAKER_0:  These are three different entities.
SPEAKER_0:  All of them are in bankruptcy.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's not clear to the extent.
SPEAKER_0:  that they were co-mingling funds.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's clear that they were commingling funds to some extent. They kind of were taking from each other.
SPEAKER_0:  And that is where the fraud happens, right? Because
SPEAKER_0:  Going back to our earlier analogy, if you're supposed to set funds aside.
SPEAKER_0:  and I find out you were using it to go make all these arbitrage trades or do market making or all these activities.
SPEAKER_0:  you were known for for your like hedge fund trading firm thing, that's a huge problem because
SPEAKER_0:  He basically lied about this.
SPEAKER_0:  And especially when he's saying explicitly that.
SPEAKER_0:  We have these things, we have these funds, and these things turn out to be lies.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, again, the question of fraud comes in and it's just like...
SPEAKER_0:  There's no way he didn't know.
SPEAKER_0:  So the obvious question might be, well, why isn't he locked up?
SPEAKER_0:  why is he running around? And it's because...
SPEAKER_0:  Really, his story is that he didn't know any of it.
SPEAKER_0:  He found out.
SPEAKER_0:  They had.
SPEAKER_0:  to steal man's position, he would say...
SPEAKER_0:  He was.
SPEAKER_0:  totally disconnected from what Alameda was doing.
SPEAKER_0:  he had no idea that they had such a large margin position.
SPEAKER_0:  that they had an accounting quirk.
SPEAKER_0:  and that accounting quirk hit $8 billion.
SPEAKER_0:  from um...
SPEAKER_0:  his view.
SPEAKER_0:  And so when he was saying that they had money to cover it.
SPEAKER_0:  He was saying that.
SPEAKER_0:  truthfully to the best of his ability, and he just was so distracted at the time that he made a series
SPEAKER_0:  of increasingly embarrassing mistakes.
SPEAKER_0:  And now he owes it to the people.
SPEAKER_0:  to right those wrongs.
SPEAKER_0:  by publicly making this huge apology tour. You might have seen him on.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, he's been talking to nearly everyone.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  about basically how he's just.
SPEAKER_0:  didn't know what he was doing, he's the stupidest man alive.
SPEAKER_1:  So what are some interesting things you've learned from those interviews?
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  I've appreciated why you don't talk in that position. Most people wouldn't talk. Most people would listen to their legal counsel and—
SPEAKER_0:  and not talk, I do not think he's.
SPEAKER_0:  any lawyer worth their salt would tell him to talk because right now...
SPEAKER_0:  I think the danger of what he's doing is he's locking himself into a story.
SPEAKER_0:  of how things.
SPEAKER_0:  happened?
SPEAKER_0:  And I don't think that story is going to hold up in the coming months.
SPEAKER_0:  because I think it's impossible.
SPEAKER_0:  from the insider conversations I've had with Alameda research employees, with FTX employees.
SPEAKER_0:  It's impossible to square.
SPEAKER_0:  what they are telling me.
SPEAKER_0:  with no
SPEAKER_0:  like incentive to lie.
SPEAKER_0:  with what SBF is telling me.
SPEAKER_0:  with every incentive to lie, which is fundamentally
SPEAKER_0:  that he didn't know they were commingling funds. He didn't know they were gambling with customer money.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It was basically this huge mistake and-
SPEAKER_0:  It's Alameda's fault, but he wasn't involved in Alameda, a company here.
SPEAKER_1:  So like a compassionate but heart.
SPEAKER_1:  hidden gangster that you are.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... we saw a very recently you interact with sbf on uh... title a he
SPEAKER_1:  the suspenders as you're saying this.
SPEAKER_1:  You interact on Twitter spaces with SBF.
SPEAKER_1:  and uh...
SPEAKER_1:  really put his feet to the fire.
SPEAKER_1:  with some hard hitting questions.
SPEAKER_1:  What did you ask and what did you learn from that interaction?
SPEAKER_0:  Sure I should save first.
SPEAKER_0:  This was not a willing interaction. I mean, I thought that was kind of the funny part of it because I've been asking him for an interview for a while. He's been giving interviews to nearly everyone who wants one, big channels, small channels.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, he didn't give me one, but I managed to get some by sneaking up on some Twitter spaces and DMing the people and like being like, Hey, can I come up?
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't get him to ask everything that I wanted because he like would leave sometimes.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... you know after i asked some of the questions but
SPEAKER_0:  Really, what I asked was about this 8 billion and...
SPEAKER_0:  Zooming in on the improbability
SPEAKER_0:  of his lack of knowledge.
SPEAKER_0:  It's sort of like if you run a company and you know...
SPEAKER_0:  the insides and outs, and you're the top.
SPEAKER_0:  of your field.
SPEAKER_0:  Top in class.
SPEAKER_0:  and all of a sudden it all goes bust and you say, I had no idea how any of this works.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't know, it's like the guy who runs Water Burger saying, I didn't know where we sourced our beef. I didn't know where we, that's a Texas example actually. Thank you, I appreciate that. Let's take it like worldwide, Walmart, like.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't know we used Chinese manufacturers. It's like, that's impossible.
SPEAKER_0:  to become Walmart, you have to know.
SPEAKER_0:  how your supply chain works. You have to know, even if you're at a high level, you know how this stuff works.
SPEAKER_1:  Can I do a hard turn on that and go as one must to Hitler?
SPEAKER_1:  Hitler's writing is not on any of the documents around as far as I know.
SPEAKER_1:  on the final solution.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  in some crazy world.
SPEAKER_1:  He could theoretically say, I knew.
SPEAKER_1:  I didn't know anything about death camps.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  So there's this plausible deniability.
SPEAKER_1:  in theory.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  That's, but that most people would look at that and say.
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh
SPEAKER_1:  It's very unlikely, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  No. Especially if all the insiders are coming out and saying, no, no, no, of course he knew. He was directing us from the top.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, um...
SPEAKER_0:  What was clear, what's interesting about the structure and like, I love the nitty-gritty. We're back to SPF.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, sorry. We went to Hitler, now we're back to the SBL. I wanted to turn us as fast as possible away from Hitler. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Bye!
SPEAKER_1:  So the insiders in what I'll make.
SPEAKER_0:  Alameda research. What was interesting...
SPEAKER_0:  is that there was this sort of one-way window going on.
SPEAKER_0:  between Alameda?
SPEAKER_0:  and FTX, where FTX employees didn't know a lot of what was going on.
SPEAKER_0:  Alameda insiders.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say by design.
SPEAKER_0:  knew almost everything that was going on at FTX.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  So I think that was really interesting from the perspective of a lot of.
SPEAKER_0:  the so-called, like what you could, what he's trying to ascribe to as like.
SPEAKER_0:  failures or mistakes or ignorance and negligence.
SPEAKER_0:  When looked at closely,
SPEAKER_0:  are much more designed.
SPEAKER_0:  and they sort of don't arise spontaneously.
SPEAKER_0:  Because like, let's say, so there's this thing in banking and like trading where
SPEAKER_0:  If I run a bank and you run like a trading firm, we need to have informational walls between us because there's huge conflicts of interest that can arise.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  So the negligent argument might be that like.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, we just didn't know. We're sort of these dumb kids in the Bahamas. So we shared information equally.
SPEAKER_0:  But when you see a one-way wall, that starts to look a lot different, right? If I have a backend source of looking at, or sorry, you're the trading firm, so you have a backend way to look at all my accounts.
SPEAKER_0:  and I have no idea that you're doing that.
SPEAKER_0:  that all of a sudden looks like a much more designed thing.
SPEAKER_0:  It would be plausible, let's say, going to use another analogy too.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're saying, look, I co-mingled funds because I was so bad at corporate structures.
SPEAKER_0:  you'd expect.
SPEAKER_0:  those companies to have a very.
SPEAKER_0:  simple corporate structure because you didn't know what you're doing, right?
SPEAKER_0:  But what we see with FTX and Alameda.
SPEAKER_0:  is they had something like
SPEAKER_0:  50 companies and subsidiaries and it's inc...
SPEAKER_0:  impossibly complicated web.
SPEAKER_0:  of corporate activity.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't get there by accident.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't wake up and go, oh, I designed like this watch that ticked a very specific way, but it was all accidental.
SPEAKER_0:  If you really didn't know what you were doing, you'd end up with a simple structure.
SPEAKER_0:  So even just like from a fundamental perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  what SBF was doing and like the activities they were engaging in.
SPEAKER_0:  We're so complicated and-
SPEAKER_0:  purposely designed to obfuscate what they were doing, it's impossible to subscribe to the negligence.
SPEAKER_0:  argument.
SPEAKER_0:  And I wanna quickly say too, like...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think a lot of people have honed in on this. There was insider trading going on.
SPEAKER_0:  from Alameda's perspective, where...
SPEAKER_0:  they would know what coins FTX was going to list on their exchange.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a famous effect where.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's say you're this legitimate exchange. You list a coin, the price spikes.
SPEAKER_0:  Insiders told me it was a regular practice for Alameda insiders.
SPEAKER_0:  to know that FTX was going to list a coin.
SPEAKER_0:  and as a company buy up that coin.
SPEAKER_0:  so they could sell it after it listed.
SPEAKER_0:  and they made millions of dollars. How do you do that accidentally?
SPEAKER_1:  And that's.
SPEAKER_1:  That's illegal.
SPEAKER_0:  Totally illegal.
SPEAKER_0:  That's illegal from like, and if an individual does it, it's illegal, it's fraud.
SPEAKER_0:  What if a company is systematically doing it?
SPEAKER_0:  And you can't tell me that FTX.
SPEAKER_0:  or somewhat at FTX wasn't feeding that information about.
SPEAKER_0:  to Alameda.
SPEAKER_0:  or somehow giving them.
SPEAKER_0:  to know that. And that would happen at the highest level. It would happen at SPS level. And this is why his arguments of...
SPEAKER_0:  I was dumb, I was naive, I was sort of ignorant.
SPEAKER_0:  are so preposterous because he's dumb and ignorant the second it becomes criminal to be smart and sophisticated, right?
SPEAKER_1:  but then also coming out and talking about it, which is...
SPEAKER_1:  That's a bizarre move. That's a bizarre move.
SPEAKER_1:  almost a dark move.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you tell the story of the 8 billion? You mentioned 8 billion. What's the 8 billion? What's the missing 8 billion? Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So
SPEAKER_0:  It's really interesting because it's sort of like wire fraud. You sort of-
SPEAKER_0:  He's sort of copping to like smaller crimes to avoid the big crime. The big crime is you knew everything and you were behind it, right?
SPEAKER_0:  The smaller crimes are like a little wire fraud here, little wire fraud there. So what the 8 billion is.
SPEAKER_0:  is that FTX didn't always have banking. It's hard to get banking as a crypto exchange. There's all these questions of like, where's the money coming from? Is it coming from money launderer?
SPEAKER_0:  For a variety of reasons, it's always been hard for exchanges to get bank accounts. So before...
SPEAKER_0:  when FTX was just getting started, they didn't have a bank account. So how do you put money on FTX? Well.
SPEAKER_0:  they would have you wire your money to their trading firm.
SPEAKER_0:  their wiring instructions would go to their trading firm, it's easier to get banking as a trading firm.
SPEAKER_0:  So you'd put your money with the trading firm and then they'd credit you the money.
SPEAKER_0:  on FTX.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, first of all, this is a whole circumvention of all these banking guidelines and regulations.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the first like.
SPEAKER_0:  that I think is legal, but...
SPEAKER_0:  basically what SPF argued.
SPEAKER_0:  is that.
SPEAKER_0:  There was an accounting.
SPEAKER_0:  glitch error problem.
SPEAKER_0:  where when you'd send money to Alameda.
SPEAKER_0:  even though they'd credit you on FTX.
SPEAKER_0:  They wouldn't safeguard your deposits. Like your deposits would go into what he called a stub account.
SPEAKER_0:  which is just like some.
SPEAKER_0:  account that's not very well labeled.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of like a placeholder account.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  he didn't realize that those were Alameda's funds or they were playing with those funds.
SPEAKER_0:  and that they basically should have safeguarded that for customers. That's his explanation.
SPEAKER_0:  It's preposterous because it's $8 billion, but anyways.
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Just poor labeling of accounts.
SPEAKER_0:  of an eight billion dollar account.
SPEAKER_1:  What's a billion between... A billion between...
SPEAKER_0:  This is like what- I do this all the time in programming. This is the craziest thing. Like he was talking to me and at one point in the conversation, he's like-
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I didn't have precise, because he said I didn't have knowledge of Alameda.
SPEAKER_0:  And I said, well, Forbes a month ago was getting detailed accounting of Alameda.
SPEAKER_0:  And he goes, oh.
SPEAKER_0:  That wasn't detailed accounting. I just knew I was right within 10 billion or so.
SPEAKER_0:  What is that error margin? $10 Billion?
SPEAKER_0:  for a company that is arguably never worth more than 100 million.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably never even worth more than 50 billion.
SPEAKER_0:  Your error margin is $10 billion. You have to be, this is a guy who is sending around $10 billion.
SPEAKER_0:  statements that like there was no risk involved.
SPEAKER_0:  And you're telling me he had a...
SPEAKER_0:  error margin of $10 billion, that is the difference between a healthy company and a company so deep underwater you're going to jail.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to believe.
SPEAKER_0:  that he is impossibly stupid.
SPEAKER_0:  and square that with the sophistication that he brought to the table. I think it's an impossible argument. I don't even think it's...
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think he is incompetent, insane, or evil?
SPEAKER_1:  if you were to bet.
SPEAKER_1:  money on each of those.
SPEAKER_0:  Incompetent, insane, or evil.
SPEAKER_1:  Insane meaning he's lying.
SPEAKER_1:  to everyone but also to himself.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  which you could.
SPEAKER_1:  which is a little bit different than incompetence.
SPEAKER_0:  He's not incompetent.
SPEAKER_0:  So the, I think he's some combination of insane and evil.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's impossible to know unless we know deep inside his heart.
SPEAKER_0:  How?
SPEAKER_0:  self.
SPEAKER_0:  like diluted he is.
SPEAKER_0:  versus a calculated strategy.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think if you look at SBF, he's such a...
SPEAKER_0:  I think he's a fascinating individual.
SPEAKER_0:  Just, I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, he's a horrible human being. Let's start there.
SPEAKER_0:  but he's also.
SPEAKER_0:  somewhat. Uma Gata
SPEAKER_0:  interesting from a psychology perspective because
SPEAKER_0:  He's very open about the fact that he...
SPEAKER_0:  understands image.
SPEAKER_0:  and he understands how to.
SPEAKER_0:  cultivate image, the importance of image.
SPEAKER_0:  so well.
SPEAKER_0:  that I think a lot of people, even though they've talked about it.
SPEAKER_0:  emphasizing that enough.
SPEAKER_0:  when interacting with him. This is a man whose entire history.
SPEAKER_0:  is about.
SPEAKER_0:  Cultivating the right opinions at the right time to achieve the right effect
SPEAKER_0:  Why do you think he would suddenly change that approach?
SPEAKER_0:  when he has all the more reason to cultivate an image.
SPEAKER_1:  So he is...
SPEAKER_1:  extremely good naturally or
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if he's good, but he's like, he's a hyper aware.
SPEAKER_1:  So he's deliberate in cultivating a public image and controlling the public image.
SPEAKER_0:  You know about the like Democrat donations. Like he he knew to donate to the right people forty million dollars.
SPEAKER_0:  He says on a call that we released with Tiffany Fong.
SPEAKER_0:  He says on a call that.
SPEAKER_0:  He donated the same amount to Republicans. There's speculation on whether this is true because he's a liar or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  So, caveat there. But he said he donated to Republicans the same amount.
SPEAKER_0:  but he donated dark.
SPEAKER_0:  because he knew.
SPEAKER_0:  most journalists are liberal and they would kind of hold that against him.
SPEAKER_0:  So he wanted all the...
SPEAKER_0:  all the sides to be on in his favor in his pocket.
SPEAKER_0:  while simultaneously understanding the entire media landscape.
SPEAKER_0:  and playing them like a fiddle.
SPEAKER_0:  cultivating this image of I'm this progressive woke.
SPEAKER_0:  billionaire who wants to give it all away.
SPEAKER_0:  I do everything for charity. I drive a Corolla while living in a million dollar print house, multi-million.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  But that was sort of the angle. He understood so well how to play the media.
SPEAKER_0:  and um...
SPEAKER_0:  I think he underestimated when he did this.
SPEAKER_0:  how much people would.
SPEAKER_0:  put him under a deeper microscope?
SPEAKER_0:  and I don't think he has achieved.
SPEAKER_0:  the same level of success.
SPEAKER_0:  in cultivating this new image, because I think people are so skeptical now, no one's buying it.
SPEAKER_0:  But I think he's trying it, he's doing it to the best of his ability.
SPEAKER_1:  has work leading up to this particular.
SPEAKER_1:  wobbly situation.
SPEAKER_1:  So before that, wasn't there a public perception of him being?
SPEAKER_1:  force for good, a financial force for good.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah
SPEAKER_0:  Somebody from Sequoia Capital, you know, wrote this glowing review that he's gonna be the world's first trillionaire. There's so many pieces done on he's the most generous billionaire in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  That um
SPEAKER_0:  He was sort of like.
SPEAKER_0:  The...
SPEAKER_0:  steel man of, you know, it's possible to make tons of money.
SPEAKER_0:  This is like the effect of altruism movement. Make as much money as you can, as fast as you can, and give it all away.
SPEAKER_0:  And he was sort of like the poster child for that.
SPEAKER_0:  and he did give some of it away and got a lot of press for it.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think that was kind of by design. I want to address a real quick point.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of people have said that like finance played a role.
SPEAKER_0:  And while they catalyzed this...
SPEAKER_0:  insolvency.
SPEAKER_0:  is a problem that will eventually manifest either way.
SPEAKER_0:  So I don't put any blame on CZ for...
SPEAKER_0:  basically causing this.
SPEAKER_0:  meltdown.
SPEAKER_0:  the underlying foundation was unstable and it was gonna fall apart at the next push. I mean, he just happened to be the final.
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of like.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, the straw that broke the camel's back. The meet and greet.
SPEAKER_1:  That was the review.
SPEAKER_0:  But yeah, but it's like I don't I don't think he's culpable for FTX is like malfeasance and how they handled
SPEAKER_0:  Accounts if that makes sense. So what?
SPEAKER_1:  What role?
SPEAKER_1:  Did they play? Could they have help?
SPEAKER_1:  alleviate some of the pain of
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  investors.
SPEAKER_1:  of people that held funds there.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  Probably.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, I would see some kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  weird
SPEAKER_0:  obligation like with the two billion they made.
SPEAKER_0:  on FTX. Remember they got two billion, some of it in cash, some of it in-
SPEAKER_0:  some of it in FTT tokens. I don't know how much actual cash they have from that deal.
SPEAKER_0:  But they have billions from the success of what seems to be a fraud, seems to have been a fraud from early on. They had the back door.
SPEAKER_0:  as
SPEAKER_0:  early as 20, early 2020 from what I can tell. So the
SPEAKER_1:  the back door between FTX and Alameda. Alameda, yes. Alameda research. Yes. Do you think CZ saw?
SPEAKER_1:  who SPF is.
SPEAKER_1:  What is he doing?
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  I think
SPEAKER_0:  I think CZ is like, he's a shark. I think he's good at building a big business.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Like a good truck or a bad truck?
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know. I think sharks just eat. I mean, I don't
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, I think...
SPEAKER_1:  My relationship with shark has like a finding Nemo. There's a shark in that.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know. Like Jeff Bezos is a shark.
SPEAKER_0:  So whether people have loaded connotations of like.
SPEAKER_0:  how they feel about Jeff Bezos.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I would say like, I think CZ is a ruthless businessman.
SPEAKER_0:  I think he's cold, he's calculated, he's very...
SPEAKER_0:  deliberate and
SPEAKER_0:  I think what he should do in this position is forfeit the funds that he profited from that investment.
SPEAKER_0:  because largely I think it was.
SPEAKER_0:  It's owed to the customers. There's so much hurting out there. So I think they could do a lot of good around that.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, I don't know if they will.
SPEAKER_0:  because I don't know if he sees it in his best interest. I think that's probably how he's thinking.
SPEAKER_0:  but...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think they could have.
SPEAKER_0:  or if they s-
SPEAKER_1:  could still help there. Who do you think suffered the most?
SPEAKER_1:  so far.
SPEAKER_0:  the little account holders, this is always true.
SPEAKER_0:  So one of the big temptations with fraud.
SPEAKER_0:  covered a lot of scams, frauds.
SPEAKER_0:  is everyone looks at the big number.
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone, that's the headline.
SPEAKER_0:  billions of dollars, the top 50 creditors, or whatever one thinks at first.
SPEAKER_0:  But quickly when you dig down, you realize that most people who lost $10 million, I mean, I'm sure that's terrible for them I wish them to get their money back, but...
SPEAKER_0:  It's usually the people with like...
SPEAKER_0:  50,000 or less that are most impacted. Usually they do not have the money.
SPEAKER_0:  to spare, usually they're not diversified in a sophisticated way.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  So I think it's those people, I think it's the small account holders that I feel the worst for, and unfortunately they often get the least.
SPEAKER_0:  press time or air time.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the really difficult truth of this is that especially in the culture of cryptocurrency this
SPEAKER_1:  a lot of young people who are.
SPEAKER_1:  not diversified their...
SPEAKER_1:  basically all in on a particular crypto.
SPEAKER_1:  and it just breaks my heart to think that there's somebody with 50,000 or 30,000 or 20,000, but the point is that money.
SPEAKER_1:  is everything they own.
SPEAKER_1:  And now...
SPEAKER_1:  Now what? This level has aimm carbohydrate bar, but was fats up Intra- 101e3 specific limit.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, you know, imagine you're 18, 19, 20, 21 years old.
SPEAKER_1:  You saved up, you've been working, you saved up.
SPEAKER_1:  And this is basically destroying a life.
SPEAKER_0:  What's so brutal about this is that.
SPEAKER_0:  This all comes on the back, the entire crypto market.
SPEAKER_0:  comes on the back of.
SPEAKER_0:  comes from the deepest distrust of traditional finance.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, yeah, 2008.
SPEAKER_0:  Everybody lost trust in the banking systems.
SPEAKER_0:  and they lost trust.
SPEAKER_0:  that if those banking systems acted in a corrupt way.
SPEAKER_0:  they would receive the justice. It turned out that the banks received favorable treatment. People didn't.
SPEAKER_0:  So people.
SPEAKER_0:  lost faith in the...
SPEAKER_0:  the structure of our financial system in a way that we're still feeling the reverberations of it.
SPEAKER_0:  And so when crypto came along, it was like kind of this way to reinvent the wheel.
SPEAKER_0:  reinvent the world.
SPEAKER_0:  for the.
SPEAKER_0:  the sort of lowly and the less powerful.
SPEAKER_0:  and kind of level the playing field.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's so sad about events like this.
SPEAKER_0:  is you see that.
SPEAKER_0:  fundamentally a lot of the
SPEAKER_0:  the power structures are the same where the people at the top.
SPEAKER_0:  face little repercussions for what they do. The people at the bottom are still getting screwed.
SPEAKER_0:  people at the bottom are still getting lied to.
SPEAKER_0:  and law enforcement is way behind the ball.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think this really...
SPEAKER_1:  damaged people trust in cryptocurrency. For sure.
SPEAKER_0:  way bigger than Luna, way bigger than Three Arrows Capital.
SPEAKER_0:  It's because of who SBF was. It's not just the dollar figure behind it.
SPEAKER_0:  It's because he wooed so many of our media elites who should have been
SPEAKER_0:  calling him out.
SPEAKER_0:  or at least investigating him and not rubber stamping him.
SPEAKER_0:  It's an indictment of our financial system, even our most sophisticated people in BlackRock, in Sequoia, who didn't see this coming, who also rubber stamped him.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and you just wonder like if you can't trust.
SPEAKER_0:  the top people in crypto who are supposedly.
SPEAKER_0:  the good guys, the guys saving crypto.
SPEAKER_0:  month, just a month ago or two months ago.
SPEAKER_0:  He was the guy on Capitol Hill that was talking to Gary Gensler to all the top people in Washington. He was orchestrating the regulation of crypto. With that guy...
SPEAKER_0:  is a complete fraudster, liar, psychopath, and nobody knew it until it was too late.
SPEAKER_0:  What does that mean about the system itself that we're building?
SPEAKER_1:  So you are one of not the best.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, fraudster.
SPEAKER_1:  investigators in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  Did you sense, was this on your radar at all, SBF in the?
SPEAKER_1:  over the past couple years.
SPEAKER_1:  Were any red flags going off for you? Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  Funny enough, like...
SPEAKER_0:  one of my videos from six months ago or so.
SPEAKER_0:  blew up because, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I gotta give a lot of credit to Matt Levine of Bloomberg, great journalist, great finance journalist.
SPEAKER_0:  And I want to say when I like talk about Media Elite.
SPEAKER_0:  people doing great work.
SPEAKER_0:  in these mainstream institutions. It's not a monolith. Just like independent media isn't all doing great work and all the corporate media is bad or whatever. There's like these overarching narratives that I don't subscribe to.
SPEAKER_0:  So Matt Levine's a great journalist. He did an interview with SBF where-
SPEAKER_0:  He got.
SPEAKER_0:  Sam to basically describe a lot of what was going on in DeFi.
SPEAKER_0:  but it kind of a larger philosophy around crypto.
SPEAKER_0:  He described a Ponzi scheme.
SPEAKER_0:  where you just described this black box, it does nothing.
SPEAKER_0:  But if we ascribe it value, then we can create more value and more value and more value. And it kind of was this ridiculous description of a Ponzi scheme, but there was no moral judgment on it. It was like, oh yeah, this is great. We can make a lot of money.
SPEAKER_0:  And Matt is like, well, it sounds like you're in the Ponzi business and business is good.
SPEAKER_0:  I made a video about that. I said, this is ridiculous, this is absurd, whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  obscene.
SPEAKER_0:  um
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't explicitly call SPF a fraud there.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think if I'm being...
SPEAKER_0:  I think I saw some of it.
SPEAKER_0:  but.
SPEAKER_0:  like many people.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of us were kind of like.
SPEAKER_0:  I think a lot of us missed.
SPEAKER_0:  How wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  everyone could be at the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  I did notice leading up to the crash.
SPEAKER_0:  what was happening and I caught it out a day or a day and a half before it happened.
SPEAKER_0:  because I saw my friends post a dirty bubble media.
SPEAKER_0:  And this was the first real look into the heart of their finances, because they're this black box.
SPEAKER_0:  You just kind of had to evaluate them.
SPEAKER_0:  without knowing much.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Once we got a peek under the hood of what their finances were...
SPEAKER_0:  I realized, oh my gosh, these guys might be completely insolvent, so I made a tweet about it.
SPEAKER_0:  I hope some people saw it and got their money out.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  But pretty quickly after that, I...
SPEAKER_0:  taught the narrative of what was really going on at Alameda.
SPEAKER_0:  that it was basically this.
SPEAKER_0:  the ponzi scheme that they had built.
SPEAKER_1:  sit like Batman in the dark since he fight crime.
SPEAKER_1:  and wonder.
SPEAKER_1:  like sad just staring into the darkness and thinking I should have caught this earlier.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I think...
SPEAKER_1:  in your in your
SPEAKER_1:  uh... ten billion dollars to ten million dollars ten million dollars we're working our way there
SPEAKER_1:  Um... wut wut who borr 55 finish
SPEAKER_0:  Sure, like, it's never enough. It's never enough.
SPEAKER_0:  Like you always could be catching stuff sooner.
SPEAKER_0:  You always could be doing more.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, the fascinating thing you said is that.
SPEAKER_1:  One of the lessons here is.
SPEAKER_1:  that a large number of people
SPEAKER_1:  influential smart people could all be wrong at the same time.
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of their.
SPEAKER_1:  Evaluation of SBF.
SPEAKER_1:  This is-
SPEAKER_0:  This is one thing that I don't understand too, is like...
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's one thing to not see something.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's another thing to like rubber stamp or explicitly endorse.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of people didn't look too close at SBF because I think...
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of the warning signs were there.
SPEAKER_0:  But my feeling is, if you're a Sequoia, if you're a Black Rock...
SPEAKER_0:  Wouldn't you do that due diligence? I mean like-
SPEAKER_0:  Like before just endorsing something
SPEAKER_0:  especially in the crypto space. This is just why I don't do any deals in the crypto space ever.
SPEAKER_0:  because it's impossible to know which ones are going to be the like.
SPEAKER_0:  big hits or the big frauds or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you're gonna make that bet, if you're gonna make that play,
SPEAKER_0:  You would think...
SPEAKER_0:  that you would do all the research in the world and you would get sophisticated looks.
SPEAKER_0:  at their liabilities, at how they were structured.
SPEAKER_0:  All that stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  And that is the most shocking part.
SPEAKER_0:  is not that.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, people missed it because you can miss fraud.
SPEAKER_0:  but that there were so much.
SPEAKER_0:  So many glowing endorsements like, this guy is not gonna be that thing. We explicitly endorse him. I saw a Fortune magazine. He was called the next Warren Buffett.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just crazy.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think it's possible to have enough like Tom Brady?
SPEAKER_1:  endorsements that you don't really investigate. So like, there's a kind of momentum, like societal social momentum.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's the problem.
SPEAKER_0:  I actually think that's hugely.
SPEAKER_0:  a blinds like a
SPEAKER_0:  a blind spot of our society as we have all these.
SPEAKER_0:  Heuristics?
SPEAKER_0:  that can be...
SPEAKER_0:  points of failure.
SPEAKER_0:  where like
SPEAKER_0:  A rule of thumb is if you go to an Ivy League, well, you must be smart.
SPEAKER_0:  A rule of thumb is if you're both your parents or Harvard lawyers, you must know the law. You must, like, kind of be sophisticated.
SPEAKER_0:  The rule of thumb is if you're running a billion dollar exchange, you must be somehow somewhat ethical, right?
SPEAKER_0:  And all of these heuristics can lead to giant blind spots where
SPEAKER_0:  you kind of just go, oh, we'll check. Like I don't really, it's a lot of energy to look into people.
SPEAKER_0:  And if enough of those rules of thumb are met, we just kind of check them off and put them through the system. So...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's been hugely exposing for sort of like
SPEAKER_1:  And you don't know wha-
SPEAKER_1:  maybe hard to look at, for example, there's a few assumptions.
SPEAKER_1:  Now there's a lot of people are very skeptical of institutions of government and so on, but for, um,
SPEAKER_1:  Perhaps.
SPEAKER_1:  too much so I agree but for some part of history
SPEAKER_1:  There was a...
SPEAKER_1:  too much faith in government.
SPEAKER_1:  So right now I think there's faith in certain large companies.
SPEAKER_1:  There's distrust in certain ones and...
SPEAKER_1:  trust in others. Like people seem to distrust Facebook.
SPEAKER_1:  extremely skeptical of Facebook.
SPEAKER_1:  but they trust.
SPEAKER_1:  I think Google with their data?
SPEAKER_1:  I think they trust Apple with their data, much more so.
SPEAKER_1:  Search.
SPEAKER_1:  People don't seem to be Google search like.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm just gonna, I'm gonna put... Throw it in there. Have you ever looked at your Google search history? Your Google search history has gotta be some of the darkest things. Oh!
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think I've ever looked at my Google search history. You should. I mean it's full with like
SPEAKER_0:  browser hygiene and
SPEAKER_0:  uh... stuff like that because i think it's
SPEAKER_1:  Well, Google search history, unless you explicitly delete is there. I recommend you look at it. It's fascinating. Look because it goes back to.
SPEAKER_1:  the first days of you using Google search history.
SPEAKER_0:  Fun fact actually about that. No, no, no, I am aware of that. I just mean for like
SPEAKER_0:  certain sensitive topics where like, I'm investigating some fraud and I go sign into their website, right? So I log in and secure that iodine.
SPEAKER_0:  I won't use a traditional browser, I'll use a VPN and I'll put it on Brave or something like that.
SPEAKER_1:  You log in, you create an account is Lex Friedman.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, exactly. Exactly. Exactly. You mentioned effective altruism.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  you know as the others been associated with this effect of altruism
SPEAKER_1:  which made me look twice at
SPEAKER_1:  EA.
SPEAKER_1:  see like wait
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  I ID what's.
SPEAKER_1:  What's going on here?
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, is this, was this used by SBF to give himself a good public image or
SPEAKER_1:  Is there something about effective altruism that makes it easy to misuse?
SPEAKER_1:  by bad people.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's interesting. He could have endorsed a wide range of philosophies, and I guess you just have to wonder.
SPEAKER_0:  Are all those, would those philosophies also be tainted if...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  he had gone bad.
SPEAKER_0:  I guess Effective Altruism is sort of unique because he used it as part of his brand.
SPEAKER_0:  It wasn't like he described himself as a consequentialist and like
SPEAKER_0:  ended up mattering.
SPEAKER_0:  It was like.
SPEAKER_0:  He described himself as an effective altruist, and he used that part of the brand to lift himself up. I guess that's why it's getting so much scrutiny.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the merits of it
SPEAKER_0:  should speak for themselves. I mean, I don't personally, I'm not personally an effective altruist.
SPEAKER_0:  um...
SPEAKER_0:  I personally am motivated by giving in part emotionally.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  for some reason that I can't exactly describe.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's somewhat important. I don't think you should detach giving.
SPEAKER_0:  from some personal connection.
SPEAKER_0:  I find trouble with that.
SPEAKER_0:  And like I said, it's for reasons I can't describe because effective altruism is sort of the most
SPEAKER_0:  logical ivory tower position you could possibly take. It's like, strip all humanity away from giving, let's treat it like a business, and how many people can we serve through the McDonald's line of charity?
SPEAKER_0:  for like the dollar.
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I just personally don't resonate with that.
SPEAKER_0:  but I don't think the entire movement.
SPEAKER_0:  is like.
SPEAKER_0:  indicted because of it.
SPEAKER_0:  typically most people who
SPEAKER_0:  care about.
SPEAKER_0:  giving and charity.
SPEAKER_0:  On the whole.
SPEAKER_0:  are nice people.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I can't speak for the whole movement. I certainly don't think SBF indicts the whole movement, even though I personally don't subscribe to it.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it made me pause.
SPEAKER_1:  reflect and step back like.
SPEAKER_1:  about the movement and about anything.
SPEAKER_1:  that has a strong ideology. So if there's anything in your life.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a strong.
SPEAKER_1:  set of ideas behind it, be careful.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, look-
SPEAKER_0:  I kinda feel like.
SPEAKER_0:  teaches me and what I kind of think about.
SPEAKER_0:  when I think about systems.
SPEAKER_0:  is that no system saves you from the individual.
SPEAKER_0:  No system saves you from the individual.
SPEAKER_0:  their intentions.
SPEAKER_0:  their
SPEAKER_0:  their lust for power or greed.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  I think one of the great ideas.
SPEAKER_0:  is the decentralization.
SPEAKER_0:  of power and like this is why.
SPEAKER_0:  I think democracies are so great is because they decentralize.
SPEAKER_0:  power.
SPEAKER_0:  across a wide range of
SPEAKER_0:  like interests and groups.
SPEAKER_0:  and that being an effective way to kind of
SPEAKER_0:  try as best as you can.
SPEAKER_0:  to spread out the impact of one individual.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  One bad individual can do a lot of harm.
SPEAKER_0:  as clearly as seen here.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  Now I don't think it has anything to do with ideology because it's not like being an effective altruist.
SPEAKER_0:  made Sam Bankman free to fraud.
SPEAKER_0:  He was a fraud who happened to be an effective altruist. Lord has power.
SPEAKER_1:  sense. So there is something about yes no system protects you from an individual by some system.
SPEAKER_1:  enable or service.
SPEAKER_1:  better catalyst than others for
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  for the worst aspects of human nature.
SPEAKER_1:  So for example, communist ideology.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if it's the ideology or its implementation in the...
SPEAKER_1:  in the 20th century.
SPEAKER_1:  It seemed like such a sexy and
SPEAKER_1:  powerful and viral ideology that it somehow allows
SPEAKER_1:  the evil bad people to like sneak into the very top.
SPEAKER_1:  And so like, that's what I mean about certain ideas Sounds so nice
SPEAKER_1:  that allow you, like the lower classes, the workers, the people that do all the work, they should have power.
SPEAKER_1:  They have been screwed over for far too long. They need to take power back.
SPEAKER_1:  That sounds like a really powerful idea.
SPEAKER_1:  And then it just seems like with those powerful ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  Evil people sneak in.
SPEAKER_1:  to the top and start to abuse that power.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I don't have a lot of.
SPEAKER_0:  probably big brain political takes.
SPEAKER_0:  But what I can say is that you can never get away from both the system and the individual mattering.
SPEAKER_0:  For sure.
SPEAKER_0:  Some systems incentivize some behaviors in certain ways.
SPEAKER_0:  But some people will take that and go, okay, all we need to do is design the perfect system and then these individuals will act.
SPEAKER_0:  completely rationally or responsibly.
SPEAKER_0:  in accordance to what our incentives say. That's not true.
SPEAKER_0:  You could also say all we have to do is focus on the individual.
SPEAKER_0:  And all we have to do is just create a society which raises very well adjusted people, and then we can throw them into any system with any incentives, and they will act like responsibly, ethically, morally, and I also don't think that's true.
SPEAKER_0:  So incentives are real, but also.
SPEAKER_0:  the individual ultimately plays a large role too. So yeah, I don't know. I come down sort of in the middle there.
SPEAKER_1:  and some of.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just accidents of history too. Which individual finds which system.
SPEAKER_1:  You know. Come the face of that.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, with FTX versus Coinbase versus...
SPEAKER_1:  Binance.
SPEAKER_1:  or which individual, which kinds of ideas and.
SPEAKER_1:  life story
SPEAKER_1:  come to power.
SPEAKER_1:  things that that matters it's kind of fascinating.
SPEAKER_1:  that history turns on these small little events.
SPEAKER_1:  Bye bye.
SPEAKER_1:  small little individuals.
SPEAKER_1:  that Hitler's a failed artist or you have FDR or you have.
SPEAKER_1:  all these different characters that do good or do evil onto the world. And it's like single individuals and they have a life story.
SPEAKER_1:  and it could have turned out completely different.
SPEAKER_1:  It's the flap of the butterfly wings.
SPEAKER_1:  So yeah, you're right, we should.
SPEAKER_1:  be skeptical as attributing too much to the system or the individual.
SPEAKER_1:  It's all like a beautiful mess.
SPEAKER_0:  That's like a that was like a Lex line. I've heard I've heard quite a few episodes and that's like such a Lex line It's a beautiful man. All right, beautifully said. All right. I'm a fan
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, okay, alright, I love you too.
SPEAKER_1:  Alright
SPEAKER_1:  Can you think of possible trajectories how this...
SPEAKER_1:  FTX SBF Saga ends.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  And which one do you hope for?
SPEAKER_1:  Do you hope that SPF goes to jail?
SPEAKER_1:  that's the individual and in terms of the investors and the customers, what do you hope happens and what do you think are the possible things that can happen?
SPEAKER_0:  So A, yeah, I definitely think SPF.
SPEAKER_0:  should go to jail.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  for nothing else, for a semblance of justice.
SPEAKER_0:  facsimile of justice to occur for all the investors.
SPEAKER_0:  I also think there are people probably...
SPEAKER_0:  several
SPEAKER_0:  steps down the chain that probably knew, at least Caroline Ellison.
SPEAKER_0:  you can have questions about sort of their.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, Dan Friedberg, who I'd love to talk about as well.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, there were a lot of people in that room who I think knew, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  We do so much of like.
SPEAKER_0:  The one guy is all to blame. Let's throw everything at him.
SPEAKER_0:  when clearly this was a
SPEAKER_0:  company.
SPEAKER_0:  wide issue.
SPEAKER_0:  So everyone who knew, I think should face...
SPEAKER_0:  the same punishment, which I think should be jail for all of those people.
SPEAKER_0:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  in part to send a signal to anybody that tries this kind of stuff in the future.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, absolutely. I mean, one of the big things that you saw, like, okay,
SPEAKER_0:  Take a microcosm of all of this action.
SPEAKER_0:  and just look at like the influencer space.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a ton of deals that were done that I've covered ad nauseum.
SPEAKER_0:  about.
SPEAKER_0:  Influencer finds out they can make a lot of money selling a crypto coin
SPEAKER_0:  The first thing they wonder is, am I gonna get caught?
SPEAKER_0:  If I do this...
SPEAKER_0:  Is there a consequence?
SPEAKER_0:  And if the answer is no...
SPEAKER_0:  then it's a pretty easy decision as long as you don't.
SPEAKER_0:  like have any moral scruples about it, which apparently none of them did, or a lot of them didn't, I should say.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  As soon as somebody steps in and regulates that...
SPEAKER_0:  math changes and all of a sudden there's a self-interest reason to not go do the bad thing.
SPEAKER_0:  So, for example, and I can give a concrete example of this.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a NFT, the first ever NFT sort of like.
SPEAKER_0:  official
SPEAKER_0:  indictment or the DOJ released this press release.
SPEAKER_0:  that they're charging these guys who ran a NFT project.
SPEAKER_0:  that they didn't follow through on their promises. They made all these promises, lied and then ran away with the money.
SPEAKER_0:  first ever consequence for anyone in the NFT space.
SPEAKER_0:  That day that that press release came out, I saw several NFT.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  projects come back to life from the dead.
SPEAKER_0:  Why? Because all those founders are freaking out.
SPEAKER_0:  and they realized we scammed people, we have to go at least make it look like we're doing the right thing, right? Even just, so that's on the optic side, but there's also...
SPEAKER_0:  tons of people who now go, oh.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, law enforcement is on the scene.
SPEAKER_0:  We can't do the same thing, so.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a very pragmatic reason to-
SPEAKER_0:  for this punishment. It's very much just because.
SPEAKER_0:  people work it into their math of.
SPEAKER_0:  Should I commit fraud?
SPEAKER_0:  and the last several years have been very...
SPEAKER_0:  What has it been like?
SPEAKER_0:  a little bit of a...
SPEAKER_0:  Nihilistic.
SPEAKER_0:  landscape where no one was getting punished.
SPEAKER_0:  And so there's this question of.
SPEAKER_0:  You're almost an idiot if you didn't take the deals.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... so i think it's really important extremely important for
SPEAKER_0:  kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  Law enforcement.
SPEAKER_0:  to play a role.
SPEAKER_0:  regulation to play a role to make it harder to commit those crimes, and if you commit those crimes-
SPEAKER_0:  there's actual real world punishment for it.
SPEAKER_0:  Your point about like what's gonna happen to the investors. I think that was kind of your question.
SPEAKER_0:  It's tough.
SPEAKER_0:  because if the money's not there, the money's not there. I mean, there's going to be the guy.
SPEAKER_0:  They got the best in class guy. It's the guy who ran the-
SPEAKER_0:  dissolving of Enron, so I mean, I can't imagine someone better equipped.
SPEAKER_0:  to run a complicated corporate fraud like.
SPEAKER_0:  dissolution but.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's tough because everyone's going to get probably, I don't know, 10 cents on the dollar, maybe less.
SPEAKER_1:  I wonder if there's a way to do a progressive redistribution of funds.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm just really worried about the pain that small investors feel.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think there's a lot of.
SPEAKER_0:  thought around that.
SPEAKER_0:  I forget if...
SPEAKER_0:  If they actually do do this, I mean, I know there's a lot of law about like-
SPEAKER_0:  You can't treat.
SPEAKER_0:  predators differently, you have to treat them all the same.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it'll be some kind of proportional.
SPEAKER_0:  payback. It's certainly not going to be that
SPEAKER_0:  the guys at the top get a significant amount of their money back and the rest get nothing.
SPEAKER_0:  Unfortunately, I think there's such a...
SPEAKER_0:  small amount of assets that back this whole thing in the end.
SPEAKER_0:  And that value is actually declining every day because
SPEAKER_0:  It was.
SPEAKER_0:  inextricably tied to FSPF. It was like the FTT tokens, which now what are those worth?
SPEAKER_0:  The serum tokens that was his project or the project they made
SPEAKER_0:  What is that worth? Basically nothing.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it's a very, it's a hard situation. And you know, there's a bigger ethical concern.
SPEAKER_0:  which is FTX US.
SPEAKER_0:  It's unclear how backed it was, but it was clearly more backed.
SPEAKER_0:  than FTX International.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you take all that money?
SPEAKER_0:  and throw it into a big pot and give people money back?
SPEAKER_0:  Or...
SPEAKER_0:  Do you?
SPEAKER_0:  give the US people back.
SPEAKER_0:  their amount of money, which is probably going to be significantly more and leave everyone internationally out in the cold.
SPEAKER_0:  To add to that ethical issue, let's say you're a liquidator and you're US based.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a tremendous.
SPEAKER_0:  question like legal questions about
SPEAKER_0:  You know, how do you ethically do that? It's not clear.
SPEAKER_0:  There's tremendous incentives to just favor the US people over everyone else, because it's our country, America, whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  But I don't know if that's necessarily fair.
SPEAKER_0:  It's really hard. It's like, it's impossible.
SPEAKER_1:  And some I forget where you said this but one of the I mean it probably permeates a lot of the investigations you do Which is this idea that
SPEAKER_1:  It's really sad that the middle class in most situations like this get fucked over.
SPEAKER_1:  So the IRS.
SPEAKER_1:  go after the middle class, then go after the rich. is basically
SPEAKER_1:  everyone who doesn't have a lot of leverage in terms of
SPEAKER_1:  lawyers.
SPEAKER_1:  Money.
SPEAKER_1:  Get fucked over.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes. And then.
SPEAKER_0:  They're the ones.
SPEAKER_0:  Like it's always the rich and powerful who get the favorable treatment. Is it like a microcosm of this funny story?
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  One of the big criticisms of crypto.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think rightly so.
SPEAKER_0:  is the irreversibility of the transaction. Thanks again, on behalf of wishedCenter exactly 50 dollars a month, and local delivery Cheryl
SPEAKER_0:  I accidentally send a transaction somewhere, it's gone.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Crypto.com accidentally sent a lady $10 million.
SPEAKER_0:  and now they want the money back and they're suing her.
SPEAKER_0:  But the funny thing is, is if you are on Crypto.com and you send
SPEAKER_0:  Let's say I accidentally send you money and I come knocking on your door. Let's say I didn't mean to send you-
SPEAKER_0:  You know, like.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... a thousand dollars i need my money back
SPEAKER_0:  Or if I go to crypto.com and I said, hey, I sent that to the wrong person, can you reverse it? That's right, after take 3, Put me in. Type.
SPEAKER_0:  Screw off, no way.
SPEAKER_0:  If I go to court, they'll kill me in court.
SPEAKER_0:  Cause they're going to go, look, this is how the blockchain works.
SPEAKER_0:  But then they do it, they do the exact same thing. I send this lady 10 million dollars.
SPEAKER_0:  They're suing Arnold, they're gonna win. Now what's in court is not whether they get the money back. It's.
SPEAKER_0:  Should she be liable for theft, I believe.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's just another case of.
SPEAKER_0:  The same rules apply differently to different people, whether you have the money to back you or not. It's a very sad thing.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's why I think people like, you need.
SPEAKER_0:  Journalists
SPEAKER_0:  fighting for.
SPEAKER_0:  the little person.
SPEAKER_0:  We really need it.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's kind of like this unfortunate thing where that's the most risky thing to do, like legally. You should.
SPEAKER_0:  not be doing that but um...
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's important to do. It's the ethical thing. It's the right thing to do.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think about influencers and celebrities that supported FTX and SBF? Should they be punished?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think they should take a huge reputational hit. I mean, I think they should be embarrassed.
SPEAKER_0:  I think they should be.
SPEAKER_0:  ashamed of themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  but it was really hard to know, sorry to interrupt, for them to know.
SPEAKER_1:  Like for example, I think about this a lot. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Who do I?
SPEAKER_1:  Because I don't investigate, you know, like, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Sponsored by Athletic Greens.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, see nutritional drink.
SPEAKER_1:  Should I investigate them deeply?
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, you just kinda use reputational, like it seems to work for me, should I?
SPEAKER_1:  Like I think I think.
SPEAKER_0:  really have pins on...
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  your credibility hit will depend on what domain you're an expert in.
SPEAKER_0:  if you're sponsored by a robotics company.
SPEAKER_0:  and you're an expert in robotics.
SPEAKER_0:  If that company turns out to be a disaster and fraud.
SPEAKER_0:  then you should have looked more deeply.
SPEAKER_0:  We're talking mostly about.
SPEAKER_0:  Like I hold Tom Brady a lot less accountable.
SPEAKER_0:  than financial advisors, financial influencers, because...
SPEAKER_0:  That is their world of expertise. And you treat their recommendation differently.
SPEAKER_0:  proportionally to what you think their expertise is.
SPEAKER_0:  So in some ways I don't actually think.
SPEAKER_0:  Tom Brady, I'm sure he reached a lot of people.
SPEAKER_0:  I personally didn't feel it all moved by his recommendation, because you know it's just money.
SPEAKER_0:  But when you hear somebody who should be an expert in that thing...
SPEAKER_0:  endorse a product in that space.
SPEAKER_0:  You hold that.
SPEAKER_0:  opinion to a higher standard and when they're completely cat is
SPEAKER_0:  cataclysmically wrong?
SPEAKER_0:  it's gonna be a different level of accountability. And I think rightfully so.
SPEAKER_0:  when um...
SPEAKER_0:  Jim Cramer.
SPEAKER_0:  was saying Bear Stearns is fine. He made that terrible call with Bear Stearns in 2008.
SPEAKER_0:  He was rightfully-
SPEAKER_0:  reamed.
SPEAKER_0:  for all of that.
SPEAKER_0:  even though it could be considered that like, well.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, did he have all the information? Maybe not.
SPEAKER_0:  He's a financial advisor. He does this for a living.
SPEAKER_0:  If you go on and you make a big call and you turn out to be wrong and people lose tons of money,
SPEAKER_0:  you are going to take a hit, and I think rightfully so. But no, I don't think these people should go to jail or anything like that. I don't think you should be out there again.
SPEAKER_1:  It's such a complicated thing. I mean, I just feel it personally myself. I get it
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  You still feel the burden of the fact that you're
SPEAKER_1:  opinion has influence.
SPEAKER_1:  I know it shouldn't.
SPEAKER_1:  I know Tom Brady's opinion on financial investment should not have influence, but it does. That's just the reality of it.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a real burden.
SPEAKER_1:  I didn't know anything about SBF or FTX. It wasn't on my radar at all.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, but I could see myself.
SPEAKER_1:  taking them on as a sponsor. I've seen a lot of people I respect.
SPEAKER_1:  Bye.
SPEAKER_1:  Sam Harris and others, like.
SPEAKER_1:  talk with SPF.
SPEAKER_1:  Mike, he's doing good for the world.
SPEAKER_1:  So I could see myself being hoodwinked, having not done research. And the same thing makes me wonder.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, I don't want to become cynical.
SPEAKER_1:  But it makes you wonder who are the people in your life you trust that are like.
SPEAKER_1:  that could be the next.
SPEAKER_1:  SPF or worse.
SPEAKER_1:  big powerful leaders hitler and all that kind of stuff
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  To what degree do you want to investigate?
SPEAKER_1:  Do you want to?
SPEAKER_1:  Hold their feet to the fire
SPEAKER_1:  see through their bullshit, call them on their bullshit. And also as a friend, if you happen to be friends or have a connection how to help them.
SPEAKER_1:  not slip into the
SPEAKER_1:  Land of fraud.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, all of it is just overwhelming.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, I mean we should be clear like finance is sort of a special space
SPEAKER_0:  where
SPEAKER_0:  You're talking about people's money.
SPEAKER_0:  You're not talking about whether someone takes a bad supplement.
SPEAKER_0:  or like a supplement that is just, they're $50 out.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the scale of harm and therefore responsibility.
SPEAKER_0:  escalates depending on what field you're in. Just like-
SPEAKER_0:  I wouldn't hold Tom Brady as
SPEAKER_0:  Like if he gives a bad football opinion, right?
SPEAKER_0:  and he should have known better.
SPEAKER_0:  That is a different scale of harm.
SPEAKER_0:  than a doctor giving bad advice.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, like life's it, like he tells you a pill works and the pill.
SPEAKER_0:  kills you or something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  There's just different levels of accountability depending on the field you're in and you have to be aware of it.
SPEAKER_0:  Finance is an extreme. You have to be extremely conservative if you're going to give financial advice.
SPEAKER_0:  because you're playing with people's lives and you cannot play with them haphazardly, you cannot gamble with them, you cannot play with them on a bet because you're getting paid a lot of money.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just the nature of the space. And so with the space comes the responsibility and the accountability. And I don't think you can get around that.
SPEAKER_1:  Who was Dan Friedberg that you mentioned? Some of these figures in the SBF realm that are interesting to you.
SPEAKER_0:  super interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of subject because Dan Friedberg.
SPEAKER_0:  is the former general counsel for ultimate bet.
SPEAKER_0:  Ultimate Bet was a poker site.
SPEAKER_0:  where famously they got in a scandal because...
SPEAKER_0:  The owner, Russ Hamilton, was cheating with a little software.
SPEAKER_0:  piece of code they call God Mode.
SPEAKER_0:  God mode allowed you to see.
SPEAKER_0:  the guy across from you's hand.
SPEAKER_0:  Obviously you can imagine you can win pretty consistently if you know exactly what your opponent has.
SPEAKER_0:  Very unethical.
SPEAKER_0:  They, I should be clear.
SPEAKER_0:  for some inexplicable reason. I don't think they were ever-
SPEAKER_0:  charged and convicted of a crime.
SPEAKER_0:  but they were investigated by a gambling commission that found they made tens of millions of dollars this way.
SPEAKER_0:  for sure.
SPEAKER_0:  Dan Friedberg is the general counsel. He's caught on a call.
SPEAKER_0:  basically conspiring with Russ to hide.
SPEAKER_0:  This.
SPEAKER_0:  Fraud.
SPEAKER_0:  He's saying we should blame it on a consultant third party. And Russ Hamilton famously says, It was me. I did it. I don't want to give the money back.
SPEAKER_0:  find basically a way to get rid of this.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's Dan Friedberg's big achievement.
SPEAKER_0:  Like that's what he's known for, he's most known for.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is the guy they pick as their chief regulatory officer.
SPEAKER_0:  for FTX.
SPEAKER_0:  Why do you hire somebody who...
SPEAKER_0:  I get it, not formally charged and convicted, investigated, there's all the, and there's tape out there. So I want to be clear about what's actually available evidence.
SPEAKER_0:  but someone whose seemingly only achievement is hiding fraud.
SPEAKER_0:  Why do you hire that guy?
SPEAKER_0:  if the intention is not to hire.
SPEAKER_0:  is not to hide fraud.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is a question I put to Sam Bankman Fried and his answer was...
SPEAKER_0:  Well, we have a lot of lawyers. And I said, well, it's your chief regulatory officer. He's like, well, we did regulate a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was just this big dance of, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically...
SPEAKER_0:  He's done great work, he's a great guy.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I think that tells you everything you need to know.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's figures like that probably even at the lower levels, like just infiltrate the entire organization.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it's just like, why, yeah, why wasn't there a CFA? Why wasn't there anyone in that space who could seemingly-
SPEAKER_0:  be the eyes that goes holy
SPEAKER_0:  Whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  We need to, we were in dangerous territory here, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Um, so yeah, it seems very deliberate. I mean, I talked to one FTX employee that they talked about.
SPEAKER_0:  who's told me they talked about.
SPEAKER_0:  taking.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it was taking FTX US public.
SPEAKER_0:  and Sam was very against the idea.
SPEAKER_0:  and the employee in retrospect.
SPEAKER_0:  speculated that it might have been because you'd faced so much scrutiny.
SPEAKER_0:  like regulation-wise, like you'd have to, you know, go through.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  like more thorough audits, all that kind of stuff, that basically he knew they would never pass.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  So yeah, I mean, it's red flags all the way down with that guy.
SPEAKER_1:  and you hope all of them get.
SPEAKER_1:  punished.
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone who knew.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  For sure, there are people at FTX who didn't know.
SPEAKER_0:  I think there are some people at Alameda.
SPEAKER_0:  who didn't know.
SPEAKER_1:  There's degrees, sorry to interrupt, but there's degrees in not knowing. Yes! There's a-
SPEAKER_1:  looking away.
SPEAKER_1:  When you kind of know shady stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  That's still the same as knowing, right?
SPEAKER_1:  That's might be even worse.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, yeah, like I was talking to one insider.
SPEAKER_0:  and we're talking about the inside of trading.
SPEAKER_0:  They were telling me about this insider trading.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I said, do you think this was?
SPEAKER_0:  criminal.
SPEAKER_0:  and they said it was probably criminal in hindsight, yes.
SPEAKER_0:  And the question is someone who answers a question like that.
SPEAKER_0:  What does that mean? It was probably criminal. so
SPEAKER_0:  You're right, there are different degrees. I mean-
SPEAKER_0:  I'll say at the most basic, I would be very happy if everyone who had direct knowledge
SPEAKER_0:  went to jail, which I don't think will happen to be clear. I think a lot of people are going to cut deals.
SPEAKER_0:  prosecutors are going to cut deals so they actually nail Sam Bankman Fried. I think that's their only focus.
SPEAKER_1:  What about his reputation waiting about all these interviews.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think they are helping him? Do you think they are good for the world?
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think they're bad for the world? Like what's your sense and-
SPEAKER_1:  Like say you get to sit down.
SPEAKER_1:  interview with him for three hours.
SPEAKER_1:  and I'm holding the door closed.
SPEAKER_1:  What, is that a useful conversation or not? Or at this point?
SPEAKER_1:  It should be legal.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's it.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's useful.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I think it's all about how you interview him. You can interview someone responsibly, you can interview him.
SPEAKER_0:  irresponsibly.
SPEAKER_0:  I think we've seen examples.
SPEAKER_0:  of both.
SPEAKER_1:  What's an irresponsible? I keep interrupting you rudely. That's okay. No, no, no.
SPEAKER_0:  No, no, no, I think it's fine.
SPEAKER_0:  There was like a New York Times interview which...
SPEAKER_0:  spends any amount of time talking about his sleep.
SPEAKER_0:  And he's like, yeah, I'm sleeping great.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I think that's so deeply disrespectful.
SPEAKER_0:  to the victims.
SPEAKER_0:  and especially when you're...
SPEAKER_0:  You're not even releasing an interview live. It's like you have time to triage what you're going to talk about.
SPEAKER_0:  Why would you spend any amount of time talking about the sleep?
SPEAKER_0:  that I-
SPEAKER_0:  fraudster.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just so weird.
SPEAKER_1:  and well it's a cast your man that case
SPEAKER_1:  I don't think it turned out well. I think that's... I think...
SPEAKER_1:  I could see myself talking while somebody sleeps.
SPEAKER_1:  or getting in somebody's mind.
SPEAKER_1:  if i knew have a moment time
SPEAKER_1:  I knew I had like four hours because you get into the mind the person how they think how they see the world
SPEAKER_1:  because I think that ultimately reveals.
SPEAKER_1:  if they're actually really good at lying.
SPEAKER_1:  It reveals.
SPEAKER_1:  the depths, the complexity of the mind, that through like osmosis, you get to understand like this person.
SPEAKER_1:  This person is not as trivial as you realize. Also, it makes you maybe realize that this person is.
SPEAKER_1:  has a lot of hope.
SPEAKER_1:  has a lot of.
SPEAKER_1:  Positive ambition.
SPEAKER_1:  That's like...
SPEAKER_1:  that has developed over their life and then certain interesting ways things went wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  become corrupt and all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  You just, that's all fine.
SPEAKER_0:  This conversation was not properly contextualized in the world of what he did.
SPEAKER_0:  And I've asked about this interview because I was like so curious. It was out of the New York Times.
SPEAKER_0:  and there was not much mention of fraud or jail or the big crimes like misappropriation of even client assets.
SPEAKER_0:  It was just sort of this.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, Sam sat down with me.
SPEAKER_0:  he's under investigation, but there's not much specifics. And then it's like, yeah, he's playing storybook brawl. He's sleeping, he's...
SPEAKER_0:  And it's just like, okay, this isn't adding to the conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  Especially when they're in New York Times, it's like a...
SPEAKER_1:  You should be grilling.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, right, exactly. So topic six two, we definitely, we're gonna focus on times and for rough purposes what
SPEAKER_0:  But as I've said, I mean, it's all arranged the gamut and some interviews like some of it's okay and then some of it's weird like.
SPEAKER_0:  the Andrew Sorkin interview.
SPEAKER_0:  He asked some hard-hitting questions, which I really appreciated.
SPEAKER_0:  And then at the end he goes, ladies and gentlemen, Sam Bankman Friede, and everyone gives like an ovation.
SPEAKER_0:  for.
SPEAKER_0:  Sam.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, the steel man of that of course is like, they're actually applauding.
SPEAKER_0:  Andrew Sorkin.
SPEAKER_0:  But the way you like lay it up, I wouldn't go like, ladies and gentlemen,
SPEAKER_0:  It's like an applause line. Ladies and gentlemen, the Eagles Elton John.
SPEAKER_0:  Lex Friedman. And so to go to, so you have this like.
SPEAKER_0:  Dealbook Summit.
SPEAKER_0:  where you have all these important figures that are positively important.
SPEAKER_0:  And at the end you have Sam Bankman Fried, a fraudster. And yo, ladies and gentlemen, this is Sam Bankman Fried, everyone's applauding.
SPEAKER_0:  That I think is a net, like I think that's a negative. I think the way that
SPEAKER_0:  The optics of that just were all wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I think, yeah, you have to be very responsible.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's useful, going back to how you can usefully do this.
SPEAKER_0:  You can, even when somebody's determined to lie to you.
SPEAKER_0:  always important to...
SPEAKER_0:  pin them down to an accounting of events.
SPEAKER_0:  because that is.
SPEAKER_0:  unimaginably helpful when it comes to a prosecutor trying to prove this guy's guilty.
SPEAKER_0:  is
SPEAKER_0:  If you say you didn't do a crime, but you don't tell me any details about it,
SPEAKER_0:  Day of the trial, you can basically make up any story.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you tell me in detail where you were that day...
SPEAKER_0:  I can go hunt down you say you were with Joe. I go hunt down Joe and he says he wasn't with you. Boom, you've lost credibility and now...
SPEAKER_0:  you're much more, you're much more.
SPEAKER_0:  likely to be convicted.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's really important to get SBF's exact accounting of how things went wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  because
SPEAKER_0:  Right now, he's positioning himself to throw his...
SPEAKER_0:  Alameda CEO Caroline Ellison under the bus like she did everything
SPEAKER_0:  She knew everything, I knew nothing.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, is Caroline Ellison gonna take the stand and go, well, I have all these text messages and this is all a lie, then Sam Bankman Fried is gonna be completely.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  ruined, like self-ruined by his own design. so
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's more like a legal type of uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I get the details of where he was, what he was thinking, what the... I think it's...
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, yeah, I think the public probably cares to get to know what happened to. And again, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're s- if you're careful
SPEAKER_0:  you can expose someone for as they lie to you.
SPEAKER_0:  without.
SPEAKER_0:  giving into those lies, right? Like without capitulating.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, I'm just going to assume you're correct.
SPEAKER_0:  I think you can point to, well, Lex, you say it happened this way, but you've lied about X, Y, and Z. Why should we believe you? That's suddenly a totally different conversation than just being like, okay, that's how it happened.
SPEAKER_1:  The thing I caught.
SPEAKER_1:  Bothered me.
SPEAKER_1:  And the thing I hope to do in interviews is if.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  if I eventually get good at this thing, is the human aspect of it, which is like.
SPEAKER_1:  which I think you have to do in person.
SPEAKER_1:  is he seems a bit nonchalant about the pain and the suffering of people.
SPEAKER_1:  I have read flags about...
SPEAKER_1:  the way.
SPEAKER_1:  He's-
SPEAKER_1:  He communicates about...
SPEAKER_1:  the loss of money, the pain that people are feeling about the money.
SPEAKER_1:  I get red flags, like you're not...
SPEAKER_1:  uh... forget if you're involved in that pain or not you're not
SPEAKER_1:  feeling that pain.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, he'll say he is, but he'll be playing a game of League of Legends while doing it.
SPEAKER_1:  I just see from his face the dynamic. I know.
SPEAKER_0:  And that needs to be grilled.
SPEAKER_1:  that little human dance there. That's why I mean I.
SPEAKER_1:  I considered.
SPEAKER_1:  I talked to him.
SPEAKER_1:  I considered doing an in-person interview with him.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  And in that- Are you still considering it?
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, do you think I should, in person?
SPEAKER_0:  I think it depends if you think you have anything to add to the conversation. A lot of people have.
SPEAKER_1:  has been already, you did an incredible job. Thanks.
SPEAKER_1:  I think I would like to grill the shit out of him.
SPEAKER_1:  as a fellow human, but not investigated.
SPEAKER_0:  He's ill-investigated.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, yeah
SPEAKER_1:  Like.
SPEAKER_1:  Like another human being.
SPEAKER_1:  another human being who I can have compassion for.
SPEAKER_1:  who has caused a lot of suffering in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  Like that, that grilling.
SPEAKER_1:  Like basically...
SPEAKER_1:  convey the anger that people and the pain that people are feeling.
SPEAKER_1:  Right, like that.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it'd be really hard. I mean, like that guy is sort of a master dancer and what he would say at the end of it, because I've listened to so many-
SPEAKER_0:  Interviews of him.
SPEAKER_0:  I probably am like a GPT model for Sam.
SPEAKER_0:  I think he would do some kind of thing about like...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  I really, um...
SPEAKER_0:  I really hear you and it's just terrible. I feel such an obligation to the people who've lost money and-
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it's just, it's a lot of money. It's a lot of money.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, he'd do something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  and it would be very superficially like.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay?
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  When you drill down to the details of what he did.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just impossible that he didn't know.
SPEAKER_0:  And one of the things that I wish I had asked.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe I can talk about like.
SPEAKER_0:  I wish I had gone on this. It's just so hard when you're doing a live interview to kind of focus on one thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone's asked about the terms of service. So in the terms of service, there was like...
SPEAKER_0:  We can't touch your funds, your funds are safe. We're never going to do anything with that.
SPEAKER_0:  Anytime anyone brings that up, he says, oh.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, there's this.
SPEAKER_0:  other terms of service over here with margin trading accounts. Remember we talked about it's a derivatives platform.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're in our derivative side,
SPEAKER_0:  you're subject to different terms of service, which kind of lets us like move your money around with everyone else.
SPEAKER_0:  So we treat it as one big pool of funds.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's sort of the explanation of how this all happened is we had this huge leverage position and we lost everything.
SPEAKER_0:  but what no one has sort of done a good enough job getting to the heart of.
SPEAKER_0:  is that.
SPEAKER_0:  This pool of funds never was segregated properly.
SPEAKER_0:  It was all treated under the same umbrella of we can use your funds.
SPEAKER_0:  There was no amount of we have the client deposits which were just deposited with us and not like used.
SPEAKER_0:  to margin trade or do anything over here.
SPEAKER_0:  These funds over here, we have saved. They didn't.
SPEAKER_0:  Fundamentally, they lied from the get-go about how they were treating the most precious assets, which is your customer deposits that you said you didn't invest.
SPEAKER_0:  Clearly, you put them all over here, you yolo-gambled them, and then when everyone starts to rep-
SPEAKER_0:  withdrawing from here.
SPEAKER_0:  They don't have any money over here.
SPEAKER_0:  So that is like one of the most fundamental things.
SPEAKER_0:  I haven't seen anyone grill him on.
SPEAKER_0:  And the next time if I get the chance to...
SPEAKER_0:  Ambush him again. That's that's what I'm going to drill down on because it's impossible for that not to be fraud
SPEAKER_0:  There's no world where you had a pool of funds over here and now you don't have them without you somehow
SPEAKER_0:  Borrowing.
SPEAKER_0:  over here.
SPEAKER_0:  Because if you deposited one bitcoin and I never sold that bitcoin and it's earmarked...
SPEAKER_0:  Lex Friedman.
SPEAKER_0:  and you come and it's not there, something had to happen.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, so this is so interesting. So for me.
SPEAKER_1:  The...
SPEAKER_1:  Approach that.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you said, the most important question.
SPEAKER_1:  of, uh, cause for you it's like-
SPEAKER_1:  with those funds segregated.
SPEAKER_1:  For me the question is...
SPEAKER_1:  as a human being.
SPEAKER_1:  How would you feel if you were observing that?
SPEAKER_1:  Sike.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, that like marshmallow test with the babies.
SPEAKER_1:  Like it's the human thing, it's the human nature question.
SPEAKER_1:  I can understand there's a pile of money.
SPEAKER_1:  and you
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  the good faith interpretation is like, well I know what to do with that pile of money, to grow that pile of money, let me just take a little bit of that.
SPEAKER_1:  Like how willing are you to do that kind of thing? How able are you to do that kind of thing? And when shit goes wrong?
SPEAKER_1:  What goes through your mind?
SPEAKER_1:  How does it become corrupted? How do you begin to delude yourself?
SPEAKER_1:  How do you, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  delegate responsibility for the failures.
SPEAKER_1:  Like.
SPEAKER_1:  as opposed to getting facts?
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  try to sneak.
SPEAKER_1:  into the human mind of a person when they're thinking of that. Because the facts-
SPEAKER_1:  they're gonna start waffling.
SPEAKER_1:  They're gonna
SPEAKER_1:  start like trying to make sure they don't say anything, they get some incriminated. right Hendrick
SPEAKER_1:  but I just, I want to understand the human being.
SPEAKER_1:  there.
SPEAKER_1:  Because I think that indirectly gives you a sense of where were you in this big picture?
SPEAKER_0:  I think I've talked to so many people.
SPEAKER_0:  who have sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  committed some range of like outright fraud to like misleading marketing.
SPEAKER_0:  No one thinks they're a bad person.
SPEAKER_0:  Nobody.
SPEAKER_0:  admits that they did it and they knew they did, or almost nobody does.
SPEAKER_0:  There's actually one funny exception, but.
SPEAKER_0:  I had a guy who admitted like, yeah, I did it. It was wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  And, you know, but I did it and I wanted the money, which was kind of like.
SPEAKER_0:  almost refreshing in its honesty.
SPEAKER_0:  But, um...
SPEAKER_0:  The reason I focus on like the facts.
SPEAKER_0:  is because
SPEAKER_0:  Unless you find a bright red line.
SPEAKER_0:  humans can rationalize anything.
SPEAKER_0:  I can rationalize any level of like, well, I did this because I had the best of intentions. And if you play the intention game, you'll never convict anyone because everyone has good intentions. Everyone's honest. Everyone's doing the best they can and got misleaded and da da da da.
SPEAKER_0:  Ultimately, you have to drill down to the concrete and go look.
SPEAKER_0:  I get it.
SPEAKER_0:  You're just like the last 50 guys that I interviewed. You had the best of intentions. It all went wrong. I'm very sorry for you.
SPEAKER_0:  But at the end of the day, there's people hurting and there's people that have significant damage to their life because of you.
SPEAKER_0:  What did you actually do and what can we prove?
SPEAKER_0:  taking intention out of it, taking motivation out, what can we prove that you did that was unethical, illegal or immoral?
SPEAKER_0:  And like that is.
SPEAKER_0:  sort of what usually I try to go to because
SPEAKER_0:  I will do those human interviews, but...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it's just like, it's just a re-
SPEAKER_0:  like the same record on repeat. I mean, a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  I got it. Same. I'm with you, I'm with you on everything you said, but there is ways to do.
SPEAKER_1:  to avoid the record on repeat. I mean, those are different skill sets. You're exceptionally good at the investigative.
SPEAKER_1:  like investigating.
SPEAKER_1:  I do believe there's a way to break through the repeat. There's different techniques to it. One of which is like taking outside of their particular story. Yes, when everyone looks at their own story, they can see themselves as a good player doing good. But you can do other thought experiments.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, there's a...
SPEAKER_0:  But they'll follow you, they'll know what the thought experiment is.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, it depends. It depends, my friend.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, the, like, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, to me...
SPEAKER_1:  There's a million of them, but...
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  just exploring your ethics.
SPEAKER_1:  Would you kill somebody to protect your family?
SPEAKER_1:  and you explore that.
SPEAKER_1:  You start to sneak into like, what's your sense?
SPEAKER_1:  uh... of
SPEAKER_1:  the in-group versus the out-group.
SPEAKER_1:  how much damage you can do to the R group and who is the R group.
SPEAKER_1:  and you start to build that sense of the person.
SPEAKER_1:  Are we like the two mobsters that we're dressed as?
SPEAKER_1:  Do we protect the family and fuck everyone else?
SPEAKER_1:  You're with us and the ones who are against us, fuck them.
SPEAKER_1:  Or do we have a sense that human beings are all?
SPEAKER_1:  have value, equal value, and we want to, that we're a joint humanity. There's ways to get to that. You start to build up this sense.
SPEAKER_1:  of like
SPEAKER_1:  Some people that make a lot of money are better than others. They deserve to be at the top.
SPEAKER_1:  If you have that feeling...
SPEAKER_1:  You start to get a sense of like...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, the poor people are the dumbasses, they're the idiots. If you believe that, then you start to understand that this person may have been at the core of the school corrupt.
SPEAKER_1:  organization.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, two things.
SPEAKER_0:  One.
SPEAKER_0:  I think you should join me on this side of the table. We'll put SBF over here. Well, good guy, bad guy, human. Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  it facts like you're the
SPEAKER_1:  You're the bad guy. I'm like, no, no, no, slow down coffee
SPEAKER_0:  What is your feeling about humanity?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I-
SPEAKER_1:  Have you been getting enough?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, right. So I think there's a lot of truth to what you said.
SPEAKER_0:  One thing I've noticed that is hard to combat.
SPEAKER_0:  is sort of like.
SPEAKER_0:  preference falsification and just like
SPEAKER_0:  Just the outright lying about those things.
SPEAKER_0:  is tough to kind of pin down. But yeah, you're absolutely right. There's ways to interview people. There's all sorts of interesting techniques. And yeah, I don't disagree.
SPEAKER_1:  Good cop, bad cop. We should do this, this would be like a sitcom. Okay....
SPEAKER_1:  You did an incredible documentary on SafeMoon.
SPEAKER_1:  The title is, I uncovered a billion dollar fraud.
SPEAKER_1:  Akin, you tell me the story of SafeMoon.
SPEAKER_0:  So, safe moon.
SPEAKER_0:  was a crypto coin that exploded on the scene.
SPEAKER_0:  in a
SPEAKER_0:  2021, I think at this point.
SPEAKER_0:  Sorry, I'm losing track of my years. One year in crypto is like five years in real life.
SPEAKER_0:  But it kind of gained a huge amount of popularity because of this idea.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  It's in the name. You go safely to the moon.
SPEAKER_0:  How they were gonna do this is with sort of a sophisticated smart contract idea.
SPEAKER_0:  where
SPEAKER_0:  There's.
SPEAKER_0:  I kind of have to explain the way some...
SPEAKER_0:  Contracts get rug pulled for a second or
SPEAKER_0:  there's scams happen.
SPEAKER_0:  So in the...
SPEAKER_0:  Sometimes it's called like the shit coin space, the alt coin space, anything like below Bitcoin, Ethereum and maybe the top five or ten.
SPEAKER_0:  is kind of seen as this wasteland of gambling and like, you know, you don't know if they're-
SPEAKER_0:  developers are going to become anything or not.
SPEAKER_0:  You're kind of like.
SPEAKER_0:  reading the white paper, trying to figure it out.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's this big question about like, how can you get scammed? How can-
SPEAKER_0:  back to the interests you don't want.
SPEAKER_0:  the developer to have some like.
SPEAKER_0:  parachute cord where they can pull all the money out.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  One way this happens is that in decentralized
SPEAKER_0:  decentralized finance.
SPEAKER_0:  There's something called the liquidity pool.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically this big pot of money.
SPEAKER_0:  that allows people to trade.
SPEAKER_0:  between
SPEAKER_0:  two different currencies. So let's say like SafeMoon.
SPEAKER_0:  and Bitcoin, right? Or Ethereum or it's actually on the Binance Smart Chain. So it'd be...
SPEAKER_0:  BNB.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and this pool of money.
SPEAKER_0:  can be controlled by the developers in such a way they can steal it all.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? They can just grab it.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't want to go too much into details because I feel like I'll lose people here, but the point of SafeMoon was.
SPEAKER_0:  The core idea.
SPEAKER_0:  was we're locking this money up.
SPEAKER_0:  You can't touch it.
SPEAKER_0:  And actually every transaction.
SPEAKER_0:  that you buy Safemoon with?
SPEAKER_0:  We'll take a 5% tax of that.
SPEAKER_0:  We'll do a 10% tax, but 5% of it.
SPEAKER_0:  We'll go back to all the holders of Safeman.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay. And 5% of it will go back into this little pool of money.
SPEAKER_0:  So the idea is as you trade.
SPEAKER_0:  As this token becomes more viral.
SPEAKER_0:  Two things will happen. One, the people who are holding it long-term will be rewarded for holding it long-term by receiving this 5% tax.
SPEAKER_0:  that's distributed to everyone.
SPEAKER_0:  And two, you can kind of trust that you're.
SPEAKER_0:  your money's gonna have this stable value because.
SPEAKER_0:  This pool of money here in the middle, that's kind of guaranteeing you can get your safe moon out into this actually valuable currency.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not gonna move.
SPEAKER_0:  So the story of SafeMoon was that.
SPEAKER_0:  Fundamentally, this was not the case. They promised that this money was gonna be locked up. It was not actually locked up at all. They said it was automatically locked up. You don't have to worry about it.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it was very manually locked up, and they didn't actually lock a lot of it up.
SPEAKER_0:  They took a lot of it for themselves, for the developers.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a lot of players in this.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of the, a lot of them have left by now. There's kind of this main CEO that everyone knows John Coroney now.
SPEAKER_0:  And...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, despite saying that they were gonna lock up all the funds for four years, somehow he's gone from as everyone else in the-
SPEAKER_0:  and the token has lost 99% of the value of the token.
SPEAKER_0:  So they've lost 99%.
SPEAKER_0:  He's gotten.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... like
SPEAKER_0:  a $6 million crypto portfolio.
SPEAKER_0:  multi-million dollar real estate portfolio.
SPEAKER_0:  invested millions into various companies.
SPEAKER_0:  So he's accrued this huge wealth.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I made a video basically exposing that and showing how this coin which-
SPEAKER_0:  once had a $4 billion market cap, it was just viral everywhere. Everyone was talking about it because of these viral ideas. It is sort of a-
SPEAKER_0:  captivating idea that...
SPEAKER_0:  By holding it, you could get.
SPEAKER_0:  returns right like you just hold on to it you automatically get money
SPEAKER_0:  And it's a viral idea that this money in the middle in the pot isn't going to leave you.
SPEAKER_0:  when those things turned out to be false.
SPEAKER_0:  This community has had a slow death.
SPEAKER_0:  as a lot of people realized it was a scam.
SPEAKER_0:  and there's been a core part of the community.
SPEAKER_0:  which gets to an interesting dynamic we can talk about if you want to.
SPEAKER_0:  where they have like doubled down on the belief in Karony.
SPEAKER_0:  And so part of it was out of a hope to let those people know what was really going on in their coin.
SPEAKER_0:  and like hopefully save some of them.
SPEAKER_0:  Not in like some altruistic sense, but like.
SPEAKER_0:  or not in some like, I'm like a hero sense, but in the sense of, um,
SPEAKER_0:  I think a lot of them didn't know, like literally didn't know. So just sort of like as a public service.
SPEAKER_0:  letting them know.
SPEAKER_0:  so they could get their money out and hopefully save themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of pain and suffering.
SPEAKER_1:  So yeah. They really dug in.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's- Some did, some did, some did, some left. I mean, a lot of people have left, but the people who are left are people with large amounts of-
SPEAKER_0:  Safe moon hoardings.
SPEAKER_0:  that are down immensely, and you can imagine at a certain point in losses...
SPEAKER_0:  There's a tremendous psychological pressure to go, look, I'm in it.
SPEAKER_0:  I gotta go for the long haul.
SPEAKER_0:  and then you want to believe that this thing is legitimate and will succeed.
SPEAKER_0:  Because A, there's an ego component around, I haven't been scammed, I'm too smart to get scammed.
SPEAKER_0:  It's tremendously.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it hurts psychologically to acknowledge you've been taken for a ride.
SPEAKER_0:  And also you just want this thing to succeed for your financial wellbeing. So you like want to believe it. So there's tremendous psychological pressure to build.
SPEAKER_0:  cult-like communities around these tokens.
SPEAKER_0:  And I've noticed with the incentive of like.
SPEAKER_0:  community built.
SPEAKER_0:  sort of new to finance. There's like these.
SPEAKER_0:  meme coins or these...
SPEAKER_0:  These cults.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't want to, it's not really fair to call all of them cults, like some of them are open to criticism, but
SPEAKER_0:  One of the things that defines cults is they're not open to...
SPEAKER_0:  sunlight or criticism.
SPEAKER_0:  there's these financial communities that are opening up.
SPEAKER_0:  with
SPEAKER_0:  crypto with a few stocks.
SPEAKER_0:  where if you criticize them, you are attacked.
SPEAKER_0:  and the entire community has every incentive to kind of like...
SPEAKER_0:  downplay your legitimate criticisms or kind of
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  go after you. Start intro-
SPEAKER_0:  It creates this interesting dynamic that's so fascinating.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think about?
SPEAKER_1:  Bitcoin then.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think it's one of those communities that does attack you when criticized? So which, I guess which coins do you think are open to criticism and which are not?
SPEAKER_0:  It's kinda tough, like...
SPEAKER_0:  No, community is a monolith. So just like, it's just.
SPEAKER_0:  a spectrum of how open.
SPEAKER_0:  They are, there's just like, there's always this core contingent.
SPEAKER_0:  of extreme believers.
SPEAKER_0:  who will.
SPEAKER_0:  Go after anyone who criticizes them.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's just about how wide of a band that makes up the entire token.
SPEAKER_1:  how intensely, how active that small community is. So it's in Bitcoin, they're called Bitcoin maximalists, but you can also call.
SPEAKER_1:  and you.
SPEAKER_1:  Any communities.
SPEAKER_1:  subgroup like that maximalist whatever the belief is right i don't know
SPEAKER_1:  uh... don't condones maximus
SPEAKER_1:  That community is probably small in terms of attacking you online. You know which community has a very intense?
SPEAKER_1:  following.
SPEAKER_1:  I got attacked on the internet.
SPEAKER_1:  when I said Messi's better than Ronaldo.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  And so that's a very intense maximalist community there.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, the other one that surprised me...
SPEAKER_1:  is when I said...
SPEAKER_1:  Now I did it in jest.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, folks?
SPEAKER_1:  I said Emacs is a better ID than Vim.
SPEAKER_0:  I love you, Max. I agree.
SPEAKER_1:  Listen.
SPEAKER_1:  I have trauma, I wake up.
SPEAKER_1:  sweating sometimes at night thinking.
SPEAKER_0:  That's Emax Master X.
SPEAKER_1:  The Vim people are after me, they're everywhere. They're in the shadows. Vim is an amazing and it's actually.
SPEAKER_1:  Surprise, I've recently learned that it's.
SPEAKER_1:  But still.
SPEAKER_1:  even more so than before, an incredibly active community. So a lot of people.
SPEAKER_0:  But do you use space max? It's just emax and vim.
SPEAKER_1:  No, I haven't.
SPEAKER_1:  I use raw. Old school Emacs? But hold on a second. I actually recently, I have recently said, you know what?
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Let's make love not war. I went to VS code.
SPEAKER_1:  I went to a more modern ID. attend hands, because I would beæœ to everyone right now.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  because I did most of my programming in Emacs. I did most of anything as one does in Emacs.
SPEAKER_1:  just because I also love Lisp, so I can customize everything. Then I realized like-
SPEAKER_1:  Like how long will Vim and Emacs be around really? I was thinking as a programmer...
SPEAKER_1:  looking like 10, 20 years out.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I should challenge myself to learn new ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  to learn.
SPEAKER_1:  the new tools that the majority of the community is using.
SPEAKER_1:  so that I can understand what are the benefits and the costs, I found myself getting a little too comfortable with the tools that I grew up with.
SPEAKER_1:  I think one of the fundamental ways of being as a programmer, as anyone involved with technology,
SPEAKER_1:  based on how quickly it's evolving is to keep learning new tools like
SPEAKER_1:  The way of life should be constantly learning.
SPEAKER_1:  You're not a mathematician or a physicist or.
SPEAKER_1:  and you have those disciplines that are more stable. This is like everything is changing. Crypto is, like you said, a perfect example of that.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to constantly update your understanding.
SPEAKER_1:  of the...
SPEAKER_1:  of digital finance constantly in order to be able to function, in order to be able to criticize it.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... in order to be able to know what to invest in so yeah that that was why i did uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I tried Partcharm a bunch, the whole JetBrains infrastructure and then...
SPEAKER_1:  Also VS Code, because that's really popular, and you know, Adam and...
SPEAKER_1:  Sublime all of those I've been I've been exploring I've been exploring yes code is amazing. You should check out
SPEAKER_0:  I'm just going to give one more pitch for it. It's just basically like a customizable configuration. Well, Emacs is already customizable, but it's a...
SPEAKER_0:  It's pretty useful. Not even much of a coder.
SPEAKER_0:  but for like certain.
SPEAKER_0:  journaling applications or like time management, I find it really useful.
SPEAKER_0:  Anyway, we're so like, I feel like half this podcast is what it should have been and then half of it's just us nerding out our own engineering like idiosyncrasies.
SPEAKER_0:  Sorry guys.
SPEAKER_1:  All right.
SPEAKER_1:  So what were we talking about? Safe moon.
SPEAKER_1:  and Bitcoin, Bitcoin, what do you think? Is there a-
SPEAKER_1:  Have you made enemies?
SPEAKER_1:  in certain communities. What do you think about Bitcoin?
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I've made certain enemies in the sort of crypto skeptics space because there's sort of this range of skepticism you can have about cryptocurrency.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm obviously a skeptic of a lot of it.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  There are certain aspects of crypto that I think are inevitable, and I'm going to do my best to kind of describe those here.
SPEAKER_0:  but I'm not committed to any crypto specifically, but.
SPEAKER_0:  There are some.
SPEAKER_0:  I've taken a lot of heat, ironically, for not being skeptical enough. There's some people who believe that, like, the entire thing is a complete waste of time.
SPEAKER_0:  They're rslashbuttcoin on Reddit. It's an amazing community, actually. It's very funny.
SPEAKER_0:  They have. What's a buck coin? It's like a play on Bitcoin. They're like, they're just like, at least we admit it's a scam. Very funny guys.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... very funny people there
SPEAKER_0:  So, but they like, but they'll, they'll be like, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Coffee's delicious, just admit that all of it's a giant Ponzi scheme, all of it's a basically like.
SPEAKER_0:  NOT.
SPEAKER_1:  real.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's all basically all the Ponzi-nomics. It's all, it's-
SPEAKER_0:  It's Ponzinomics all the way down. It's like.
SPEAKER_0:  There is no fundamental use case that.
SPEAKER_0:  Is that useful? I don't know if-
SPEAKER_0:  I guess I don't want to strawman them here.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't want to say that.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if they're saying that.
SPEAKER_0:  It's all useless.
SPEAKER_0:  At minimum, they're saying.
SPEAKER_0:  the level of interest in cryptocurrencies.
SPEAKER_0:  FAR
SPEAKER_0:  The actual usefulness of it is far less.
SPEAKER_0:  then
SPEAKER_0:  the amount of attention and time and money that's being poured into it. So like the revolutionariness of this technology is not at all revolutionary.
SPEAKER_0:  Let me-
SPEAKER_0:  kind of steel man what I think the pro crypto take is.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Technologies are sort of this inert thing.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  The success of them, in my opinion, is not based on
SPEAKER_0:  PR, it's not based on marketing.
SPEAKER_0:  It's based on cheaper, faster, better.
SPEAKER_0:  Fundamentally, the success of any technology relies on those three things.
SPEAKER_0:  and longevity of it.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I have two employees.
SPEAKER_0:  and both of them are out of the country.
SPEAKER_0:  So I have to frequently make international wire payments to them.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Is one of them SPF just, as a reporter I have to ask. No. Well, I can explain the spf just as fx, so the spf just, the spec file re persisting
SPEAKER_1:  He's not an apparel.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think we'd have to pay.
SPEAKER_1:  me.
SPEAKER_1:  hard hitting.
SPEAKER_0:  to get your questions.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  With these international payments, you face all sorts of...
SPEAKER_0:  Slow.
SPEAKER_0:  fees and you face like kind of like this time thing.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's this painful process.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  If I use different cryptocurrencies, some of them are like really fast, some of them have really low fees.
SPEAKER_0:  I just believe in a world where
SPEAKER_0:  digital currencies with fast payments with cheap payments.
SPEAKER_0:  Revolutionize.
SPEAKER_0:  the global exchange of currency.
SPEAKER_0:  And I don't know if this.
SPEAKER_0:  if this is going to include the blockchain.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just that the blockchain is the first thing that's really embraced truly digital currency, which doesn't need to go through this complicated
SPEAKER_0:  system of wire transfers and just happens.
SPEAKER_0:  So I can send you, let's say I wanna send you Ethereum or Bitcoin.
SPEAKER_0:  I can send it to you just as fast.
SPEAKER_0:  If I send you...
SPEAKER_0:  A dollar?
SPEAKER_0:  or
SPEAKER_0:  a billion dollars and I can send it to you just as fast.
SPEAKER_0:  if you're across from me or if you're across the world from me.
SPEAKER_0:  That I think is a...
SPEAKER_0:  step change and easier, faster, better.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of like, just this.
SPEAKER_0:  really basic.
SPEAKER_0:  international payments kind of idea. I think at like its core, if the lowest...
SPEAKER_0:  form use case of cryptocurrencies is that.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it will.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  change the world in some variety. It's just kind of the larger question is, is that technology going to include the blockchain specifically?
SPEAKER_0:  or not.
SPEAKER_0:  The other benefit.
SPEAKER_0:  is transparency.
SPEAKER_0:  which I personally like as an investigator.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just that.
SPEAKER_0:  Previously, it's like hard to describe how...
SPEAKER_0:  Opaque
SPEAKER_0:  our financial system is.
SPEAKER_0:  until you've tried to investigate someone or something.
SPEAKER_0:  Understanding finances, unless you have a subpoena, unless you're like the FBI or like the SEC and you can get a subpoena for someone's finances.
SPEAKER_0:  or you're going through discovery.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't know what someone has.
SPEAKER_0:  You're basically playing poker with everyone and the cards are face down.
SPEAKER_0:  For the first time.
SPEAKER_0:  the blockchain to some extent because there are ways to obfuscate it.
SPEAKER_0:  and in some ways cryptocurrency has enabled more fraud.
SPEAKER_0:  which is kind of this irony.
SPEAKER_0:  But in some ways, it's enabled people to also audit.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot better.
SPEAKER_0:  and in real time, and I think that is a structural change.
SPEAKER_0:  that is fundamentally for the better.
SPEAKER_0:  The question of all this is, do those betters?
SPEAKER_0:  Outway.
SPEAKER_0:  the cons.
SPEAKER_0:  that this introduces.
SPEAKER_0:  and how much can regulation mitigate those cons?
SPEAKER_0:  some of those cons being like fraud, money laundering, all these negative.
SPEAKER_0:  externalities that are easier with cryptocurrency.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think cryptocurrency in particular seems to attract?
SPEAKER_1:  fraudulent people.
SPEAKER_1:  like scammers and fraudsters.
SPEAKER_0:  Because it's unregulated, it's the Wild West, and you can transmit large amounts of money very quickly across the world.
SPEAKER_0:  What about with very little?
SPEAKER_1:  creating new crypto projects like new coins
SPEAKER_0:  uh, because you have to show very little actual use case. You can just promise. This is like true of any emerging technology.
SPEAKER_0:  So much vaporware happens at the beginning when it's all promise.
SPEAKER_0:  because fundamentally, let's say you're legitimate, I'm illegitimate.
SPEAKER_0:  we look the same at the start of a technology because both of us are promising what this can do. And in fact,
SPEAKER_0:  the less scruples and morals I have, in some ways I can out-compete you. Cause I can say, mine does what Lexus does, but like way better and way faster, and it's gonna happen in a year rather than 10 years.
SPEAKER_0:  You're being honest, I'm playing a dishonest game, I look better.
SPEAKER_0:  Once this space matures and you actually have some people.
SPEAKER_0:  doing the things that they say they're going to do.
SPEAKER_0:  Suddenly this equation changes. Now you're Amazon, you're delivering in two days. I can say whatever I want.
SPEAKER_0:  you do the thing you do and I have no credibility. So I think that like.
SPEAKER_0:  part of.
SPEAKER_0:  Part of the fraud is.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, just the ability to transmit so much money so quickly with such little oversight.
SPEAKER_0:  Part of it is like, this just happens with any emerging technology.
SPEAKER_0:  Vaporware is a real thing and hopefully...
SPEAKER_0:  as this space matures, as regulation comes in.
SPEAKER_0:  Things will improve.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask you your own psychology.
SPEAKER_1:  You're going after...
SPEAKER_1:  some of the richest, some of the most powerful people in the world, do you worry about?
SPEAKER_1:  your own financial, legal, and psychological well-being.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I do. I mean, I'm not totally oblivious.
SPEAKER_0:  to the precariousness.
SPEAKER_0:  of like
SPEAKER_0:  any kind of journalism like this?
SPEAKER_0:  Obviously there's risks.
SPEAKER_0:  I've always believed.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a quote and I'm going to butcher it, but I hope you guys understand the spirit of it.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, news is when you print something someone else doesn't want you to print, everything else is public relations.
SPEAKER_0:  I really believe to do meaningful journalism.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to go after people. Like it's not.
SPEAKER_0:  inherently a safe profession.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, if you're gonna do important work.
SPEAKER_0:  you have to have risk tolerances.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think everyone has a line of what that risk tolerance is.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's different for everyone.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think I could do what Edward Snowden did.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that would be my bright red line, is going against my own government.
SPEAKER_0:  It's such a...
SPEAKER_0:  In my opinion, I really see him as a hero. Like it's such a selfless act.
SPEAKER_0:  of self destruction, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  that the-
SPEAKER_0:  the party you're going after has all the power and will CRUSH you!
SPEAKER_0:  and you do it anyway out of the like-
SPEAKER_0:  the true.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, platonic ideal of journalism. I think that's beautiful. I don't think I could do that. I think I need-
SPEAKER_0:  some ability to live and subsist in the society that I...
SPEAKER_0:  MN
SPEAKER_0:  And I think my bright red line would be like, if I'm forced to flee the country for my work, I think I'd finally have to say...
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  for as journalists go, I'm pretty risk.
SPEAKER_0:  take risk pretty well.
SPEAKER_0:  I especially think risk is important to take when you're young.
SPEAKER_0:  And when you can do that, I think...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I'm married, so when I have a family, I think I will probably dial this risk.
SPEAKER_0:  Think down.
SPEAKER_0:  being honest, I mean, I think you kind of have to.
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  But right now, I mean, I'm kind of like running on all cylinders. I'm willing to take on quite a-
SPEAKER_0:  Quite a range of people.
SPEAKER_0:  But, um...
SPEAKER_1:  Well, you're also- I think a lot about it.
SPEAKER_1:  Wolfpack of one.
SPEAKER_1:  small.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, Wolfpack.
SPEAKER_1:  as opposed to having like a New York Times behind you or.
SPEAKER_1:  a huge organizations with lawyers, with a team, with a history with
SPEAKER_0:  These people are less
SPEAKER_0:  This is the dirty truth.
SPEAKER_0:  The bigger the organization, the more conservative a lot of them are. It's true that sometimes they like
SPEAKER_0:  And this is not to bash big organizations. I'm just saying this as an observation.
SPEAKER_0:  of someone who's talked to a lot of.
SPEAKER_0:  people.
SPEAKER_0:  and especially in the world of fraud.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of them are scared to engage.
SPEAKER_0:  in fraud that is obvious but hasn't been litigated yet.
SPEAKER_0:  This is why you'll never see documentaries about ongoing fraud on Netflix.
SPEAKER_0:  It's too much of a liability.
SPEAKER_0:  They'll sue Netflix to hell.
SPEAKER_0:  and they know that if they win, Netflix has the money to pay it.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  corporations like the New York Times, a lot of these.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of them are very like they're as courageous as they can be but at the bottom line if someone sues you to hell and back
SPEAKER_0:  and you have to pay up, you will disappear.
SPEAKER_0:  and you're relying on liability insurance, which you're already paying out the ass for.
SPEAKER_0:  to try to cover you if you get sued. But if you get sued, even if you win, that liability insurance now goes up in price the next year.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you're the New York Times, it goes up by a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I think there's work that independent journalists can do.
SPEAKER_0:  uniquely that
SPEAKER_0:  they can actually take like in some ways more risk.
SPEAKER_0:  than a giant institution, which has a lot more, in my sense, to lose, even though it would appear like they have more in terms of defense too.
SPEAKER_1:  Get, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  You can be bullied legally. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  You get.
SPEAKER_1:  Afraid of that?
SPEAKER_0:  Sure, I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  i'd just uh...
SPEAKER_0:  All these things are things you have to be aware of and then forget to do your job.
SPEAKER_0:  Like you have to be, you know, it's like, it's like being like a snowboarder and it's like, do you realize you could hit your head?
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like, yeah, of course, but in order to go do the, like the flip or whatever, you have to just accept the risk.
SPEAKER_0:  mitigate the risk as much as possible and move on. So I wanted toㅠㅠ
SPEAKER_0:  We have like
SPEAKER_0:  Insurance
SPEAKER_0:  We keep.
SPEAKER_0:  like a pool of funds for that kind of thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Like I'm very conservative with how I spend my money basically all on.
SPEAKER_0:  production and like
SPEAKER_0:  trying to make my life as secure as I can.
SPEAKER_0:  And then I just do the work that I...
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  I want to do because...
SPEAKER_1:  So 99% of your fund goes into the studio.
SPEAKER_1:  and then into that elaborate space of yours. Yeah, of course.
SPEAKER_1:  How many kittens had to die to manufacture that studio? But anyway, that's my investigation for later.
SPEAKER_1:  What keeps you mentally strong?
SPEAKER_1:  all of this.
SPEAKER_1:  What's your source of mental strength, of your psychological strength through this?
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh...
SPEAKER_0:  I think there was a time when I was getting a lot of cease and desists.
SPEAKER_0:  Some people were like actually like.
SPEAKER_0:  like saying like they're gonna show up to my house, other kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think I was that. I think I was pretty worried about that for a while. My wife was.
SPEAKER_0:  huge source of strength here.
SPEAKER_0:  where she was like, hey.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're not comfortable with it, you need to get out of the game.
SPEAKER_0:  or you need to.
SPEAKER_0:  basically like suck it up and
SPEAKER_0:  Like this is what it is.
SPEAKER_0:  if you're gonna go after these people.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically...
SPEAKER_0:  um, be mentally strong around this.
SPEAKER_0:  And seeing her...
SPEAKER_0:  have that realization helped me have the same realization.
SPEAKER_0:  and I really deeply admire and respect that about her.
SPEAKER_0:  And it
SPEAKER_0:  solved a lot of my concerns around that.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just, it just made me realize.
SPEAKER_0:  Every profession has risks.
SPEAKER_0:  It is what it is, you mitigate and then you move on.
SPEAKER_1:  Why do you think there are so few journalists like you?
SPEAKER_1:  You're basically the embodiment, at least in the space you operate, of what great journalism should be.
SPEAKER_1:  Why do you think there's very few like you?
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  Such an enormous compliment and probably overstatement.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  I first want to pay respect.
SPEAKER_0:  are a lot of great journalists, and a lot of them
SPEAKER_0:  are
SPEAKER_0:  I don't wanna just kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  take it and go, yeah, you know, it's just me. There's so many great journalists.
SPEAKER_0:  Matt Levine, Kelsey Piper.
SPEAKER_0:  You've got anonymous journalists like Dirty Bubble. You've got citizen journalists like Tiffany Fong.
SPEAKER_0:  But! But!
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're gonna be in this space in the long term, you do need to accept certain risks.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think in the long term, it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know how easy it is to play that game for a long period of time.
SPEAKER_0:  because you make.
SPEAKER_0:  To do great journalism, you don't get paid a lot, compared to what you could get paid if you did.
SPEAKER_0:  press pieces or anything like that.
SPEAKER_0:  You take a lot of risks legally, you take physical risks, you take...
SPEAKER_0:  It's just like.
SPEAKER_0:  If you care about money,
SPEAKER_0:  It's not the profession.
SPEAKER_0:  and I feel like...
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of people, when they get notoriety, they move to like, well, I can just maximize.
SPEAKER_0:  the money security side of things?
SPEAKER_0:  And I think it.
SPEAKER_0:  takes out a lot of would-be great journalists.
SPEAKER_1:  And also, so first of all, comfort of all.
SPEAKER_1:  of physical and mental wellbeing. Yes. Also being invited to parties with powerful people.
SPEAKER_1:  You
SPEAKER_1:  You make enemies, rich and powerful enemies doing this.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  But that's why I mix it.
SPEAKER_1:  That's why it's admirable.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  You know it's it's an interesting case study.
SPEAKER_1:  that you've been doing it as long as you have.
SPEAKER_1:  and I hope you keep doing it, but it's just interesting that it's rare.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll say.
SPEAKER_0:  I wanna make a call like.
SPEAKER_0:  I think societies can.
SPEAKER_0:  Create.
SPEAKER_0:  better journalists and worse journalists.
SPEAKER_0:  in so far as they...
SPEAKER_0:  support the journalists who are doing great work.
SPEAKER_0:  And I want to call out Edward Snowden specifically.
SPEAKER_0:  because what we have done to him is such a travesty.
SPEAKER_0:  And the only lesson you can learn if you're a logical human being
SPEAKER_0:  is that you should never whistle blow on the United States government after looking at what they did to Snowden.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  As a society.
SPEAKER_0:  We can put pressure on lawmakers to make it easier for people to do the great work.
SPEAKER_0:  by not punishing the people who do great work, if that makes sense, and de-risking it for them.
SPEAKER_0:  because we shouldn't expect journalists to be martyrs to do great work.
SPEAKER_0:  right? To do important work.
SPEAKER_0:  And part of that comes from protecting whistleblowers.
SPEAKER_0:  There's like very common sense things.
SPEAKER_0:  I love like-
SPEAKER_0:  It's great to.
SPEAKER_0:  Heroicize, you know people like Edwards known and stuff like that, but we shouldn't expect them to be heroes to do that work
SPEAKER_1:  Do you ever think about going?
SPEAKER_1:  even focused on financial fraud.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you ever think about going after other centers of power?
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, like.
SPEAKER_1:  government Excerpts
SPEAKER_1:  Politics.
SPEAKER_0:  Politics, it seems to me, you can't do good work.
SPEAKER_0:  um...
SPEAKER_0:  Like everybody doing good work in politics is to some extent.
SPEAKER_0:  from my limited perspective, as I said, not that into it.
SPEAKER_0:  It seems like.
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone has to take a side.
SPEAKER_0:  Because even if you do great work...
SPEAKER_0:  whoever you're exposing.
SPEAKER_0:  Half the other people, no matter how good your work is, are going to claim it's just for partisan hackery.
SPEAKER_0:  and they're going to malign you?
SPEAKER_0:  So it seems like.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of journalists have to take.
SPEAKER_0:  a slant, even if it's not explicit like bias.
SPEAKER_0:  They have to take a slant on who they expose. I hate that. I would really like a world where-
SPEAKER_0:  you could freely expose.
SPEAKER_0:  both sides.
SPEAKER_0:  without having a constant.
SPEAKER_0:  malignment of like, you know
SPEAKER_0:  who are you working for or you did this for XYZ or whatever like
SPEAKER_0:  I really find that.
SPEAKER_0:  deeply problematic about our current, like.
SPEAKER_0:  journalism in the political sphere.
SPEAKER_0:  As far as government stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's easy to do, not easy, but like it's.
SPEAKER_0:  much more.
SPEAKER_0:  enticing to do foreign journalism?
SPEAKER_0:  than to do local journalism.
SPEAKER_0:  on positions of power.
SPEAKER_0:  Because if you question...
SPEAKER_0:  It's so easy to just get.
SPEAKER_0:  The bigger cases you expose locally, your...
SPEAKER_0:  you get in danger.
SPEAKER_0:  because it's just very clear cut.
SPEAKER_0:  bigger the case.
SPEAKER_0:  the more your financial wellbeing, your access to your entire life is like sort of in jeopardy.
SPEAKER_0:  Whereas if you do foreign journalism, you can do great work.
SPEAKER_0:  and largely you're protected by your own.
SPEAKER_0:  government.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's kind of this weird thing where if you want great journalism on America...
SPEAKER_0:  Sometimes going abroad might be...
SPEAKER_1:  But the politician thing that's interesting, you mentioned that and going abroad.
SPEAKER_1:  I think the way you think about your current work, I think applies in great journalism and in politics as well.
SPEAKER_1:  So what happens, I have that sense.
SPEAKER_1:  because I aspire to be like you in the sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  in the conversation space of like with politicians, I tried to talk to people on the left and the right.
SPEAKER_1:  and do so in a nonpartisan way and criticize but also steelman their cases.
SPEAKER_1:  What happens of learned?
SPEAKER_1:  As you can talk to somebody on the right.
SPEAKER_1:  the right kind of brings you in. Like yes, we'll keep you comfortable.
SPEAKER_1:  Come with us and then the left attacks you.
SPEAKER_1:  It's so.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... in the same happens on life talk a lot the right attacks you you know left they come with us
SPEAKER_1:  So like there's a.
SPEAKER_1:  there's a temptation, a momentum to staying to that one side, whatever that side is.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm the same with foreign journalism. You can cover Putin critically.
SPEAKER_1:  there's a strong pull to being.
SPEAKER_1:  pro Ukraine, pro Zelensky, pro...
SPEAKER_1:  basically really covering in a favorable way to the point of propaganda, to the point of PR.
SPEAKER_1:  the Zelensky regime.
SPEAKER_1:  If you criticize the Lensky regime, there's a strong pull.
SPEAKER_1:  towards then being supportive of.
SPEAKER_1:  not necessarily the Putin regime, but a very different perspective on it, which is like
SPEAKER_1:  NATO is the one that-
SPEAKER_1:  created that war. There's narratives that pull you and what I think a great journalist does.
SPEAKER_1:  is make enemies and plus size.
SPEAKER_1:  and walk through that fire and not get...
SPEAKER_1:  pulled in to the protection of anyone's side.
SPEAKER_1:  because they get so harshly attacked. Anytime they deviate.
SPEAKER_0:  the center. I think also like.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a criticism of all centrists.
SPEAKER_0:  which I think in some way is fair. And I say that to someone largely who's disinterested.
SPEAKER_0:  which is that this what about is, or like this.
SPEAKER_0:  What about the left? What about the right?
SPEAKER_0:  can skew.
SPEAKER_0:  when it's not a one, it's not a both sides issue.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  In the case of Russia, Ukraine, I think I'm strongly in favor of Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  even though I tend to go like on both sides. And that might be partly because one of my employees is Ukrainian.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think...
SPEAKER_0:  what a great journalist does, especially like in politics.
SPEAKER_0:  is I think they criticize.
SPEAKER_0:  the regime that's most in power.
SPEAKER_0:  most of it controls the keys and is the most corrupt at that time.
SPEAKER_0:  and they might appear to be like, let's say during the realm of Trump.
SPEAKER_0:  a great journalist would criticize Trump.
SPEAKER_0:  But that same journalist who held Trump's feet to the fire should be capable of holding Biden's feet to the fire.
SPEAKER_0:  four years later.
SPEAKER_0:  If that kind of makes sense.
SPEAKER_1:  Exactly right, yeah. Yeah
SPEAKER_1:  So any
SPEAKER_1:  uh... revealing any so attacking any power center
SPEAKER_1:  for the corruption for the flaws they have.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... you respect
SPEAKER_0:  of like your
SPEAKER_0:  political agenda or your political ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so that and that's what I mean about sort of the war in Ukraine. There's several
SPEAKER_1:  players.
SPEAKER_1:  NATO.
SPEAKER_1:  Russia.
SPEAKER_1:  Ukraine
SPEAKER_1:  China.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh
SPEAKER_1:  India.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, there's several less important players, maybe some of the like Iran and
SPEAKER_1:  like Israel and maybe Africa.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  what great journalism takes.
SPEAKER_1:  requires is basically revealing the flaws of each one of those players.
SPEAKER_1:  irrespective of the attacks you get. And you're right that-
SPEAKER_1:  throughout any particular situation.
SPEAKER_1:  There is some-
SPEAKER_1:  some parties that are worse than others and you have to...
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  weigh your perspective accordingly. But also it requires you to be fearless in certain things. Like for example,
SPEAKER_1:  I don't even know.
SPEAKER_1:  what it's like to be a journalist covering China.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, that's an exact case of like
SPEAKER_0:  China has made it so difficult to be a good journalist.
SPEAKER_0:  that they've effectively squashed criticism because
SPEAKER_0:  To be a journalist in China means constantly risking.
SPEAKER_0:  your life every single day.
SPEAKER_0:  to criticize that government.
SPEAKER_0:  And so the best journalists are a lot of times outside the country.
SPEAKER_0:  or they have sources inside the country who are like there's like this
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  different, there's layers to the journalism where there's insiders.
SPEAKER_0:  who are leaking information, but they themselves cannot publish because it's like, it's-
SPEAKER_0:  You know it's.
SPEAKER_0:  It's extremely risky, so.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think as a society...
SPEAKER_0:  one measure of
SPEAKER_0:  how healthy.
SPEAKER_0:  the political structure is.
SPEAKER_0:  is how well you can criticize it without fearing for your safety.
SPEAKER_1:  In that sense, the chaos and the bickering going on in the United States politics is a good thing.
SPEAKER_1:  that people can.
SPEAKER_1:  criticized very harshly. Very harsh. And be, in terms of safety, are pretty safe.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, absolutely.
SPEAKER_0:  I think our only challenge is like...
SPEAKER_0:  where it gets dangerous is around like top secret information.
SPEAKER_0:  The government comes down so hard.
SPEAKER_0:  that
SPEAKER_0:  The danger in covering politics here is...
SPEAKER_0:  You can expose something that's top secret that should be exposed.
SPEAKER_1:  and they'll ruin you.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's where you again give props to Snowden.
SPEAKER_1:  for stepping up. 100.
SPEAKER_0:  percent.
SPEAKER_0:  100%.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the origin of...
SPEAKER_1:  the suspender wearing Batman.
SPEAKER_1:  How did you come to do what you do? Like we talked about where you are and how your mind works, but how did it start?
SPEAKER_0:  kind of always been interested in fraud or...
SPEAKER_0:  Or at least I saw fraud early on and I was just like curious about what is this? I didn't know what I was really looking at.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, my mom got cancer when I was...
SPEAKER_0:  in high school and
SPEAKER_0:  It was pretty traumatic. I mean, she's fine. I mean, she's got thyroid cancer, which is-
SPEAKER_0:  We didn't know it at the time. It's like cancer's cancer.
SPEAKER_0:  fairly easily treatable with surgery.
SPEAKER_0:  It's one of the better.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, survivable ones.
SPEAKER_0:  And I just watched her get like bombarded with all these like phony health scams of, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  like colloidal silver, all these different remedies.
SPEAKER_0:  And she was very into, you know, all the...
SPEAKER_0:  different ways that she might treat her cancer. Obviously surgery is very daunting.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I was just confused. I was like, why are we doing so many different...
SPEAKER_0:  remedies that all seem a very dubious health value.
SPEAKER_0:  Later I'd find out that these are like all grifters. I mean, they take advantage of...
SPEAKER_0:  free speech in America to advertise their products as
SPEAKER_0:  you know, life-saving miracles, whatever, when they're, of course, not.
SPEAKER_0:  Eventually she got the surgery, thank God, but...
SPEAKER_0:  I know people in my life who...
SPEAKER_0:  Parents passed away because they didn't have the surgery. They instead...
SPEAKER_0:  took the alternative option. i know Deepak and I think that was the only option.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't want to go into specifics because I don't want to mention their specific case, but-
SPEAKER_0:  They're...
SPEAKER_0:  Family member went to Mexico for some alternate treatment, health treatment, instead of getting an easy surgery, and they died.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  I realized, you know, where is the outrage about this? Where's the-
SPEAKER_0:  who covers this stuff and I realized, well, not many people do. Then I went to college, I was getting a chemical engineering degree.
SPEAKER_0:  and all my friends were like telling me.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, hey, you should come to this meeting.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, we don't need this.
SPEAKER_0:  You're doing this engineering stuff, that's great. You're going to make like 70k a year.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't you want to get like rich now? Like why wait till you're 60 years old to retire? Like you can be rich now Lex.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I'd go show up to a hotel.
SPEAKER_0:  and there'd be an MLM.
SPEAKER_0:  like multi-level marketing pitch for.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Amway or whatever it was that day.
SPEAKER_0:  And...
SPEAKER_0:  I was once again fascinated. I didn't know what I was looking at, but I was like, what is this weird game we're all playing where we sit in this room?
SPEAKER_0:  We're looking at the speaker who says he's so successful, but why is he taking a Friday?
SPEAKER_0:  or a Saturday to do this pitch at night.
SPEAKER_0:  And they're gonna telling me I'm gonna be financially free, but they're working on their Saturday and Sunday.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it's like, how financially free are they?
SPEAKER_0:  So I was just like confused. I was like, you know, none of my friends were rich. They all said they were gonna be rich. No one ever seemed to get rich.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I was sort of baffled by what I was looking at.
SPEAKER_0:  Later, I graduate.
SPEAKER_0:  I had no interest in doing engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  which we can kind of get into, but I want to do something in media.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and I started covering a variety of topics, but eventually...
SPEAKER_0:  I sort of revisited this interest in fraud and I started.
SPEAKER_0:  talking about these kind of get-rich-quick grifters that were online.
SPEAKER_0:  sort of the Tai Lopez variety, you know, 67 steps or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  5 steps to get rich, 5 coins to 5 million, you know, these get rich quick schemes.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of people were interested in.
SPEAKER_0:  No one seemed to get rich once again except for the people at the tippity tippity top selling the get rich quick thing.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was like fascinated by the structure of it. And I was like, does nobody see what this is? Like, does nobody get it?
SPEAKER_0:  So I started making a series of videos on that.
SPEAKER_0:  And the response was palpable. I mean, it was like, I've made a lot of stuff before that. I had made stuff that got-
SPEAKER_0:  A million views.
SPEAKER_0:  I'd had some marginal success.
SPEAKER_0:  The response.
SPEAKER_0:  of like the emails that came in, the...
SPEAKER_0:  I could tell this work.
SPEAKER_0:  even though it had far less
SPEAKER_0:  views at the time.
SPEAKER_0:  was having a different level of impact.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what I was really interested in.
SPEAKER_0:  One of my.
SPEAKER_0:  problems with engineering was
SPEAKER_0:  from my.
SPEAKER_0:  standpoint, I did chemical engineering at Texas A&M.
SPEAKER_0:  And like, I was like, is my future just gonna be in a chemical plant improving some process by 2%?
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like my-
SPEAKER_0:  gift to the world. Just you
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't see the hard impact.
SPEAKER_0:  And that maybe that's a lack of imagination because chemicals matter, but-
SPEAKER_0:  I needed, I wanted to see an impact in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  And so when like...
SPEAKER_0:  I did start doing this fraud stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  exposing fraud, I clicked in my brain, I was like, whoa.
SPEAKER_0:  This is kind of doing what I want to do.
SPEAKER_0:  And so...
SPEAKER_0:  I started posting videos. At first, it really focused on like...
SPEAKER_0:  Get Rich, Quick Scheme, Grifty Advertising.
SPEAKER_0:  which I think is super predatory and we can go into.
SPEAKER_0:  Why? But, um...
SPEAKER_0:  It eventually graduated to crypto and
SPEAKER_0:  It snowballed, I guess, because now we're talking Samrsambhackinstbutton.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, grifty advertising.
SPEAKER_1:  So actually, just to step back, what is a multi-level marketing scheme?
SPEAKER_1:  What?
SPEAKER_1:  because I've experienced a similar thing. I remember,
SPEAKER_1:  I worked at, I sold women's shoes at Sears.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, and a bank and I just remember like.
SPEAKER_1:  Some kind of forgot the name of the company, but you'd like you can sell like knives or whatever. Like that's a couple of come
SPEAKER_0:  I know what you're talking about. I'm-
SPEAKER_1:  I'm sure there's a lot of things like this, right? And I remember feeling a similar thing like why?
SPEAKER_1:  To me, what was fascinating about it is like...
SPEAKER_1:  Wow, like human civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  is interesting like a pyramid scheme.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I didn't maybe didn't know the words for that.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's like, it's cool. Like you can like.
SPEAKER_1:  get in a room, you convince each other of ideas, and you have these ambitions, there's a general desire, especially when you're young.
SPEAKER_1:  to like.
SPEAKER_1:  Like life sucks right now.
SPEAKER_1:  Nobody respects you. You have no money.
SPEAKER_1:  You want to do good and you want to be sold this dream of like
SPEAKER_1:  If I work hard enough at this weird thing, I can shortcut and get to the very top. Yes. I don't know what that is and it was.
SPEAKER_1:  I also in me felt that like life really sucks and I could.
SPEAKER_1:  Do good.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm lucky. I found a way to do good. I'm like.
SPEAKER_1:  And I don't know, you connect with us somehow. I think there's like this weird fire inside people to like.
SPEAKER_1:  to make better of themselves, right? I don't know if it's just an American thing or if it's-
SPEAKER_1:  But anyway, that was fascinating to me from a human nature perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  Grifters play on this though, right? Like this is-
SPEAKER_0:  So the
SPEAKER_0:  best salesman play on true narratives.
SPEAKER_0:  that you already believe.
SPEAKER_0:  So the true narrative is.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, life is unfair.
SPEAKER_0:  It is tough.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  The American Dream as described by GoToAJob.
SPEAKER_0:  work at the same company for 40 years and then retire to a safety net that you're positive is gonna be there, that is largely dead. And so they like play on those fears.
SPEAKER_0:  and those problems to then sell you a pill, a solution, a thing. And the problem is that the solution is usually worse.
SPEAKER_0:  than even the problem they sketched out. Like you will do better.
SPEAKER_0:  most of the time by going with the regular company than you will by going with these goofy multi-level marketing. But let me answer your question. What is a multi-level marketing?
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a criticism, first of all, that, well, let me get to what it is in theory.
SPEAKER_0:  at its most ideal.
SPEAKER_0:  Multi-level marketing.
SPEAKER_0:  is where you have a product that you're selling.
SPEAKER_0:  and one of the ways you help sell it.
SPEAKER_0:  is by rather than going through traditional marketing.
SPEAKER_0:  like where you go and you...
SPEAKER_0:  put out print advertising.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like sort of a social network of marketing.
SPEAKER_0:  I sell to you.
SPEAKER_0:  And then actually Lex, not only can I sell to you, you can then go sell this product and you'll make money selling it.
SPEAKER_0:  And you know what, to incentivize me to get other salesmen, because when I get another salesman, I'm actually giving myself competition.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's bad.
SPEAKER_0:  So to incentivize me to do that, they'll pay me part of what you make.
SPEAKER_0:  and then you go out and you go, okay, well I can sell this product, I also can get new salesmen to like sell for me.
SPEAKER_0:  and I'm gonna make money from you, whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  So it goes down the line of you create multiple levels where you can profit from their marketing.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  problem with this system.
SPEAKER_0:  is that however well intentioned it is.
SPEAKER_0:  is that usually the emphasis of that selling.
SPEAKER_0:  and making money?
SPEAKER_0:  ends up not being about the product at all.
SPEAKER_0:  and ends up entirely being about.
SPEAKER_0:  Recruiting new people to recruit new people to recruit new people
SPEAKER_0:  That's the real way to make money in multi-level marketing.
SPEAKER_0:  This is where the very true criticism of
SPEAKER_0:  Most multi-level marketing, if not all, are pyramid schemes in structure.
SPEAKER_0:  because what a pyramid scheme is, is it's all about.
SPEAKER_0:  I put in $500.
SPEAKER_0:  and I recruit two people to put in $500 and that comes up to me and they get two people to put in $500 and it goes to them. And the reason it's a flawed business model is.
SPEAKER_0:  In order for it to work and everyone to make money, you'd have to assume an infinite human race.
SPEAKER_0:  And so that's not the case. Most people end up getting screwed in multi-level marketing and in pyramid schemes.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what that is. That's that thing.
SPEAKER_1:  and the quality of the product, it doesn't necessarily matter where you're selling.
SPEAKER_0:  people who are financially incentivized to like
SPEAKER_0:  Buy this thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and so you're...
SPEAKER_1:  You're selling the dream of becoming rich to the people down in the pyramid.
SPEAKER_0:  that's the real product of multi-level marketing. Unfortunately,
SPEAKER_0:  And so you look at the statistics of these companies.
SPEAKER_0:  and although they'll make it seem like it's so easy to be the top.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, 0.1% who's making all this money.
SPEAKER_0:  The statistics are that 97% make less than a minimum wage.
SPEAKER_0:  doing this. They spend an enormous amount of time.
SPEAKER_0:  And just what's so cruel about it is that's not advertised up front.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's like, if I go at work at McDonald's, I know what I'm getting.
SPEAKER_0:  If I go work at Amway, I have visions of, they've sold me visions of...
SPEAKER_0:  beaches and whatever and
SPEAKER_0:  more than likely I'm losing money.
SPEAKER_0:  So better than 50% of people lose money, but 97% of people make less than minimum wage. It's like-
SPEAKER_0:  It's such a bad business.
SPEAKER_0:  for the vast majority of people.
SPEAKER_0:  who join it?
SPEAKER_0:  and the
SPEAKER_0:  people at the very top.
SPEAKER_0:  who are lying to the people at the bottom saying they all can do it when they can't
SPEAKER_0:  are making all the money. TIT Â° TITTO
SPEAKER_0:  It's yeah, it's really messed up.
SPEAKER_1:  And the interesting thing I've noticed, maybe myself too, because I've participated in the knife selling for like a short amount of time. That's probably the experience that most people have. Cutco, is it?
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, I don't think it was quite good.
SPEAKER_0:  I know what you're talking about.
SPEAKER_1:  But I think there's several variations of it. I think I was part of a
SPEAKER_1:  uh... let less popular one
SPEAKER_1:  It doesn't.
SPEAKER_1:  I keep wanting to say it was called vector. yup
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, something with a V was what I was gonna say. It might be Vector. Yeah, I get what you're saying though. It's a multi-level marketing knife selling.
SPEAKER_1:  The thing is, I just remember...
SPEAKER_1:  my own small experience with it.
SPEAKER_1:  I was too embarrassed at myself for having like...
SPEAKER_1:  Participate it.
SPEAKER_1:  I think there's an embarrassment. That's why people down in the pyramid don't like.
SPEAKER_1:  Speak about it, right?
SPEAKER_1:  that your part like.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm trying to understand the aspects of human nature that facilitate this.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, this is one of the problems with fraud is there's a tremendous embarrassment to being had.
SPEAKER_0:  Also, if you buy, so.
SPEAKER_0:  slightly different human nature is that if you buy into a get rich quick scheme
SPEAKER_0:  and then it doesn't deliver, you're more likely to blame yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  than blame the product for not actually working. You go, well, there must be something flawed with me. That's true, yes, exactly. And they constantly reinforce this. They go, well, it's all about your hard work. The system works, look at me, I did it. So if you're failing, it must be some indictment of your character.
SPEAKER_0:  and you have to always double down. The system can't be flawed, you must be flawed.
SPEAKER_0:  And so yeah, it's.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a really messed up system. It really preys on people's psychology to keep them in this loop.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's why in some ways these things are so viral, even though they don't actually get most people a significant amount of wealth.
SPEAKER_0:  and they cost most people money. So,
SPEAKER_0:  It's very unfortunate.
SPEAKER_1:  Most people do have the dream of becoming rich.
SPEAKER_1:  most young people.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, and-
SPEAKER_0:  The thing is that everyone knows in business.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you?
SPEAKER_0:  You sell. You sell solutions to problems.
SPEAKER_0:  of so many young people want to get rich.
SPEAKER_0:  The product is.
SPEAKER_0:  It's you sell them the dream.
SPEAKER_0:  why this gets so grifty and so-
SPEAKER_0:  cruel and predatory.
SPEAKER_0:  is because there is no easy solution to this. There is no solution that people are going to buy.
SPEAKER_0:  Because the real solution people want is...
SPEAKER_0:  No work, no education, no skills required.
SPEAKER_0:  No money upfront.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  People will pay any price for that magic pill.
SPEAKER_0:  and people are happy to sell that magic pill.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think those people are very cruel.
SPEAKER_0:  and I think deserve to get exposed.
SPEAKER_1:  posed for it.
SPEAKER_1:  So somebody...
SPEAKER_1:  that's been criticized for.
SPEAKER_1:  MLM type schemes is Andrew Tate.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, somebody that I'm.
SPEAKER_1:  very likely to.
SPEAKER_1:  talk with people who have been.
SPEAKER_1:  telling me that I'm too afraid to talk to Andrew Tate. First, let me just say...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not a f-
SPEAKER_1:  afraid to talk to anyone.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just that certain people require preparation and you have to allocate.
SPEAKER_1:  your life in such a way that you want to prepare properly for them. Sure. And you have to kind of think.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  who you want to prepare for because I have other folks that have more power.
SPEAKER_1:  than this particular figure that I'm preparing for. So you have to make sure you, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  allocate your time.
SPEAKER_1:  wisely but i do think he's a very influential person
SPEAKER_1:  that raises questions of what it means to be a man in the 21st century.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  And that's a very important and interesting question.
SPEAKER_1:  because young people look up.
SPEAKER_1:  to philosophers, to influencers about what it means to be a man.
SPEAKER_1:  They look up to Jordan Peterson, they look up to Andrew Tate, they look up to others, to other figures. I think it's important to...
SPEAKER_1:  Talk about that to think what does it mean to be a good man in the society?
SPEAKER_1:  Of course, in the other gender, there's the same question. What does it mean to be a good woman?
SPEAKER_1:  I think obviously the bigger question is what does it mean to
SPEAKER_1:  be a good
SPEAKER_1:  person.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Hehehe
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, did now intro. Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, so on that said, one aspect of the criticism that Andrew's received is not just on massaging.
SPEAKER_1:  is on the MLM aspect.
SPEAKER_1:  of the multi-
SPEAKER_1:  level marketing schemes. So is there some truth to that? Is there some fraudulent aspect to that?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I definitely think so. I mean, that's the main reason I criticized him.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's back up.
SPEAKER_0:  there's a few clarifications I need to make.
SPEAKER_0:  What Andrew Tate is selling is not.
SPEAKER_0:  multi-level marketing, although he is selling the dream.
SPEAKER_0:  he's selling an affiliate marketing thing, which is slightly different.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  In multi-level marketing, if I sell to you and then you go sell to two other people, I make money from those two other people down the chain. Multi-level.
SPEAKER_0:  Affiliate marketing is sort of like one level. I only make-
SPEAKER_0:  Money.
SPEAKER_0:  So Andrew Tate had this affiliate program where, if you sold Hustlers University,
SPEAKER_0:  to somebody else.
SPEAKER_0:  which sounds like something people would, boomers would put on Facebook in like 2010, like I went to Hustlers University. School of Hardbite.
SPEAKER_1:  By the way, you...
SPEAKER_1:  Or hunterjobs.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I joined. I became a hustler. That's in large part due to my...
SPEAKER_0:  Why I'm so successful is because of my Hustler University membership.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm just kidding. Um, but-
SPEAKER_0:  So it's an affiliate program. So you'd sell, like I sell to you this $50 course and I make like $5 and Andrew Tate.
SPEAKER_0:  in perpetuity makes $50 a month off of you.
SPEAKER_0:  What does this course actually sell, right? Because ultimately he's selling the dream. He's selling, hey,
SPEAKER_0:  The Matrix has enslaved you. He's really gone down this like neo rabbit hole.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, so the matrix has enslaved you.
SPEAKER_0:  Your life is controlled by these people who want to keep you kind of weak.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  lazy, whatever, you need a breakout and you need to achieve.
SPEAKER_0:  the new dream which is sort of like.
SPEAKER_0:  hustling your way to the top. You don't need the antiquated systems of.
SPEAKER_0:  of school, you can just pay me $50 a month and I will teach you everything. Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  So what do you actually get?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, and why is it a scam? So you actually, I think it's just a scam in terms of like value and like you're selling based on these completely unrealistic things. Like let's get rich.
SPEAKER_0:  Get a series of Discord rooms.
SPEAKER_0:  You know what Discord, most people know what Discord is. It's like a bunch of chat rooms basically, right?
SPEAKER_1:  So it's like AOL or is it like? Yeah, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, right. Well, I'm talking to the guy who...
SPEAKER_0:  to quit Emacs, so I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  There's Discord servers and in these, there's like seven.
SPEAKER_0:  different.
SPEAKER_0:  rooms you can go in, or there's several rooms, and each one is like a different field of making money.
SPEAKER_0:  e-commerce, trading.
SPEAKER_0:  cryptocurrency.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  fulfillment by Amazon.
SPEAKER_0:  like copywriting.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, so I went to all of these, I checked them out.
SPEAKER_0:  I checked all their money making tools.
SPEAKER_0:  The first funny thing is that Andrew Tate is nowhere to be found. The supposed successful guy that you like bought into is nowhere to be found.
SPEAKER_0:  It's these professors.
SPEAKER_0:  that you have now, he has hired and said, these guys are super qualified.
SPEAKER_0:  So like looked up some of what some of these guys have done.
SPEAKER_0:  and some of them have launched like scammy crypto coins.
SPEAKER_0:  the cryptocurrency professor was like shilling a bunch of coins that did bad and then like deleted the tweets I mean just completely
SPEAKER_0:  exactly what you'd expect.
SPEAKER_0:  behind the paywall, it's nothing of substance. you're not going to learn to get rich.
SPEAKER_0:  by escaping the matrix and going to work for Jeff Bezos. Fulfillment by Amazon is not escaping the matrix, right? Like that's not the way to hustle to the top.
SPEAKER_0:  It's literally a field of making money that everyone in the world has access to.
SPEAKER_0:  If you want to differentiate yourself and make money, the first thing you realize is
SPEAKER_0:  going into skill sets that literally anyone with an internet account can do is a bad way to do that because you have to have some differentiating factor to add value.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just such a...
SPEAKER_0:  obvious and complete.
SPEAKER_0:  scam because there is no
SPEAKER_0:  value to this so-called education.
SPEAKER_0:  Professors are crap.
SPEAKER_0:  the advice, they're like hiding some of the bad things they've done and Andretta tastes nowhere to be found. Ultimately, that's why everyone joins.
SPEAKER_0:  What he's done is very interesting because
SPEAKER_0:  and I'll give him credit in his marketing.
SPEAKER_0:  He's been very savvy to like.
SPEAKER_0:  Make the reasons you admire him.
SPEAKER_0:  NOT
SPEAKER_0:  the thing he's sort of selling.
SPEAKER_0:  Which is weird.
SPEAKER_0:  He's selling Get Rich Quick.
SPEAKER_0:  which
SPEAKER_0:  Teams.
SPEAKER_0:  like it relates to his persona.
SPEAKER_0:  but is actually very orthogonal to it.
SPEAKER_0:  His persona is like...
SPEAKER_0:  the tell it how it is.
SPEAKER_0:  Paul Buff, Rich Guy.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like actually.
SPEAKER_0:  his persona that you're buying into, and then he's selling you this thing to the side.
SPEAKER_0:  which when people get in there and they're not delivered on the product.
SPEAKER_0:  he still is those things that you first thought he was. So it's like, I think it's, to some extent, he's made a lot of
SPEAKER_0:  Money.
SPEAKER_0:  by making the thing that he makes money on.
SPEAKER_0:  not the thing he gets.
SPEAKER_0:  so much pushback online for and what he's also loved for.
SPEAKER_0:  So people will push back for his misogyny, but the real way he's making money is just like,
SPEAKER_0:  basic get rich quick schemes that are super obvious to spot, but everyone's distracted by like
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, he said some crazy stuff about women or, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  all these various other scandals he's gotten himself in.
SPEAKER_1:  to get more and more and more attention.
SPEAKER_1:  So with the persona.
SPEAKER_1:  Is the Hustler University still operating?
SPEAKER_0:  I think they've rebranded it. I'm part of their pitch knob.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm like, they put me on as like.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean as like
SPEAKER_0:  The Matrix is trying to take us out, Lex. And then it's me saying like...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, they put me in like saying, I'm part of the matrix. They put me in saying. You know, they put me in saying.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, this guy sucks, you know, I joined, it sucks. And so they'll play that and they do like a bass drop and it's like...
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  don't listen to people like this, dah, dah, dah, dah. I mean, it's, I'm basically like an in-ear little. in co-op-
SPEAKER_1:  the matrix to attack.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes. You're an insider threat that infiltrated. Right?
SPEAKER_1:  being used by the Matrix to attack him.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, to- Everyone who criticizes him is part of the Matrix.
SPEAKER_0:  He won't say who the Matrix is, it's just-
SPEAKER_0:  It's just the shadowy cabal of rich, powerful people.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just like the easy narrative for people who are disaffected and...
SPEAKER_0:  who feel cheated by the system.
SPEAKER_0:  You just collectivize that system and you make it the bad guy and you go, look, look.
SPEAKER_0:  those guys, those guys who have been cheating you.
SPEAKER_0:  They're the bad guys. They want-
SPEAKER_0:  Me.
SPEAKER_0:  Shut up.
SPEAKER_0:  And then now...
SPEAKER_0:  person that
SPEAKER_0:  the people who harmed you, they want this guy shut up, you're gonna listen to him. Jan and Bill and I each asked them some questions.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like the most basic.
SPEAKER_0:  psychological manipulation that everyone seems to constantly fall for, it's
SPEAKER_0:  Really, uh-
SPEAKER_0:  trivial and stupid but-
SPEAKER_1:  Can you still man?
SPEAKER_1:  the case for Hustlers University where
SPEAKER_1:  It's actually.
SPEAKER_1:  giving young people confidence.
SPEAKER_1:  teaching invaluable lessons about like actually incentivizing them to do something like fulfillment by Amazon the basic thing to try it sure to learn about it
SPEAKER_1:  to fail or maybe see like, to try to give a...
SPEAKER_1:  a catalyst and incentive to try these.
SPEAKER_0:  As much as it pains me, I will try to give a uh...
SPEAKER_0:  a succinct.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe Steel Man.
SPEAKER_0:  of it.
SPEAKER_0:  as best as I can thinking that it's such a greft.
SPEAKER_0:  But I think what you would say.
SPEAKER_0:  is that.
SPEAKER_0:  Some people.
SPEAKER_0:  in order to make a change in their life.
SPEAKER_0:  Need A.
SPEAKER_0:  someone who they can look up to.
SPEAKER_0:  and men don't have a lot of like strong role models.
SPEAKER_0:  big male presences in their life.
SPEAKER_0:  who can serve as a proper example.
SPEAKER_0:  So the most charitable interpretation would be.
SPEAKER_0:  Andrew Tate.
SPEAKER_0:  would encourage you to go reach for the stars, I guess.
SPEAKER_0:  My problem is I have a deep, like...
SPEAKER_0:  I have a deep issue with the like.
SPEAKER_0:  Lust and
SPEAKER_0:  greed that centers all these things. It's like this glorification of-
SPEAKER_0:  Wealth equals status, wealth equals good person, wealth and Bugatti equals...
SPEAKER_0:  You are meaningful, you matter.
SPEAKER_0:  And like.
SPEAKER_0:  Dark.
SPEAKER_0:  underlying thing.
SPEAKER_0:  is that.
SPEAKER_0:  None of that.
SPEAKER_0:  None of that matters. It matters that you make a decent living, but
SPEAKER_0:  past.
SPEAKER_0:  Just like that.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the lust for more stuff and the idolization of these people that is just like opulence.
SPEAKER_0:  Is Annette bad?
SPEAKER_0:  So that's like, my steel man has to stop there because I really disagree with like the values that are pushed.
SPEAKER_0:  people like that.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, no, I agree that that's the thing that should be criticized. I shouldn't say it doesn't matter
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's just like an amazing meal.
SPEAKER_1:  at a great restaurant that matters. It's money.
SPEAKER_1:  and Bugatti's.
SPEAKER_1:  for many people make life.
SPEAKER_1:  Beautiful like those are all components, but I think.
SPEAKER_1:  money isn't the you can also enjoy a beautiful life on a hike in nature you can
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot of ways to enjoy life.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  One of the deepest has been tested through time is the intimacy, close connection, friendship with other people or with a loved one. They don't talk about like.
SPEAKER_1:  Love.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, what it means to be deeply connected with another person.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just like.
SPEAKER_1:  Get women.
SPEAKER_1:  get money, all those kinds of things.
SPEAKER_1:  But that, I think, I don't wanna dismiss that because there's value in that, there's fun in that.
SPEAKER_1:  I think the positive.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't, I haven't.
SPEAKER_1:  investigated at Huston University. But
SPEAKER_1:  The positive I see.
SPEAKER_1:  in general as young people.
SPEAKER_1:  Don't get...
SPEAKER_1:  Much respect from society.
SPEAKER_1:  I know it's easy to call it the matrix and so on, but...
SPEAKER_1:  there's a kind of a
SPEAKER_1:  Dismissal.
SPEAKER_1:  of them as human beings, as capable of contributing, of doing anything special.
SPEAKER_1:  And then here you have young people sitting there broke.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, with big dreams.
SPEAKER_1:  They need the mentors. They need somebody to inspire them. So like.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  I would criticize the flawed nature of the message, but also it's just like, you have to realize like there needs to be.
SPEAKER_1:  institutions.
SPEAKER_1:  or people or influencers that help.
SPEAKER_1:  Inspire, right?
SPEAKER_0:  The problem is though, is the people who are pitching
SPEAKER_0:  unrealistic versions of that.
SPEAKER_0:  are getting a lot of attention.
SPEAKER_0:  Where it's like...
SPEAKER_0:  There's so many great free courses where you can learn everything and more.
SPEAKER_0:  about.
SPEAKER_0:  Filmin by Amazon or about.
SPEAKER_0:  copywriting or all these different things.
SPEAKER_0:  that I think like so often the air is just, the oxygen is sucked up.
SPEAKER_0:  by all the grifters who promise everything. It's back to what we said about vapor wear.
SPEAKER_0:  This is one of the reasons that
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  like educational products.
SPEAKER_0:  can so often be co-opted by grifters.
SPEAKER_0:  Is vaporware is very hard to distinguish?
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  prompt like
SPEAKER_0:  The feedback loop on education is not clear.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not obvious immediately. So I can sell you a book.
SPEAKER_0:  And I can say this is gonna change your life if you apply it.
SPEAKER_0:  If you don't, if your life doesn't change, I just say, well, you didn't apply it, right? Like it's, it's, there's this weird relationship. It's not clear the value. It's not so easy to like quantify education.
SPEAKER_0:  So that gets co-opted by people who make all the promises.
SPEAKER_0:  They get a ton of attention, a ton of money, and then those
SPEAKER_0:  People are often left.
SPEAKER_0:  left confused and like.
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  disillusioned maybe thinking, well, this didn't work.
SPEAKER_0:  in one year, so it's not gonna work at all.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and so I think, yeah, they're
SPEAKER_0:  There are problems there. There's certainly a need for like male role models. There's certainly a need for somebody kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  to speak to.
SPEAKER_0:  a younger generation.
SPEAKER_0:  I just think.
SPEAKER_0:  that person shouldn't.
SPEAKER_0:  shouldn't be maybe Andrew Tate, like personally.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so you have to criticize those particular individuals.
SPEAKER_0:  I also- And yeah, I think the Bugatti aspiration is so stupid.
SPEAKER_1:  Like it's like, it's so... Let me steal man. So I'm a person who doesn't care about money, don't like money.
SPEAKER_1:  Um
SPEAKER_1:  The women.
SPEAKER_1:  maybe I appreciate the beauty of the other sex, but like.
SPEAKER_1:  Cars in particular is like, really, is this really the manifestation of all the highest accomplishments?
SPEAKER_1:  A human being can have a life. Yes, I can criticize all that.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  The to steel man that case is um...
SPEAKER_1:  A young person.
SPEAKER_1:  A dreamer.
SPEAKER_1:  has ambition.
SPEAKER_1:  And I often find that education throughout my whole life.
SPEAKER_1:  There's been people who love me.
SPEAKER_1:  teachers.
SPEAKER_1:  who saw ambition in me.
SPEAKER_1:  and try to reason with me.
SPEAKER_1:  that my ambition is not justified.
SPEAKER_1:  Looking at the data.
SPEAKER_1:  Look, kid.
SPEAKER_1:  You're not that special. Yeah. Look at the data. Right. You're not, and they, they want it. Do they want you to like.
SPEAKER_1:  Not dream, essentially.
SPEAKER_1:  And then again, I look at the data, which is.
SPEAKER_1:  All the people, I just talked to Hajar Gracie.
SPEAKER_1:  Hodge of Gracie is just a person.
SPEAKER_1:  widely acknowledges.
SPEAKER_1:  probably the greatest of all time.
SPEAKER_1:  dominated everybody, but for the longest time he sucked.
SPEAKER_1:  And he's so he was surrounded by people that kind of, you know, don't.
SPEAKER_1:  don't necessarily believe in him, you have to believe in himself.
SPEAKER_1:  It's nice to have somebody I just as older I get and I've seen it.
SPEAKER_1:  It's so powerful to have somebody who comes to you.
SPEAKER_1:  an older person.
SPEAKER_1:  whether it's real or not, that says you got this kid. I believe in you.
SPEAKER_0:  Sure.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah it does, I mean
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I think dreaming is actually-
SPEAKER_0:  really important?
SPEAKER_0:  I'm more protective over...
SPEAKER_0:  people co-op those dreams for money. Yes, yes, absolutely. And like, I do think it matters so much that we encourage people to take risks.
SPEAKER_0:  That's one of the great things about America is it lionizes like sort of people who have taken risks in one.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's just a weird.
SPEAKER_0:  vapid thing when like the reason you do all of it
SPEAKER_0:  is for this thing you can get out at the end of the day. When we all know, and you've just heard a million interviews, like nobody ever is.
SPEAKER_0:  gets the Bugatti and goes, this now completely fulfills me. Everyone knows.
SPEAKER_0:  the beauty and the fulfillment actually comes from.
SPEAKER_0:  becoming obsessed about what you're doing for its own sake, sort of the journey, the beauty of that thing.
SPEAKER_0:  um...
SPEAKER_0:  And I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Money's just this thing we have to deal with.
SPEAKER_0:  to be able to do cool stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  I acknowledge that, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  you need money to build the $10 million studio. Like you gotta get the cameras, you gotta get the lights, and I'm very blessed to be able to have gotten that.
SPEAKER_0:  past a certain point, like I think that is really the function of money is to just
SPEAKER_0:  Do cool stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  But ultimately, if you can't...
SPEAKER_0:  fall in love with the process and like the craft itself.
SPEAKER_0:  You will be left.
SPEAKER_0:  very unhappy at the end of it.
SPEAKER_0:  And so to start people off on that journey.
SPEAKER_0:  by pointing to the shiny object and going like, that's what you should care about.
SPEAKER_0:  seems to me so backwards, we should learn from the actual people who have done it and said
SPEAKER_0:  That shiny thing did nothing for me.
SPEAKER_0:  Learn to love the journey and like, that's the thing we pitch people.
SPEAKER_0:  as unsexy as that might be.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, absolutely. That that's what's in the same applies to like the Red Pill community that talks about dating and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  that there is a...
SPEAKER_1:  It's not just about the number of hot women.
SPEAKER_1:  you go to bed with.
SPEAKER_1:  It's also about intimacy and love and all those kinds of things. And so like distinct and it's like we forcibly
SPEAKER_1:  There is...
SPEAKER_1:  components to a fulfilling life.
SPEAKER_1:  that uh...
SPEAKER_1:  is important to.
SPEAKER_1:  to the
SPEAKER_1:  educate young people about. Totally. But at the same time, feeding the dream the same take big risks.
SPEAKER_1:  and you.
SPEAKER_1:  The little you.
SPEAKER_1:  that has no evidence of ever being great.
SPEAKER_1:  can be great because there's evidence time and time again.
SPEAKER_1:  of people that come from very humble beginnings and doing incredible things that change the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and there's just a tremendous like...
SPEAKER_0:  funny thing where you can't become great.
SPEAKER_0:  without having a willful denial of the statistics.
SPEAKER_0:  Like in some ways you have to take the chance, even if that chance is so improbable.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's always those people who did take that chance to end up winning some.
SPEAKER_1:  Probably SBF and FTX is.
SPEAKER_1:  the biggest thing you've ever covered. But previously-
SPEAKER_1:  You've called the Save the Kids scam the world's.
SPEAKER_1:  Influencers scam that like the the the the biggest in the world and forces scam you've ever seen
SPEAKER_1:  Can you describe it?
SPEAKER_0:  Sure, so Save the Kids was a charity coin.
SPEAKER_0:  that was launched by...
SPEAKER_0:  a number of extremely popular influencers. I think they had over 50 million followers together.
SPEAKER_0:  huge names and they basically said, hey guys, invest in this coin. We're going to save the kids.
SPEAKER_0:  A portion of the proceeds go to charity.
SPEAKER_0:  And this coin, it's unruggable. So, rugging is the term.
SPEAKER_0:  Remember earlier we talked about Safemoon, you just grab the pool of funds in the middle, you take them out.
SPEAKER_0:  It's unrockable because we have this smart code.
SPEAKER_0:  that is gonna prevent.
SPEAKER_0:  people who are quote whales, which is a crypto term.
SPEAKER_0:  for saying you have a large portion of the tokens.
SPEAKER_0:  It'll prevent those people from selling a large amount of that.
SPEAKER_0:  at one time.
SPEAKER_0:  And so basically you don't have to worry about trusting us.
SPEAKER_0:  It just is what it is.
SPEAKER_0:  Join and we will.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  change the world, save the kids, whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  It was really skeezy from the beginning and sketchy because
SPEAKER_0:  Their logo matched the Save the Children logo, which is like an actual charity that, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  So they basically copied it and said, We're saving the kids.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, like a knockoff brand.
SPEAKER_0:  and almost immediately the project rugs.
SPEAKER_0:  They stole the money.
SPEAKER_0:  and tracing back through.
SPEAKER_0:  The code was changed at the last second before launch.
SPEAKER_0:  Like if you looked at their code that they launched as a test.
SPEAKER_0:  versus the code they launched in actuality, they changed only like two lines and it was the whale code.
SPEAKER_0:  basically make the whale code non-existent. Like you can sell as much as you want, as fast as you want.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  And it turned out that some of the influencers had not only...
SPEAKER_0:  Sold.
SPEAKER_0:  that and made money, but also...
SPEAKER_0:  had a pattern of pump and dumping tokens.
SPEAKER_0:  So we can talk about what that is. Yeah, what's pumping up?
SPEAKER_0:  A pump and dump is just where you have a huge following.
SPEAKER_0:  you promote your little Lex coin to everybody.
SPEAKER_0:  while holding a big portion of it. And as everyone rushes in to buy it, the price is going to pump.
SPEAKER_0:  and you dump at the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's where the name comes from, Pump and Dump.
SPEAKER_0:  You pump the price, sell all your tokens, make a lot of money.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I traced basically their wallets on the blockchain and found that
SPEAKER_0:  Two of the actors specifically had had a long history of doing this.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  which really proved malicious intent, and why I called it the worst is not-
SPEAKER_0:  It certainly wasn't the worst in terms of like the amount of people affected.
SPEAKER_0:  it relatively was like a small pump and dump.
SPEAKER_0:  rugged almost immediately.
SPEAKER_0:  but in terms of the amount of...
SPEAKER_0:  people that were involved in it.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of the amount of malicious behavior before it that like sort of proved that this wasn't an accident.
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that there was like this whale code, it was one of the most cynical attempts to just take.
SPEAKER_0:  the money of the followers you had and just like.
SPEAKER_0:  That's mine now.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's why I.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's to save the kids.
SPEAKER_1:  So that was...
SPEAKER_0:  That was a lot of the phase members and it was.
SPEAKER_0:  think Addison Rae. There were a lot of people who seemed like they were kind of taking shrapnel on it.
SPEAKER_0:  There was like this guy, Tico, who he didn't even sell the tokens. He just like held onto it the entire time and lost.
SPEAKER_0:  a few thousand dollars or maybe even, I forget the exact amount, he lost a lot of money.
SPEAKER_0:  Our decent mount.
SPEAKER_0:  And so like, he took a lot of shrapnel with that.
SPEAKER_0:  but there are also people who are maliciously doing this. So...
SPEAKER_0:  in that investigation like.
SPEAKER_0:  Several of the members of Faze got kicked out.
SPEAKER_0:  one of them got like permanently banned and then.
SPEAKER_0:  This other guy that I talked about fled the country. He sold all his belongings and fled the country.
SPEAKER_0:  and hit out in London or wherever he is now.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't really know where he is. Somewhere in the UK area.
SPEAKER_1:  So the basic idea there is to try to convert your influence into money.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the basic idea behind a lot of influencer crypto.
SPEAKER_1:  motions.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, but...
SPEAKER_1:  Right, but that little word influencer means something because they're
SPEAKER_1:  Are most crypto scams, influencer scams, they're not, right? Most.
SPEAKER_1:  most current
SPEAKER_0:  Check out most high profile ones.
SPEAKER_0:  Like.
SPEAKER_0:  just by nature, they tend to be made high profile by the influencer.
SPEAKER_0:  So sometimes they are.
SPEAKER_0:  You're right, a lot of money has been lost and like nobody finds out because there's no one big sort of attached to it. They just steal a lot of money.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  Influencers are great salespeople because like
SPEAKER_0:  in order to overcome the resistance.
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  getting you to buy some random coin. There's to be a reason.
SPEAKER_0:  And so much of the 21st century content creator generation is defined as-
SPEAKER_0:  by these strange parasocial relationships where people feel like they know you.
SPEAKER_0:  Not the character you play, but you.
SPEAKER_0:  and you have some friendship with them.
SPEAKER_0:  When in actuality you don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  the viewers.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you have a sense, but you don't actually know.
SPEAKER_0:  all of these people.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  that relationship.
SPEAKER_0:  is ex-
SPEAKER_0:  extremely powerful in terms of persuasion.
SPEAKER_0:  so you can say, I believe in this, and I've watched you.
SPEAKER_0:  year for years and all of a sudden I say like if Lex believes in it I believe in it I trust him as a human
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  that differentiates these coins and all of a sudden the coin
SPEAKER_0:  blows up.
SPEAKER_0:  gets really popular, you made this side deal, you make a ton of money.
SPEAKER_1:  I have to say podcasting in particular is an intimacy. Like I'm a huge fan of podcasts and I feel like I'm friends with the people I listen to.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Boys that are responsibility.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's why it...
SPEAKER_1:  really hurts me to announce that I am launching Lexcoin.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh!
SPEAKER_1:  No, man, I hate money. I hate this kind of the scheming of all of this.
SPEAKER_1:  The use.
SPEAKER_1:  the use of any kind of degree of fame that you have for that kind of stuff. There's something just-
SPEAKER_0:  It's so frustrating as.
SPEAKER_0:  These people, I have a general sense of what they were like.
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of what I'm...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm in the-
SPEAKER_0:  Even though I wouldn't describe myself as an influencer, I make content on YouTube.
SPEAKER_0:  I know that especially since they were taking these huge corporate sponsorships, they were making tons of money. They didn't have need for...
SPEAKER_0:  these scams. I mean, I think it's one thing to scam if you're like...
SPEAKER_0:  broke on the street.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, and you're playing three card Monte to like, live.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think it's a whole other ethically cruel thing to do.
SPEAKER_0:  if you're basically trying to upgrade your penthouse.
SPEAKER_0:  to the building next door. And like you're already well off and you just kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  want to get even further ahead. I think that's where it.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, this is the fascinating thing. I've been very fortunate recently to sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  whatever, a larger platform.
SPEAKER_1:  And when you find out is like life is amazing. I always thought life is amazing, but it becomes more amazing like, you meet so many cool people and so on. But what you start getting is.
SPEAKER_1:  You have more opportunities to like.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, like.
SPEAKER_1:  like scammers will come to you and try to use you, right? And I could see for somebody it could be tempting to be like, ooh, it would be nice to make some money.
SPEAKER_0:  I wanted to say, like, on this, kind of we're on this topic of opportunities you get, you know, kind of when you get a platform.
SPEAKER_0:  So one of the reasons kind of I railed a little bit earlier against them.
SPEAKER_0:  materialism or whatever, I think to the extent to which you can moderate your own greed.
SPEAKER_0:  you can play longer term games.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think so many people.
SPEAKER_0:  end up cutting an otherwise promising career short.
SPEAKER_0:  by just wanting it too fast?
SPEAKER_0:  So I think it's like a huge edge, just like discipline.
SPEAKER_0:  is in terms of like achieving what you want.
SPEAKER_0:  I think I'm like a very moderate, like being comfortable with a moderate existence and finding happiness in that.
SPEAKER_0:  is a huge edge.
SPEAKER_0:  because really your overhead is so much cheaper than the people who need a Ferrari or...
SPEAKER_0:  a super nice house to feel fulfilled. And when your overhead is less, you have the luxury to say no to like sketchy offers. You have freedom that other people don't have. music
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of times people don't pitch it this way. They pitch a Ferrari as freedom or like big houses like you've made it. In a lot of ways, those shackle you back to like, you gotta find the cashflow for those things. It's never a free ride.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, that's really beautifully put. I've always said that I had fuck you money at the very beginning.
SPEAKER_1:  I was broke for most of my life.
SPEAKER_1:  the way you have fuck you money.
SPEAKER_1:  is by not needing much to say fuck you. That's right. I mean, that's the overhead that you're talking about if you're gonna live.
SPEAKER_1:  if you can live simply and be truly happy.
SPEAKER_1:  and be truly free.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  That means you could be free in any kind of situation. You could make the wise kind of decisions. In that case, money...
SPEAKER_1:  uh... enables you in certain ways to do more cool stuff but doesn't shackle you like you said
SPEAKER_1:  too many people in the society would shackle.
SPEAKER_1:  because material possession is kind of like...
SPEAKER_1:  draw you into this race.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  of uh, more more more more.
SPEAKER_1:  and then you feel the burden of that, bigger houses and all that kind of stuff, and now you have to keep working, you have to keep doing this thing.
SPEAKER_1:  that you have to make more money and if it's a YouTube channel and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to get more and the same, it's not even just about money.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  That's why I-
SPEAKER_1:  Deliberately don't check views and likes and all that kind of stuff
SPEAKER_1:  is you don't want that dopamine of like...
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  of pulling you in, I have to do the thing that gets more and more attention or.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  More more.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, like money and.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's so wise. Yeah, great. It's a huge negative hit on your arm.
SPEAKER_1:  and you're a
SPEAKER_1:  ability to do creative.
SPEAKER_0:  Can I ask you about that? I'm always interested in this.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I completely agree.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's funny because when you abstract yourself out to the people you admire and respect
SPEAKER_0:  who inspired you to do the creative work you do.
SPEAKER_0:  you never think about.
SPEAKER_0:  like the views they were getting, or the money they were making, or the influence they had, all you ever think about is the work itself.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's funny.
SPEAKER_0:  when a lot of people get in this position.
SPEAKER_0:  Your temptation is to focus on that which you can measure, which is like all the
SPEAKER_0:  stuff you said, like the likes the views.
SPEAKER_0:  That's not actually.
SPEAKER_0:  the target or what you got into it for.
SPEAKER_0:  If you get into it for like, because you're inspired or whatever, your goal is inspiration, impact plaguing the water, you could be inspired or this Close to World to inscrute your expansion
SPEAKER_0:  And like that can't be quantified that same way.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's interesting, you have to find a way.
SPEAKER_0:  as a
SPEAKER_0:  creator of any of this stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  to like deliberately detach yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  from the measurable.
SPEAKER_0:  and focus on this thing, which is kind of abstract. And I was wondering if you have any ideas for that.
SPEAKER_1:  So one.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, there's a bunch of ideas. So one is
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  Figure out ways where you don't see.
SPEAKER_1:  the number of views.
SPEAKER_1:  on things.
SPEAKER_1:  So I have a-
SPEAKER_1:  I wrote a Chrome extension for myself that hides the number of views.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, that's really.
SPEAKER_0:  That's funny. No, what's funny is I have-...
SPEAKER_0:  Because it's useful for other people's content. Oh my gosh, that's freaky. I'm going to need to borrow this. That was my problem. I actually have.
SPEAKER_0:  some Chrome extensions for.
SPEAKER_0:  Like I don't like.
SPEAKER_0:  going down like recommendation rabbit holes when I'm at work. I just wanna like search for a video, find it. I don't wanna see like all the up next cause I'll waste time.
SPEAKER_0:  So I use Chrome extensions for that. But the views is a problem because it's relevant to me as a creator, like, is this a big video? So just check the video playlist for the results.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, which is why I really hurt when they remove like likes and dislikes because I want to know for tutorials and so on
SPEAKER_1:  What's I mean, that's probably really useful for you the dislikes. Yeah
SPEAKER_0:  Do you have that? Do you ever?
SPEAKER_0:  ever considered making that Chrome extension public? Sure!
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and there will be a good philosophy behind it, right? Like don't if you're
SPEAKER_0:  I really like it. I love the idea. I've wanted this thing before. I don't know if it necessarily exists.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't think I've made up.
SPEAKER_1:  a Chrome extension public. That'd be cool. I'd love to see.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I would go to that process of adding it to the...
SPEAKER_1:  Cause I love like open sourcing stuff. So yeah, I'll go add it to the Chrome extension, like the store.
SPEAKER_0:  I totally have.
SPEAKER_0:  I've hated this for like a long time.
SPEAKER_0:  YouTube made a change and they just continue to make the analytics front and center, which makes sense from their perspective. They're trying to give people better data.
SPEAKER_0:  on what is successful and what makes something successful. They're trying to train their creators.
SPEAKER_0:  But in the process...
SPEAKER_0:  it can lead to some unhealthy habits of thinking views define a video
SPEAKER_0:  And so I've long thought, okay, I've learned analytics, I understand retention, now I sort of wanna do like the zen, like forget it all.
SPEAKER_0:  And you can only do that if it's out of your site.
SPEAKER_1:  It depends how many friends you have who are creators. The other really important thing...
SPEAKER_1:  And I found this has nothing to do with creatives.
SPEAKER_1:  people
SPEAKER_1:  respect very much in my life.
SPEAKER_1:  Some of them people would know.
SPEAKER_1:  could be famous.
SPEAKER_1:  They will come to me and say.
SPEAKER_1:  they will comment on how popular a video was on YouTube.
SPEAKER_1:  that will sort of complement.
SPEAKER_1:  The success. The success defined by the popularity. Even for a podcast where most of the listenership is not on YouTube or in Spotify now is getting crazy.
SPEAKER_1:  they will still compliment the YouTube number.
SPEAKER_1:  So one of the deliberate things I do is I either, depending if it's a close friend, I'll get offended and made fun of them for that.
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of signal to them. This is not the right thing. Yeah, I don't want that.
SPEAKER_1:  And for people more like strangers that complement that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  I-
SPEAKER_1:  shown zero interest.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't receive the compliment well.
SPEAKER_1:  and I'll focus on the aspects of the compliment that have to do with like...
SPEAKER_1:  What do they find interesting?
SPEAKER_1:  like, you know, I kind of make them.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  Reveal to them that you shouldn't care about the number of views.
SPEAKER_0:  strange. There's like this weird hypnotism that happens when you get past a certain number.
SPEAKER_0:  and that number is some approximation. It's like, it's always like hard numbers. It's like.
SPEAKER_0:  100,000, a million, 10 million.
SPEAKER_0:  People just see a number and they just go like, wow, that is, and they assign a quality to it that-
SPEAKER_0:  may not, like it usually means nothing at all.
SPEAKER_0:  I agree, I've never...
SPEAKER_0:  I've never been good at like handling that because you're like
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it's like, okay.
SPEAKER_1:  That said, I do admire, very different from me, but I admire Mr. Beast.
SPEAKER_1:  unapologetically.
SPEAKER_1:  says like the numbers all that matters like basically the number
SPEAKER_1:  shows like the number of views you get.
SPEAKER_1:  Shows like how much.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know joy you brought to people's lives because if they watch the thing
SPEAKER_1:  day.
SPEAKER_1:  kept watching the thing, they didn't turn to now, that means they loved it. You brought value to their life, you brought enjoyment, and I'm going to bring the-
SPEAKER_1:  the maximum amount of enjoyment to the maximum number of people.
SPEAKER_1:  and I'm gonna do the most epic videos and all that kind of stuff. I admire that.
SPEAKER_1:  when you're so unapologetically into the numbers.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, he's sort of, it's interesting, he's like...
SPEAKER_0:  Gosh, we're getting way too in the way tonight.
SPEAKER_0:  Is this a, I don't know, I'm like constantly self-monitoring about like what topics we're on, but if we can.
SPEAKER_0:  MrBeast is so interesting because he's almost done what? Have you ever seen Moneyball?
SPEAKER_0:  Yes. This is a story of how someone brought statistics to baseball and it revolutionized everything.
SPEAKER_0:  He's Moneyballed YouTube.
SPEAKER_0:  He took statistics to YouTube and it changed everything.
SPEAKER_0:  Everybody now.
SPEAKER_0:  So many people are playing catch up.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it would be interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  in a few years to see how he develops.
SPEAKER_0:  And now that he's kind of revolutionized the data side of things.
SPEAKER_0:  how he
SPEAKER_0:  then approaches future videos.
SPEAKER_0:  because there's a point at which.
SPEAKER_0:  You've optimized, you've optimized, you've optimized.
SPEAKER_0:  But optimizing for short-term video performance is not the same as optimizing for long-term viewer happiness.
SPEAKER_0:  And how do you do that?
SPEAKER_0:  assuming the YouTube algorithm does not perfectly already do it for you, which it doesn't.
SPEAKER_0:  but they're trying to obviously do that.
SPEAKER_0:  optimized for long-term happiness, but.
SPEAKER_1:  and also growing Optimizer for long term.
SPEAKER_1:  creative growth.
SPEAKER_1:  I think the thing that people don't.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, maybe I don't know. I don't actually don't know enough about Jimmy, but like.
SPEAKER_1:  To me.
SPEAKER_1:  The thing that
SPEAKER_1:  seems to be special about him.
SPEAKER_1:  isn't.
SPEAKER_1:  the moneyball aspect.
SPEAKER_1:  That's really important.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like.
SPEAKER_1:  taking the data seriously.
SPEAKER_1:  But to me, it's the part of the idea generation.
SPEAKER_1:  the constant brainstorming coming up with videos.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's nice to connect the idea generation with the data.
SPEAKER_1:  but like.
SPEAKER_1:  How?
SPEAKER_1:  many people.
SPEAKER_1:  when they create on YouTube and other platforms.
SPEAKER_1:  really generate a huge amount of ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  I constantly brainstorm.
SPEAKER_1:  Constantly, constantly brainstorm.
SPEAKER_1:  At least for me, I don't.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't think I go.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... so many
SPEAKER_1:  Steps ahead in my thinking.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't like try to come up with all possible conversations. I don't come up with all possible videos I can make.
SPEAKER_0:  But you can't, so the one mistake to make is to map.
SPEAKER_0:  Jimmy's philosophy onto every genre, because not every genre fits that model.
SPEAKER_0:  Your model is not.
SPEAKER_0:  an idea-centric model. It's a people-centric model.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you like.
SPEAKER_0:  If you were in the business of creating just mass entertainment for the sake of mass entertainment,
SPEAKER_0:  you might focus on, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  The reason going idea-focused instead of person-focused is such a revolutionary idea in some senses
SPEAKER_0:  is because ideas can be broader.
SPEAKER_0:  more broadly appealing than any single human can be.
SPEAKER_0:  But you're not going for that. You're going for a podcast interview. And I think for you,
SPEAKER_0:  The goal should always be how deep can you get with interesting guests and like finding the most interesting guest.
SPEAKER_0:  which is a different probably set of skills.
SPEAKER_1:  Well put, really well put, but I think the right mapping there is finding the most interesting guess.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and I think.
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh
SPEAKER_1:  I don't do enough work on that. So for example, I...
SPEAKER_1:  I try to be, something I do prioritize is talking to people that nobody's talked to before.
SPEAKER_1:  because it's like I kind of assume
SPEAKER_1:  Myself is not a good. I know a lot of people that much better than me. I really admire
SPEAKER_1:  I think Joe Rogan is still the GOAT. He's just an incredible conversationalist.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's like, all right.
SPEAKER_1:  Who is somebody?
SPEAKER_1:  Joe's not gonna talk to.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Either he's not interested or it's not gonna happen. Like I wanna talk to that person. I wanna reveal the interesting aspect of that person.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think...
SPEAKER_1:  I should do a Mr. Beast style rigger.
SPEAKER_1:  in searching for interesting people.
SPEAKER_0:  and you should probably find people.
SPEAKER_0:  to help you search.
SPEAKER_1:  So he does that, but if we're being honest.
SPEAKER_1:  He does that of course with other folks.
SPEAKER_1:  But he's the main engine.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, you need like sort of like a...
SPEAKER_0:  a pre-filter.
SPEAKER_0:  You're the final filter.
SPEAKER_0:  Cause your problem is...
SPEAKER_0:  Your only.
SPEAKER_0:  able to think of humans that you've thought of before?
SPEAKER_0:  or been exposed to.
SPEAKER_0:  and most of the world you've never been exposed to.
SPEAKER_0:  So you need people to like pre-filter and go.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  These guys are just interesting humans. Lex has never heard of them.
SPEAKER_0:  and then you sort of take a batch of like.
SPEAKER_0:  a hundred people and you go, who seems the most interesting for me?
SPEAKER_1:  But by the way, on that topic, we're we's into we's, I have almost done a building up.
SPEAKER_1:  I programmed.
SPEAKER_1:  this guest recommendation.
SPEAKER_1:  where I wanna get suggestions from other people cause I really wanna find
SPEAKER_1:  people that nobody knows. This is the tricky thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Not you're not famous, but I the idea is there's probably fascinating humans out there that nobody knows. Correct!
SPEAKER_1:  That I want to find those and I believe in the crowdsourcing aspect will.
SPEAKER_1:  raise them. And now of course the top 100 will be crypto scams. No.
SPEAKER_1:  But yes.
SPEAKER_1:  So like, I have to make sure that these kinds of swarms of humans that recommend
SPEAKER_1:  I can filter through and there's this whole kinds of systems for that, but I want to find the walkthrough.
SPEAKER_1:  the fascinating people out there nobody's ever heard from and
SPEAKER_1:  From a programmer perspective, I thought surely I could do that by just building the system.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... that's how program
SPEAKER_0:  always think they'll just automate a system to do it.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the Jamie money ball, right? Like looking at the data.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Weeds on weeds. How do we get to Mr. Beast exactly? I'm not sure. Okay,
SPEAKER_1:  Save kids.
SPEAKER_1:  Influencer. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask you more on the guru front.
SPEAKER_1:  You've, uh, okay. Let's start with somebody that you've covered that.
SPEAKER_1:  I think you've covered a lot and I'm really embarrassed to not know much about them.
SPEAKER_1:  I think this is like old school coffee cell. You've been through stages. You've been through stages.
SPEAKER_0:  stages and phase.
SPEAKER_1:  this ah
SPEAKER_1:  A character named Dan Lok.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Who is he? You've exposed him for cult-like-
SPEAKER_1:  uh... human and his cult-like practices who is he what is he done
SPEAKER_0:  So Dan Lok is sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  He's gone through a number of iterations, but he was.
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of this like sales trainer guy.
SPEAKER_0:  who really made a hard push.
SPEAKER_0:  into what he called high ticket sales.
SPEAKER_0:  and he was telling people that they could kind of escape the nine to five rat race if they just learn high ticket sales.
SPEAKER_0:  and they can have the life of their dreams.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, it's like, I'll teach you to sell, but I'll teach you to ask.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, not only will I teach you to sell you that pen, but I'll teach you to sell it for $50,000 instead of a dollar.
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  So I talked to a lot of the people who had taken this course, because it was pretty expensive. I think it was like...
SPEAKER_0:  $2500 or $1000 and mind you the people who are taking it are like
SPEAKER_0:  teachers and like people who don't have a lot of money.
SPEAKER_0:  and then you take the course and immediately find out.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, well there's an upsell.
SPEAKER_0:  At the end of the course.
SPEAKER_0:  You're not ready.
SPEAKER_0:  You need to go from like.
SPEAKER_0:  High Ticket Closer, which is one of the products.
SPEAKER_0:  too.
SPEAKER_0:  inner circle.
SPEAKER_0:  or like the level up, right? And all of these courses are structured like this.
SPEAKER_0:  So they spend a tremendous amount on Google ads.
SPEAKER_0:  to get people in the door.
SPEAKER_0:  promising the dream.
SPEAKER_0:  And then once you're in, you're actually not done being like the product.
SPEAKER_0:  You're actually
SPEAKER_0:  in this system that tries to upsell you again and again and again and again. And eventually you're paying monthly and you're getting more and more. You're constantly paying for access to Dan Lok's wisdom and like...
SPEAKER_0:  Ideas.
SPEAKER_0:  and f-
SPEAKER_0:  Fundamentally.
SPEAKER_0:  this sales system wasn't working for people. I mean I talked to like for example a teacher.
SPEAKER_0:  who put in like $25,000.
SPEAKER_0:  was in debt at one point and has nothing to show for it.
SPEAKER_0:  I know.
SPEAKER_0:  and it was sort of these tactics.
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  Pressuring, pressuring, pressuring. And then anytime anyone would complain, he would try to silence them. So I heard from like...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Funny enough.
SPEAKER_0:  This lady was a teacher as well.
SPEAKER_0:  she put together a...
SPEAKER_0:  Facebook group basically saying, I think this guy's a scam, his course didn't work, it's not working for a lot of people.
SPEAKER_0:  because fundamentally the promise of turning someone from a non-salesman into a-
SPEAKER_0:  person who's making six figures selling.
SPEAKER_0:  is not an easy thing to do. It's not just a matter of just like take my course. But anyways.
SPEAKER_0:  It wasn't working. She created a Facebook group about it.
SPEAKER_0:  and he likes Suser.
SPEAKER_0:  or and was like legally pressuring her.
SPEAKER_0:  to stop doing that.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  and I realized like somebody has to speak out about this than everyone who is.
SPEAKER_0:  is getting silenced.
SPEAKER_0:  I was like, I'm gonna use my platform to raise awareness to this. And people came out of the woodwork. I mean saying that this guy defrauded me or he scammed me.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I want to just really quickly.
SPEAKER_0:  Take a second, take a beat.
SPEAKER_0:  to explain why.
SPEAKER_0:  Get rich quick schemes.
SPEAKER_0:  different.
SPEAKER_0:  than let's say selling a water bottle and saying it's the greatest water bottle.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Because sometimes people wonder, they go like, well, doesn't like
SPEAKER_0:  Nissan say their car is gonna make you happy and then it doesn't make you happy. Like why is that different?
SPEAKER_0:  from the kind of advertising of.
SPEAKER_0:  Get Rich Quick Course. I mean, both of them are sort of promising things that aren't true.
SPEAKER_0:  But you get something, you take some kind of a training, you know, isn't it the same thing?
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  Here's why.
SPEAKER_0:  There's this concept in economics called elastic demand and inelastic demand.
SPEAKER_0:  What it essentially means is that if I raise the value of this water bottle
SPEAKER_0:  There's a point at which you're just gonna be like, no.
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't make any sense, right?
SPEAKER_0:  but there are areas in our lives.
SPEAKER_0:  where we have desperation.
SPEAKER_0:  around them.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  can get deeply predatory very quickly because they have no
SPEAKER_0:  There's no.
SPEAKER_0:  elasticity around their demand. For example,
SPEAKER_0:  your health.
SPEAKER_0:  If you get cancer and I have the pill.
SPEAKER_0:  that will solve it, or at least, let's say I don't, I have a sugar pill here, but if I can convince you that this pill will-
SPEAKER_0:  Solve your cancer.
SPEAKER_0:  or treat your cancer. You will pay any amount of money you have on this earth.
SPEAKER_0:  to get this pill.
SPEAKER_0:  But obviously that gets really predatory really quick because
SPEAKER_0:  selling.
SPEAKER_0:  something that isn't real is almost as compelling as selling something that is real.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  This happens in the get rich quick space too. There's any amount of money you would pay to make.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot more money.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  So these products have inelastic demand. That's why you see what is essentially...
SPEAKER_0:  a few webinars.
SPEAKER_0:  getting sold for $2,500.
SPEAKER_0:  courses that literally have.
SPEAKER_0:  identical videos on YouTube, like very similar course curriculums, that are selling for such extravagant amounts of money.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I think there can be comparisons made to college, because obviously there's
SPEAKER_0:  similar like
SPEAKER_0:  questions about.
SPEAKER_0:  Benefits?
SPEAKER_0:  But in this case, there's not even statistics available that even shows the average person gets something out of it.
SPEAKER_0:  That's true of like, if you go to college, your average income will improve, right?
SPEAKER_0:  That's the justification there. There's none of that. There's no case studies. There's nothing backing their extravagant claims of you're gonna make all this money, you're gonna make all this wealth. Instead, they're just, as we said before, they're selling you a dream.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's why I find all those.
SPEAKER_0:  like types of Git Ridge quick schemes so problematic and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  That's why I've railed against them for-
SPEAKER_0:  significant amount of time.
SPEAKER_1:  What have you learned from attacking, exposing some of the things that deadlockers.
SPEAKER_1:  What have you learned about human nature?
SPEAKER_1:  and fraudsters and gurus and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  Good question.
SPEAKER_0:  I think one of them.
SPEAKER_0:  is that
SPEAKER_0:  There's this systemic problem that
SPEAKER_0:  The phrase, there's a sucker born every minute.
SPEAKER_0:  It's very true.
SPEAKER_0:  There is no end to the people.
SPEAKER_0:  too.
SPEAKER_0:  will fall for something like this.
SPEAKER_0:  And the problem is, is because there's just no end to need and want.
SPEAKER_0:  and like.
SPEAKER_0:  and just lack.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's easy to...
SPEAKER_0:  on the one hand, criticize people's greed, but a lot of times you have to put yourself in their shoes.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're at a dead-end job.
SPEAKER_0:  You have nothing going for you.
SPEAKER_0:  If you don't have the money to go to college, you don't want to get in debt, fair play.
SPEAKER_0:  Where do you go?
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  As you said, there's somebody who's there saying they believe in you, they believe you can make six figures.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you're.
SPEAKER_0:  you're gonna believe in that. And so-
SPEAKER_0:  I really felt like...
SPEAKER_0:  It made a lot more sense to tackle it from the...
SPEAKER_0:  other side.
SPEAKER_0:  from the side of people that can stop.
SPEAKER_0:  that can basically...
SPEAKER_0:  be exposed and basically be.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Have sort of like.
SPEAKER_0:  a negative put on their work. I mean-
SPEAKER_0:  they're largely going under the radar so.
SPEAKER_0:  I kind of felt like.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, do you want to educate?
SPEAKER_0:  Do you want to like blame it on the victims and say you should have known better? You should have done this. Stop.
SPEAKER_0:  But they're-
SPEAKER_0:  There's no end to that. or
SPEAKER_0:  you go after the grifters themselves. And so that's what I realized. I realize like-
SPEAKER_0:  That's the tactic.
SPEAKER_0:  that I went with.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's tough because it's a little like, it's completely risky to do that, but.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, you just gotta be smart about it.
SPEAKER_1:  So your platform has gotten...
SPEAKER_1:  really big, so there's some responsibility to that. Weirdly big, yeah. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  Let's say, thx for watching
SPEAKER_0:  only a year ago it was like a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  smaller and then it's hard to.
SPEAKER_0:  make that adjustment, you know? Cause like to me it's just the same.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the same show.
SPEAKER_1:  been doing.
SPEAKER_1:  So how do you avoid becoming a guru yourself or?
SPEAKER_1:  Ah, your ego growing.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's different trajectories it could take, one of which is
SPEAKER_1:  you can start seeing.
SPEAKER_1:  Everybody is a scammer.
SPEAKER_1:  and only you can reveal it.
SPEAKER_1:  and like every.
SPEAKER_1:  And like you have a audience of people who love.
SPEAKER_1:  seeing the epic coffeezilla grilling. Sure. And you can destroy everyone and that power now is getting to your head.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you avoid that?
SPEAKER_0:  Well.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, this is like less optically obvious. I think the main way is like.
SPEAKER_0:  My circle of friends doesn't care about any of that.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye again.
SPEAKER_0:  My wife doesn't care. The people whose opinion I value.
SPEAKER_0:  has no relation to like...
SPEAKER_0:  a subscriber metric or anything like that.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's like.
SPEAKER_0:  Tangibly the most important thing to just staying grounded. As far as like becoming a guru, I just don't have anything to like-
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I'm not interested in.
SPEAKER_0:  teaching people finance. I'm not interested in teaching people, not interested in selling a course.
SPEAKER_0:  And I've kind of-
SPEAKER_0:  given myself a hard line on that, which I think has helped me a bit.
SPEAKER_0:  is
SPEAKER_0:  There's a temptation to go.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I can tell what's a scam.
SPEAKER_0:  So let me tell you what's not a scam.
SPEAKER_0:  And a lot of people have offered a lot of money to do that and basically be like-
SPEAKER_0:  Hey.
SPEAKER_0:  I have such and such legitimate product, come be like an endorser.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I just don't do that because I think it undermines a lot of what I do.
SPEAKER_0:  is if you get like...
SPEAKER_0:  if you're taking money in on the side to say this is legit.
SPEAKER_0:  and you're saying this isn't legit, it's a huge conflict of interest.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think it's about.
SPEAKER_0:  managing conflicts of interest and keeping people around me that
SPEAKER_0:  are grounded and also I think...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, my only interest really is just like...
SPEAKER_0:  make cool stuff and I guess I'll do that until people stop watching.
SPEAKER_1:  Question from on that topic from the coffee's little subreddit shout out.
SPEAKER_1:  Shout out.
SPEAKER_1:  How does Koffe find the strength to maintain his integrity and resist temptation of being paid a great amount of money to advertise or promote a potential scam?
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, I think that's like-
SPEAKER_0:  goes back to what we've been talking about a lot, which is just on what you prioritize, what you value. I've just never, I guess I grew up kind of lower middle class.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I had a great time. I had a great childhood. I had very loving parents.
SPEAKER_0:  And because of that.
SPEAKER_0:  I guess intuited at an early age that
SPEAKER_0:  Money doesn't do a whole lot. And I knew a lot of people who were way better off.
SPEAKER_0:  who had miserable childhoods.
SPEAKER_0:  because whether their dad was always gone at work or like.
SPEAKER_0:  They just.
SPEAKER_0:  had other family issues that just money can't buy.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I realized.
SPEAKER_0:  I guess quickly.
SPEAKER_0:  um...
SPEAKER_0:  Money's a very like...
SPEAKER_0:  It's a glittery object that isn't what it appears to be.
SPEAKER_0:  And so...
SPEAKER_0:  To me, I'm like, I'm having the time of my life making my show.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not gonna have the time, like, I could, you could ruin all that just trying to go for this quick check.
SPEAKER_0:  when it's like, no, I'm having a great time.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's actually
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  maybe you're probably the same way, but for me, there's a lot of happiness and having integrity.
SPEAKER_1:  in looking in the mirror and knowing that you're the kind of person that has that.
SPEAKER_1:  In fact...
SPEAKER_1:  walking away from money is also fun.
SPEAKER_1:  because it's like promising your.
SPEAKER_1:  Like it's showing, it's easy to like just say you have integrity. It's nice to like.
SPEAKER_1:  Ha, I actually, I've discovered several times in my life that I have integrity.
SPEAKER_0:  You can put like basically to the test.
SPEAKER_1:  I've said, I don't know if I publicly said, but to myself, I say like, you can't buy.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot of things you can't buy with me, like $4 billion.
SPEAKER_1:  like a trillion dollars.
SPEAKER_1:  But it'd be nice to get tested that way.
SPEAKER_1:  It'd be cool to see, cause you never know until you're in that room.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm the same with power given power. I'd like to believe on the kind of person
SPEAKER_1:  That wouldn't abuse power, but you don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  until you're tested.
SPEAKER_1:  Anyway.
SPEAKER_1:  You're in a really tricky position because you're doing...
SPEAKER_1:  Incredibly you are a world-class journalist straight up
SPEAKER_1:  And so there is pressure on that of like.
SPEAKER_1:  not having.
SPEAKER_1:  Earing on the side of caution with like having conflicts, adventures and stuff like that. It's a really tough seat.
SPEAKER_1:  to sit in.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  It's really tough, it's really tough, but it's unfairly tough, I feel like.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's good that you're sort of...
SPEAKER_1:  weighing all of those. That said.
SPEAKER_1:  Go donate to Coffeezilla.
SPEAKER_1:  Donate all.
SPEAKER_1:  Everything.
SPEAKER_1:  Support him.
SPEAKER_1:  is a really, really important human being.
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  The other guy I did, I think is the first person I discovered that you
SPEAKER_1:  investigated as Brian Rose of London Real.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you talk about his story?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Brian Rose, he was sort of this interesting figure cause he was like
SPEAKER_0:  trying to be...
SPEAKER_0:  to one level or another, the Joe Rogan of London, which I don't think he did a terribly bad job of, especially initially, he had some really interesting podcasts.
SPEAKER_0:  with some really interesting people.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's funny enough, I started out as I would watch him. I mean, I don't know if I was a huge fan, but I was like, I like some of his interviews. He had some really good, like big gets in terms of...
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  Great guests.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm
SPEAKER_0:  However, when...
SPEAKER_0:  kind of
SPEAKER_0:  COVID started, he went down this really weird.
SPEAKER_0:  grifting rabbit hole where
SPEAKER_0:  He did like this interview with...
SPEAKER_0:  David Icke, who's, as you know, like a pretty big COVID conspiracy theorist.
SPEAKER_0:  um...
SPEAKER_0:  And I mean like actual, like he believes some of the Royals are literally lizards.
SPEAKER_0:  So he got shut down for that.
SPEAKER_0:  and he kind of made a big stink, which I think it's fine. Nobody likes to be censored.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm not even saying that he should have been.
SPEAKER_0:  Censored.
SPEAKER_0:  but his reaction to that was to like...
SPEAKER_0:  raise a ton of money from his audience, promising this-
SPEAKER_0:  digital freedom platform.
SPEAKER_0:  And at first it was like, oh, we want to raise $100,000. And then they raised it like within a day.
SPEAKER_0:  So he's like, well, we gotta raise.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot more money, and so eventually, they raised a million dollars, and he's trying to raise $250,000 a month.
SPEAKER_0:  to kind of keep putting.
SPEAKER_0:  his viewers money into this stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  So I started digging into the platform they were building and there was nothing free about it.
SPEAKER_0:  They had censorship guidelines.
SPEAKER_0:  And there was nothing about a platform at all. There was no.
SPEAKER_0:  underlying infrastructure he just
SPEAKER_0:  got some white label.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, live streaming thing.
SPEAKER_0:  I criticized him for that. It was just this ridiculous thing. All the donators expected one thing. They thought Brian Rose was gonna take on Google and Facebook and like bring free speech back for everybody. And of course he didn't.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And then it kind of got worse because...
SPEAKER_0:  He started taking a lot of heat for that.
SPEAKER_0:  and he really pivoted hard until...
SPEAKER_0:  the DeFi grift, so he started selling this course about
SPEAKER_0:  DeFi Mastery and this is a guy who knows nothing about crypto.
SPEAKER_0:  or very little at the least.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  It just got really kind of, he just kind of doubled down on this.
SPEAKER_0:  course model of you're gonna be rich if you just follow me. It was.
SPEAKER_0:  Ultimately, you just type in Brian Rose on YouTube, you can see what his audience thought of that, and you just wait.
SPEAKER_0:  All of them have left him at this point. He's getting like a thousand views a video.
SPEAKER_0:  And it wasn't because of me. I mean, it was like.
SPEAKER_0:  People.
SPEAKER_0:  lost taste in...
SPEAKER_0:  just the constant ask for more money, more money, more money. At some point, people get sick of it, and it's like...
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone—
SPEAKER_0:  has an understanding that like no one works for free, but.
SPEAKER_0:  when it starts to be.
SPEAKER_0:  ego driven and driven around money. Everything's about money.
SPEAKER_0:  it uh...
SPEAKER_1:  drives people away.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, you're a part of that sort of helping. It's nice to have a voice.
SPEAKER_0:  I certainly spoke out. I mean, it wasn't like I was quiet. I was very loud about it at the time.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  But I mean in the sense that.
SPEAKER_0:  There are.
SPEAKER_0:  If you look at someone like Andrew Tate, I made a video about him.
SPEAKER_0:  Even though he's been banned off all the platforms, he gets more views than Brian Rose.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's just like it was a testament to how much Brian Rose was like doing like the grift.
SPEAKER_0:  that people could.
SPEAKER_0:  even people who were fans and didn't care about what I said.
SPEAKER_0:  like couldn't look past, you know, just the constant ask for more and more.
SPEAKER_0:  Money, people just get burned out.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there some aspect that you worry about where
SPEAKER_1:  with a large audience.
SPEAKER_1:  There seems to be a certain aspect of human nature where people like
SPEAKER_1:  like the sea others destroyed. Sure.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, do you worry about hurting people?
SPEAKER_1:  They don't deserve it.
SPEAKER_1:  or rather
SPEAKER_1:  sort of a...
SPEAKER_1:  Attacking people with their grifter light.
SPEAKER_1:  but.
SPEAKER_1:  They get like a giant storm.
SPEAKER_1:  of negativity towards them.
SPEAKER_1:  and therefore sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... overpoweringly cancel them really hurt them
SPEAKER_1:  disproportionately.
SPEAKER_1:  Sure.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  I try to be sensitive to...
SPEAKER_0:  my platform.
SPEAKER_0:  And as I've grown...
SPEAKER_0:  I've tried to make sure my video topics have grown with me.
SPEAKER_0:  and like
SPEAKER_0:  It does reach this tricky point where if you're exposing a grifter with like 50,000 subs who's doing
SPEAKER_0:  Some harm.
SPEAKER_0:  Are you punching down?
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  So far, there's been enough.
SPEAKER_0:  high profile things that I can distract myself with.
SPEAKER_0:  where this has never been a problem.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't ever want to be...
SPEAKER_0:  Sort of like.
SPEAKER_0:  Sir Lancelot in retirement.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Where have you heard this analogy?
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, so there's this great analogy where it's like...
SPEAKER_0:  Sir Lancelot's the guy who's...
SPEAKER_0:  Slays the dragon, right?
SPEAKER_0:  He gets a lot of fame and he gets a lot of fortune for saving the dragon or at least a lot of people love him.
SPEAKER_0:  But what happens after he slays the first dragon?
SPEAKER_0:  He's gotta go find a bigger dragon. So he goes find a bigger dragon.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Eventually, depending on how many dragons you think there are in the world, maybe he kills all the dragons.
SPEAKER_0:  And one day people go see Sir Lancelot and he's in a field with cows and he's chopping their heads. And he's sort of put himself in retirement.
SPEAKER_0:  but he can't even enjoy the fruits because his whole thing is like, I'm killing the dragon.
SPEAKER_0:  So I try to be cognizant and I try to always make myself willing to.
SPEAKER_0:  Hang up my...
SPEAKER_0:  my suspenders, I guess. I got my hat.
SPEAKER_0:  I try to be aware of like-
SPEAKER_0:  If I significantly improve the problem, I put myself out of business.
SPEAKER_0:  I want to be okay with that.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically.
SPEAKER_0:  um...
SPEAKER_0:  and just be fun with it. I don't-
SPEAKER_0:  The funny thing is I was more worried about this as like an issue.
SPEAKER_0:  Earlier?
SPEAKER_0:  because I thought there was a finite like.
SPEAKER_0:  I was like, man, I'm gonna solve this faster.
SPEAKER_0:  especially as it started gaining traction, like I'm going to solve this fast, I got this, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Classic Naive.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, you know, we all think we're so influential.
SPEAKER_1:  X comes along.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, yeah, you just get like, with time you get humbled because you talk to people. I've talked to like versions of Coffeezilla.
SPEAKER_0:  that are older.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, it's like, oh, yeah, they didn't solve it. They probably were better.
SPEAKER_1:  I just imagine a smoke filled room of just...
SPEAKER_1:  like retired.
SPEAKER_1:  Batman.
SPEAKER_1:  and you're at this young...
SPEAKER_1:  bright eyed.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  And you don't- Binary-spirited investigator. Yeah, exactly.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the process of investigation that you can speak to? What is some interesting...
SPEAKER_1:  things you've learned about what it takes to do great investigations.
SPEAKER_0:  Sure. Investigations reveal something new.
SPEAKER_0:  or bring something to light?
SPEAKER_0:  So I think...
SPEAKER_0:  What everyone thinks in terms of investigations is like a lot of like...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, Googling or like...
SPEAKER_0:  searching through articles.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's the first thing you want to get away from.
SPEAKER_0:  and you wanna try to...
SPEAKER_0:  Talk to people.
SPEAKER_0:  doing like the non-obvious things and just trying to get perspectives.
SPEAKER_0:  that are beyond just what is available.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of it's just.
SPEAKER_0:  having conversations is so enlightening.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  both to victims and also obviously trying to get, to the people themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  Secondly...
SPEAKER_0:  There's sometimes some-
SPEAKER_0:  analysis you can generate that's meaningful like blockchain evidence.
SPEAKER_0:  So in the case of SafeMoon...
SPEAKER_0:  For example.
SPEAKER_0:  going back to that.
SPEAKER_0:  I found someone's secret account where they were pumping, dumping coins. They were saying things like...
SPEAKER_0:  Who saw it? I'll- I'll-
SPEAKER_0:  you know, I'm so mad at the guy who sold, F the guy who sold, and you look at his account and he was the guy selling.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like that is just
SPEAKER_0:  That's great stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Digging through the blockchain, I've gained some skills there.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And that's kind of this fun.
SPEAKER_0:  I guess I would say it's this weird edge I have right now.
SPEAKER_0:  because a lot of people.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't know too much about that.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I have this weird expertise that works now
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think that'll work forever, because I think people will.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of figure out how to do very similar analyses.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's like kind of an interesting edge right now that I have.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's like a data driven investigation, but you also do interviews, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, definitely. And then also recently I've tried to get more response, speaking to your point about like as your platform gets bigger, you need more responsibility.
SPEAKER_0:  I've tried to get much more.
SPEAKER_0:  responsible about like reaching out or somehow giving the
SPEAKER_0:  subject some way to talk.
SPEAKER_0:  because I think in early on, I was such a small channel that A, I-
SPEAKER_0:  If I asked them, they wouldn't answer.
SPEAKER_0:  B, I kind of felt like I was launching these videos into the abyss.
SPEAKER_0:  And when some of my videos had real traction, I was like, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Hang on a second.
SPEAKER_0:  Double check this, let's triple check it. Let's try to make sure.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  All this stuff is correct and there's no other side of the story.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll say this has interesting implications because, for example,
SPEAKER_0:  I investigated this thing called Genesis, their billion-dollar crypto lender.
SPEAKER_0:  And my conclusion was that they were insolvent.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a huge accusation. So what do you do? Well, I emailed their press team, everybody. I said, hey, I think you're insolvent.
SPEAKER_0:  I think you're this, I think I laid out all my accusations.
SPEAKER_0:  And I said, you have till.
SPEAKER_0:  I think 2 p.m.
SPEAKER_0:  the next day to respond.
SPEAKER_0:  at 8 a.m.
SPEAKER_0:  before.
SPEAKER_0:  I made my video.
SPEAKER_0:  They announced to all their investors that they're freezing withdrawals. They don't have the money.
SPEAKER_0:  So they front.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if they saw the inter, like I don't know if they actually saw that email. I don't want to take credit for collapsing them or whatever, but...
SPEAKER_0:  My point is, had I not taken that level of kind of care and just said,
SPEAKER_0:  Hey, you're a scammer, you're frauds.
SPEAKER_0:  Ironically...
SPEAKER_0:  Could I have done more good by allowing people to withdraw their money early?
SPEAKER_0:  I made some tweets that people did see that like some people got their money out.
SPEAKER_0:  but my YouTube audience is much larger and could I have helped more people had I?
SPEAKER_0:  NOT
SPEAKER_0:  given them basically the ability to know what I was gonna produce when I produced it. TEXT BOARD
SPEAKER_1:  your life is difficult.
SPEAKER_1:  because you can potentially hurt the company that doesn't deserve it if you're wrong
SPEAKER_1:  or you.
SPEAKER_1:  If you're right and you warn the company, you might hurt the...
SPEAKER_1:  Oof.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, well, I'm glad your wife is a supporter and keeps you strong. That's a tough, tough decision.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Ultimately, I guess you want to err on the side of the individual people.
SPEAKER_1:  of the investors and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's tough, it's always a really, really tricky decision.
SPEAKER_1:  Very tricky.
SPEAKER_1:  That's so interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  And then...
SPEAKER_1:  The thing I've seen in your interviews, I-
SPEAKER_1:  that I don't remember, because I think...
SPEAKER_1:  When you I watched you earlier in your career
SPEAKER_1:  You were a little bit harsher, you were like trollier.
SPEAKER_1:  You're having a little more fun. Sure. I've seen you recently.
SPEAKER_1:  You do have the fun.
SPEAKER_1:  But whenever you interview...
SPEAKER_1:  You seem respectful, like-
SPEAKER_1:  Like you attack in good faith.
SPEAKER_1:  which is really important for an interviewer. So then people...
SPEAKER_1:  can go on and actually try to defend themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  That's really important signal to send to people because then you're not just about tearing down, you're after like the-
SPEAKER_1:  It's cliche to say, but the truth, you're really trying to actually investigate in good faith.
SPEAKER_1:  which is great, so that signal is out there. So people like SBF could.
SPEAKER_1:  Like he should go on your platform, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, now it's like.
SPEAKER_1:  in full.
SPEAKER_1:  not just like a half-assed conversation on Twitter space, but in full. So that's great that that signal's out there. But of course the downside of sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  as you become.
SPEAKER_1:  more famous people might be scared to sort of go on.
SPEAKER_1:  But you do put that signal being respectful out there, which is really, really important.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  It surprises me. I know it surprises other people because other people have commented.
SPEAKER_0:  but it consistently surprises me how many people still talk to me.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  And maybe it's because they, and I really do give a good attempt to try to argue in good faith. I try not to just like-
SPEAKER_0:  load up ad homonyms or anything like that. I just try to present the evidence and let the audience make up their mind.
SPEAKER_0:  um...
SPEAKER_0:  But it surprises me sometimes that people will just be like, yeah, they want to talk, they want to talk, they want to talk.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  It's very.
SPEAKER_0:  Human in a way.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think it's like almost.
SPEAKER_0:  It's almost like good. Like one of the things that is always told to everyone who's gonna talk to the cops like you should never talk to the cops, whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  Tom.
SPEAKER_0:  Which is true, you shouldn't talk to the cops.
SPEAKER_0:  Because even if you're innocent, they can use your words, they can twist your words with that.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  There's something that gets lost in that.
SPEAKER_0:  like almost robotic like
SPEAKER_0:  you know, self-interest.
SPEAKER_0:  that I think having open conversations.
SPEAKER_0:  Even if you've done something wrong, I think there's something really compelling about that.
SPEAKER_0:  that continues to make people talk in interrogation rooms.
SPEAKER_0:  in Twitter spaces, wherever you are.
SPEAKER_0:  Regardless of.
SPEAKER_0:  whether you totally shouldn't be talking.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I don't want to downplay that. That's actually really important. I mean, it's like a lot of-
SPEAKER_0:  Cases get solved, a lot of investigations go farther.
SPEAKER_0:  because people sort of make the...
SPEAKER_0:  miscalculation to talk.
SPEAKER_0:  but I think it's like almost important in a way that we have that human bias to like.
SPEAKER_0:  Connect in spite of self-interest.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, but also they're judging the integrity.
SPEAKER_1:  and the good faith of the other person.
SPEAKER_1:  So I think when people consume your content, especially your latest content,
SPEAKER_1:  They know that you're...
SPEAKER_1:  a good person.
SPEAKER_1:  I found myself.
SPEAKER_1:  Like there's a lot of journalists that reach out to me.
SPEAKER_1:  and I find myself like not wanting to talk to them.
SPEAKER_1:  because I don't know if the other person on the side is coming in good faith.
SPEAKER_1:  Even on silly stuff, I'm not a- Same way.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I'm not a...
SPEAKER_1:  I don't have anything to hide. You don't really have anything to hide, but you don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  what their spin is.
SPEAKER_0:  Can I tell you an example?
SPEAKER_0:  I'm dying because I believe so strongly that journalists have done themselves such a disservice.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, one of the truest things is that like
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone loves journalism in theory and almost everyone
SPEAKER_0:  dislikes journalists as a whole.
SPEAKER_0:  Like there's a deep distrust of journalists and there's a deep love for journalism. This is Weird Disconnect.
SPEAKER_0:  I think a lot of it can be summarized in, there's this book called The Journey to the West.
SPEAKER_0:  Ah.
SPEAKER_0:  Is that thing called the journalist and the murderer?
SPEAKER_0:  It's written by Janet Malcolm.
SPEAKER_0:  the first line of this book.
SPEAKER_0:  is that every journalist who knows what they're doing...
SPEAKER_0:  Who isn't too s-
SPEAKER_0:  is smart enough to know what they're doing, knows what they're doing is deeply unethical.
SPEAKER_0:  or something like that, and what they're talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  is that there's a tradition in journalism to betray the subject.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  Lie to them.
SPEAKER_0:  in the hopes of getting a story.
SPEAKER_0:  and play to their ego and to their...
SPEAKER_0:  sense of self.
SPEAKER_0:  to make it seem like you're gonna write one article and you stab them in the back at the end when you press publish and you write the totally different article.
SPEAKER_0:  This is what actually everyone hates about journalists.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's happened to me before. So I did a story like way back in the day, I got interviewed about something that was like data with YouTube.
SPEAKER_0:  I made a few comments about data on YouTube, and somehow by the time the article got published, I had had a lot of comments aboutá¹
SPEAKER_0:  me endorsing their opinion that PewDiePie is an anti-Semite.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm like, I reach out to this person and I say, I never said that. Like, what are you, how did you even twist my words to say that?
SPEAKER_0:  And I felt so disgusted and betrayed to have like...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm like this mouthpiece for an ideology or like a thought that I do not actually agree with.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  And when journalists do this, they think, well, I'm never gonna interview this person again, so it's okay.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  almost like the ends justify the means, I get the story.
SPEAKER_0:  But the ends don't justify the means because you've now undermined the entire field's credibility.
SPEAKER_0:  with that person.
SPEAKER_0:  And when that happens, enough time.
SPEAKER_0:  times you end up.
SPEAKER_0:  sitting across from Lex Friedman and it's like, well, I don't know if they're gonna represent me fairly. Because the.
SPEAKER_0:  Base Assumption.
SPEAKER_0:  is that regardless of what the journalist says, they could betray you and they might betray you at the end of the day and be saying you're great while they're secretly writing like a hit piece about like
SPEAKER_0:  you know how much.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you're a bad.
SPEAKER_0:  force for the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Where?
SPEAKER_0:  Whereas there's an alternate universe.
SPEAKER_0:  where if the journalist was somewhat upfront about their approach...
SPEAKER_0:  Or at least didn't mislead and didn't say like, I love you. I think you're great.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  you would end up with.
SPEAKER_0:  less access.
SPEAKER_0:  but you would end up with more trusted journalism, which I think in the long run would be.
SPEAKER_0:  We get more access.
SPEAKER_0:  I think in the long term, yeah, but all of these, like everything we're talking about is long-term games versus short-term games.
SPEAKER_0:  In the short term, you get more access if you suck up to the person, if you say this, say this, say this, and you stab them in the back later. Long-term, you build a long-term reputation, and people trust you, it actually matters more.
SPEAKER_1:  It's nice when that reputation is your own individual. It's like you have a YouTube channel, you're one individual.
SPEAKER_1:  So people trust that because
SPEAKER_1:  You have a huge disincentive to scoop people over.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like if you're in New York Times.
SPEAKER_1:  If you screw somebody over, the New York Times gets the hit, not you individually.
SPEAKER_1:  so you can like...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  you're safer, but like.
SPEAKER_1:  The reason I don't screw people over is I know that, well, there's my own ethics and integrity. Also, there's a strong incentive to like.
SPEAKER_1:  because you're now, I'm going, that person is gonna go.
SPEAKER_1:  public with me screwing them over completely lying about everything.
SPEAKER_1:  how I presented the person, for example.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's just gonna, you know, that's gonna percolate throughout.
SPEAKER_1:  the populace and they're gonna be like, Alex is the person that's at the line.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... line second shit
SPEAKER_1:  And so there's a huge disincentive to do that.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, yeah, I still have that.
SPEAKER_0:  That is what's interesting about the move towards independent journalism.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I think we'll probably end up at a space where...
SPEAKER_0:  It's so interesting. Mainstream journalism has so much work to do to repair the trust.
SPEAKER_0:  with the average individual.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and it's going to take a lot of self-reflection. I've talked to a few mainstream journalists about this.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of them will admit it behind closed doors, but like...
SPEAKER_0:  There's this general sense that, oh, the public's not being fair to us. They're very self-
SPEAKER_0:  Defensive, I guess, in a way.
SPEAKER_0:  And I understand why, because...
SPEAKER_0:  Sometimes it's just a few bad apples that ruin it for everybody.
SPEAKER_0:  without the acknowledgement of the deep distrust.
SPEAKER_0:  that they have with...
SPEAKER_0:  good portion of our society, there's no way to rebuild that.
SPEAKER_0:  just like when there's no acknowledgement of the
SPEAKER_0:  corruption of the 2008 financial crash.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no way to rebuild that, even if most bankers, most traders are not unethical or duplicitous or-
SPEAKER_0:  totally normal people who maybe aren't deserving of the bad reputation, but you have to acknowledge the damage that's been done.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  bad actors before you can like heal that system.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, what do you think about Elon just opening the door to a journalist to see all the emails that were sent?
SPEAKER_1:  uh, the
SPEAKER_1:  quote unquote, Twitter files.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that's really interesting. I mean, I saw a lot of-
SPEAKER_0:  I'm like in this weird thing where I see, I'm so.
SPEAKER_0:  I follow a lot of independent people and I follow a lot of mainstream journalists and the-
SPEAKER_0:  that are very polar opposite takes on that.
SPEAKER_1:  People really quickly politicize it, but to me, the thing that was fascinating is just the transparency.
SPEAKER_1:  that I've never seen from one of the really frustrating things to me.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of this podcast has been about interviewing tech people, CEOs, and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  and they're just so guarded with everything.
SPEAKER_1:  It's hard to get to and so it's nice to get.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Hopefully this is a signal look you can be transparent
SPEAKER_1:  Like this is signaled to...
SPEAKER_1:  Increase transparency.
SPEAKER_1:  Hopefully so.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's been tribalized so quickly, it's like I've lost a lot of faith in that. You
SPEAKER_0:  And unfortunately, it's been this like bludgeon match of like
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  If you're on the right, you think.
SPEAKER_0:  It's uncovering the greatest story ever about Hunter Biden. If you're on the left, you think.
SPEAKER_0:  They were just silencing revenge porn pics of Hunter Biden. So therefore it was justified. And by the way, Trump also.
SPEAKER_0:  sent messages to Twitter, so doesn't that mean that we should be criticizing Twitter? I mean, this is animals.
SPEAKER_0:  goes back to why I don't touch politics is because I think.
SPEAKER_0:  As many problems as I have, I think when you become a journalist that-
SPEAKER_0:  not even a political journalist, when you become a journalist in politics.
SPEAKER_0:  You have like
SPEAKER_0:  twice the problem, so I'm happy to be.
SPEAKER_0:  Well outside of that.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of sphere.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's an interesting, forget Twitter files, but Twitter itself is really, really...
SPEAKER_1:  Interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  forearm.
SPEAKER_1:  the virality of information transfer.
SPEAKER_1:  And from a journalistic perspective, it's like...
SPEAKER_1:  how information travels, how it becomes distributed.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think?
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think about?
SPEAKER_0:  Twitter.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm always conflicted on Twitter because
SPEAKER_0:  I almost
SPEAKER_0:  hate
SPEAKER_0:  how much I...
SPEAKER_0:  Enjoy using it.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm like, this is like this mindless bird app.
SPEAKER_0:  consuming my time.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  It's this incredible networking tool.
SPEAKER_0:  But what's weird is, when I think about my own presence on Twitter...
SPEAKER_0:  They've almost made it too easy to like say something that.
SPEAKER_0:  you've half thought.
SPEAKER_0:  Like the friction to send a tweet is so much less than like
SPEAKER_0:  if I'm gonna make a YouTube video, there's several points at which I'm like, well...
SPEAKER_0:  What's the other side? What's this? What's that?
SPEAKER_0:  There's no friction there.
SPEAKER_0:  And so one thing I've noticed is everyone I follow on Twitter.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of them, after reading all their tweets, I think nothing-
SPEAKER_0:  More of them, nothing less of them.
SPEAKER_0:  but there's a lot of them that I think less of. And I don't think I've ever had an experience where I've read someone's tweets.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think more of them?
SPEAKER_0:  in a way. And I'm like, what does that say that
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, what is that? Like there's so many people I-
SPEAKER_1:  Admire.
SPEAKER_1:  that the worst of them is represented on Twitter.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot of-
SPEAKER_0:  There's a million examples.
SPEAKER_1:  like snarky and
SPEAKER_1:  sometimes mocking and derisive and...
SPEAKER_1:  Negative and like emotional messes
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, yeah, what is that?
SPEAKER_1:  Um, maybe...
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe we shouldn't criticize it and accept that as like a beautiful, raw aspect of that human being, but not encompassing.
SPEAKER_1:  not representing the full entire idea.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's reflect like
SPEAKER_0:  It's impossible to not.
SPEAKER_0:  reflected to some extent, or you'd have to counter that bias really carefully because that is them, it is a thought they had, it's just probably something that should have been an unexpressed.
SPEAKER_0:  thought perhaps.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  So yeah, I kind of wonder like my.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm like, should I be on Twitter? But the problem is, it's such a-
SPEAKER_0:  a great place where so many
SPEAKER_0:  Like, so much of the news happens on Twitter, so much of-
SPEAKER_0:  the journalism breaks on Twitter. Even people in the New York Times, will tweet their scoop.
SPEAKER_0:  And they'll put that out on Twitter first.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's this really weird thing where...
SPEAKER_0:  I'd love to be off it.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's like too useful for my job, but I kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  Kinda hate it.
SPEAKER_1:  No, no, you need to... well, it depends, but...
SPEAKER_1:  From my perspective, you should be on it.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, I definitely am. Yeah. So like a coffee zone should definitely be on Twitter.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  have developed the calluses in the
SPEAKER_1:  the strength to...
SPEAKER_1:  not give into the sort of the lesser aspects like.
SPEAKER_1:  Because you're silly, you're funny, you can be cutting with your humor.
SPEAKER_1:  I wouldn't give into the...
SPEAKER_1:  like the darker aspects of that, like low effort negativity.
SPEAKER_1:  If you're the way you are in your videos, I would say if you're ever negative.
SPEAKER_1:  or making fun of stuff, I think that's high effort.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  I would still put a lot of effort into it, calmly thinking through.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  because, and also not giving into the dopamine.
SPEAKER_1:  Desire to do to say something that's gonna get a lot of likes
SPEAKER_1:  uh... you know i have that all the time you use twitter enough you realize
SPEAKER_1:  certain messages that are going to get more likes than others.
SPEAKER_1:  And, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  the ones that are extreme more extreme yeah and like emotional like
SPEAKER_0:  Lex is an idiot or like Lex is the greatest human being ever. It's much better than, oh wow, what a polite nuanced conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  I can tell you right now which of those three tweets it isn't going to perform with.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so I.
SPEAKER_1:  I think extremes are okay if you believe it. Okay. So I will sometimes say.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  positive things. I said that the Twitter files release was historic.
SPEAKER_1:  Of course, this before...
SPEAKER_1:  I realize, I mean, the reason I said it.
SPEAKER_1:  is not.
SPEAKER_1:  is because the transparency. It's so refreshing.
SPEAKER_1:  to see some annual of transparency.
SPEAKER_1:  And then of course...
SPEAKER_1:  those kinds of comments, the way Twitter does, is every side will interpret it in the worst possible way for them and they will run with it. Or some side, when it's political, yeah, one side will interpret, yes.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... i agree with the latest
SPEAKER_0:  Historic they might not have even read the article. They just like they literally or the tweet thread
SPEAKER_0:  And they're just like, it is historic.
SPEAKER_1:  His story is because Hunter Biden was finally the collusion or whatever it is. And then the other side is like, no, it's a nothing burger.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, that that aspect of nuance and that's frozen in time even with editing there's a so tough it's it's tricky But if you maintain a
SPEAKER_1:  a cool head through all of that.
SPEAKER_1:  and uh...
SPEAKER_1:  call to your ethics and your ideas and use it.
SPEAKER_1:  to spread the ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  which you do extremely well on YouTube.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it could be a really powerful platform.
SPEAKER_1:  There's no other platform.
SPEAKER_1:  that allows for the viral spread of ideas, good ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  then
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  than this, and this is where...
SPEAKER_1:  Like especially with Twitter spaces.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, where else?
SPEAKER_1:  What I see.
SPEAKER_1:  I think twice impromptu conversations.
SPEAKER_1:  we will...
SPEAKER_0:  Never.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, nowhere else. Because he wasn't gonna come on my show. He wasn't gonna come on some big prepared thing. It's like, hey.
SPEAKER_0:  YOLO, let's go into Twitter space and I like pop up.
SPEAKER_0:  You know what's funny?
SPEAKER_0:  And this, I hope this release is late enough or well, SPF probably won't see this. Thank you.
SPEAKER_1:  Although I'm sure he's a- and unfortunately.
SPEAKER_1:  Unfortunately, he will. Oh, yes.
SPEAKER_0:  Hopefully I'll have time to enact my little plan.
SPEAKER_0:  But I'm hoping if he goes on any future spaces I can like haunt him from-
SPEAKER_0:  interview to interview, which is like I keep showing up and he's like
SPEAKER_0:  I hate this guy.
SPEAKER_1:  But I think he's already kind of probably.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  has like PTSD of like, in the shadows lurks a coffeezilla.
SPEAKER_1:  That just would be, that would just...
SPEAKER_0:  It's just like, that really amuses me.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean there is a...
SPEAKER_1:  I think he honestly would enjoy talking to you. There's an aspect of Twitter spaces that's a little...
SPEAKER_1:  uncertain of like, what are we doing here?
SPEAKER_1:  There's an urgency because other voices might want to butt in. Exactly. Exactly. If it's an intimate one-on-one.
SPEAKER_1:  where you can like breathe, like hold on a second.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's much easier.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's since.
SPEAKER_1:  This piece is a little bit negative.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, that.
SPEAKER_1:  there's too many voices, especially if it's a very controversial kind of thing. So it's tricky. But at the same time,
SPEAKER_1:  the friction, it's so easy to just jump in.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  So I can just...
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, just imagine like a Twitter space with like Zelensky and Putin.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_1:  how else are these two going to talk, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Can't you imagine? If you try to set it up on Zoom, like it's never happening. It's never happening. David богol
SPEAKER_0:  Just imagine a poon like-
SPEAKER_1:  sitting there like.
SPEAKER_0:  Zalensky's live.
SPEAKER_1:  Just live, right? Just jumping in.
SPEAKER_1:  hilarious
SPEAKER_1:  Let's speak Russian.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... the actions of small changes so how how you have a productive day to have any insights in
SPEAKER_1:  how to manage your time optimally.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, I've gone the gamut of.
SPEAKER_0:  from obsessive time tracking in 15 minute buckets.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of like the other extreme where it's more...
SPEAKER_0:  kind of like large scale.
SPEAKER_0:  some deep work here, two hour bucket, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Count for an hour of lunch and...
SPEAKER_0:  some other thing, but now.
SPEAKER_0:  Now I just roughly, because I manage a team there's some things that
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  Come up.
SPEAKER_0:  It's only a team of two, it's not like big, but I just have things that are not necessarily controllable by me, I like have to take some meetings or whatever. It's not as easy to plan out my day ahead of time.
SPEAKER_0:  So I do a lot of.
SPEAKER_0:  retrospective time management, where I look at my day, and that's what I mostly do now.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and I account, did I spend this day productively? What could I do better? And then try to implement it in the future.
SPEAKER_0:  So a lot of this, I realized, is very personal for me.
SPEAKER_0:  I-
SPEAKER_0:  do very well in long streaks of working.
SPEAKER_0:  And if I, I can't do a lot of work in 15 minutes, I can't do a lot of work in even an hour.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you give me like three hours or five hours or six hours of uninterrupted work.
SPEAKER_0:  That's like.
SPEAKER_0:  That's where I get most of my stuff done.
SPEAKER_1:  So from the, it just, it'd be fun to explore those. The one you did 15 minute buckets.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  You have a day.
SPEAKER_1:  in front of you and you have like a Google sheet or a spreadsheet or something. Yeah, I did an Excel. So.
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh
SPEAKER_1:  and you're her.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you have a plan for the day or do you go like when you did it?
SPEAKER_1:  Bye.
SPEAKER_1:  Or you just literally...
SPEAKER_1:  sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  focus on a particular task.
SPEAKER_1:  And then you're tracking as you're doing that task every 15 minutes.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I would kind of do it live.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not, so one of the reasons I'm so obsessive about it is because I'm not organized by nature.
SPEAKER_0:  And I lost, like in college I learned how.
SPEAKER_0:  much.
SPEAKER_0:  lack of organization can just hurt you in terms of output.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I realized like I just had to build systems that would enable me to become more.
SPEAKER_0:  organized so.
SPEAKER_0:  Uhhh...
SPEAKER_0:  Really, I think...
SPEAKER_0:  Doing that?
SPEAKER_0:  really taught me a lot about time.
SPEAKER_0:  in the same way that tracking calories can teach you about food. Yes. Learning, accounting for these things.
SPEAKER_0:  will give you skills that eventually you might not need to track on such a granular level because
SPEAKER_0:  you've kind of like figured out. So that's kind of how I feel about it. I think everyone should-
SPEAKER_0:  if you care about productivity and stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  should do a little bit of it. I don't think it's sustainable in the long-term. It just takes so much effort and time to like...
SPEAKER_0:  And I think the marginal.
SPEAKER_0:  Effect of it in the long term is kind of minimal. Once you learn these basic skills, you're going to be able to do it.
SPEAKER_0:  But, um...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I was basically tracking like live what I did.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  What I saw is that.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of my real work would be done in small sections of the day.
SPEAKER_0:  and then it'd be like a lot of just nothing.
SPEAKER_0:  like a lot of small things where I'm busy.
SPEAKER_0:  but little is being achieved.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I think that's.
SPEAKER_0:  a really interesting insight.
SPEAKER_0:  I've never figured out how to un-busy myself and focus on the
SPEAKER_0:  core essentials, I'm still.
SPEAKER_0:  Getting to that.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  It is interesting realizing most of your day is like a lot of nothing and then like some real deep work where most of your value comes from is like 20% of your day.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I tried to start every day with that. So the hardest task of the day and you focus for long periods of time. And I also have the segment of two hours.
SPEAKER_1:  where it's a set of tasks that I do every single day.
SPEAKER_1:  What are the ideas you do that?
SPEAKER_1:  for like your whole life.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like long-term investment.
SPEAKER_1:  of Anki and-
SPEAKER_1:  It's just like.
SPEAKER_1:  learning and
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  reminding yourself of facts that are useful in your everyday life.
SPEAKER_1:  And then for me, I'll also music. I'll play a little bit of music. Play the piano.
SPEAKER_1:  piano.
SPEAKER_1:  So like
SPEAKER_1:  keeping that regular thing as part of your life.
SPEAKER_0:  And one thing that I've really taken from this because I've read all the like
SPEAKER_0:  I had a self-improvement phase in my early 20s.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  And one thing you learn is that everyone wants to give you a broad general solution.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  really
SPEAKER_0:  The real trick of figuring out like optimizing.
SPEAKER_0:  is figuring out the things that work for you specifically. So like one interesting thing you said is like, oh, I like to do.
SPEAKER_0:  my hard work at the beginning of the day.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I know.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of people recommend this.
SPEAKER_0:  I've tried so many times.
SPEAKER_0:  and I just do better work.
SPEAKER_0:  late at night.
SPEAKER_0:  And so usually my streak of work is from like...
SPEAKER_0:  After dinner?
SPEAKER_0:  730 to like.
SPEAKER_0:  2 a.m. that's my.
SPEAKER_0:  prime time.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And so like a lot of my videos, which you'll see, which is like lit from this studio, which appears to be daytime, it's like shot at 3 a.m.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, just like in a caffeine fueled rush.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  but that's kind of how it works for me. And then also like with the social outlets and stuff like that which-
SPEAKER_0:  It's easy and I feel like we think similarly on this. So it's easy to discount these things as.
SPEAKER_0:  less relevant because they don't have
SPEAKER_0:  quantitative.
SPEAKER_0:  metrics associated with them.
SPEAKER_0:  But in terms of longevity and
SPEAKER_0:  like.
SPEAKER_0:  I think to be able to.
SPEAKER_0:  do creative work.
SPEAKER_0:  there's an amount of recharge and like re-inputting stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  that is frequently discounted by people like us who are like.
SPEAKER_0:  obsessed with quantitative metrics.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I really found that.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of my best work gets done after I take a break or I'll go play live sets of music.
SPEAKER_0:  And I mean, like that's like for me really recharging, but nowhere on a spreadsheet is that gonna show up as productive or like meaningful.
SPEAKER_0:  But for me...
SPEAKER_0:  For whatever reason, it recharges me in a way that like...
SPEAKER_0:  I need to pay attention to.
SPEAKER_1:  I usually have a spreadsheet of 15 minute increments when I'm socially interacting with people and I evaluate how I'm getting roasted right now. No, I'm not. It's actually
SPEAKER_1:  I probably roasting myself.
SPEAKER_1:  I do find that...
SPEAKER_1:  when I do have social interactions.
SPEAKER_1:  I like to deal with people that are outside of that exceptionally busy.
SPEAKER_1:  themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  because then you understand the value of time.
SPEAKER_1:  And when you understand the value of time, your interaction.
SPEAKER_1:  becomes more intimate and intense.
SPEAKER_1:  like.
SPEAKER_1:  The cliche of work hard.
SPEAKER_1:  party hard or whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  the shade. Play hard. Play hard dammit.
SPEAKER_1:  Whatever the English.
SPEAKER_0:  interaction
SPEAKER_1:  No, I'm just kidding.
SPEAKER_1:  Um
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  The...
SPEAKER_1:  That, I mean that cliche, there's a truth to that, but the intensity.
SPEAKER_1:  of the social interaction.
SPEAKER_1:  Even like-
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's not even the intensity, it's not even the party heart, it's like, um...
SPEAKER_1:  even if you're going hiking and relaxing taking in nature says very relaxed
SPEAKER_1:  but you understand the value of that. There's Maria Wong in our programs and the touchscreen,
SPEAKER_1:  when you put a huge amount of value on those moments.
SPEAKER_1:  in nature.
SPEAKER_1:  That recharges me much more.
SPEAKER_1:  So you have to surround yourself with people that think of life that way.
SPEAKER_1:  that think about the value of every single moment.
SPEAKER_1:  That's one of the things you do when you break it up in 15 minute increments is you realize how much
SPEAKER_1:  Time there's in the day.
SPEAKER_1:  how much awesomeness there's in a day to experience, to get done and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  And then so you can feel that when you're with somebody.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  And then for me personally, like when I interact with people.
SPEAKER_1:  I really like to be.
SPEAKER_1:  fully present.
SPEAKER_1:  for the interaction like.
SPEAKER_0:  I can tell this is.
SPEAKER_0:  For anyone who has, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  I've been the audience forever, so I-
SPEAKER_0:  I haven't been on this side of the table before. You're very intense. OH MY GOD STFU
SPEAKER_0:  right in the eye. You're like. Right in the eye.
SPEAKER_1:  eye contact is an issue but yes.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a soulful gaze guys just in case you're wondering. Yeah, it's very soulful. All right, very all right reading It's like a bug back to serious
SPEAKER_1:  is talk. Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  You've studied a lot of people who lie, who defraud.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, cheat and scam.
SPEAKER_1:  on a basic human level.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  How?
SPEAKER_1:  Do you have trouble trusting human beings in your life?
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  What's your relationship with trust?
SPEAKER_1:  other humans? Great question.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Funny enough, before I did this, I was like an incorrigible optimist.
SPEAKER_0:  I-
SPEAKER_0:  everything, the sun shined.
SPEAKER_0:  every which place.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, I always saw like.
SPEAKER_0:  Everybody is fundamentally.
SPEAKER_0:  good, nobody was bad, it just was like sort of wrong place, wrong time, bad incentives.
SPEAKER_0:  That view has darkened significantly.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, but.
SPEAKER_0:  I just try to remember my sample set.
SPEAKER_0:  and just like I'm just sampling sort of the worst.
SPEAKER_0:  And I try not to let it bleed into my...
SPEAKER_0:  day to day life and I think I've.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's probably because I was such an optimist early on.
SPEAKER_0:  that I've.
SPEAKER_0:  I've been able to kind of retain some of it.
SPEAKER_0:  I call it enlightened optimism.
SPEAKER_0:  like choosing to be optimistic in the face of.
SPEAKER_0:  a realistic sense of the problems in the world, and with a realistic sense of like the scale and the challenge ahead.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I actually think it's much braver to be an optimist.
SPEAKER_0:  when you're aware of what's going on in the world then you're more than to be a cynic, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Being a complete cynic is maybe...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not saying it's wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  but I'm saying it's maybe the easier way.
SPEAKER_0:  Just mentally.
SPEAKER_0:  said cope.
SPEAKER_0:  with so much negativity.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like.
SPEAKER_0:  just saying, well, it's all bad, it's all doomed to fail, it's all gonna go bust.
SPEAKER_0:  is
SPEAKER_0:  easier.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, that leap into believing that's a good world is...
SPEAKER_1:  It's a little baby act of courage.
SPEAKER_1:  Or at least I think so.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't think it's naive.
SPEAKER_0:  No, it can be. Some people are naive that are optimistic, but oftentimes...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Just because someone's optimistic does not mean they're naive. They could be full well aware of how-
SPEAKER_0:  troubling the world is.
SPEAKER_1:  And I also believe some of the people you study.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm a big believer that all of us are capable of good and evil.
SPEAKER_1:  So in some sense, the people you study are just the successful ones.
SPEAKER_1:  the ones who are
SPEAKER_1:  chose.
SPEAKER_1:  sort of the dark path and we're successful at it. I think all of us can choose the dark path in life.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a, that's like the.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the responsibility we all carry, is we get to choose that.
SPEAKER_1:  at every moment.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's like a big responsibility.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's a chance to really have integrity. It's a chance to stand for something good in this world.
SPEAKER_1:  All of us have that because I think
SPEAKER_1:  All of us are capable of you.
SPEAKER_1:  All of us could be good Germans, all of us could in atrocities.
SPEAKER_1:  be part of the atrocities.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think it's...
SPEAKER_0:  I really have, especially in recent years.
SPEAKER_0:  try to.
SPEAKER_0:  somewhat depersonalize my work.
SPEAKER_0:  And, um.
SPEAKER_0:  it almost like as like a...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  like a force of nature that I'm fighting more than like
SPEAKER_0:  individuals.
SPEAKER_0:  Because of this exact thing, I think like.
SPEAKER_0:  sort of, therefore but the grace of God, their go I is kind of a
SPEAKER_0:  really profound way to understand yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  rather than it's just like fundamentally.
SPEAKER_0:  good and like
SPEAKER_0:  full of integrity.
SPEAKER_0:  acknowledging that so much of that is a product of your environment and your family and your upbringing.
SPEAKER_0:  and so much of the people who don't have that is a product of
SPEAKER_0:  their environment, it doesn't absolve them.
SPEAKER_0:  but it gives you more perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  Too tr-
SPEAKER_0:  like to sort of deal fairly.
SPEAKER_0:  Does that make sense?
SPEAKER_0:  and not approach it from a place of anger?
SPEAKER_0:  or a place of
SPEAKER_0:  outrage
SPEAKER_0:  There is a sense of sadness for the victims. There's a sense of outrage for the victims.
SPEAKER_0:  approach the individual who's done the thing.
SPEAKER_0:  From that.
SPEAKER_0:  place of understanding of.
SPEAKER_0:  This isn't just this person. There's like a whole broader thing going on here.
SPEAKER_1:  idea of advice for young people
SPEAKER_1:  of how to live this life.
SPEAKER_1:  how to have a career they can be proud of. So high school students, college students, or maybe a life they can be proud of.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me think about this.
SPEAKER_0:  for a second.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't be afraid to go against the grain.
SPEAKER_0:  and sort of challenge.
SPEAKER_0:  the expectations on you.
SPEAKER_0:  um...
SPEAKER_0:  Like you sort of have to do this weird thing where you acknowledge
SPEAKER_0:  how difficult it will be to achieve something great, while also
SPEAKER_0:  having the courage to go for it anyways.
SPEAKER_0:  and understanding that.
SPEAKER_0:  other people don't have it figured out, I think, is a big theme of my work.
SPEAKER_0:  which is that everyone wants like
SPEAKER_0:  the guru to show them the way.
SPEAKER_0:  to show them the secrets, so much of life and achieving anything.
SPEAKER_0:  is learning to figure it out yourself and like.
SPEAKER_0:  The Meta Skill.
SPEAKER_0:  of being an autodidactic where you can.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if I said that word right. You basically use self teach.
SPEAKER_0:  you learn the meta skill of like learning to learn.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's such an underrated aspect of education. People leave education, they go, when am I going to use two plus two?
SPEAKER_0:  We're not gonna learn, you know, use calculus.
SPEAKER_0:  but so much of it is learning this higher level abstract thinking.
SPEAKER_0:  that can apply to anything.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Getting that early on is, um...
SPEAKER_0:  incredibly powerful.
SPEAKER_0:  So yeah, I would say like a lot of it.
SPEAKER_0:  is
SPEAKER_0:  is I guess to some extent, like you kind of have to do that Steve jobs thing where you realize that
SPEAKER_0:  Nobody else in the world is smarter than you.
SPEAKER_0:  and that.
SPEAKER_0:  Both means that like
SPEAKER_0:  They can't show you the perfect way, but it also means you could do great things.
SPEAKER_0:  and kind of chart your own path, I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  That's so cheesy.
SPEAKER_0:  This is why I hate giving advice. I feel like it's cheesy. And I don't think it is. I think my journey is so full of luck and like-
SPEAKER_0:  specific experience. I wonder how generalizable it is, but
SPEAKER_0:  if I've learned anything, and if I could talk specifically to myself, I guess that's what I would say.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, you've taken a very difficult path.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think part of taking that path, like of a great journalist, frankly, is like.
SPEAKER_1:  I can be that person.
SPEAKER_1:  I just believing in yourself that you could take that.
SPEAKER_1:  Because if you see...
SPEAKER_1:  A problem in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  You could be the solution to that problem.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you can solve that problem. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that's like, uh, it's really important to believe that.
SPEAKER_1:  Is the...
SPEAKER_1:  It depends.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe you're lucky to have the belief inside yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe the thing that you're saying is like, don't look to others for that strength.
SPEAKER_0:  And also, and also like be really comfortable failing, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  One of the-
SPEAKER_0:  Best things that like you would never know about me?
SPEAKER_0:  just looking at my background that helped me.
SPEAKER_0:  was
SPEAKER_0:  playing music live.
SPEAKER_0:  I had incredible amounts of stage fright.
SPEAKER_0:  Growing up.
SPEAKER_0:  mostly because I was terrible at piano. I was like shocked.
SPEAKER_0:  And I specifically, I taught myself how to play.
SPEAKER_0:  and I joined jazz band in like high school.
SPEAKER_0:  Did it through college.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember-
SPEAKER_0:  all my recitals, I messed up every single solo I ever did.
SPEAKER_0:  I never like actually nailed it.
SPEAKER_0:  And every time I'd go up there, I'd have so much dread around this.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was easier to get up there because there were sort of some people up there.
SPEAKER_0:  But eventually...
SPEAKER_0:  I started like playing live too and I sucked at that.
SPEAKER_0:  And I've just gone through the trenches of like, just like...
SPEAKER_0:  being.
SPEAKER_0:  publicly sort of
SPEAKER_0:  in my mind humiliated.
SPEAKER_0:  prepared me so much for what I do now of trying to basically being fearless.
SPEAKER_0:  of failure.
SPEAKER_0:  in the face of like a wide audience.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't have that anymore, because I've experienced so many...
SPEAKER_0:  iterations of it at a smaller scale of just like.
SPEAKER_0:  Abject public humiliation to where it's like not something that bothers me. I have no stage fright
SPEAKER_0:  that doesn't bother me anymore.
SPEAKER_0:  You'd think like, oh, maybe he just was always good at this. I was terrible at it. I had a complete phobia.
SPEAKER_0:  about.
SPEAKER_0:  public anything.
SPEAKER_0:  So, um...
SPEAKER_0:  It was that rapid iteration of just failure. And eventually I just came to the conclusion that I want to love it.
SPEAKER_0:  I wanna like, love like-
SPEAKER_0:  getting up on a stage and bombing?
SPEAKER_0:  If you can learn to bite.
SPEAKER_0:  Love that?
SPEAKER_0:  and be fearless there.
SPEAKER_0:  Almost nothing you can't do.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, that's brilliant advice. I'm with you still terrifying to me like live performance.
SPEAKER_1:  But yeah, that's exactly the feeling is.
SPEAKER_1:  loving.
SPEAKER_1:  the fact that you tried.
SPEAKER_1:  And somehow...
SPEAKER_1:  Failure.
SPEAKER_1:  is like.
SPEAKER_1:  a deeper celebration of the fact that you tried.
SPEAKER_1:  Because success is easy. But failure is like bombing. I mean, music, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  on the smallest and the largest of stages.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not gonna say who.
SPEAKER_1:  But there's a huge band.
SPEAKER_1:  Huge band that wanted to be on stage.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Probably will happen.
SPEAKER_1:  but like...
SPEAKER_1:  but I turned it down because I was like...
SPEAKER_1:  No.
SPEAKER_1:  Cause I'm gonna suck for sure.
SPEAKER_0:  The question is.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you do it? Wanna suck?
SPEAKER_1:  in a
SPEAKER_1:  in front of a very large live audience. Yep.
SPEAKER_1:  And uh...
SPEAKER_1:  And then I turned it down, I was like, no.
SPEAKER_1:  But now I realize...
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  Embrace it. It's gonna be good. It's gonna be good for you. It's gonna crush your ego to the degrees remaining. And it's just good for you. It's good not to take yourself seriously and do those kinds of things. But honestly, I feel that way.
SPEAKER_1:  in an audience.
SPEAKER_1:  I can't open mic.
SPEAKER_1:  It hurts.
SPEAKER_1:  That's why I really admire comedians.
SPEAKER_1:  I go to open mics all the time with comedians and musicians.
SPEAKER_1:  I just see them bomb and you'll play-
SPEAKER_1:  play in front of like just a.
SPEAKER_1:  a few folks and
SPEAKER_1:  They're putting their heart out and especially the ones that kind of suck, but are going all out anyway.
SPEAKER_0:  I think open mics are the best place to learn though, because it's the lowest stakes you can get.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, while still being public.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're gonna face fears around this, because we're talking very specifically public speaking or any kind of like...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, being in front of a camera.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're gonna face your fear.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to do it.
SPEAKER_0:  And the easiest way to do it is to lower the stakes.
SPEAKER_0:  You're not gonna start being Lex Friedman on stage with a huge band. You don't wanna be.
SPEAKER_0:  Like it's like in that way, it is so impossible.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  But the more you lower the stakes and just like open it up to like two strangers, five strangers.
SPEAKER_0:  the most dive bar open mic you can go to.
SPEAKER_0:  and like start performing.
SPEAKER_0:  That's really what I did is like, like I love open mics now because it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  Low stakes on the one hand, but you really get the feeling of like.
SPEAKER_1:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_1:  And get better and better and better at that. Yeah, for sure.
SPEAKER_1:  and then
SPEAKER_1:  you'll get the strength to take bigger and bigger and bigger risks.
SPEAKER_1:  Listen, Koff, I'm a huge fan of yours.
SPEAKER_1:  not just for who you are and
SPEAKER_1:  but for what you stand for.
SPEAKER_1:  People like you.
SPEAKER_1:  are rare and they're a huge inspiration.
SPEAKER_1:  I just, I'm inspired by your.
SPEAKER_1:  Fearlessness, the year.
SPEAKER_1:  that you're taking on some of the.
SPEAKER_1:  most powerful and richest people in this world in doing so.
SPEAKER_1:  with respect, I think, with good faith, but also with the boldness and fearlessness. Listen, man, I'm a huge fan. Keep doing what you're doing.
SPEAKER_1:  As long as you got the strength for it, because I think you inspire all of us. You're doing important work, brother.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for having me.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with Coffeezilla.
SPEAKER_1:  To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now...
SPEAKER_1:  Let me leave you with some words from Walter Lippmann.
SPEAKER_1:  There can be no higher law in journalism.
SPEAKER_1:  than to tell the truth.
SPEAKER_1:  and to shame the devil.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for listening and hope to see you.
SPEAKER_1:  next time.