SPEAKER_0:  when it's quiet.
SPEAKER_0:  That's when it hits ya.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what I think that's what a lot of people experience when they come back from a conflict zone.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, the uh...
SPEAKER_0:  everything that was life and death.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything that mattered, all the noise, all the chaos, all the people that are around you that would die for you, kill for you.
SPEAKER_0:  you would kill for them.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll leave.
SPEAKER_0:  millions of dollars worth of equipment and stuff like that you were responsible for now are all gone and it's just you
SPEAKER_1:  The following is a conversation with Ed Calderon.
SPEAKER_1:  a security specialist who has worked for many years.
SPEAKER_1:  encounter narcotics and organize crime investigation.
SPEAKER_1:  in the northern border region of Mexico.
SPEAKER_1:  I highly recommend.
SPEAKER_1:  You follow the writing and courses.
SPEAKER_1:  on his Patreon and website.
SPEAKER_1:  EdsManifesto.com
SPEAKER_1:  This is the Lex Friedman podcast.
SPEAKER_1:  To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now...
SPEAKER_1:  Dear friends
SPEAKER_1:  Here's Ed.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll do wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  What does your experience in counter-narcotics, investigating the Mexican drug cartel, teach you about human nature?
SPEAKER_0:  Wow.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  First off, anybody can be God.
SPEAKER_0:  anybody can be corrupted.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, you know, you...
SPEAKER_0:  You work in that field and you...
SPEAKER_0:  you.
SPEAKER_0:  Realistically the training we got and profiling and investigation and stuff like that was basically you learn from the older guys there
SPEAKER_0:  And some of those guys were already corrupted from the start. So...
SPEAKER_0:  Trust no one.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember seeing that X-Files episode where that was stated.
SPEAKER_0:  you quickly learn that even if you are somebody that, to your own mind appears incorruptible.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, small changes happen around you, wheels get greased, money gets put in front of you and or things get threatened like your life.
SPEAKER_0:  And sometimes a payment for some of this corruption is just to continue on living.
SPEAKER_0:  you encounter people that seem incorruptible, that go through FBI background checks, that go through all of the uh...
SPEAKER_0:  the security measures that all of us were put through, polygraph test. And then later on, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  turns out they were on the take or they became somebody that was corrupted.
SPEAKER_0:  I think what I found out is that anybody...
SPEAKER_0:  at any level. They could be a very strong, hard to get person right now.
SPEAKER_0:  people.
SPEAKER_0:  corrupted through their families.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, through need.
SPEAKER_0:  Mexico is a
SPEAKER_0:  place where a lot of uh...
SPEAKER_0:  instability occurs.
SPEAKER_0:  So financial needs, health.
SPEAKER_1:  so a crack could form through the wall of integrity and then...
SPEAKER_1:  over time.
SPEAKER_1:  It seeps in.
SPEAKER_0:  Mexico has a culture of corruption. Like, you know, you have your kid that goes to school at public school and you want him to be in the morning, not in the afternoon school.
SPEAKER_0:  time period.
SPEAKER_0:  You go off and grease the wheels with the director of the school. People hearing this in Mexico will nod their heads because this is something that happens from early on.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's a systemic and cultural thing to it, as far as getting around rules. And this happens because the people that are in charge in Mexico, the government is.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there are tandem amount of trust between criminals and the cartels down there for a lot of the culture. So people don't trust the government and much less criminality.
SPEAKER_1:  When you meet a person...
SPEAKER_1:  sticking on human nature, do you think it's possible to figure out if they can be trusted?
SPEAKER_1:  So you said...
SPEAKER_1:  Anyone can be corrupted.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, how long would you need to talk to a person?
SPEAKER_1:  and you're even in your own personal private life, just a friend.
SPEAKER_1:  or is trust a thing that's never really guaranteed.
SPEAKER_0:  I think trust is never really guaranteed. I know a lot of people are going to say that's a sad way and hard way of living your life, but life experience is my end.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, people change. You know, the dynamics of a relationship might change. I look at people's character, specifically their past and past experiences if I can.
SPEAKER_0:  somebody that presents themselves in front of you as somebody, but you quickly learn that that somebody is just a mask or a persona that they kind of created for themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  And they might not even be aware of the persona. Like is there some deep sex?
SPEAKER_0:  stuff sometimes.
SPEAKER_0:  I've experienced a lot of a...
SPEAKER_0:  failure in my life. You can see it in my nose. You can see it in my lack of a...
SPEAKER_0:  love
SPEAKER_0:  a digit, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  the amount of uh...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, the amount of failures you can see in somebody and how they wear them sometimes is a pretty telling thing as far as them being able to be trusted or that you can trust their story or their experience.
SPEAKER_0:  And when I say experience, I mean, I've met some criminals, like former criminals or, you know, some people of that background that I trust with my life, you know, because they're not reformed.
SPEAKER_0:  But they figured out that that's not not a life that can live long enough to kind of continue on and
SPEAKER_0:  And I've also met people that are in law enforcement that I wouldn't trust with my car keys, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  because whatever persona they adopted over the years.
SPEAKER_0:  is a pretty good one, pretty good mask. Sometimes such a good mask they don't even know they're wearing it.
SPEAKER_1:  And on top of that, it's not just the psychology, there's also in your biology to it.
SPEAKER_1:  I've been very fortunate.
SPEAKER_1:  and deliberate.
SPEAKER_1:  to surround myself with good people throughout my life.
SPEAKER_1:  but I've recently gotten to sort of observe.
SPEAKER_1:  close to me but...
SPEAKER_1:  Nearby.
SPEAKER_1:  somebody that could be classified as a sociopath.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  and a narcissist. Like I don't wanna use those psychological terms, but just-
SPEAKER_1:  It's like, oh.
SPEAKER_1:  people.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, come with different biology too.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's not just like the trauma you might experience in your early life and all the deep complexity that leads.
SPEAKER_1:  all the deep complexity that leads to the
SPEAKER_1:  the psychology that you have as an adult.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's also the biology come with the nature.
SPEAKER_1:  that you might not just have the...
SPEAKER_1:  the machine.
SPEAKER_1:  that can empathize deeply with the experience of others, or maybe a machine that gets off.
SPEAKER_1:  gets a dopamine rush from the manipulation of other humans.
SPEAKER_0:  Or the control of other humans. Yeah, I mean, put an example of my own background.
SPEAKER_0:  My mom didn't have a father.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, he left really early on in their childhood. You know, my mom raised.
SPEAKER_0:  her two sisters.
SPEAKER_0:  and basically kept a household.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, she was.
SPEAKER_0:  But great, Mom.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  She was a badass, she was very independent. She showed me how to be independent. She showed me how to watch out for others and build me up in that way.
SPEAKER_0:  And I had a great childhood as far as, you know, as far as.
SPEAKER_0:  per
SPEAKER_0:  and kind of like how she molded me. And later on I figured out.
SPEAKER_0:  that uh... when i had my own kid
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I...
SPEAKER_0:  I figure out that she was basically trying to make me into what she didn't have.
SPEAKER_0:  in a way.
SPEAKER_0:  and if I can get to see somebody's parents, you know, that's usually a sign of something at least for me as far as figuring out where people are.
SPEAKER_0:  I think there's something to be said about nature and nurture and how some people come up.
SPEAKER_0:  Some people are just born with that predatory instinct.
SPEAKER_0:  and you'll never know. I mean, they spend their whole life practicing how to hide it.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you can figure out somebody's background, childhood, where they're from.
SPEAKER_0:  can kind of tell something about them. I'm from Tijuana, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm a survivor. That's my background as far as where I'm from.
SPEAKER_1:  culturally, genetically.
SPEAKER_1:  psychologically.
SPEAKER_1:  the full shebae.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I guess some people are born with certain...
SPEAKER_0:  predispositions and
SPEAKER_0:  If they're in the right environment, some of the negative aspects might flourish more than others.
SPEAKER_0:  For me, I mean, I grew up skateboarding.
SPEAKER_0:  in Tijuana.
SPEAKER_0:  and I remember breaking into my first backyard pool.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a house that I...
SPEAKER_0:  cartel guy owned and we used to skate the pool in the back of it.
SPEAKER_0:  So I learned how to bop open padlocks with a small vehicle.
SPEAKER_0:  hydraulic lift.
SPEAKER_0:  And I remember doing that. And later on in life, I got to train with people from other parts of Mexico. And,
SPEAKER_0:  and work with them. And I remember pulling that trick off and they were like looking at me like.
SPEAKER_0:  Where'd you learn that?
SPEAKER_0:  like some burglars at Tijuana.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  And they're like, wow, that's interesting. Are all people from Tijuana like that?
SPEAKER_0:  And I said, no, we're not all like that, but I guess in some way we are because, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Tijuana produces some.
SPEAKER_0:  produces kids like that, you know, she produces like the environment itself produces.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... produces a pretty specific person i guess you know where our normal is our normal or baseline normal is way different than most
SPEAKER_1:  The trajectories that you can take in life are.
SPEAKER_1:  are defined in a way that aren't.
SPEAKER_1:  available elsewhere in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  And so you develop, I mean, part of that is psychological, part of that is cultural and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  part of this is cultural trauma.
SPEAKER_1:  but then also the ethical lines.
SPEAKER_1:  based on the corruption.
SPEAKER_1:  As I grew up in the Soviet Union, there's the same kind of understanding.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  There's some gray area of corruption.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  It's always there, like on the outskirts or even in the center.
SPEAKER_0:  how you can grease things to make things easier.
SPEAKER_0:  and how it's like a personal thing. I'll just pay off the-
SPEAKER_0:  In Tijuana we have a mordida is what we call it, when you pay a cop off.
SPEAKER_0:  A bite means a bite.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  But what's out?
SPEAKER_1:  What's the bite at-
SPEAKER_0:  So you get stopped for a traffic violation of some sort and the cop walks up to you. Obviously you don't say the word bite, but it's like a slang term for it.
SPEAKER_0:  And he asks for your paperwork and if you...
SPEAKER_0:  get fined or get a ticket, you say, can I pay the ticket here?
SPEAKER_0:  is what they say.
SPEAKER_0:  and put their money inside the paperwork and hand it over to the cops. You think it's, you know, I'm just going to do it and nobody knows.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's a systemic thing, everybody. Like a lot of people do it and then they don't trust the police because they are fed with this.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, same thing was in the Soviet Union, it's funny.
SPEAKER_1:  But then there's something inside you.
SPEAKER_1:  or that kind of...
SPEAKER_1:  Those opportunities come with a police officer where you realize you can just pay a little bit of money.
SPEAKER_1:  and get out of the thing.
SPEAKER_1:  and then you realize you can pay a little bit of money or do a favor.
SPEAKER_1:  to get your kids in a better school.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  But there comes opportunities where you...
SPEAKER_1:  Where, all right.
SPEAKER_1:  If I do this little thing.
SPEAKER_1:  I can make.
SPEAKER_1:  I can get a huge promotion, I can get a huge increase in my power.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't get a lot of money.
SPEAKER_1:  And something inside you says no.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, that's not right. Yeah. I wonder what that is that because like, um,
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I want because it feels different than the legal systems of the language operate. There's some kind of basic human integrity, human decency.
SPEAKER_1:  I wonder if that's like constructed or it's always there.
SPEAKER_1:  Again, nature versus nurture.
SPEAKER_0:  I think for me it was looking at seeing that in somebody else.
SPEAKER_0:  that I kind of learned about it.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a man that I consider a mentor figure.
SPEAKER_0:  His name is Lieutenant Colonel Liza Oda
SPEAKER_0:  He was a Lieutenant Colonel from the Army that basically came over and took over the group that I used to work with.
SPEAKER_0:  He was incorruptible. You know, that was the essence or the aura that he projected.
SPEAKER_0:  Um,
SPEAKER_0:  The first time he went off on patrol, when he was placed in charge of us, I actually drove him around Tijuana.
SPEAKER_0:  He was one of the lead from the front type of people
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  the amount of assassination attempts he got.
SPEAKER_0:  It was basically a proof of how uncorruptible he was because they kept trying to pay him off. And when that didn't work, they tried to kill him several times. I think the last assassination attempt took the use of his legs.
SPEAKER_0:  That man is still a dangerous person in my mind.
SPEAKER_0:  But for me...
SPEAKER_0:  and you know people can.
SPEAKER_0:  gather a little bit about my background and where I'm from and some of the access I currently have to train the federal institutions here in the US as far as
SPEAKER_0:  my background and if I was corrupted or not because there's a lot of that out there.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  The...
SPEAKER_0:  The Catholic guilt that's kind of built into some of us is always kind of there, you know. El cucuy vive bajo la cama. The devil was under the bed.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't consider myself Catholic, consider myself culturally Catholic, I think, is what I kind of say with that.
SPEAKER_0:  I had a pretty good structure with my dad and my mom at the house and you know they never let me get away with it.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  things.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think my mom was a pretty big moral compass for me.
SPEAKER_0:  but Lieutenant Colonel leading from example and seeing his work and how
SPEAKER_0:  how much profound change he caused in the people that work with him as far as, you know, we felt supported and we felt like we had a guiding figure.
SPEAKER_0:  during this.
SPEAKER_0:  Tijuana was the most dangerous city on the planet when I was working there and he took charge.
SPEAKER_1:  What does it take to be a man, Lieutenant Colonel?
SPEAKER_1:  who maintains integrity after assassination attempts.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it possible for a normal human to do that?
SPEAKER_1:  or again as a genetic.
SPEAKER_0:  That's an interesting question. I'll say this.
SPEAKER_0:  Seeing him, I mean, the last assassination attempt he had, that took the use of his legs, he was with his kid.
SPEAKER_0:  Aha.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a recklessness to it.
SPEAKER_0:  I can see that now, now that I have enough distance from it.
SPEAKER_0:  I could see that there's a recklessness to being that way.
SPEAKER_0:  And also you're putting jeopardy people around you if you take that route.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think there's a sacrifice to it, a very powerful and hard one to make for a lot of people.
SPEAKER_0:  For me, it was I wouldn't get picked to...
SPEAKER_0:  get on board with some of the operations groups that I wanted to work with because I was known for not
SPEAKER_0:  taking money or...
SPEAKER_0:  not being trusted by certain older segments of the organization that I was with.
SPEAKER_0:  with stuff because they knew that I wouldn't.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I wasn't on the-
SPEAKER_0:  I wouldn't get money.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's always a weird sacrifice to it and you're almost kind of like masochistic in that way when you...
SPEAKER_0:  When you get approached with it, they're like, why are you being an idiot? Why are you driving around that beat up car? Look at the Hummer H2 that just drove in with the other guy that is doing exactly your same job.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Society as a whole down there.
SPEAKER_0:  doesn't reward it or at least doesn't see it in the people that don't take that route in Mexico you know for them is all cops are corrupt.
SPEAKER_0:  all of them.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  you know, seeing it from the outside. I'm not there anymore.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... there is
SPEAKER_0:  There's almost like a, why didn't you add?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  that could have been easier maybe, or you could have been dead long ago, because people that are on the take down there are usually owned by one.
SPEAKER_0:  side or the other and when that gets found out, you know, if you have somebody that you're paying off that hints you off of drug operations in the area.
SPEAKER_0:  your rivals are pretty keen on killing you.
SPEAKER_1:  Money aside, so like a hummer aside, how much of a motivator is fear?
SPEAKER_0:  big one.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  I'll say...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, for me, I didn't think I was gonna live to see 30.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was sure of it.
SPEAKER_1:  Did that concept scare you or was that just a.
SPEAKER_1:  as a principle of life.
SPEAKER_1:  That's something you're operating under.
SPEAKER_0:  Uhhhh...
SPEAKER_0:  I lost my brother when I was 13.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, he was 19.
SPEAKER_0:  He was like the...
SPEAKER_0:  the VIP of the family, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  You miss him?
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, every day.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  kids are.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, he was a, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  skateboarded BMX.
SPEAKER_0:  motorcycle hunter.
SPEAKER_0:  one of the best marksmen that I've ever seen shoot.
SPEAKER_1:  than you at everything.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, he was the best of us is what we would say.
SPEAKER_0:  And when he died, there was a, there was, it was almost like a concert at this funeral.
SPEAKER_0:  I met three of his girlfriends that all introduced themselves like the one.
SPEAKER_0:  I w-uh
SPEAKER_0:  to this day every now and then I get uh
SPEAKER_0:  pull this eye down when I go back home and the, you know, Eric's.
SPEAKER_0:  Eric's brother.
SPEAKER_0:  despite all the stuff that I've done, I'm still, you know, every now and then I get recognized.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  That made my mom and my dad go into a horrible depression and basically left me to my devices when I was a kid.
SPEAKER_0:  from 13 onwards.
SPEAKER_0:  I had this self-destructive aspect to me after that, I think. It's not something that's come up in therapy after I've gone through all that.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  and had this notion that if I can only die good in some way, shape or form or.
SPEAKER_0:  for something.
SPEAKER_0:  that it would.
SPEAKER_0:  it would matter and they would kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  look at me with the same reverence I did to my brother.
SPEAKER_1:  So dying.
SPEAKER_1:  isn't the problem.
SPEAKER_1:  The goal of life is to die for something good.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, at least.
SPEAKER_0:  That was my...
SPEAKER_0:  That was my mindset going through that job.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't remember.
SPEAKER_0:  I was in medical school before that.
SPEAKER_0:  second year medical school.
SPEAKER_0:  was doing pretty good and then 9-11 happened.
SPEAKER_0:  That wasn't an option anymore for me. The economy was horrible.
SPEAKER_0:  I couldn't afford to stay there.
SPEAKER_0:  I saw this ad in the newspaper and my big brother...
SPEAKER_0:  who's still live in Hed-
SPEAKER_0:  He's like
SPEAKER_0:  You're not going to do that shit. You know, we wouldn't dare.
SPEAKER_0:  And all of a sudden I was in a field having my hair shaved off.
SPEAKER_0:  a bunch of the uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Gafis, the guys that later turned into the Zeta Cartel.
SPEAKER_0:  military were in charge of our training.
SPEAKER_0:  I went through that process. And what
SPEAKER_1:  field wore you and why is your head being shaved?
SPEAKER_1:  and what the hell was going through your mind.
SPEAKER_1:  What was the leap that you took?
SPEAKER_0:  I was sold the idea of this being a new...
SPEAKER_0:  Americanized police force that they were constructing in Mexico
SPEAKER_1:  So, Elite.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. Special force, kind of a.
SPEAKER_0:  prestigious elite, the people in charge of our training were a lot, basically ex-Mexican gaffa people, gaffas are
SPEAKER_0:  what the Special Forces kind of originated. A lot of their members turned into the Zeta Cartel. so
SPEAKER_0:  they were brutal in their training.
SPEAKER_0:  We were sold this idea of it being, you know, scientific, like, educated-based.
SPEAKER_0:  career path.
SPEAKER_0:  And all of a sudden we're in this, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  refurbished prison.
SPEAKER_0:  that wasn't good enough to be a prison and they turned it into a training ground.
SPEAKER_0:  And I quickly kind of realized that they were training us to be a paramilitary group, not a community policing organization.
SPEAKER_0:  which in my mind, that's what I thought, that's what we're going to be doing.
SPEAKER_0:  What was the hardest?
SPEAKER_1:  process of that training.
SPEAKER_1:  Because this is like a...
SPEAKER_1:  Fragile innocent boy becomes a man kind of
SPEAKER_0:  process. It's turning us into something that they could use.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's a breaking down.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  they break down the individual, you know, it's a...
SPEAKER_1:  physically, mentally.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think it's a...
SPEAKER_0:  It's a half-done initiation process, I think, in a way, looking at it from now.
SPEAKER_0:  into the past via.
SPEAKER_0:  the shaving of the hair, the stripping off your identity, you know, everybody gets a...
SPEAKER_0:  gets a number.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  the uniforms, the...
SPEAKER_0:  running around and
SPEAKER_0:  and being treated like human garbage.
SPEAKER_0:  The first thing they said to us when we were lined up in that field was,
SPEAKER_0:  There's bread and shit to eat here, the bread is over.
SPEAKER_0:  which means there's bread and dick to eat here, and the bread ran out.
SPEAKER_0:  a week ago.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  It was, I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  I can't equate it to anything in the military over here in the United States because people down there could actually get physical with us. I mean they could actually.
SPEAKER_0:  and punches and shit like that which is...
SPEAKER_0:  not allowed here anymore, at least in most of the military, as horrible as down there.
SPEAKER_0:  The AK-47 is being shot around us too.
SPEAKER_0:  simulate reality, basically causing hearing loss, that type of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  to chaos.
SPEAKER_1:  abuse really challenging you again physically.
SPEAKER_0:  And an open door there always so if you don't want to be here you can just walk out and the more you go into it
SPEAKER_0:  time wise you're more invested you are so.
SPEAKER_0:  in a way you're kind of building your own chains while you're going through that process.
SPEAKER_1:  Were you tempted to walk out?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, several times.
SPEAKER_0:  several times, specifically seeing some of the ways that...
SPEAKER_0:  people that I thought were better.
SPEAKER_0:  were stronger than we were walking out or quitting.
SPEAKER_0:  Ah.
SPEAKER_0:  because of something that happened in there.
SPEAKER_0:  or with some sexual.
SPEAKER_0:  assault stuff happening in there as well.
SPEAKER_1:  Are you afraid of that?
SPEAKER_0:  Always, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  you're in a place like that and there's females in the environment and some of the instructors are...
SPEAKER_0:  doing what they do.
SPEAKER_0:  So that was like a cause for alarm. I mean, these people are in charge of our safety and education and look at what's happening here. So you could see some of the.
SPEAKER_0:  the smarter.
SPEAKER_0:  one's leaving, you know, not looking at this as a viable choice for life.
SPEAKER_1:  How did that change those few months?
SPEAKER_0:  I had this idealistic motivation in my head of making a difference.
SPEAKER_0:  they drill.
SPEAKER_0:  They drill a lot of, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Nationalistic.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, you know, the flag marching.
SPEAKER_0:  it being part of a group and the group being behind you and all of this.
SPEAKER_1:  What was the nationalistic pride?
SPEAKER_1:  It was in the nation of Mexico. Yeah, yeah. What's the vision of this great nation of Mexico that you were, did you believe that it'd get into your-
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  I got into my, I mean, it's indoctrination, you know, it's a
SPEAKER_0:  It's a paramilitary group, so everything there is basically modeled after the military. So that's what they were trying to kind of instill in us.
SPEAKER_0:  I was a...
SPEAKER_0:  I was a team leader in there after.
SPEAKER_0:  Three months, basically I was...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  We went through a bunch of trials, physical trials, mental trials and stuff like that. Some of us were named team leaders.
SPEAKER_0:  and I bought into it.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I'm the, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm supposed to be here, look at me, I'm-
SPEAKER_0:  I'm
SPEAKER_0:  I'm making headways.
SPEAKER_0:  Mama.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm sticking out a bit.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I was pretty proud of.
SPEAKER_0:  what I was going through there, six months.
SPEAKER_0:  then you get the reality check when you sign the dotted line.
SPEAKER_0:  and how that none of it really.
SPEAKER_0:  meant anything as far as what we were about to go out and do.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  An example of this, we were trained with a 92FS Beretta.
SPEAKER_0:  which is a 9mm pistol.
SPEAKER_0:  Italian made.
SPEAKER_0:  We got to shoot 20 rounds out of that gun.
SPEAKER_0:  And then when we got out, we were handed a Glock.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, 17.
SPEAKER_0:  Which
SPEAKER_0:  I've never seen one in my life.
SPEAKER_0:  I was trying to figure out where the safety was and...
SPEAKER_0:  A few other people there were...
SPEAKER_0:  uh... handling those guns in a horrible manner
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So we were very under trained under equipped and there was a lot of assumptions about what we knew and all of a sudden we were being cast into this the start of one of the
SPEAKER_0:  you know, bloodiest and longest lived modern conflicts.
SPEAKER_0:  in our history that doesn't get called that, but it's basically been an ongoing war in Mexico that...
SPEAKER_0:  that is still to this day.
SPEAKER_0:  amassing bodies.
SPEAKER_0:  to the Mexican drug war.
SPEAKER_0:  the Mexican drug war, which is...
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  It's hard to pinpoint exactly when it started because when I was going through training, there was already stuff going on. I went into training in 2004 and there were already, you know...
SPEAKER_0:  major cartel related events all over Mexico by then, but not at the size or scope as I was about to go into.
SPEAKER_0:  President Felipe Calderon took office down there and actually officially kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  kicked it off by...
SPEAKER_0:  putting the military in play as part of a...
SPEAKER_0:  part of it is basically militarize the drug war, including us.
SPEAKER_1:  Who are the major players in this drug war?
SPEAKER_1:  So the politicians...
SPEAKER_1:  The military, the police force.
SPEAKER_1:  cartels.
SPEAKER_1:  All Mexican.
SPEAKER_1:  and the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  China.
SPEAKER_1:  Just the layout.
SPEAKER_1:  all the pieces on the board.
SPEAKER_0:  First off, there are giant local drug markets in Mexico that are fought over.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, just local drug markets that are.
SPEAKER_0:  huge in scope.
SPEAKER_1:  exporting to other locations.
SPEAKER_0:  Just a start. Yeah. Yeah. So a big problem in Mexico is basically those local drug markets and
SPEAKER_0:  An example of that and one I have a lot of experience with is the one in Tijuana.
SPEAKER_0:  which not only feeds the local populace, but also feeds the populace from San Diego that crosses down into Tijuana and buys their product there.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And now, you know, a phenomenon that's occurring now is marijuana trafficking is going from California down into Mexico because they produce better weed, you know, which is.
SPEAKER_0:  Fascinating to see now.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's already a channel and you're kind of reusing it.
SPEAKER_0:  channel. Yeah, there's a lot of people in vehicles getting checked when they drive down in Tijuana.
SPEAKER_0:  is being called San Diego South now because all the economic migrants are living down their own就是說 Apply
SPEAKER_0:  90% of all houses in Tijuana, new houses are being bought up by Americans. So that'll tell you something about the impact and change that's going on down there.
SPEAKER_0:  So you have these local drug markets that are being fought over.
SPEAKER_0:  You also have these drug routes that go through Mexico, up into Mexico, around Mexico, through the ocean, under the wall, drug tunnels.
SPEAKER_0:  over the wall.
SPEAKER_0:  and on backpacks and on
SPEAKER_0:  migrants that go up into the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  Not only do the cartels make money off drug trafficking, but also extortion.
SPEAKER_0:  money laundering, paid protection schemes.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, any mining operation in Mexico will have to pay protection, you know, or else they'll get hit.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of times the largest money makers for some of these criminal groups are...
SPEAKER_0:  protecting and taxing anybody that goes across the border.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's also a big issue.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's not just, again, some Americans think it's like the cartels, you know, they imagine this single or-
SPEAKER_0:  maybe two or three groups, there's several out there.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't have a current estimate, but last time I checked it was somewhere in the vicinity of...
SPEAKER_0:  50, 70.
SPEAKER_0:  different groups, some small, that just dedicate themselves to a single little town somewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  there are armed groups that are basically in control of that area to some bigger federations like the Sinaloa cartel which is
SPEAKER_0:  probably currently the largest and most powerful one in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  and the new generation cartel which is...
SPEAKER_0:  growing exponentially right now.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  So
SPEAKER_0:  these criminal groups are players in that conflict.
SPEAKER_0:  then...
SPEAKER_0:  Another player that doesn't get talked about is politics, politicians.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a...
SPEAKER_0:  There's an ongoing discussion that has been going on, I think, since Trump was elected.
SPEAKER_0:  about cartels being terrorist organizations or not, or if they fit that description.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you know, we are living through...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  multiple assassinations on political candidates on New Mexico right now. And
SPEAKER_0:  Most of those assassinations are motivated by...
SPEAKER_0:  One side.
SPEAKER_0:  sponsoring one candidate and the other side sponsoring the other. What I mean by sides, I mean cartel groups.
SPEAKER_0:  So they have elected officials that are on the take. And this is we have, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  many governors who are under investigation on the run or in prison right now.
SPEAKER_0:  state governors.
SPEAKER_0:  So politics is involved in it. That's a big player as well. That doesn't, you know, when you think about cartel problems, you don't think.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, at least most people don't think about that aspect of it.
SPEAKER_1:  So to have integrity as a politician in Mexico means...
SPEAKER_1:  You have no protection.
SPEAKER_1:  and under constant threat of assassination.
SPEAKER_0:  We just seen the arrest and prosecution of the head of all Conrad Cartel operations when I was active in the form of Garcia Luna.
SPEAKER_0:  who was the guy.
SPEAKER_0:  Felipe Calderon who kicked off the drug war. That was his guy.
SPEAKER_0:  Turns out he was.
SPEAKER_0:  Turns out he was on the dig, at that level.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there like a...
SPEAKER_1:  spectrum of how on the take you can be.
SPEAKER_1:  Are there ethical lines that you can cross?
SPEAKER_1:  Some of it is money and then.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it possible to operate in a gray area?
SPEAKER_1:  that does not.
SPEAKER_1:  result in destructive.
SPEAKER_1:  ethical violations.
SPEAKER_0:  I have no idea. I don't think there is, realistically. I mean, anything that kind of supports some of these groups.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you're supporting things of a horrible nature.
SPEAKER_0:  Ah.
SPEAKER_0:  There, I just posted recently on my Instagram account of a lady that was in Guanajuato.
SPEAKER_0:  She's one of seven recently assassinated women that are looking for their...
SPEAKER_0:  Kids, basically.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a bunch of groups and organizations out there in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  some in Tijuana that I've actually walked with.
SPEAKER_0:  who are...
SPEAKER_0:  taking control of
SPEAKER_0:  trying to find the bodies of their kids.
SPEAKER_0:  That's her up there.
SPEAKER_1:  Maria Carmela Vasquez, a mother who searched
SPEAKER_1:  our missing son was shot to death outside her home.
SPEAKER_1:  On Sunday, her son, Osmar Vasquez, disappeared on June 14th. The 46-year-old woman is the fifth mother to be killed this year while searching for their missing loved ones. She was a member.
SPEAKER_1:  of the Pyamore Missing Person Collective.
SPEAKER_0:  there's many groups out in Mexico who basically have given up on trusting the government to find their kids.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  the number of missing in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  is.....
SPEAKER_0:  debated topic because the government itself doesn't release those numbers or at least hasn't done a good job about keeping them and or releasing them.
SPEAKER_0:  Mexico is a country that has industrialized body disposal.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, in Tijuana we had the stew maker, the legendary stew maker, which is a guy that basically...
SPEAKER_0:  use caustic acid.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  get rid of bodies at a.
SPEAKER_0:  massive level.
SPEAKER_1:  for getting rid of bodies and muscles.
SPEAKER_0:  At least in Tijuana we saw that phenomenon and it's obvious that it's going on all over Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  Who's having those discussions?
SPEAKER_1:  about.
SPEAKER_1:  mass murder and getting rid of people. I've been reading a lot about
SPEAKER_1:  World War II recently and there's
SPEAKER_1:  was aggressive innovation on the Nazi side of how to get rid of a large number of people.
SPEAKER_1:  For the longest time both the Soviets and the Soviets were more brutal with this.
SPEAKER_1:  It's literally, it's a engineering problem of how you kill.
SPEAKER_1:  a large number of people and get rid of their bodies.
SPEAKER_1:  So the Soviets were more into...
SPEAKER_1:  Just lame people
SPEAKER_1:  Laying people down into the grave.
SPEAKER_1:  face down and shooting them in the back of the head.
SPEAKER_1:  and then doing that on my scale. So you just pile people on.
SPEAKER_1:  And then there's obviously innovation with the Holocaust in terms of gassing people and all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not sure exactly where these...
SPEAKER_0:  Tradecraft skills are coming from specifically you hear discussions of Israelis training some of the cartel groups back in the
SPEAKER_0:  late 90s, specifically the Ariana Fias cartel. There's a lot of stories about that.
SPEAKER_0:  security specialist coming down and showing them things like how to make caustic soda.
SPEAKER_0:  how to put rocks inside of bodies and then chicken wire them around and throw them into the ocean or rivers so that their bodies don't float.
SPEAKER_0:  And when you kind of put rocks inside.
SPEAKER_1:  of body to make sure the body doesn't
SPEAKER_0:  So you open up the intestinal tract, put rocks inside.
SPEAKER_0:  You cut where tattoos are, you take off hands and faces and throw them somewhere else.
SPEAKER_0:  and you wrap them in chicken wire. To make it not identifiable.
SPEAKER_0:  and throw them into a body of water.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is.
SPEAKER_0:  This is a horrible thing.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's actually a craft. It's a trade craft. It's trade craft and it's a
SPEAKER_0:  there's a link to the US as far as that Melladrait graph. You have to remember that.
SPEAKER_0:  The United States had a thing called School of the Americas.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  and the CIA and they showed things and a lot of that stuff is out there in the hands of people that are
SPEAKER_0:  of that generation.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a manual.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a manual somewhere.
SPEAKER_1:  like with chapters and it's like how to get
SPEAKER_0:  of the body. There's manuals out there.
SPEAKER_1:  time constraints.
SPEAKER_1:  or what are how
SPEAKER_1:  Identifiable can the body be afterwards.
SPEAKER_1:  What are geographical constraints?
SPEAKER_0:  all that kind of stuff. I think that was common back in the early 2000s and maybe the late 90s when some of these things were going on.
SPEAKER_0:  but they've lost.
SPEAKER_0:  Even that.
SPEAKER_0:  As far as respect for the government or bodies being found, right now, what you usually see is just bodies being burnt to a crisp and buried in a field somewhere. That's usually what you'll see.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of the groups like this woman belong to basically taking upon themselves to go out.
SPEAKER_0:  find clandestine graves in.
SPEAKER_0:  the outskirts of the towns that they live in.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm probing the ground with these metal probes.
SPEAKER_0:  and seeing if the whatever they encounter in the bottom of these.
SPEAKER_0:  These clandestine graves stinks or not. If they find IDs or clothing, they kind of gather that and they basically present it to the investigative authorities in the towns or the states they live in, which basically are doing their jobs.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, over 90% of all murders in Mexico were never solved.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's...
SPEAKER_0:  So they've even stopped trying to get rid of bodies in that way.
SPEAKER_1:  How does a cartel?
SPEAKER_1:  Take power.
SPEAKER_1:  How does it gain control of this local?
SPEAKER_1:  area that you mentioned and then grow.
SPEAKER_1:  get take control of a region.
SPEAKER_1:  And how does it do so in this?
SPEAKER_1:  dynamic.
SPEAKER_1:  relationship between.
SPEAKER_1:  politicians and the military and the police force.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a thing that happens over time.
SPEAKER_0:  there has always been a big effort, even when I was in, to...
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  or own certain members of the police force. Even when we're going through training, some people get pulled out during training because they...
SPEAKER_0:  or found out to have some sort of parent or...
SPEAKER_0:  sibling that was a cartel member or the uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Their FBI background check came back negative, you know, when they were already in the training program.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, so.
SPEAKER_0:  I think part of it is.
SPEAKER_0:  First off, they take advantage of the fact that Mexico is a young country. It's a country of young people.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  We have a big group of young people that have.
SPEAKER_0:  little to no opportunities to come up.
SPEAKER_0:  When I was in when I went to take that career path a lot of my friends took the other option
SPEAKER_0:  they went to work for some of these criminal groups.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So they have this going for them. They basically have a lot of bodies to hire cheaply.
SPEAKER_1:  and leverage in terms of
SPEAKER_1:  forcing.
SPEAKER_1:  those bodies to do whatever is needed because the alternative for those people is
SPEAKER_0:  There's nothing. No options.
SPEAKER_0:  You have a kid somewhere who is working on a field, you know, or you have a kid like me that was out of the job, out of school.
SPEAKER_0:  and the only options for me was...
SPEAKER_0:  that in the newspaper, which seemed like a long shot or...
SPEAKER_0:  going with some of my friends that had cars now and were hanging out all night at these bars and some of them had, you know, just...
SPEAKER_0:  Draco, AK-47.
SPEAKER_0:  pistols in their cars and it would look cool, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  So there is a trajectory, there's many trajectories possibly in your life where you could have been.
SPEAKER_1:  still operating.
SPEAKER_1:  in a...
SPEAKER_1:  criminal organization.
SPEAKER_0:  in Mexico. I mean, there's not a lot of options, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you think you'd be good at it?
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know. I mean, I'm pretty good at what I do now, which is teaching people how to detect it and kind of fight against it. Yeah, so I think, uh.
SPEAKER_1:  I have a sense of that.
SPEAKER_1:  the skills transfer pretty well.
SPEAKER_1:  That's also the dark side of this whole thing.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of the people that I used to work with, you know, I know things and I have some training and I have some specialized training and I currently do, I've done, you know, presentations for the Secret Service and the FBI and...
SPEAKER_0:  You name it, I'll-
SPEAKER_0:  gone there and showing them what I do.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of the people that I used to work with who are out of the job are in the wind. Some of these people are way more trained than I am.
SPEAKER_0:  It's interesting what the.
SPEAKER_0:  The reason why I get so-
SPEAKER_0:  get looked for and they ask me questions is because I actually have the experience that my university was.
SPEAKER_0:  the most dangerous city on the planet.
SPEAKER_0:  And when people ask me about some of that stuff, I could speak from experience as far as encountering some of that directly.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of the people that I used to work with were way better at it than I am.
SPEAKER_0:  are in the wind.
SPEAKER_0:  interesting thing in Mexico, if you are of a police organization and you get
SPEAKER_0:  fired or you quit.
SPEAKER_0:  you are ineligible to join another police organization.
SPEAKER_0:  that discounts you. So for somebody like me who is a professional.
SPEAKER_0:  operations group member or police officer in Mexico of that region.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no options for me outside of that.
SPEAKER_0:  So they themselves basically have created this.
SPEAKER_0:  inescapable box for some of these people that go into that line of work.
SPEAKER_0:  What do they go after?
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  I've heard offers of $12,000 to join.
SPEAKER_0:  some of the organizations out there.
SPEAKER_0:  plus, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  They get benefits, not like the government, you know? I'm still waiting for my liquidation check. This has been out of service for like six, seven years. I'm still waiting for my check.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  So some of these people, it's obvious that the opportunities are presented to them out there are stronger, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  And again, the youth is.
SPEAKER_0:  what gets eaten by this war.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's...
SPEAKER_0:  one of the main things that they start with.
SPEAKER_0:  Just the youth.
SPEAKER_0:  We had a phenomenon in Tijuana.
SPEAKER_0:  early early night late 90s early 2000s called the Narco juniors
SPEAKER_0:  Nakojunas are basically bored.
SPEAKER_0:  middle-class or upper-class families.
SPEAKER_0:  had kids that were bored and they just joined some of these cartel groups.
SPEAKER_0:  these cartel groups on them.
SPEAKER_0:  opportunities to get into regular industry.
SPEAKER_0:  to go through the family businesses to kind of establish themselves, use.
SPEAKER_0:  some of those businesses for storage or.
SPEAKER_0:  figure out how to use some of their transportation businesses for drug mueling.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is how they start.
SPEAKER_0:  in getting into different areas that they regularly couldn't.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  That's how it starts. You owe somebody, they get into paid protection type schemes, which are also common all over Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  and sooner or later they start owning businesses.
SPEAKER_0:  They regulate.
SPEAKER_0:  some of their income.
SPEAKER_0:  So they become part of the...
SPEAKER_0:  of the local economy in a big way.
SPEAKER_0:  I had this experience in Sinaloa where we were driving down this shitty street.
SPEAKER_0:  And all of a sudden it became a cool, nice, curvy highway type thing. And I looked around there, it's like, this is a nice road.
SPEAKER_0:  And the guy was with me, he said, Yeah, the cartels built it.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  You go to some of these towns and...
SPEAKER_0:  The cartels are the government there. They build the hospitals, they build the churches, they build the schools.
SPEAKER_0:  COVID happens, they're enforcing the mask mandates.
SPEAKER_0:  They're out enforcing the mass mandates, the stay-at-home policies.
SPEAKER_0:  They're the ones delivering supplies to the townspeople in bags, courtesy of so-and-so cartel.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, so.
SPEAKER_0:  They become the Robin Hood characters of their environments. If they're smart, these groups basically turn into that Robin Hood, stealing from the rich and giving to the poor, or at least that's the projection that they give.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the role of violence in this operation?
SPEAKER_0:  Ah.
SPEAKER_0:  extreme. It used to be that there were rules, as you say, like...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, don't go after kids, don't go after women.
SPEAKER_0:  but all those things are gone now. You know, they had been gone for...
SPEAKER_0:  decades, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  the escalation of violence. You kill one of mine, I'll kill four of yours. You kill four of mine, I'll go after your family because you are hiding.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  There's stories of...
SPEAKER_0:  high-level cartel people getting there.
SPEAKER_0:  sons and daughters murdered, mutilated in revenge killings.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's at a point where it spiraled out of.
SPEAKER_0:  semblance of a rule set as far as who can get exposed to some of this violence.
SPEAKER_0:  those highly produced ISIS videos.
SPEAKER_0:  or they show torture in executions.
SPEAKER_0:  Ah.
SPEAKER_0:  according to some of the sources that I've talked to here in the United States, that we're looking at that phenomenon.
SPEAKER_0:  They said that it seems to be that that was influenced by some of the narco blog videos that were coming out of Mexico in the early 2000s.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically that some of these groups were the first ones that got wind of the fact that you can.
SPEAKER_0:  export.
SPEAKER_0:  Terror.
SPEAKER_0:  or the horror that an execution has through social media.
SPEAKER_0:  Way back when Facebook was a bit more.
SPEAKER_0:  bit more of a wildland area. You could see these in news feeds, videos of executions, tortures and stuff like that coming out of Mexico. on Facebook.
SPEAKER_0:  Way back when. Wow. This was a different time.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  people who criticize social media in the moderation
SPEAKER_1:  Is it tough?
SPEAKER_1:  It's a tough job.
SPEAKER_1:  because the brutal world out there.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I remember seeing some of these ISIS videos on Facebook way back when and they cracked down on all that.
SPEAKER_0:  But, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  One that's kind of clear and I'll see ya.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not gonna...
SPEAKER_0:  say where to find it but people out there might have seen it because some of these videos get shared through whatsapp groups and
SPEAKER_0:  chat groups out there. One of the ones that caught my attention way back when was a guy getting two guys getting executed by chainsaw.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  you know.
SPEAKER_0:  people can kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  I can't imagine what that would be like, but...
SPEAKER_1:  produced on purpose. Like it's videotaped.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a cartel group caught two rival cartel members.
SPEAKER_0:  and a way to send a message to those of the rival cartel is to
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, I execute these people in front of a camera.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, you can't get to your rivals, but you can.
SPEAKER_0:  you can make them see what they're doing, or at least make their people look at what happens.
SPEAKER_0:  if you invade their territory.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's an escalation of brutality in the violence as well.
SPEAKER_1:  mean, and that leads to terror.
SPEAKER_1:  to a mass communication of terror.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, you have videos of some of these people engaging in cannibalism in front of a video to see how brutal they are, or...
SPEAKER_0:  uh... people taking out somebody's heart while they're alive you know and filming it and you know it used to be social media as a whole you'll see some of these videos they would
SPEAKER_0:  put down in a few days.
SPEAKER_0:  but now there's telegram groups. There's a...
SPEAKER_0:  There's live leaks, there's a bunch of other sites out there that kind of disperse some of these videos.
SPEAKER_0:  It's basically a bulletin board for them as far as, you know, hey, you got into my territory. Well, this is what's going to happen to you.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there a game theoretic?
SPEAKER_1:  way to uh...
SPEAKER_1:  remove this kind of brutality to de-escalate the brutality because it seems like if a cartel takes
SPEAKER_1:  power that exceeds the power of politicians.
SPEAKER_1:  in a locality, there's a strong incentive to reduce the brutality.
SPEAKER_1:  to crack down on this kind of chainsaw.
SPEAKER_1:  executions.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a recent leak.
SPEAKER_0:  of government files.
SPEAKER_0:  the Wacamaya Lakes. It's our version of the Wicky Lakes I guess.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was mostly.
SPEAKER_0:  documents coming out of the Mexican military.
SPEAKER_0:  I haven't seen it talked about a lot here in stateside, but it's a pretty big thing down in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  And in some of those documents it reveals how.
SPEAKER_0:  powerless the government is. I mean as far as the military goes.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  That's another player in Mexico, the military.
SPEAKER_0:  the military.
SPEAKER_0:  has been out in the streets basically doing a policing role since Felipe Calderon was in his administration. He basically militarized the drug war.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Philippe Calderon was to the right of the political spectrum.
SPEAKER_0:  and his main rival who was his way to the left is now in power.
SPEAKER_0:  And one of the campaign promises he had was to demilitarize the
SPEAKER_0:  the drug war to send the military back to its barracks and all that.
SPEAKER_0:  And he's basically continuing on. And he just passed some legislation that basically keeps the military on the streets for a few more years.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think some of these documents that were leaked are very telling as far as why that is.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, we have...
SPEAKER_0:  The military now has a vast amount of power when it comes to security.
SPEAKER_0:  industry. I mean, they're in charge of building airports and train lines in Mexico now.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  their documents themselves show how certain regions in Mexico who have a specific military presence.
SPEAKER_0:  work for one side or favor one side of the cartel.
SPEAKER_1:  They're corrupted too.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's these military forces that are in part corrupted? Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  and uh
SPEAKER_1:  cartel who operates with violence somehow finding a balance between each other and no
SPEAKER_1:  It just feels like...
SPEAKER_1:  Throughout human history, there's a...
SPEAKER_1:  dictators or leaders that come.
SPEAKER_1:  into situations like this and really crack down on the violin.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like that's not happening.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like there's a kind of a-
SPEAKER_1:  Market of violence happening here.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a systemic amnesia that happens every presidency in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  The president comes in, he has five to six years to do whatever he needs to do.
SPEAKER_0:  and he does everything and as soon as he's gone...
SPEAKER_0:  everything he did, even the...
SPEAKER_0:  what was working.
SPEAKER_0:  Good.
SPEAKER_0:  chopped off.
SPEAKER_0:  police organizations get defunct.
SPEAKER_0:  or the names get changed.
SPEAKER_0:  Uniforms change.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's a lot of turnover.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, everywhere. Every five years federally, there's a turnover.
SPEAKER_0:  and that things change.
SPEAKER_1:  What about the cartels? Do they persist?
SPEAKER_1:  the leadership persist.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, the Sina Law Cartel has had a figurehead.
SPEAKER_0:  behind it since the 80s, the same one.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's a federation of smaller cartels that are all kind of linked up, but that pretty much historically was considered the head of the Sino-Lock Cartel.
SPEAKER_0:  Omaya Sambhata has been there since, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  since the 80s. So in a way, yeah, he's persisting.
SPEAKER_0:  He's surviving all of these, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  presidencies.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, these documents that were leaked are a clear sign of.
SPEAKER_0:  what strengths and weaknesses there are as far as the government's main weapon against some of these criminal group which is the military.
SPEAKER_0:  and if people doubt.
SPEAKER_0:  this. They can look it up now online because all these documents are out there. But you know, just a clear thing.
SPEAKER_0:  the Mexican
SPEAKER_0:  Navy or the marina doesn't work with the Mexican army. They don't speak to each other.
SPEAKER_0:  So that should tell you everything you need to know as far as trust.
SPEAKER_1:  That could be just bureaucratic dysfunction. They don't trust each other.
SPEAKER_1:  Are they both struggling with the co-
SPEAKER_0:  problem of corruption.
SPEAKER_0:  some of these documents that are already out there talk about the ports in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  which are probably the main conduit of precursors of methamphetamines and precursors of things like fentanyl into the country.
SPEAKER_0:  They're operated and guarded by the marina.
SPEAKER_0:  So these things are happening under their watch.
SPEAKER_0:  then you get talks about the army in certain places, basically working,
SPEAKER_0:  uh... counter cartel operations on to to specifically one side not not another you know as far as the rival groups out there
SPEAKER_0:  And we have a long history of some of these military groups going rogue. Los Etas are a prime example of this. These special forces units that basically...
SPEAKER_0:  turned around and went to work as bodyguards for the golf cartel.
SPEAKER_0:  Decided to...
SPEAKER_0:  But what they basically did was an internship with a cartel.
SPEAKER_0:  They went out there, did bodyguarding for the golf cartel.
SPEAKER_0:  and then realize they can do a better job than they were doing, so they start their own.
SPEAKER_0:  barking off one of these, again, one of the bloodiest, kind of like a
SPEAKER_0:  internal cartel wars in Mexico's history.
SPEAKER_0:  Who was El Chapo? El Chapo was a part of the leadership, or at least a faction of the leadership in the cartel. A faction of small organizations.
SPEAKER_0:  basically families or organizations that conform this larger group, which is the Sinaloa cartel that is based out of Sinaloa.
SPEAKER_0:  basically, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  They are people that...
SPEAKER_0:  have family and power nucleuses there in Sinaloa.
SPEAKER_0:  Who was he? I think he was a high-level operator for the scene in La Carte. He had his own drug routes, his own networks, his family. His family nucleus down there is still in control of...
SPEAKER_0:  of those operations so
SPEAKER_0:  his arrest really didn't change anything.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  But he wasn't the...
SPEAKER_0:  mastermind, number one leader that I think...
SPEAKER_0:  the media and the government kind of portrayed him as.
SPEAKER_0:  Who was the mastermind?
SPEAKER_0:  If you...
SPEAKER_0:  go down there and you read what most of the
SPEAKER_0:  brave journalist in Mexico that we have.
SPEAKER_0:  I'd say another aspect of this war is that a lot of journalists get killed. I think Mexico has a...
SPEAKER_0:  I think has some of the top numbers in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  This is not no secret to anybody. El Mayo Zambada is the name of the historical.
SPEAKER_0:  figurehead of this cartel or at least
SPEAKER_0:  Somebody who?
SPEAKER_0:  people theorize or suspect to be the...
SPEAKER_0:  the main guy or the main person that is in charge of some of the sub-discriminal group as well.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the going rumor that he's still very much alive. The interesting thing about him is that he learned his craft in Los Angeles.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  people thinking that scene in the lower cartel isn't a Mexican thing.
SPEAKER_0:  He apparently learned a lot of his craft from...
SPEAKER_0:  people in the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's the craft of leadership, the craft of business, the craft of witchcraft.
SPEAKER_0:  The craft of getting a product from Colombia, putting it through Mexico. And the logistics. The logistics part of it.
SPEAKER_1:  And he somehow is...
SPEAKER_1:  Operating in the shadows, so he's not a known and
SPEAKER_0:  I don't have a clear number of this, but he was interviewed by a magazine called Proceso in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  and some pictures were taken of him.
SPEAKER_0:  This was over 10 years ago, probably, and that's the last time anybody's ever seen a picture of them.
SPEAKER_1:  What's it like to be a journalist in that?
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, can a journalist have a conversation with him?
SPEAKER_0:  and live. Nonetheless, he asks to have that conversation. I think he...
SPEAKER_0:  He reached out.
SPEAKER_0:  to this journalist to talk about it.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a...
SPEAKER_0:  There's a media wing to the work that we do, a sister page called Demo Lair.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  and it's run by some pretty good people.
SPEAKER_0:  The way we met is that I was basically training them how to work in hostile environments. And they were like, oh, we're going to go report on cartel activity in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was like...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, that is.
SPEAKER_0:  A year and a half ago, a reporter went to the president's daily briefing.
SPEAKER_0:  press conference that he has. They call them La Mayoneras.
SPEAKER_0:  President Manuel Lopez Obrador.
SPEAKER_0:  and told him to his face, like, I have threats on my life, they're trying to kill me.
SPEAKER_0:  And it happened.
SPEAKER_0:  There's been a slew of-
SPEAKER_0:  assassinations and murders of members of the press all over Mexico. It's not an easy job.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh-huh.
SPEAKER_0:  Either.
SPEAKER_0:  They say too much.
SPEAKER_0:  or they say things that favor one side or the other, which is another aspect of it that is interesting. I don't-
SPEAKER_0:  I don't consider myself a reporter. I don't report on the news in Mexico. I have.
SPEAKER_0:  friends that do that very well.
SPEAKER_0:  commentate on some of it only.
SPEAKER_0:  But you see a lot of these cartel reporters go down there, talk to a specific side and basically...
SPEAKER_0:  speak one side of the story and that is not something that the other side wants.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, if you're...
SPEAKER_0:  If you go down there and speak to one side, you're saying what they want people to know or hear. In a way, you're spreading some of their cartel propaganda.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's how some people.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, get shot.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think it's possible?
SPEAKER_1:  to go in there and have a conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  with a cartel leader.
SPEAKER_1:  Or somebody like me.
SPEAKER_1:  for something like champagne.
SPEAKER_0:  This is what I will say after that whole Sean Penn thing.
SPEAKER_0:  I think a lot of people would reconsider a meeting with anybody of any level that has any variety here in the United States. They wouldn't trust anybody to get that close.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  There are people out there that will talk to reporters and help people that are working on a
SPEAKER_0:  on a laboratory somewhere in a hillside somewhere down south in the Sierra.
SPEAKER_0:  low-level people that get authorization to speak to reporters and stuff like that, but they don't say anything that isn't being taught or shown in various different ways or outlets out there for them.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, some of these guys have Instagram accounts, you know, some of these guys said blog about it, you know, but not the leaders, Tik Tok, no, not the leaders.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  after what happened to Ojapa Guzman. I think that opportunity, that win that was closed for some of the leadership down there.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  I disagree. I think they're just more sensitive.
SPEAKER_1:  realizing that there has to be a deep trust.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not just anybody.
SPEAKER_1:  and not any high profile. I've gotten a chance to speak.
SPEAKER_1:  to some very high profile leaders that don't speak to journalists.
SPEAKER_1:  and they understand the value of trust.
SPEAKER_0:  if they have something to say, which I don't think they do.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think they at least unless
SPEAKER_0:  at some point in the future, which is something I suspect might be coming.
SPEAKER_0:  that there is some sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  armed intervention and or external attack on some of these criminal groups.
SPEAKER_0:  that really puts the pressure on them.
SPEAKER_1:  You don't think there's a...
SPEAKER_1:  human aspect to this.
SPEAKER_1:  of a human being wanting.
SPEAKER_1:  their story to be known.
SPEAKER_1:  versus
SPEAKER_1:  versus this is different than the propaganda machine of.
SPEAKER_1:  I have something to say, I have-
SPEAKER_1:  some message to put out there to play the game of politics and power.
SPEAKER_1:  and money and all that kind of stuff. Isn't there also a human being underneath all that armor?
SPEAKER_1:  for the sake of perhaps ego.
SPEAKER_1:  legacy wants to be a
SPEAKER_0:  I think in a way they already do that.
SPEAKER_0:  There's corridos, which are basically Mexican folk songs that get sung about some of them. So in a way...
SPEAKER_0:  some of these singers.
SPEAKER_0:  are reporting on some of their lives. And it's like a, it's a great honor to have a corrido made about you. Somebody made a corrido about me based on my interviews. I didn't pay for it, so it's a real one.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  It feels cool. So creating a myth, the legend of the man.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's about...
SPEAKER_0:  I think a way you can.
SPEAKER_0:  you can find somebody like that is.
SPEAKER_0:  somebody that wants to get their story specifically clear and straight.
SPEAKER_0:  You know
SPEAKER_0:  coming from that culture.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  getting to work for the government down there and then not being not working for the government down there.
SPEAKER_0:  and being on the outside, being critical of not only the government that is in place now, but also the government that I actually work with.
SPEAKER_0:  I can tell you that there's villains all over the place down there. Everybody's a villain.
SPEAKER_0:  at all levels in some way, shape, or form. And some of these people.
SPEAKER_0:  I think in a way including El Chapo.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that some of that meeting was about.
SPEAKER_0:  film rights and stories and being able to get his story out there.
SPEAKER_0:  I think. I'm not too sure, because I wasn't there. But I suspect that some of that was going on.
SPEAKER_0:  If you can...
SPEAKER_0:  bring an honest voice down there they can trust.
SPEAKER_0:  put that out there.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  I think you could try.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm interested in that kind of thing. Yeah, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  because ultimately in some of those places.
SPEAKER_1:  Like.
SPEAKER_1:  inside a cartel at the very top.
SPEAKER_1:  is when you can really look at the raw.
SPEAKER_1:  aspects of human nature in a way you can.
SPEAKER_1:  can't necessarily elsewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  there's a youth coming into power down there.
SPEAKER_0:  When I say youth, I mean some of the old guard is going out and some of the new guard is coming in.
SPEAKER_0:  El Chapo Guzman's sons, who are now...
SPEAKER_0:  in their own right, kind of gaining legendary status. There was an attempted arrest on his son that led to...
SPEAKER_0:  the famous Culiacanazo incident.
SPEAKER_0:  which we are now learning more about because some of the guacamaya leagues are kind of
SPEAKER_0:  speaking more about what happened that day.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically a federal operation.
SPEAKER_0:  to arrest Del Chapo Guzman's son.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  turn into a siege.
SPEAKER_0:  to try and get them free.
SPEAKER_0:  They called in the cavalry, basically the whole of the Sinaloa cartel showed up to try and rescue them.
SPEAKER_0:  Interesting thing about that is in reading some of the documents and also just seeing some of the videos and stuff like that came out of that incident.
SPEAKER_0:  The cartels were the ones evacuating the citizenship from the area.
SPEAKER_0:  They were the ones going restaurant to restaurant. They want to exit the city go through here.
SPEAKER_0:  Take your families, get down, but you have to leave because the Army's coming here and gonna fight us.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's like a
SPEAKER_1:  A deep morality too to all of that. Underneath the violence, there's a humanity. You mean it's their home?
SPEAKER_0:  It is their home and they were fighting for their.
SPEAKER_0:  and they were fighting for leadership from their home.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  There is a morality, there is a humanity there, and again.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if people want to paint them all with the villainy aspects, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, everybody's a villain in somebody else's story, you know, if you kind of look at it that way.
SPEAKER_1:  People should check out your Patreon, you should check out your Field Notes. You're a really good writer, your Instagram too. You write about...
SPEAKER_1:  You have a quote in your field notes about villains.
SPEAKER_1:  I once worked for a villain.
SPEAKER_1:  a savior to some.
SPEAKER_1:  and the biblical demon of old to others, a true product of his environment.
SPEAKER_1:  He was the best and the worst of us.
SPEAKER_1:  We're all potential villains in someone else's story.
SPEAKER_1:  He would say to us,
SPEAKER_1:  as we would head out into the unknowns.
SPEAKER_1:  that the night had waiting for us.
SPEAKER_1:  It was during one of these nights that I looked around me and saw horns and pitchforks among
SPEAKER_1:  My people unrealized.
SPEAKER_1:  what he meant.
SPEAKER_1:  We were no knights of the round table, whatever we were.
SPEAKER_1:  were needed. In the end, I guess that justified most of what was about to happen.
SPEAKER_1:  I do think out job but do you think people like him are.
SPEAKER_0:  good or evil.
SPEAKER_0:  I think there's no one without the other. I think there's a cost to...
SPEAKER_0:  There's a cost to...
SPEAKER_0:  their goodness that they do.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, the roads they built, the hospitals, the career paths that they paid for. There are doctors in Mexico that their careers were paid for by some of these groups.
SPEAKER_0:  and they do a lot of
SPEAKER_0:  amazing good for the community. I remember
SPEAKER_0:  There was a...
SPEAKER_0:  surgeon.
SPEAKER_0:  reconstructing cleft palates.
SPEAKER_0:  In one of my travels that I did out there, I spent some time actually going out there after I deteriorated my 15.6 skill set.
SPEAKER_0:  out of the job to train people and.
SPEAKER_0:  that's the type of stuff that I show people.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh...
SPEAKER_0:  They are...
SPEAKER_0:  They told me, I told them, you're doing God's work? This stuff is legit, this is God's work?
SPEAKER_0:  building smiles for people. I was like, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  And then can I talk to you?
SPEAKER_0:  He said, you know, my career path was paid for by...
SPEAKER_0:  cartel.
SPEAKER_0:  a group of cartel members, they paid for my career path because they wanted somebody on hand that could fix their teeth.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think some aspects of that is just sort of manipulative control?
SPEAKER_1:  or is some of it also just.
SPEAKER_1:  Again, I care for the population, for fellow human beings that are one of your own.
SPEAKER_0:  I think both.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I think there's, again.
SPEAKER_0:  It's hard to just make them saints or devils. Some of the good they do in some of their communities.
SPEAKER_0:  and don't ask anything for in return, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  And even if they don't ask it for anything in return where the military shows up, they are immediately met with rocks and roadblocks and everybody's
SPEAKER_0:  main weapon down there since most Mexicans can't buy or own firearms.
SPEAKER_0:  The main weapon down there is silence and their eyes to report.
SPEAKER_0:  to the people that they consider.
SPEAKER_0:  the good guys in their environment.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a hard question, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  I think there's a bit of both, and both the government and the criminal groups that are operating down there.
SPEAKER_1:  Silence is their main weapon.
SPEAKER_1:  So El Chapo is currently in prison.
SPEAKER_1:  Is he worth talking to?
SPEAKER_1:  I'd say yes. Is there things that to you are?
SPEAKER_1:  Interesting about him that is still not understood.
SPEAKER_1:  Is he a window into something that you don't understand about that world still?
SPEAKER_1:  or curious about in that world. I think
SPEAKER_0:  I think he's a window into the family dynamics of that world. I want to say family dynamics. Mexico has a big thing about compadres.
SPEAKER_0:  hermanos. We have people that we call family that are not necessarily our family.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  He is somebody that witnessed the...
SPEAKER_0:  the construction of what is now.
SPEAKER_0:  scene of the law cartel. Like he was in it way back when he started off as a
SPEAKER_0:  as a farmer and then went into trafficking. He's from a town called Bandirahuata, which is basically, you know, that's the Wakanda of cartels, basically. That's where a lot of that originates.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  the
SPEAKER_0:  the things that he saw as far as how some of these things got built.
SPEAKER_0:  I think would be an interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  topic of conversation with somebody like him.
SPEAKER_1:  So that story is a story of evolving family dynamics. So part of the story of the cartel is...
SPEAKER_1:  individual humans.
SPEAKER_0:  marrying other families, getting named padrino, basically godfathers to other people's kids.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  forming family and blood ties and
SPEAKER_0:  influence ties to people not only in Mexico but in the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  It's seeing how that.
SPEAKER_0:  dynamic and family dynamic is still there, you know, so he's gone.
SPEAKER_0:  He's in prison, but he is.
SPEAKER_0:  He's probably on his way to be our next.
SPEAKER_0:  clandestine saint?
SPEAKER_0:  You go to the chapel of Malverde.
SPEAKER_0:  Melberto is basically a Mexican Robin Hood folk saint down there, who is a saint of traffickers.
SPEAKER_0:  and at his shrine.
SPEAKER_0:  you have small little chapel.
SPEAKER_0:  shrine right next to it.
SPEAKER_0:  So he's on his way to sainthood in Mexico, not recognized by the Catholic Church, but that doesn't matter in Mexico anymore.
SPEAKER_0:  speaking to somebody like him.
SPEAKER_0:  Cool.
SPEAKER_0:  You can consider him somebody that lost, you know, he's arrested.
SPEAKER_0:  But his family's okay.
SPEAKER_0:  His legacy is out there. He's probably gonna be the next folk saint when he passes away.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think he feels like?
SPEAKER_1:  the new wave.
SPEAKER_1:  of what the cartel has become is betrayed and left behind.
SPEAKER_1:  or
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  because it seems like the way the cartel operated...
SPEAKER_1:  has changed over the decades.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, number one.
SPEAKER_0:  their power and influence is bigger.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, the.
SPEAKER_0:  There are Sinaloa cartel operations in Colombia straight to the source of it.
SPEAKER_0:  and then they are clear.
SPEAKER_0:  They have a clear presence in places like Chicago and Los Angeles. They're in the United States. Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  thought process that a lot of Americans have. We don't want that.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't want them to get here or build a wall and all this.
SPEAKER_1:  So they're deeply integrated into legitimate businesses.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, they've been having kids and families up here for a long time. Some of these people have American passports that work not only directly for them, but have blood ties down there. Big boys imagine that they've been having kids and parents as theirs, right?
SPEAKER_0:  dragnets and arrests of some of these criminal organizations states. The New Generation Cartel had one two three years ago where
SPEAKER_0:  The Guest Operation on the Con, I think it was called.
SPEAKER_0:  They're worth it over 80.
SPEAKER_0:  of their operatives. This is a new cartel that is very militaristic and growing in Mexico and they had 80 arrests in the United States of members of them operating here.
SPEAKER_1:  That's how you could.
SPEAKER_1:  be a legitimate operator inside the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  that's hard to detect.
SPEAKER_1:  Makes you wonder how many in the US government.
SPEAKER_1:  the politicians here.
SPEAKER_1:  because it is the role.
SPEAKER_1:  of the United States in the drug war financially in terms of power.
SPEAKER_1:  is very big.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. Surely there's politicians that have a-
SPEAKER_0:  finger into this immigration is part of it.
SPEAKER_0:  illegal immigration.
SPEAKER_0:  as part of it and the influence that has as a bargaining chip and a political chip. We saw this with the first caravan coming up and how it was politicized.
SPEAKER_0:  the money, Fast and Furious and guns being basically...
SPEAKER_0:  let walk down into Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  People that don't know basically.
SPEAKER_0:  the ATF had this operation where they were.
SPEAKER_0:  looking at straw purchasers or firearms.
SPEAKER_0:  basically people buying up a specific type of firearms that were on a shopping list that the cartels wanted to buy.
SPEAKER_0:  including 50 cows.
SPEAKER_0:  FN57 pistols which are
SPEAKER_0:  small pistols with a high velocity round that will go through a bulletproof vest.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  AR-15s of all kinds.
SPEAKER_0:  that could quickly be modified into full auto down in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  with drilling a few holes and making a few things to them.
SPEAKER_0:  So these people were buying all these, the ATF was watching them.
SPEAKER_0:  and allowing them to walk.
SPEAKER_0:  those firearms into Mexico under the guise of trying to track them somehow.
SPEAKER_0:  which doesn't make a lot of sense for most people to kind of look at that operation. The only people found, the only reason people found out about it was...
SPEAKER_0:  because of the murder of a few federal agents, of the US federal agents that were killed with those guns.
SPEAKER_0:  One of my friends was shot with one of those pistols outside of his house.
SPEAKER_0:  and they shot him and they shot his wife.
SPEAKER_0:  both of them were killed.
SPEAKER_0:  daughter was in the backseat, lost part of her arm.
SPEAKER_0:  When that happened.
SPEAKER_0:  The guns were unique. There was like, oh, we didn't ever fight.
SPEAKER_0:  The matapolicias is what they call them. They're the cop killers.
SPEAKER_0:  I haven't seen those before.
SPEAKER_0:  So they were unique and interesting and
SPEAKER_0:  later on in life I was watching CNN.
SPEAKER_0:  and seeing the hearings going on, I was like, oh!
SPEAKER_0:  That's where they came from.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Two federal agents changed a lot. It was politicized. There was a whole scandal up here.
SPEAKER_0:  But in Mexico, how many people died with those firearms?
SPEAKER_0:  you know, being let down, being let go down there.
SPEAKER_0:  and also what type of sentiment you think the local populace has of the United States after all those guns were basically handed over to some of these groups.
SPEAKER_0:  of gun trafficking as another.
SPEAKER_0:  giant part of the equation and part of the problem down there as far as as far as the amount of munitions weapons and
SPEAKER_0:  Now we were also getting.
SPEAKER_0:  Tradecraft.
SPEAKER_0:  material from conflict zones outside of Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Weaponized drones.
SPEAKER_0:  The first time we saw some of those weaponized drones was in Syria.
SPEAKER_0:  And like a few weeks later, you know, grenades were being dropped on the roofs of some...
SPEAKER_0:  public officials building.
SPEAKER_0:  Are you using drones? That's been going on for a while.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a place in Michoacan that has some pretty interesting videos. And the interesting part of them is because the federal police down there are actually working hand in hand.
SPEAKER_0:  with a United
SPEAKER_0:  Carteles Unidos group, which is basically the local cartels to try and fight off the new generation cartel moving into Michoacan.
SPEAKER_0:  So even the federal forces are fighting with the cartels to try and keep this larger cartel out.
SPEAKER_0:  and there's videos of these civilian drones basically dropping.
SPEAKER_0:  Explosives.
SPEAKER_0:  They found some explosive testing ranges out there that are basically replicating stuff that you would see the IRA use during the troubles out there.
SPEAKER_0:  from homemade mortars.
SPEAKER_0:  Um,
SPEAKER_0:  You know, IEDs have been used in Mexico with that.
SPEAKER_0:  not that much, but they're making like a presence again. We don't have a lot of ordinance around like Iraq, but we do have a big mining industry down there.
SPEAKER_0:  So mining explosives of all kinds are pretty easy to get.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  You start seeing that and also, I mean, there's some exotic weaponry coming in from the south now and from the ocean.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of it is probably US military equipment sold to various South American governments that are now...
SPEAKER_0:  not as stable as they were and they're kind of making their way into black markets.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of those 50 cowl and.
SPEAKER_0:  vehicle mounted technical type machine guns and some of the
SPEAKER_0:  RPGs and...
SPEAKER_0:  Man pads or remote control guided missiles that you that have been found in cartel hands are probably come making their way up from down south
SPEAKER_1:  to get
SPEAKER_1:  these like multi-million dollar systems like the high-mar system in the Ukraine, you like super sophisticated advanced technology or not.
SPEAKER_1:  So like this is like military grade.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not sure what the application would be exactly.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of the sophisticated stuff I see in our man pads, which is basically remote guided missiles. I've seen some of those found out there.
SPEAKER_1:  application exactly.
SPEAKER_0:  display of power.
SPEAKER_0:  there are no flight zones over parts of Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  for this reason.
SPEAKER_0:  the New Jersey Cartel.
SPEAKER_0:  down a helicopter.
SPEAKER_0:  there's been incidents of military helicopters falling from the sky and it
SPEAKER_0:  They said that it was mechanical issues.
SPEAKER_0:  But again, I'm not gonna do conspiracy theories out there, but there's a lot of videos on TikTok of the...
SPEAKER_0:  Sinaloa cartel forces at parties.
SPEAKER_0:  carrying around rocket launchers on their backs.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's an increased probability of mechanical failures over those areas.
SPEAKER_1:  When you're flying a...
SPEAKER_0:  helicopter. Yeah, there's no flight zones over some parts of Mexico. Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Another thing you're seeing now is night vision, night vision equipment that is clearly military grade.
SPEAKER_0:  from the US.
SPEAKER_0:  that was probably abandoned in some war field out there, maybe Afghanistan or somewhere like that. And it's being found in safe houses and in the hands of cartel forces.
SPEAKER_0:  You want to talk about a scary.
SPEAKER_0:  opponent.
SPEAKER_0:  Somebody wearing night vision.
SPEAKER_0:  with a suppressed firearm.
SPEAKER_0:  those types of capabilities are now.
SPEAKER_0:  out there.
SPEAKER_0:  Also.
SPEAKER_0:  There's this tendency to think in every now and then you'll see these cartel videos with these guys carrying around these 50 cows and they show
SPEAKER_0:  Stand there like, eh.
SPEAKER_0:  the boasting about their rifles and everybody laughed at them because
SPEAKER_0:  50 cal or anything like that without an optic on it.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it's like you're gonna shoot.
SPEAKER_0:  you're praying shoot basically see if you can hit anything with it.
SPEAKER_0:  But now there's a few of my sources of seen, you know, sophisticated laser-guided
SPEAKER_0:  range finders and sighting systems on some of these that are being found out there.
SPEAKER_1:  How much damage can fatigue carry? What's the application?
SPEAKER_0:  They started getting them specifically with the proliferation of armored vehicles in Mexico. Mexico has a giant industry in armored vehicles as far as-
SPEAKER_1:  So there's a race in terms of.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... armory protecting
SPEAKER_1:  especially high value.
SPEAKER_1:  targets.
SPEAKER_1:  And then...
SPEAKER_1:  weapons they can deal with those armored.
SPEAKER_1:  the protected high value targets.
SPEAKER_0:  There was an attempted assassination.
SPEAKER_0:  of a state prosecutor somewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  I think central Mexico, I forget exactly where, but she was riding around up armored.
SPEAKER_0:  cheap.
SPEAKER_0:  Cherokee, I think it was and
SPEAKER_0:  their main means of.
SPEAKER_0:  of firepower was 50 cal and that car.
SPEAKER_0:  was left in pieces.
SPEAKER_0:  he survived and I think the armored vehicle company that soldered that vehicle has it in this playroom.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... then before my time probably two three years before i was actually active
SPEAKER_0:  They tried to kill the head of public security in the state of Baja.
SPEAKER_0:  And with him, it was a grenade launcher, 40 millimeter grenade launcher.
SPEAKER_0:  it skipped off the armored vehicle and landed in the...
SPEAKER_0:  car behind it.
SPEAKER_0:  made the back explode. One of the guys that I used to work with was actually in that car.
SPEAKER_0:  survived it.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  but you started to see, oh, they're using our vehicles now. Let's get.
SPEAKER_0:  50 caliber now to try and defeat that armor.
SPEAKER_0:  So yeah, there's always this...
SPEAKER_0:  This race of technology basically down there. Armored vehicles.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, how do you take on a normal vehicle? Well, there's a few ways. 50 cows, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  if you can mount them in the right way and shoot at a car like that or...
SPEAKER_0:  a bunch of kids with balloons and acrylic paint.
SPEAKER_0:  on the front windshield and blind the vehicle so it doesn't, so they can't drive it anymore.
SPEAKER_0:  is another way.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  towline across a road.
SPEAKER_0:  painted like the...
SPEAKER_0:  painted black so you can't see it.
SPEAKER_0:  the thing in half. Again, I'm not saying any secrets. These are things that people have seen out there.
SPEAKER_0:  shoot at the radiator. Some of these radiators are not even the more sophisticated vehicles out there. Don't have sufficient armoring around the radiator or the battery housing of some of these vehicles.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a case of a guy I think his nickname was El Pelavacas or something like that. I wouldn't see in a law.
SPEAKER_0:  I love a cartel guy.
SPEAKER_0:  He had a normal vehicle, he was riding around and he got ambushed.
SPEAKER_0:  shot at his car he was like I have armor you can't shoot me
SPEAKER_0:  and somebody went up to his car and just put the barrel right in the locking mechanism.
SPEAKER_0:  and that kind of, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  It's an interesting place as far as people getting certain types of guns.
SPEAKER_0:  armor is prolific down there. I mean, everybody down there, the cartel members, you'll see them wearing plate armor.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's an issue. Is that like-
SPEAKER_0:  you can shoot somebody square in the chest and it'll go down.
SPEAKER_1:  Are they afraid to kill Americans?
SPEAKER_1:  So I know I was traveling in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  are on the front.
SPEAKER_1:  So like a lot of the journalists would travel in like armored vehicles.
SPEAKER_1:  And at first I was like, it seems like this would attract attention. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  like it seems like they would want to hit those targets. But then then I realized over time as I learned.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a fear of killing Americans.
SPEAKER_1:  there could be a drastic escalation of.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's not worth it. It's kicking a beehive.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there is a tendency to shy away or stay away from that.
SPEAKER_0:  They don't want the heat or the attention outside of that.
SPEAKER_0:  everyone's game.
SPEAKER_0:  everyone's game, but also there's been many cases of Americans being killed.
SPEAKER_0:  down there. I mean, we saw the Mormon massacre that happened down there and all of them were
SPEAKER_0:  American.
SPEAKER_0:  Mexican, they had both nationalities and blonde kids.
SPEAKER_0:  Wait.
SPEAKER_0:  being massacred in the middle of a desert.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  and the car is basically catching fire.
SPEAKER_0:  this happen.
SPEAKER_0:  and you know, the America, Americans are.
SPEAKER_0:  sent the FBI down there to kind of review some of what happened down there.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think that was.
SPEAKER_0:  when Trump started talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  reviving this whole notion of cartels being labeled as a terrorist organization.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably more for other political.
SPEAKER_0:  pressure point he was using to try and get Mexico to reinforce its southern border, which was posted here.
SPEAKER_0:  Hasn't.
SPEAKER_0:  but there's escalation.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, this already happened and nothing happened. So,
SPEAKER_0:  we can probably get away with it, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  And again, there's a newer generation moving forward now.
SPEAKER_0:  people coming into power.
SPEAKER_1:  more brutal, more technically savvy okay
SPEAKER_0:  have the experience of their parents.
SPEAKER_0:  and the people behind them and what they've done and what got away with and now...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, more savvy about information warfare.
SPEAKER_0:  Their main recruiting tool is TikTok.
SPEAKER_0:  You go to tech talk and you'll see a bunch of these kids at an archipod dancing around and.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of these are videos by cartel members filming other cartel members in cartel control territory and that's a window into that life for.
SPEAKER_0:  Who's on TikTok now?
SPEAKER_0:  kids.
SPEAKER_1:  And the enticing aspect of that is the money.
SPEAKER_1:  The fun.
SPEAKER_1:  The High Roller Life.
SPEAKER_0:  and the
SPEAKER_0:  the possibility of making it.
SPEAKER_0:  to a level.
SPEAKER_0:  You know? Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  of fame of respect.
SPEAKER_1:  power.
SPEAKER_0:  money.
SPEAKER_0:  here in the US.
SPEAKER_0:  somebody might, you know, I want to mansion.
SPEAKER_0:  I want to like that that's their mindset. I want to live, you know, like that rapper
SPEAKER_0:  down there, I mean, if you can buy.
SPEAKER_0:  a house for your mom, you know, or pay off.
SPEAKER_0:  some debts that you might have or a car.
SPEAKER_0:  That's enough to kill for.
SPEAKER_1:  So you also, one of the many things you did is security try to protect.
SPEAKER_1:  in this war try to protect people, high value people.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you do you and others? How is it possible to protect?
SPEAKER_1:  a high value target like a celebrity.
SPEAKER_1:  or an important politician in the situation.
SPEAKER_0:  So I was tasked.
SPEAKER_0:  to protect the governor of Baja and his family.
SPEAKER_0:  I was basically replacing a whole contingency of people that were already there.
SPEAKER_0:  that turned out to be corrupted.
SPEAKER_0:  That wasn't my-
SPEAKER_0:  I was operational, I was working.
SPEAKER_0:  with other people doing the counter.
SPEAKER_0:  narcotic stuff and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  the director of the institution that I was in basically called me and said they
SPEAKER_0:  you're going to go and replace these people. What happened to them?
SPEAKER_0:  Well...
SPEAKER_1:  I see you were known as a person that could be kind of trusted.
SPEAKER_0:  I was tasked for that, so I think they considered that.
SPEAKER_0:  I specifically worked for...
SPEAKER_0:  governor name
SPEAKER_0:  Jose Guadalupe Osuna Mia, who's probably one of the best governors we have had in the state.
SPEAKER_0: ...
SPEAKER_0:  People wanna...
SPEAKER_0:  see if I'm trustworthy or not, they can ask him directly. And I still speak to some members of his family, and we're still friends in that way.
SPEAKER_1:  is protecting people like
SPEAKER_1:  technically difficult.
SPEAKER_0:  It is, from my experience in that time and place, he was basically spearheading.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, counter the drug war in Baja when he was in power. So he had threats from all over.
SPEAKER_0:  Not only him, but his family.
SPEAKER_0:  The first thing I realized working that job in Mexico was that we had.
SPEAKER_0:  We had people coming in to do specialized training of that regard, Israelis, you know, teaching us how they would do things in Israel.
SPEAKER_0:  that didn't make a lot of sense for us in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  We had people that had some Secret Service experience kind of showing us how they would do like celebrity bodyguarding or bodyguarding somebody maybe in California of that nature.
SPEAKER_0:  didn't make sense for us.
SPEAKER_0:  Then we got to experience some cross-training with some NSW, Naval Special Warfare people.
SPEAKER_0:  who are coming off protection details in Afghanistan.
SPEAKER_0:  and Iraq.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there some useful crossover there?
SPEAKER_0:  we were struggling with the acceptance that we were basically doing protection details in a war zone.
SPEAKER_0:  So the approach...
SPEAKER_1:  that had to be taken in Mexico was similar to the approach she would take in Afghanistan.
SPEAKER_0:  during a war.
SPEAKER_0:  some of the overt militaristic type approaches to security that we had to adopt from.
SPEAKER_0:  We didn't move him in a single armored vehicle. We had two of them that looked exactly alike.
SPEAKER_0:  So when we would move around, we would.
SPEAKER_0:  switch one card through the other every now and then we would arrive to an event.
SPEAKER_0:  they would open the door and it would be one of us. And they were like, hey, where's the governor? He's in the back one. So they would move to that. So we had to do stuff like that.
SPEAKER_0:  And again, this is a young me who didn't have any specialized training. I was fucking evolves.
SPEAKER_0:  I was on YouTube learning some of these things, going online, learning about armor vehicles, learning about architectural armor.
SPEAKER_1:  I think you just described a large percentage of the Ukrainian military, how they operate, which is on YouTube, trying to figure out how to use some of this technology.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... that's actually incredibly effective you know i do quite a lot of stuff where i'm totally not expert totally uneducated and so on
SPEAKER_1:  It's kind of surprising how quickly you can...
SPEAKER_1:  get caught up, as we were talking offline, you take a course.
SPEAKER_1:  If you talk to an expert, if you learn from an expert, you can like...
SPEAKER_1:  catch up really quickly.
SPEAKER_0:  For me, it was all of a sudden I have this director calling me in and I'm-
SPEAKER_0:  wearing vans and jeans, t-shirt, and all of a sudden I had 80-some people that I had to move around.
SPEAKER_0:  I was in charge of securing planes, which I...
SPEAKER_0:  What do I know about that? Airport hangers?
SPEAKER_0:  armored vehicle maintenance and purchasing.
SPEAKER_0:  figuring out how to set up a counter-assault group for a protection detail, and I was like, where am I going to learn all this?
SPEAKER_1:  We able to quickly figure some of these things out.
SPEAKER_0:  on the fly basically, you know, as I was going, I remember having this experience.
SPEAKER_0:  being in the...
SPEAKER_0:  our security office on my laptop figuring out how to set up a
SPEAKER_0:  counter surveillance aside to our
SPEAKER_0:  protection detail, basically how to.
SPEAKER_0:  have people looking for people that might be looking for us, you know, type thing.
SPEAKER_0:  and then going to...
SPEAKER_0:  San Diego to Coronado.
SPEAKER_0:  and training with.
SPEAKER_0:  some people from.
SPEAKER_0:  former SEAL guys and NCIS people who did that job in war zones.
SPEAKER_0:  and seeing them.
SPEAKER_0:  critique some of the solutions that we came up with on the fly and being like, oh,
SPEAKER_0:  We never saw that before. Yeah, we're doing it down there. So getting that compliment.
SPEAKER_0:  and also getting their feedback, like we probably do this or do that.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a learning process on the fly that was pretty...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean seat of your pants level.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it possible for the family?
SPEAKER_1:  and for the high value person to
SPEAKER_1:  to have a sense of normalcy, to have a normal life.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I tried. I was already starting off on the wrong foot basically because trust had been violated.
SPEAKER_0:  by the people that I was replacing. So I had to gain that back.
SPEAKER_0:  then
SPEAKER_0:  young kids in that family that wanted to go out and stuff like that in the most violent city on the planet.
SPEAKER_0:  So I had to do my homework and figure out places where they were safe to go to.
SPEAKER_0:  make friends with certain club owners and
SPEAKER_0:  figure out ways to put security in some of these places and.
SPEAKER_0:  having to create this bubble of normalcy around some of these people was pretty difficult.
SPEAKER_0:  there's no way that that is a normal for anybody and
SPEAKER_0:  at all.
SPEAKER_0:  God bless them. I know it wasn't easy, and I know they'd affected their lives, and they lost on...
SPEAKER_0:  big part of their youth being under that security supervision and bubble.
SPEAKER_0:  does.
SPEAKER_0:  probably does a lot for somebody specifically growing up like that.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  You lose opportunities of...
SPEAKER_0:  things that we take for granted, you know, just going out, just not telling anybody and going to the store.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  because you want to get some snacks or something like that. That's not available to some of these people.
SPEAKER_0:  I have to be honest.
SPEAKER_1:  when I was in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  That was a really big benefit. It's
SPEAKER_1:  No, I couldn't hang out. I couldn't eat when I'm stressed. I would fast and not eat much. So I got lost weight. So it's great. Eat For The Diet.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a good diet to be in. Basically, to be under protective custody. That's a good idea for a good diet.
SPEAKER_1:  and just life allowed me to focus, get a lot of reading done, focus on the important things in life.
SPEAKER_1:  Heh.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I joke of course, but there's some.
SPEAKER_1:  There's some complexity to this.
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of normalcy of the family.
SPEAKER_1:  but also just how to operate.
SPEAKER_1:  Like have a mental clarity of-
SPEAKER_1:  and a lack of fear.
SPEAKER_1:  just basically be good at your job, whatever that job is. as a politician, as a leader.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... even as a soldier
SPEAKER_0:  Somebody...
SPEAKER_0:  then again I think this is a little bit older.
SPEAKER_0:  said this to me or said something like this to a group of us.
SPEAKER_0:  that there's nothing wrong with being paranoid.
SPEAKER_0:  It's about educating your paranoia and knowing what to be afraid of.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're afraid of everything, you're basically overwhelmed.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you start educating yourself as far as specifically what to prioritize as far as what to worry about.
SPEAKER_0:  in a war zone, working, protecting somebody. You're not looking at everybody's faces, you're just looking at their hands, because that's what's going to kill you.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  That's an example of focalizing.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, what you're paranoid and what you're afraid of.
SPEAKER_1:  So looking at the hands that's.
SPEAKER_1:  specific to a particular situation but
SPEAKER_1:  I was just figuring out.
SPEAKER_1:  which situations to avoid and which.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. It's okay. I mean, that's like ultimately one of the biggest.
SPEAKER_1:  things you could do. meet
SPEAKER_0:  route analysis.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to get to the airport and you send off two cars to analyze two routes. And then on the fly you just change.
SPEAKER_0:  trajectory.
SPEAKER_0:  create randomness.
SPEAKER_0:  unpredictability and have that as a security feature.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  having a convoy of four vehicles separated into.
SPEAKER_0:  two convoys and show up in different parts.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, make it hard for people to guess where you're going to be.
SPEAKER_0:  putting out false information as far as where it's going to be, who's going to be, and that type of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  It's kind of amazing how many assassination attempts Hitler avoided.
SPEAKER_1:  just by having a pretty strict schedule and being a little bit off in terms of timing.
SPEAKER_1:  just like showing up 15 minutes late.
SPEAKER_1:  or to a slightly different location.
SPEAKER_0:  We're going through training specifically around this type of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  and operational training basically.
SPEAKER_0:  showing us how to ambush people.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  when I started making a group for myself as far as counter-ambush, you know, this cat teams that they call them up here in the US, basically a group of...
SPEAKER_0:  a group to respond to a high violent ambush.
SPEAKER_0:  First off, the first rule if you find yourself in an ambush.
SPEAKER_0:  it wasn't a successful ambush because if you find yourself in it, you're alive. Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you want to create an amazing counter ambush team, you have to, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to make them ambushers.
SPEAKER_0:  and with ambushing you.
SPEAKER_0:  figure out where all the...
SPEAKER_0:  opportunities of not only successfully doing what you need to do are in your favor, but also to escape with your life.
SPEAKER_0:  We're not going to be received by virgins in heaven. That's not the type of mentality that we had down there. But-
SPEAKER_0:  we start learning about some of these things and also seeing cartel forces apply some of these ambush tactics too.
SPEAKER_0:  the military or the federal forces.
SPEAKER_1:  an ambush or what are we talking about? So that's a surprise attack with an asymmetry power
SPEAKER_0:  or kind of thing.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a.
SPEAKER_0:  contingency somewhere moving towards a place that you control and own.
SPEAKER_0:  where you have the advantages, where...
SPEAKER_0:  They can't see you, but you can see them. Or they can't predict you, but you can predict where they're gonna pass. Go through places where they forcibly have to pass.
SPEAKER_0:  places where they're predictable.
SPEAKER_0:  places where you can.
SPEAKER_0:  not only predict, but also have a plan for yourself to escape and exit that place. So how do you transform?
SPEAKER_1:  Conor Ambush.
SPEAKER_0:  You turn into a...
SPEAKER_0:  like a perfect ambusher. That's how you train for counter-ambusher.
SPEAKER_1:  trying to make sure you have more information about other people.
SPEAKER_1:  you have the element of surprise of
SPEAKER_0:  of those things. And Musashi would say, you know your enemy, know his sword. You know, basically that.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, simplified.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot of enemies around you.
SPEAKER_1:  Mexico there's a lot of uncertainty right?
SPEAKER_1:  I guess that's what route analysis is.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, you prepare for the probable.
SPEAKER_0:  And if the impossible happens, you're halfway out of it.
SPEAKER_0:  Hopefully.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you find yourself in an ambush, it wasn't a successful one.
SPEAKER_0:  as far as our training and the mindset, my experience with it.
SPEAKER_0:  You've...
SPEAKER_0:  The Adversarial.
SPEAKER_0:  thinking part of it has always been a very powerful one, I think one that a lot of people ignore.
SPEAKER_0:  leave to the wayside.
SPEAKER_0:  Specifically in all conflicts out there, there's a tendency for...
SPEAKER_0:  a military force or a conventional force of any kind to be trained in a way where they dehumanize the enemy.
SPEAKER_0:  And when that happens, you become blind to the enemy's story. It's his capability, his story, his ability.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  if you treat the other side like an inhuman monster.
SPEAKER_0:  it's hard to take notes, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  So there's a part of this.
SPEAKER_1:  is.
SPEAKER_1:  a radical empathy for it.
SPEAKER_1:  for the quote unquote enemy.
SPEAKER_0:  At least for me personally, I wasn't one of the guys that would grab them and beat the shit out of them and put them in the back of a van. Tie them up and gag them.
SPEAKER_0:  So you're able to see them as humans.
SPEAKER_0:  I learned that from my mother, you know, she said, nobody's against you there for themselves. There isn't a transition toiality, no plan, no
SPEAKER_0:  you will make friends of enemies.
SPEAKER_0:  She said that when I graduated and I've carried that with me throughout my whole career.
SPEAKER_1:  But isn't there then a pain of killing another human?
SPEAKER_1:  As always.
SPEAKER_1:  but there isn't.
SPEAKER_1:  again.
SPEAKER_1:  I apologize to go back to Ukraine as my only experience of this kind of hor-
SPEAKER_0:  It is a powerful experience.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a dehumanization that happens.
SPEAKER_1:  I suppose this is common in war.
SPEAKER_1:  There's something like a video game aspect.
SPEAKER_1:  or people are almost having fun.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a humor.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think underneath that, the prerequisite.
SPEAKER_1:  is to see the enemy in the same way you see the enemy when you play Call of Duty. You don't really think...
SPEAKER_1:  You're thinking of them as NPCs, the bad guys.
SPEAKER_1:  The Russians are called orcs.
SPEAKER_1:  in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, there's all kinds of other names.
SPEAKER_0:  For us it was Mugrosos.
SPEAKER_0:  malandros mugrosos like dirty people.
SPEAKER_0:  There's always something.
SPEAKER_1:  over time. Those are just words.
SPEAKER_1:  But over time it gathers.
SPEAKER_1:  a kind of, um...
SPEAKER_1:  like a meaning to it that's more than just the words.
SPEAKER_1:  works.
SPEAKER_1:  They're less than human.
SPEAKER_1:  They're dirty, they're...
SPEAKER_1:  too dumb to understand the evil they're doing or whatever the
SPEAKER_0:  It's useful.TEXT biomarquable
SPEAKER_1:  It's part of the program. Like that's what I've talked to soldiers.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Some of them.
SPEAKER_1:  do have stories of momentarily.
SPEAKER_1:  remembering that there's a human on the other side.
SPEAKER_1:  I talked to one woman.
SPEAKER_1:  who's this really badass soldier.
SPEAKER_1:  She saw this really brave soldier on the other side.
SPEAKER_1:  do something that's...
SPEAKER_1:  Buzz.
SPEAKER_1:  almost stupid.
SPEAKER_1:  how brave it was.
SPEAKER_1:  And then.
SPEAKER_1:  she was trying to shoot him and she missed.
SPEAKER_1:  and she said she could sleep the night after.
SPEAKER_1:  Thinking.
SPEAKER_1:  Why did she miss? Why did she miss?
SPEAKER_1:  And then she thought.
SPEAKER_1:  She missed because...
SPEAKER_1:  He was a hero.
SPEAKER_1:  And she had this brief realization that there was a hero on the other side. The other side is heroes. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  And then, but then that quickly disappeared. Yeah. This moment as a human being.
SPEAKER_1:  that rises to defend his nation, to defend his people.
SPEAKER_1:  and he could be heroic on the other side.
SPEAKER_0:  There are things that we're trained to depress or
SPEAKER_0:  Concealer Hide.
SPEAKER_0:  and kill in us when you're trained for something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  Or when you're in conflict zone like that and you hear the narrative constantly being blared out that the other side is an orc.
SPEAKER_0:  or.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, whatever word you want to use.
SPEAKER_0:  But, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  We live in a day and age when you can see Americans going off to Japan and shaking hands with some of their former enemies. Some of us have seen that.
SPEAKER_0:  and how things change.
SPEAKER_0:  I think years from now, a lot of the stuff that we are taking right now is of the utmost importance won't matter anymore.
SPEAKER_1:  The question is how many years? That's the question I asked.
SPEAKER_1:  of a lot of people.
SPEAKER_1:  in that part of the world.
SPEAKER_1:  and a lot of them currently.
SPEAKER_1:  They're also self aware about it. They're like.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not sure I trust my current feelings. But the current feelings are generational.
SPEAKER_1:  Like for decades, I will not just hate.
SPEAKER_1:  the leadership of Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  people.
SPEAKER_0:  I can't understand that on my side of my life experience because you know our war has been an internal war you know amongst our people our monster houses.
SPEAKER_1:  That is the propaganda.
SPEAKER_1:  There's also a deep grain of truth that there is a oneness to the people of that region. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  people will get very offended at that idea because right now it's a very strong
SPEAKER_1:  Nationalist Borders.
SPEAKER_1:  but there is a cultural history.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  connects people. I mean, in some deep sense, we're all connected. Welcome from Western Africa.
SPEAKER_1:  and then all came from fish before then, depending on.
SPEAKER_1:  Here, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I believe you.
SPEAKER_1:  of history of life on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  but there is a oneness to us.
SPEAKER_1:  Often you forget that.
SPEAKER_0:  in conflict. I had an experience.
SPEAKER_0:  working.
SPEAKER_0:  there was a friend of mine who took the other path.
SPEAKER_0:  Ah.
SPEAKER_0:  and went to work for some of these criminal groups.
SPEAKER_0:  I was operational and I was...
SPEAKER_0:  we saw a bunch of people in a gas station.
SPEAKER_0:  part.
SPEAKER_0:  Back then, the main modus operandi that they had was that they would impersonate or dress up as federal police.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's how they would move around the city.
SPEAKER_0:  We saw these suburbans in a...
SPEAKER_0:  and a gas station.
SPEAKER_0:  and some of the guys were carrying our AK-47s. That's not a standard issue firearm.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, we...
SPEAKER_0:  I saw that and I got off on foot.
SPEAKER_0:  and walk by.
SPEAKER_0:  to try and get her.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, better sense of what was going on. I took everything off.
SPEAKER_0:  wearing jeans and a t-shirt.
SPEAKER_0:  And I got a whistle from one of the guys.
SPEAKER_0:  that was there and my name was called.
SPEAKER_0:  It was one of the guys that I grew up with.
SPEAKER_0:  Redhead kid, look like El Canelo.
SPEAKER_0:  enough.
SPEAKER_0:  There's right heads in Mexico, by the way.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's probably.
SPEAKER_0:  some of the Irish that betrayed the American side during the last Mexican-American war that stayed down there had a bunch of kids.
SPEAKER_0:  probably from there. Love is stronger than anything else. This is Redhead Kid.
SPEAKER_0:  When I say kid, I mean, he was my age. Now to my eyes, he's always going to be younger now.
SPEAKER_0:  whistled.
SPEAKER_0:  told my name.
SPEAKER_0:  Say hey.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm like, what are you doing here? It's like, gosh, I don't just, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  going home.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's go get a taxi.
SPEAKER_0:  He's like, oh, okay. Walk as he walks over as a.
SPEAKER_0:  plate carrier with AK.
SPEAKER_0:  around magazines on his chest.
SPEAKER_0:  8k without a stock on it.
SPEAKER_0:  Just carrying in his hand.
SPEAKER_0:  He comes over and hugs me. I can feel the uh...
SPEAKER_0:  The magazine's on my chest.
SPEAKER_0:  I have a gun on me, tucked.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh...
SPEAKER_0:  NexTail is buzzing in my back pocket.
SPEAKER_0:  as people are trying to figure out what the fuck's going on.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, he asked me small talk shit like, Hey, it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  What are you doing? What do you work at? And I'm like, ah, I'm just looking for a job. I used to work at a video store.
SPEAKER_0:  So he's like, I haven't seen you in a while.
SPEAKER_0:  How's so and so of your family? Good. How's so and so of your family? Good.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, yeah, it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  this is an interesting job you have." He's like, yeah, it's pretty good. They pay as well.
SPEAKER_0:  You get a car, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  There's money.
SPEAKER_0:  and nobody fucks with you, you get respect.
SPEAKER_0:  That's awesome.
SPEAKER_0:  If you want, it can get you in. If you ever want that, it's like, ah.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm too much of a coward for that, I told them.
SPEAKER_1:  conversation like any other.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah... particularly between 2 friends.
SPEAKER_0:  He hugs me.
SPEAKER_0:  before I go.
SPEAKER_0:  I have something.
SPEAKER_0:  I can't remember what.
SPEAKER_0:  And he says, hey.
SPEAKER_0:  in my ear.
SPEAKER_0:  I know what you do for a living. It's not a safe place for you to be.
SPEAKER_0:  and I walk off.
SPEAKER_0:  A few moments later, the army showed up.
SPEAKER_0:  and you.
SPEAKER_0:  Feel them.
SPEAKER_0:  amount of rounds.
SPEAKER_0:  going off.
SPEAKER_0:  blocks away.
SPEAKER_0:  We came back.
SPEAKER_0:  with Spar Guys.
SPEAKER_0:  then it was.
SPEAKER_0:  It was over.
SPEAKER_0:  So he didn't survive that.
SPEAKER_0:  I will walk through.
SPEAKER_0:  the bodies.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  the cars that were left, you know, there was.
SPEAKER_0:  bodies all over the place, people left there.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a mess.
SPEAKER_0:  spent like an hour looking for him
SPEAKER_0:  The only way I could recognize him was his hair.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I stayed with his body.
SPEAKER_0:  All night.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a...
SPEAKER_0:  There's a bridge.
SPEAKER_0:  in Tijuana that goes over the river in a place called La Mesa.
SPEAKER_0:  and that's where the forensic offices were.
SPEAKER_0:  His body was taken there and I stayed with his body until it was released.
SPEAKER_0:  I told his family about it.
SPEAKER_0:  Because I knew them.
SPEAKER_0:  that aspect of, you know, us versus them or they're the enemy. Do you like that?
SPEAKER_0:  Hello, my mom.
SPEAKER_0:  told me those words. Nobody's against you, they're just for themselves. So don't make the mistake of dehumanizing anybody.
SPEAKER_0:  and those roles could have been.
SPEAKER_1:  easily.
SPEAKER_0:  Burst.
SPEAKER_0:  I could have been shot in the face there.
SPEAKER_0:  that aspect that conflict brings where they're saying.
SPEAKER_0:  bad guys, good guys, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  uh, heroes.
SPEAKER_0:  villains, you know, how you
SPEAKER_0:  There's an innocence to that that it goes away
SPEAKER_0:  Is your mom still with us?
SPEAKER_0:  almost three weeks before I decided to quit.
SPEAKER_0:  She passed away.
SPEAKER_0:  Did that have a role to play?
SPEAKER_0:  Major one.
SPEAKER_0:  after I got done on the protection detail with the governor.
SPEAKER_0:  Like everything down there again the whole cycle
SPEAKER_0:  He got his turn, so when he went away...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  No politics change.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  down there basically if you're a.
SPEAKER_0:  can go to the editorial candidate.
SPEAKER_0:  You have either a friend, a friend of a friend or a family member be the head bodyguard guy.
SPEAKER_0:  The guy that won the elections had his...
SPEAKER_0:  bodyguard guy already there. So all of us were sent back to whatever we came from. So I went back to work on the streets.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  I was back on the operations group. I was working with the sub director directly with him, basically back on the ground doing.
SPEAKER_0:  stuff that I was doing before that job.
SPEAKER_0:  We were moving away from the successes that had been had by people like Liza Ola when they were in charge of that whole process to people that I used to work with.
SPEAKER_0:  some of the only successes in that counter.
SPEAKER_0:  push against cartels in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  and you can kind of like, it's documented, you can read about it out there, a bunch of people wrote papers on it.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of the only successes were had by Liza Ola in the places where he had leadership. He not only...
SPEAKER_0:  pacified Tijuana.
SPEAKER_0:  He also did the same in Juarez. He was sent to be the police chief in Juarez.
SPEAKER_0:  but politics change and heroes become villains.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of people started calling him a villain because of his...
SPEAKER_0:  on orthodox approach and human rights violations and all this type of stuff kind of come.
SPEAKER_0:  the forefront.
SPEAKER_0:  and people forgot.
SPEAKER_0:  People forgot what it took to get Tijuana off the most dangerous city list on the planet.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  People were vilified.
SPEAKER_0:  people like him
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  and the police force that I was a part of started getting.
SPEAKER_0:  compromised.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of the things that were put forth to try and keep us honest. There was a program.
SPEAKER_0:  They have these centers.
SPEAKER_0:  the C3s.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, you would go there every year. You would get your-
SPEAKER_0:  financials checked, you would get a physical, psychological evaluation, you would get a polygraph exam done on you, all of the works. The jump into the
SPEAKER_0:  See if you were somebody doing something wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  And all of that was.
SPEAKER_0:  canceled because...
SPEAKER_0:  It violated.
SPEAKER_0:  human rights if you get fired from a job because of a failed polygraph exam because that was not an actual admissible way of firing somebody.
SPEAKER_0:  So all of a sudden you had people that were known cartel.
SPEAKER_0:  compromise people.
SPEAKER_0:  that were fired five, six years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  showing back up to work.
SPEAKER_0:  with their back paid and everything.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is...
SPEAKER_0:  So this started happening and.
SPEAKER_0:  it quickly realized that it was.
SPEAKER_0:  gonna be hard to stay there.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I was driving home from work.
SPEAKER_0:  and I got a call from my brother.
SPEAKER_0:  That, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  my mom had been going through some health.
SPEAKER_0:  issues.
SPEAKER_0:  that had turned into psychiatric issues.
SPEAKER_0:  We were basically taking turns trying to...
SPEAKER_0:  take care of her, you know, locking the doors so she wouldn't wander off and stuff like that so not only was I dealing
SPEAKER_0:  with the job on the street, but I was dealing with that. And also I had a
SPEAKER_0:  a two year old.
SPEAKER_0:  and a marriage that was...
SPEAKER_0:  difficult.
SPEAKER_0:  the Ted time.
SPEAKER_0:  I was trying to figure all these things out. Made more difficult by your job?
SPEAKER_0:  It's not a financially secure job, you know, and the pressures that it has and the odd hours and all that made it really hard.
SPEAKER_0:  And then all of a sudden my brother calls me and tells me that let's go to the hospital my mom.
SPEAKER_0:  Something happened to my mom?
SPEAKER_0:  It wasn't my turn to watch her, so...
SPEAKER_0:  I felt pretty shitty about that.
SPEAKER_0:  I got to the hospital and...
SPEAKER_0:  The doctors came out and told us that she was gone.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a...
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  massive heart attack.
SPEAKER_0:  She had a pacemaker by then.
SPEAKER_0:  So she was gone?
SPEAKER_0:  She was in her 60s.
SPEAKER_0:  So we kind of expected something, but that was like.
SPEAKER_0:  hard for me.
SPEAKER_0:  She was my...
SPEAKER_0:  center.
SPEAKER_0:  She was going to be the one that I would ask for advice as far as work, you know, if I should leave or not.
SPEAKER_1:  The ground was removed from under the ground.
SPEAKER_0:  There was nobody there was yeah, there's nothing underneath me
SPEAKER_0:  I get three days off work.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what they gave me.
SPEAKER_0:  And, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm trying to grieve as I go back to work.
SPEAKER_0:  Dark shit crosses my mind as I'm going through that process of trying to figure things out.
SPEAKER_0:  I like dark shake like so.
SPEAKER_1:  Suicide, right, Darkshit? Yeah. Very low for you.
SPEAKER_0:  Very, very hard. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  I wasn't allowed to grieve, basically.
SPEAKER_0:  and I wasn't allowed to read for a few years.
SPEAKER_0:  for different reasons.
SPEAKER_0:  I went back to work.
SPEAKER_1:  You weren't allowing other people, also you yourself, were not allowing yourself to agree with.
SPEAKER_0:  There was other people with me that didn't allow me to grieve.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  I went to work, got called into the office, and I was basically told that I was going to be reassigned.
SPEAKER_0:  after what I just went through.
SPEAKER_0:  the reassignment was going to be something that.
SPEAKER_0:  Ice.
SPEAKER_0:  saw as.
SPEAKER_0:  unacceptable.
SPEAKER_0:  It was, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  people in charge at that point were.
SPEAKER_0:  obviously.
SPEAKER_0:  corrupted.
SPEAKER_0:  And what I got from their conversation was that they wanted us to work for a specific side.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I knew that that was the time to go.
SPEAKER_0:  I...
SPEAKER_0:  asked for a license.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically licenses.
SPEAKER_0:  unpaid absence from work, basically a leave of absence.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's what you call it up here.
SPEAKER_0:  which by law is allowed.
SPEAKER_0:  and I was denied.
SPEAKER_0:  for no reason.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm invested in this job, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  I have a...
SPEAKER_0:  I have a good salary and I have a category in there. So you...
SPEAKER_0:  by the level of...
SPEAKER_0:  time you spend in there you get a category. So I was at.
SPEAKER_0:  pretty high category agent.
SPEAKER_0:  all this training and again, training that would be useless in the private sector or in the public sector in Mexico. I couldn't change from one corporation to another. I couldn't go to work for another police institution.
SPEAKER_0:  I took a deep breath and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I resign.
SPEAKER_0:  I went to the office, I said I need to resign.
SPEAKER_0:  They say what?
SPEAKER_0:  I need to resign. Some of the people in the office that knew me from a long time were like, What?
SPEAKER_0:  wrong with you? I thought I was having a mental breakdown.
SPEAKER_0:  Ended all over the, all the paperwork, took a big trash bag, put all my stuff in there.
SPEAKER_0:  plate armor.
SPEAKER_0:  to your gas grenades.
SPEAKER_0:  Gasmaska.
SPEAKER_0:  Satellite radio, MP5 magazines, an MP5, a submachine gun, Glock magazines, all of it, helmets.
SPEAKER_0:  and I put her in the armory.
SPEAKER_0:  And I...
SPEAKER_0:  left.
SPEAKER_0:  I made some phone calls.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I was married to a...
SPEAKER_0:  an American.
SPEAKER_0:  and my daughter's American.
SPEAKER_0:  I never envisioned myself coming to the United States, do that process for myself. So I was invested in that job. I thought I was gonna...
SPEAKER_0:  die or retire from that.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  It quickly became like an issue because everybody was wondering why I left the job so abruptly.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  There were some threats made.
SPEAKER_0:  when I left.
SPEAKER_0:  by people inside the office.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably, you know, it's anonymous shit.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's significant pressure not to leave. It's hard to leave this kind of job. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  The system makes it difficult to leave.
SPEAKER_1:  the individuals.
SPEAKER_1:  to the degree they might be corrupted.
SPEAKER_1:  Really don't want you to leave. There's no support.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there's no support. There's probably the output.
SPEAKER_1:  of support.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  almost like implied or explicit or implicit threats.
SPEAKER_0:  Luckily, I had developed some friendships in the United States with some of the people that I used to work with.
SPEAKER_0:  and cross-drain with and...
SPEAKER_0:  some friendships that I developed with people that I would...
SPEAKER_0:  Just talk to and make friends with, stateside.
SPEAKER_0:  One of them was a...
SPEAKER_0:  is a Navy SEAL reservist whose name is Dan Stanchfield.
SPEAKER_0:  and his wife, Kelly.
SPEAKER_0:  they
SPEAKER_0:  open the doors of their house to me and.
SPEAKER_0:  my kid and my wife at that time.
SPEAKER_0:  as I seek to basically...
SPEAKER_0:  Look for the American dream.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I crossed the border.
SPEAKER_0:  with my kid.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Nobody knew anything, you know, I hadn't.
SPEAKER_0:  They didn't tell anybody, just my wife.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was off.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  When I came to the States, I...
SPEAKER_0:  already kind of dabbled in the whole training field and showing.
SPEAKER_0:  some of my experience to people.
SPEAKER_0:  So ahead.
SPEAKER_0:  at least a seed of that out there.
SPEAKER_0:  people knew me for that.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  But all of a sudden I was...
SPEAKER_0:  in the middle of an avocado orchard.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh-huh.
SPEAKER_0:  in the
SPEAKER_0:  middle of California.
SPEAKER_0:  and everything's quiet.
SPEAKER_0:  and.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no more radios going off all of the night. There's no more three cell phones on the counter. There's no guns. There's no rifles. There's no...
SPEAKER_0:  80 people calling to
SPEAKER_0:  to calling to see what's going on. There's nothing, it's just quiet.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's during the time when Trump got elected, so the immigration process that usually would take.
SPEAKER_0:  and those things go in for me.
SPEAKER_0:  and migration process it would take.
SPEAKER_0:  at the most of the year took two years.
SPEAKER_0:  So I was.
SPEAKER_0:  It was not her.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not an easy process.
SPEAKER_0:  to not only come to the US, but...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, come to the US with a...
SPEAKER_0:  with that pressure.
SPEAKER_0:  of underlying pressure as far as being an immigrant at that time here.
SPEAKER_1:  and then your own personal psychological, the PTSD.
SPEAKER_1:  of going.
SPEAKER_1:  from a war zone to a...
SPEAKER_0:  avocado orchard.
SPEAKER_0:  The word PTSD.
SPEAKER_0:  and TBI and all of these things. I did not, I didn't know any of them.
SPEAKER_0:  Ah.
SPEAKER_0:  It was through people that I got to meet.
SPEAKER_0:  in the training field that were Marines.
SPEAKER_0:  seals, maraschalk guys, those types of people that started giving words to some of the things that I felt.
SPEAKER_0:  which I didn't really know.
SPEAKER_0:  we would treat post-traumatic stress with alcohol and vacation time.
SPEAKER_0:  The bottle of mezcal.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, when you see the bottom of it.
SPEAKER_0:  The troubles are gone. X issue
SPEAKER_0:  immediately.
SPEAKER_0:  I was an alcoholic.
SPEAKER_0:  as well as all the other stuff I was.
SPEAKER_0:  I was drinking myself to sleep every third night.
SPEAKER_0:  My marriage obviously was failing.
SPEAKER_0:  It wasn't easy for her, you know, she...
SPEAKER_0:  She was brave and she did what she could and I...
SPEAKER_0:  totally respect and understand her.
SPEAKER_0:  process with it but.
SPEAKER_0:  when it's quiet.
SPEAKER_0:  That's when it hits ya.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what I think that's what a lot of people experience when they come back from a conflict zone.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, the uh...
SPEAKER_0:  everything that was life and death.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything that mattered, all the noise, all the chaos, all the people that are around you that would die for you, kill for you.
SPEAKER_0:  you would kill for them.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll leave.
SPEAKER_0:  millions of dollars worth of equipment and stuff like that you're responsible for now are all gone and it's just you walking into a
SPEAKER_0:  Circle K and buying.
SPEAKER_0:  weekends at Foster's to
SPEAKER_0:  drink yourself to sleep.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, you write on your Patreon brilliantly.
SPEAKER_1:  about PTSD.
SPEAKER_1:  about the cost of things you've done and seen.
SPEAKER_1:  quote, when it's over.
SPEAKER_1:  And we are far from that chaos and noise of death being close and life being real.
SPEAKER_1:  That is when some of us remember in the quiet nights in a field in Tennessee looking at fireflies.
SPEAKER_1:  Walking through a fair.
SPEAKER_1:  Holding hands with a lover.
SPEAKER_1:  asking.
SPEAKER_1:  You what's wrong?
SPEAKER_1:  at your kid's birthday party.
SPEAKER_1:  Leave early to avoid the ending of a celebration.
SPEAKER_1:  That is what the quiet means to some of us.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's speaking to that silence, the quiet.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you live with and thrive with?
SPEAKER_1:  this newly learned term of PTSD.
SPEAKER_0:  If anything, I would recommend people that have any of these issues to go to places where other people have.
SPEAKER_0:  their issues so you can.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not a competition, but you get to see the scope of problems in the world and you sometimes feel kind of lucky as far as your own.
SPEAKER_1:  Like it humbles you. Yeah. And makes you appreciate all the different kinds of struggles that people go through.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, I went through some horrible shit, but...
SPEAKER_0:  some people that went through other more or less yet or...
SPEAKER_0:  stuff that I.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think I could have survived.
SPEAKER_0:  when I went through that process of.
SPEAKER_0:  figuring things out, you know, the first thing that glaringly pointed out or stuck out to me was my inability to...
SPEAKER_0:  Process things.
SPEAKER_0:  Like there was a big pause button there.
SPEAKER_0:  A giant one. Everything was on pause.
SPEAKER_0:  My...
SPEAKER_0:  breathing.
SPEAKER_0:  Not only my mom, but my brother.
SPEAKER_0:  So I had a pause button on me, so it was like 13 basically.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, then I got to bury...
SPEAKER_0:  Many of my friends.
SPEAKER_0:  inform their wives or...
SPEAKER_0:  girlfriends of what happened.
SPEAKER_0:  And that all, again, was paused because I...
SPEAKER_0:  wasn't uh...
SPEAKER_0:  allowed to process.
SPEAKER_0:  I spent years without going on vacation because I was a workaholic.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I found that the core of my issue is, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  alcohol.
SPEAKER_0:  a giant pause button in the form of alcohol. basically.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll drink my problems away.
SPEAKER_0:  Specifically, I would.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like if you have a mess in your house, you just put a big tarp over it, you know, to cover it up and alcohol was that for me.
SPEAKER_0:  and it fasted.
SPEAKER_0:  more and more as I
SPEAKER_0:  not only went through the process of learning about PCSD, but refusing to let that go.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, like going through therapy and seeing what other people's problems were.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't wanna...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, this is the only thing I have. I'm not, you know, I'm not.
SPEAKER_0:  hurting anybody with it, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Why, why am I, why do I need to get rid of that?
SPEAKER_0:  By this point I was traveling across the country and training people and showing some of the experiences that I had to other people speaking
SPEAKER_0:  being on podcasts and having conversations like the one I'm having with you.
SPEAKER_1:  So speaking to the skills that you've developed.
SPEAKER_0:  and in a way basically reliving and reopening a bunch of shit for myself every time I do it.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  So I was getting triggered and the way I would manage that was I would drink at the end of the night after a weekend class somewhere when I talk about the fireflies and...
SPEAKER_0:  a field in Tennessee.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a moment where I was forcing myself to try and be sober.
SPEAKER_0:  and we did this medical class out and uh
SPEAKER_0:  Out in the hills in Tennessee, this beautiful green place.
SPEAKER_0:  beautiful family there.
SPEAKER_0:  that hosted us.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's the first time I ever saw a firefly. So I was like.
SPEAKER_0:  I thought I was having a hallucinogenic experience.
SPEAKER_0:  When I say why is the dust glowing?
SPEAKER_0:  what I thought.
SPEAKER_0:  a friend of mine.
SPEAKER_0:  is a veteran.
SPEAKER_0:  Ran off to the woods and grabbed one.
SPEAKER_0:  brought it to me and showed it to me. It's like, holy shit, what is that? That's a Firefly.
SPEAKER_0:  Wow.
SPEAKER_0:  How do they glow? I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  and he's crushing it in his hand and says, gone.
SPEAKER_0:  And I.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, brought me back immediately to...
SPEAKER_0:  Holy shit, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, it kind of like.
SPEAKER_0:  I was off somewhere and I was back.
SPEAKER_0:  And I had to go drink.
SPEAKER_0:  I went through that process of going off at getting on, going off getting off at my marriage.
SPEAKER_0:  separate.
SPEAKER_0:  And that was all.
SPEAKER_0:  another end of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  aspect to everything, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  I lost my mother, I lost the job, and then the marriage failed.
SPEAKER_0:  and it was on me.
SPEAKER_0:  I...
SPEAKER_0:  basically went somewhere and
SPEAKER_0:  did a stock of everything that was going on.
SPEAKER_0:  And...
SPEAKER_0:  and made a decision to.
SPEAKER_0:  Stop drinking.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  had some bad relationships after.
SPEAKER_0:  and I just came to a place where I need to stop drinking.
SPEAKER_1:  You've gotten to a point so low.
SPEAKER_1:  Was this a decision you arrived at by yourself?
SPEAKER_1:  Was there some inspiration?
SPEAKER_1:  Or was it just the point is so low?
SPEAKER_1:  Lots so much.
SPEAKER_0:  It was the start of COVID?
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  This is recent. This is probably too... I'm gonna...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm gonna have two years over in December.
SPEAKER_1:  So when you talk to Rogan the first time, you're still struggling with this demon..
SPEAKER_0:  I was in and out of the car, basically, is what I would say. I was in and out of-
SPEAKER_0:  and then.
SPEAKER_0:  trying to get rid of it.
SPEAKER_1:  That must be a super stressful experience talking to Joe Rogan the first time you drank that night.
SPEAKER_1:  You remember?
SPEAKER_0:  The second time I was there, I went somewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  Godshitface.
SPEAKER_0:  It was.
SPEAKER_0:  It was stressful not.
SPEAKER_0:  not for any other reason than...
SPEAKER_0:  I felt the responsibility to the people that couldn't speak about it.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's suppression.
SPEAKER_0:  It was the start of COVID and things got started getting shut down and slowed down.
SPEAKER_0:  My dad got really sick and almost died.
SPEAKER_0:  We had to set up like some Jason Bourne level shit at my brother's place.
SPEAKER_0:  He was in Mexico, you know, so we had to.
SPEAKER_0:  bribe a guy to get us an oxygen tank and I had to.
SPEAKER_0:  Jimmy Riga of respirator.
SPEAKER_0:  It was some shit.
SPEAKER_0:  but my dad was like...
SPEAKER_0:  Thanks for watching!
SPEAKER_0:  He survived it, you know, everybody, the doctor would like, say goodbye.
SPEAKER_0:  And my dad was like, yeah, say goodbye to him. and you're gonna keep pouring each one of them over?
SPEAKER_1:  what's up
SPEAKER_1:  I guess he does.
SPEAKER_0:  as a gangster, I got it. Tough guy. He did some gangster shit that day.
SPEAKER_0:  But on my end, I was being isolated basically as COVID is everybody's slowing down, no more classes, no more excuses to go out there and drink and no more socializing, so.
SPEAKER_0:  Social drinking turned into alone drinking more and more and more.
SPEAKER_0:  I bought a bottle of gin.
SPEAKER_0:  because I was down in Mexico taking care of my dad.
SPEAKER_0:  and they closed down beer production in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  beer went away.
SPEAKER_0:  And beer was a way I kind of managed it, you know? It's not Howard alcohol, it's just beer, so, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  But that went away, so it was just hard alcohol. That was what was available down there.
SPEAKER_0:  IAR.
SPEAKER_0:  One night alone at the house, my dad's house, I...
SPEAKER_0:  I drank a bottle of gin, a whole bottle of gin.
SPEAKER_0:  I almost died.
SPEAKER_0:  And after that...
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  Some people started noticing that.
SPEAKER_0:  that I was.
SPEAKER_0:  isolating more and more and...
SPEAKER_0:  It was kind of eating away at me.
SPEAKER_0:  I was in a relationship at that point when I...
SPEAKER_0:  I started seeing everything just kind of fall apart around me.
SPEAKER_0:  And.
SPEAKER_0:  I...
SPEAKER_0:  I-
SPEAKER_0:  drank half of a glass of uh
SPEAKER_0:  Wine.
SPEAKER_0:  And it made me sick.
SPEAKER_0:  to my internally in my mind.
SPEAKER_0:  and my kid.
SPEAKER_0:  said, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  to me and I don't know, nobody coached her, nobody said anything to her.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a pretty intuitive kit.
SPEAKER_0:  So I don't drink anymore of that.
SPEAKER_0:  out of nowhere.
SPEAKER_0:  in the middle of the night.
SPEAKER_0:  Ah...
SPEAKER_0:  And it stopped.
SPEAKER_0:  I stopped that night, I remember.
SPEAKER_0:  waking up at three in the morning and taking a cooler that I had and just dumping all the beers in it and
SPEAKER_0:  chucking them in the garbage and with a knife.
SPEAKER_0:  poking each of them to not.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, be tempted to go pack for them.
SPEAKER_0:  And then the second day I went around and started finding the hides that I had because I had some, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  hides.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh...
SPEAKER_0:  And then I went somewhere and locked myself in for...
SPEAKER_0:  Two weeks?
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I had to.
SPEAKER_0:  the withdrawals.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  queers.
SPEAKER_0:  nightmares that I've ever had in my life or...
SPEAKER_0:  to three weeks.
SPEAKER_0:  I went somewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  I want to keep them private, but I went somewhere where...
SPEAKER_0:  They offered a place for me.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh...
SPEAKER_0:  When I ask them about it, it's a community.
SPEAKER_0:  I gave them some money for their school.
SPEAKER_0:  as a donation.
SPEAKER_0:  few thousand dollars.
SPEAKER_0:  I said, yeah, sure, come. You can go through this process here. Cool as fuck people.
SPEAKER_0:  The first thing they did when I got there is they stood me up in front of everybody to thank me for the donation.
SPEAKER_0:  and then told everybody that I was an alcoholic and if anybody saw me drinking, I was to be kicked out of there immediately.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I just felt horrible.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what that was where I started.
SPEAKER_0:  Is that temptation still there?
SPEAKER_0:  There was a moment.
SPEAKER_0:  when it was.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, and...
SPEAKER_0:  uh... some uh...
SPEAKER_0:  therapy circle.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a...
SPEAKER_0:  There's a rodeo clown friend of mine who...
SPEAKER_0:  his bodies.
SPEAKER_0:  the spine is basically fused together you know type of guy
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  We've been friends and enemies.
SPEAKER_0:  and friends again during the art therapy.
SPEAKER_0:  circle sessions.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, so like there's an intimacy there? Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  He didn't know anything about me.
SPEAKER_0:  One time when we were telling our story, he stood up and told his story.
SPEAKER_0:  and then he heard mine and then he was pissed off at me and didn't want to talk to me for a while.
SPEAKER_0:  And then later he told me that it was because he saw what I did with my experience and how much of a difference that is.
SPEAKER_0:  perceived that I was making with it.
SPEAKER_0:  and he felt jealous that he...
SPEAKER_0:  can do the same with his experience because he was just a broken.
SPEAKER_0:  X-Ray Video Cloud.
SPEAKER_0:  He told me.
SPEAKER_0:  when I was going through the process like, okay, you're an internet celebrity person, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  You're known
SPEAKER_0:  Are you worried about people finding out that you're recovering drunk?
SPEAKER_0:  And I said, yeah, it's fucking scary as shit if people find out that I am going through this process. It's scary.
SPEAKER_0:  the critique.
SPEAKER_0:  I already get a lot of shit for being an ex-police officer in Mexico and all the negativity that comes from that.
SPEAKER_0:  And he said, don't be.
SPEAKER_0:  You know that you can't pickpocket a naked man. So just get naked.
SPEAKER_0:  What does that mean?
SPEAKER_0:  Write about it.
SPEAKER_0:  post it online.
SPEAKER_0:  You never know somebody somebody out there might get inspired to do their own.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of process.
SPEAKER_0:  So I started posting about it.
SPEAKER_0:  cowardly in a way because I wanted to make other people keep me on the path, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  but in other ways, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  desperation, you know, I don't want to drink anymore. I don't want to go back to that.
SPEAKER_0:  bath which I know leads directly to a bad death.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not afraid of death. I just want a good one. I don't want a bad one.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that was going to lead me to a bad death.
SPEAKER_0:  as I'm writing about it and sharing it online, you know, through my.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... fever dreams post and...
SPEAKER_0:  just being humorous about it online.
SPEAKER_0:  Getting a lot of hate on one side, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  Having a few people and companies that I work with kind of step back and seeing this guy has some issues too.
SPEAKER_0:  having other people kind of make fun of or make light of that.
SPEAKER_0:  weakness portrayed.
SPEAKER_1:  us getting hate.
SPEAKER_1:  getting criticism.
SPEAKER_1:  because here you are.
SPEAKER_1:  A condo narcotics police officer. There's now as a drinking problem. So is that like supposed to be?
SPEAKER_1:  What, like flaws?
SPEAKER_0:  Revealed weakness.
SPEAKER_0:  or a perception of alpha in the US, I guess that some people have.
SPEAKER_0:  You were supposed to be strong.
SPEAKER_1:  And here you are.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I'm not Jocko Willnick, I'm not David Goggins, you know. I wake up at 10 in the morning sometimes and I'll have cornflakes with my 8-year-old.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  I like days off.
SPEAKER_0:  I used to wake up at 3.30 in the morning every day to review what happened during the night and then go off for a jog and then...
SPEAKER_0:  gym and just be ready to be able to murder somebody with my hands if I had to. But that is, I couldn't maintain that during the whole process of getting out of it. Now
SPEAKER_0:  Beeping alcohol.
SPEAKER_0:  Remember just being honest with it and just seeing the two sides of it, you know
SPEAKER_0:  Joe told me.
SPEAKER_0:  never read the comment section, which is beautiful.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a beautiful piece of advice.
SPEAKER_0:  but...
SPEAKER_0:  They get to you sometimes when you talk about some of these things openly.
SPEAKER_0:  and some of the comments were positive and I've been...
SPEAKER_0:  seeing people comment, sending me messages, and meeting people on the road that are.
SPEAKER_0:  Five months in.
SPEAKER_0:  Ah.
SPEAKER_0:  10 months.
SPEAKER_0:  Some people that have been on that.
SPEAKER_0:  wagon for way longer than I have.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh...
SPEAKER_0:  There's
SPEAKER_0:  It's cool when you meet people that are superhuman or...
SPEAKER_0:  perform.
SPEAKER_0:  And I've...
SPEAKER_0:  take an extreme ownership of things and are just amazing people that are.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, thriving out there.
SPEAKER_0:  inspirational. I see some of these people and I'm like holy shit I need to figure out how to get to some semblance of that.
SPEAKER_0:  But I'm not that.
SPEAKER_0:  I've been through the wringer.
SPEAKER_0:  I fucked up a shit ton of times, you know, my nose is a...
SPEAKER_0:  Example of that.
SPEAKER_0:  few missing teeth.
SPEAKER_0:  But in a way, I think all of that is...
SPEAKER_0:  part of the process that not a lot of people want to talk about.
SPEAKER_0:  independently of the experience I got down there and some of the things that I show and talk about and some of the advocacy I do related to.
SPEAKER_0:  women like her.
SPEAKER_0:  that are trying to look for a better life and trying to find their missing kids.
SPEAKER_0:  training people to not get into those situations.
SPEAKER_0:  but also showcasing the fact that people that go through some of these processes have.
SPEAKER_0:  A journey to go through.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I just came into your studio with a duffel bag.
SPEAKER_0:  straight from the airport and I'm going to leave early tomorrow morning.
SPEAKER_0:  somewhere else.
SPEAKER_0:  I've been on the road for...
SPEAKER_0:  Almost.
SPEAKER_0:  I think five years non-stop.
SPEAKER_0:  I go back to a specific place every week to see my kid for two, three days, and then I'm back out.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, some people are like, are you running? Like, are you worried? Is this afraid about something? Oh
SPEAKER_0:  But I am, you know, on this weird.
SPEAKER_0:  path I guess, trying to look for something that I think of.
SPEAKER_0:  been missing as far as my afterlife of a sort, you know, coming out of that.
SPEAKER_1:  Are you looking for some kind of deep understanding of?
SPEAKER_1:  humanity, like from the specific experiences you had to get some deeper understanding.
SPEAKER_1:  What the hell we're all doing here
SPEAKER_0:  I meet people every weekend.
SPEAKER_0:  with different stories. People come to some of my classes, I show them how to weaponize the environment, how to arm themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  how to not get abducted.
SPEAKER_0:  I meet people that have gone through those experiences and are basically trying to work through some of their own issues by going through the training like that.
SPEAKER_0:  I get to meet people that are, you know, people that I've only seen online, you know, or seen in videos, I remember.
SPEAKER_0:  meeting Royce Gracie in Harbor City.
SPEAKER_0:  I heard of that guy.
SPEAKER_0:  He's a pretty interesting character. I remember seeing him in a bootleg VHS video. I told him about it.
SPEAKER_0:  We're doing a class out at a.
SPEAKER_0:  Emerson knives. It's a knife company, but Mr. Emerson also has like a jujitsu gym there where Roy straightens out of. That's his space.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  They're teaching how to defend against somebody trying to stab you and I'm showing them.
SPEAKER_0:  all the ways you can get around that and fabricate and improvise and smuggle things, basically the adversarial side of that. That's what I'm known for.
SPEAKER_0:  the psychology and kind of the ways that people do that.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember him seeing some of the stuff that I was doing and just being like...
SPEAKER_0:  Where are you from? Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  Makes sense, you know, somebody from Brazil.
SPEAKER_0:  tipping the hat to somebody from Mexico as far as.
SPEAKER_0:  with him seeing the violence and
SPEAKER_0:  some of the art.
SPEAKER_0:  mentality behind it.
SPEAKER_1:  So for people who don't know, hoist Gracie.
SPEAKER_1:  as the legendary martial artists that probably introduced Brazilian Jiu Jitsu to the American audience to the world.
SPEAKER_1:  the process of UFC and showing the effectiveness of it.
SPEAKER_1:  And, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  in practice that a little skinny guy can defeat a big
SPEAKER_1:  Aggressive guy so
SPEAKER_0:  An Anaconda.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a small anaconda walking into that ring.
SPEAKER_0:  with his family behind him. Wearing pajamas. Wearing pajamas and everything. What is this guy wearing pajamas for?
SPEAKER_0:  and then he would strangle people with those pajamas.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember seeing that and just having it.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  probably what a generation before had with Bruce Lee, I guess.
SPEAKER_0:  our my generation was.
SPEAKER_0:  Royce walking into that uh...
SPEAKER_0:  walking into that octagon and changing paradigms.
SPEAKER_0:  seeing him in that gym.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  It's also, I have a gun owner and shooter, which is...
SPEAKER_0:  interesting, you know, having seeing somebody like him who is.
SPEAKER_0:  Well-versed with his hands also be a man that has gone into the realm of being well-versed with weaponry.
SPEAKER_0:  which is an aspect of.
SPEAKER_0:  martial arts and the martial way of thinking that, you know, some people kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  The purist will stick with one side of it, but he's obviously a warrior in a lot of ways.
SPEAKER_1:  So just as a small tangent, so you're somebody that.
SPEAKER_1:  You don't just look at unarmed combat.
SPEAKER_1:  you look at the full spectrum of the chaos of combat that's outside of
SPEAKER_1:  the realm of Jujitsu and even just mixed martial arts.
SPEAKER_1:  unarmed.
SPEAKER_1:  armed with knives and beyond.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, was his mind open to the fuller spectrum of violence?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, he was in the middle of this class that we were doing where people were basically focusing on both.
SPEAKER_0:  Ernest Emerson who's a
SPEAKER_0:  famous for his knives. He has a knife company.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a nice renaissance.
SPEAKER_0:  Not only that, but he's also a very...
SPEAKER_0:  avid martial artist. He trained with a lot of Filipino martial arts related to knives and stuff like that.
SPEAKER_0:  but a different mindset, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  a defensive mindset to train people how to defend against that.
SPEAKER_0:  And you have Royce who's a...
SPEAKER_0:  He's from Brazil.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean he has some street in him.
SPEAKER_0:  That's something that, you know, those guys, they have streets, as we say in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  seeing the ways he stepped in there and provided some encouragement to the people there as far as how people sometimes focus on the...
SPEAKER_0:  this is a system and this is a way but there's other ways out there that might negate or defeat the ways that you are concentrating on you know
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  kinda get out of that bubble. My whole-
SPEAKER_0:  kind of speciality or what I focus on is mindset and.
SPEAKER_0:  figuring out the software that some of these people gain and gather from.
SPEAKER_0:  If I need to arm myself, you know, the easiest thing to manufacture in most places is a pointed object.
SPEAKER_0:  I can take that crystal big pen that you're writing on that notepad with and using the friction from the carpet I can turn it into a hypodermic needle.
SPEAKER_0:  that you can then poke into somebody's neck. What's the process of doing that? I can do it right now if you want.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you use your words for the listener?
SPEAKER_0:  also because I'm terrified. No, basically you can take the friction, the heat and friction created from this carpet. Yes, you can grab that pen.
SPEAKER_0:  In and of itself, it will pierce flesh, but it will slow itself down because it has a few angles on the tip. Oh, you want to wear down the angles. So if you take that tip off and you grab it and grind it on an angle on the carpet, the heat will actually turn it into a hypodermic needle if you know what you're doing.
SPEAKER_1:  hypodermic meaning like it smoothens the entry.
SPEAKER_0:  It'll make a point and an angle that will guide it.
SPEAKER_0:  way into your flash.
SPEAKER_0:  So you can actually go through a torso with that if you know what you're doing.
SPEAKER_1:  As a small tangent, you also gave me a present.
SPEAKER_1:  Could be one of the most epic presents I've ever received. You give it to Rogan.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you explain what I'm holding in my hands?
SPEAKER_0:  There's a guy online.
SPEAKER_0:  Coffin Tramp is a...
SPEAKER_0:  moniker. It is
SPEAKER_0:  A
SPEAKER_0:  G10 rod. G10 is a very strong material basically capable of a lot of people make actually G10 knives which are basically non-magnetic non-ferrous objects that can...
SPEAKER_0:  be utilized as a stabbing.
SPEAKER_0:  The core of it isn't an actual pencil core, it's a G10 core and it's encased in a
SPEAKER_0:  Oak.
SPEAKER_0:  heart oak.
SPEAKER_0:  So that is capable again of stabbing through a torso. Now the guy that made that uh...
SPEAKER_0:  It's an artisan, you know, it makes that, it looks like a pencil. Concealed in the nature of the object itself.
SPEAKER_0:  But that small object is capable of.
SPEAKER_0:  being introduced into...
SPEAKER_0:  A chest cavity.
SPEAKER_0:  Um,
SPEAKER_0:  you know, all it takes is about the.
SPEAKER_0:  half of your thumb or the length of your thumb to stab into your chest cavity and now your
SPEAKER_0:  pericardium is pierced and it's being filled with blood or your whole heart is pierced then you have...
SPEAKER_0:  minutes to live if you're at a standing heart rate.
SPEAKER_1:  for this is uh...
SPEAKER_1:  This has the effectiveness of a knife, essentially.
SPEAKER_0:  It has an effectiveness of a shank or an ice pick. It's not gonna cut, but it's gonna make a hole where it's not the duchin B.
SPEAKER_1:  Here the pen is literally mightier than the sword.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, well, it's...
SPEAKER_0:  this is real
SPEAKER_1:  epic.
SPEAKER_1:  from like a...
SPEAKER_1:  perspective of an academic.
SPEAKER_1:  This is a symbol of both intelligence.
SPEAKER_1:  and violence. ———————....
SPEAKER_0:  it. And also the current state of affairs where people need to arm themselves with things that are concealed as far as their purpose.
SPEAKER_0:  in a place where in a country.
SPEAKER_0:  or in a society.
SPEAKER_0:  that limits their ability to arm themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  So you're going to...
SPEAKER_0:  safe place.
SPEAKER_0:  You're going to a place where no weapons allowed, which means a target rich environment if you're a predator.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  That's a sign of...
SPEAKER_0:  Rebellion.
SPEAKER_1:  Let this be a signal.
SPEAKER_1:  Everyone should be terrified when you're around me. Because even a pencil can murder you.
SPEAKER_0:  I intend to use this. And nobody owns life, but anybody that can hold a frying pan owns death, is a quote that I heard once, which is a beautiful one.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm looking at you. If anyone betrays me, this is the way to go.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you?
SPEAKER_1:  given all you've experienced and all the different ways you think about martial arts and violence.
SPEAKER_1:  in Mexico, in the world, speaking of hoists.
SPEAKER_1:  What is your approach to conflict like a street fight?
SPEAKER_1:  What advice would you give people in the full spectrum of what a street?
SPEAKER_1:  Altercation might entail.
SPEAKER_1:  What is the best way to approach it?
SPEAKER_0:  I think before you get there, you have to prepare. You know, this is one of the first things I tell people is if you don't have a basic TCCC,
SPEAKER_0:  training class behind you. We should.
SPEAKER_0:  reanalyzer.
SPEAKER_0:  your life and your ability to prepare.
SPEAKER_0:  TCCC.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically how to stop somebody from bleeding out or dying from a stab wound, gunshot wound or any of those types of wounds or an amputated leg during an IED scenario. Something you would see in a Boston Marathon type event or a...
SPEAKER_0:  Vegas shooting event.
SPEAKER_0:  where people are getting shot, stabbed, cut.
SPEAKER_1:  So understand how to help people, how to help yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  post.
SPEAKER_0:  You're no good to you. You don't want to be a, you don't want to be a detriment to the situation. You want to be an asset.
SPEAKER_0:  So build yourself up as an asset in a situation like that.
SPEAKER_0:  because you might be doing that on yourself or on somebody else.
SPEAKER_1:  and also it helps you understand.
SPEAKER_1:  What situations are going to result in a lot of?
SPEAKER_1:  in a difficult situation to deal with.
SPEAKER_0:  afterwards. Yeah, it also teaches you what to stab and what to shoot.
SPEAKER_0:  if you're thinking about it in a full and on all the dimensions of it, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there's...
SPEAKER_0:  all knowledge can be weaponized. And I think that's the approach I'll take.
SPEAKER_0:  people should kind of figure out for themselves when they start getting ready or if they want to take the responsibility of their own safety in their hands.
SPEAKER_1:  So in a self-defense situation, there's a lot of questions here, but what does one stab?
SPEAKER_0:  There's the carotid arteries, which are used commonly in jujitsu as something to choke because they feed a computer.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's a lot of...
SPEAKER_1:  blood flowing through that.
SPEAKER_1:  required for the success.
SPEAKER_0:  operations on computer.
SPEAKER_0:  guarding the outside world from your carotid arteries.
SPEAKER_1:  Really weird design, by the way. I like how this design is...
SPEAKER_0:  Not a smart one.
SPEAKER_1:  It doesn't even make sense because with mammals they bite each other's neck like why can't you have more?
SPEAKER_1:  Protection because this is the only like us humans don't use their mouth to kill each other But most mammals most partners do you?
SPEAKER_1:  It's like why the hell don't we-
SPEAKER_0:  protect this. We do have a defensive mechanism and you see it sometimes when people are ambushed and people try to open up each other's necks from behind.
SPEAKER_0:  if you push somebody's neck forward.
SPEAKER_0:  the carotids will actually...
SPEAKER_0:  lower themselves and be encased in more flesh and muscle.
SPEAKER_0:  if you pull ahead back.
SPEAKER_0:  Not so much.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's a way that at least I think the evolutionary we've.
SPEAKER_0:  have a defensive mechanism for that.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a few videos out there of people's
SPEAKER_0:  getting their neck sewn back shut after somebody pushed their head forward to try and slice their necks and they survived.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  This is a viable target. The heart is another one.
SPEAKER_0:  Interesting about the thing about the heart and people get alarmed when I talk about this and show it in classes
SPEAKER_0:  Again, a lot of the classes I do are for orientation and for people to recognize that behavior. So a lot of-
SPEAKER_0:  law enforcement comes to some of these classes.
SPEAKER_0:  That's horrible.
SPEAKER_0:  That's how somebody will kill somebody. Yeah, this is how people that know their thing, their shit will try and approach somebody and stab you to death. This is how they would do it.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... there's a tendency to
SPEAKER_0:  view what we see in John Wick or view what we see in...
SPEAKER_0:  this martial arts community where they're slicing and dicing people.
SPEAKER_0:  different myriad of ways.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of that is based on dueling-based cultures.
SPEAKER_0:  like the Filipino martial arts or some of the Italian martial arts out there.
SPEAKER_0:  somebody's facing off with somebody else with a similar weapon.
SPEAKER_0:  where both of us are agreeing to basically get into a stabbing competition.
SPEAKER_0:  That would make sense in that scenario, in that context, but I've never seen a lot of people actually get into these one-on-one knife altercations.
SPEAKER_0:  what we see now in a modern context when it talks about weaponry.
SPEAKER_0:  is an ambush-counter-ambush based.
SPEAKER_0:  scenario where somebody pulls out a knife during a grappling situation on the street or when somebody turns a striking exchange of punches into pulling out a knife.
SPEAKER_0:  cheap gas station knife or...
SPEAKER_0:  a pen or a pen.
SPEAKER_0:  a rock from the ground or a handgun.
SPEAKER_0:  most modern combatants.
SPEAKER_0:  when it comes to weaponry should be kind of based on the whole aspect of ambush and counter ambush. There's a lot of people showing valuable type of material and coursework on this out there.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  My whole approach and my specific kind of realm is in the aspect of how people go from the process of learning some of these things from experiential stuff. People that grew up in rural places grow up on pig farms.
SPEAKER_0:  that actually get the experiences of processing a pig, for example.
SPEAKER_0:  or processing an animal.
SPEAKER_0:  those people will have more skills as hunters.
SPEAKER_0:  Those people will have more skills with a knife if they pick it up as a weapon then.
SPEAKER_0:  most of the martial artists that I've seen approach some of these classes where I go and have a
SPEAKER_0:  a simulated torso in the form of a pig hanging in a room somewhere.
SPEAKER_1:  Some of that has to do with just the.
SPEAKER_1:  the familiarity and the comfort of just like the biology of a living organism. Like that you, if you cut off certain things, if you cut a certain thing, like it's just a meat vehicle.
SPEAKER_0:  The same thing, the medical training should come first.
SPEAKER_0:  or if you don't have that, be a hunter, or go to a butchery class. That will teach you more about how to use a knife.
SPEAKER_0:  on somebody else than anything, you know, that'll give you the experience of flash.
SPEAKER_0:  Most people, you know, I do this.
SPEAKER_0:  example every now and then where I
SPEAKER_0:  have people bring in.
SPEAKER_0:  a tactical knife and they'll bring in a butter knife. And I asked them which will go through a torso. We have a pig there, so it simulates a torso pretty closely.
SPEAKER_0:  Most people will say, nah, that butter knife is not going to go through.
SPEAKER_0:  And it does, you know, it does go through. It's thin enough, strong enough, sturdy enough that it'll go through.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Kitchen knife.
SPEAKER_0:  cheap one.
SPEAKER_0:  cost 89 cents at a Walmart and an expensive $400 one.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  The cheap one will outperform the expensive one. The tip will snap off during some of it.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I have to say that just as a small.
SPEAKER_1:  tangent I went to farm
SPEAKER_1:  And...
SPEAKER_1:  seeing the butchering of meat and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  in the processing of meat and pigs and cows.
SPEAKER_1:  Whoo, that's uncomfortable.
SPEAKER_1:  but I think it also.
SPEAKER_1:  It's honest and raw and like that's something that probably everyone should experience regularly.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Is it, it's also humbling to remind you. When I.
SPEAKER_1:  I had a dog Homer, he's a Newfoundland.
SPEAKER_1:  I was very close with him.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh
SPEAKER_1:  lost them.
SPEAKER_1:  And I just remember...
SPEAKER_1:  that carry the music.
SPEAKER_1:  200 something pounds.
SPEAKER_1:  I had to carry him, I had to put him to sleep and...
SPEAKER_1:  one of the
SPEAKER_1:  biggest realizations is like...
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, this is just the...
SPEAKER_1:  This is just a biological thing.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just, and to realize that this is just meat.
SPEAKER_1:  This is not, and you can cut it.
SPEAKER_1:  and then if you bleed, all of a sudden the life can disappear from you. It's all gone. It's like, holy shit.
SPEAKER_1:  There's this meat vehicle that some people have referred to as Lex.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm just a few stabbings away from...
SPEAKER_1:  Like leaving. Yeah, from leaving, goodbye. Goodbye, just saw the logistics.
SPEAKER_0:  It used to be that we had to hang around, you know, people would come back from battle and we would hear things next to the campfire.
SPEAKER_0:  far as, oh, he stabbed somebody here and this happens. But now we live in an age where you can, you know, when I do a class, this is a stab to the heart.
SPEAKER_0:  And here's like five videos of it happening live, you know, on live leaks or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  and we can deconstruct that, not only that, but...
SPEAKER_0:  what weapon was used. Oh, it was a gas station folder. It was a-
SPEAKER_0:  pioneer woman knife from Walmart with flowers on the handle.
SPEAKER_0:  Whatever it was.
SPEAKER_0:  and people start realizing that it doesn't take a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  that it doesn't take a lot of training because a lot of these people are not.
SPEAKER_0:  high level.
SPEAKER_0:  Assassin's Train.
SPEAKER_0:  by ninjas in the hills or anything like that. So it's important, low elétrons, a cool, the Subscribe button, to jump right into a live did you belive?
SPEAKER_0:  grew up or learned by seeing that behaviour in others.
SPEAKER_0:  And when they start coming to the realization that it's pretty easy to do that and they start figuring out like, how do you counteract that? Well, number one, learn the behavior yourself so you can recognize it. The whole aspect of being a good listener is to check out combine4u loudspeakers, some amazing
SPEAKER_0:  good counter-ambush team is to be the best ambusher in the planet.
SPEAKER_0:  So again, the whole aspect of Musashi saying, know your enemy know his sword.
SPEAKER_0:  Now you've...
SPEAKER_0:  figure that out as far as learning that behavior.
SPEAKER_0:  when you start seeing how some of these stabbings occur.
SPEAKER_0:  The first thing you notice is that one of the hands is always kind of out of the picture or there's a lack of symmetry in the people that are about to do something horrible.
SPEAKER_0:  So when you see lack of symmetry in the environment, you're thinking about somebody with their hands going backwards.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a crowd of people and two or one individual is looking counter.
SPEAKER_0:  where everybody else is looking.
SPEAKER_0:  or there's a hyper aware individual in the crowd.
SPEAKER_0:  The hyper aware are always usually out there.
SPEAKER_0:  Fuck somebody over.
SPEAKER_0:  or are they're trying to keep?
SPEAKER_0:  those predators from fucking somebody else over.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  unless you step back and you put yourself in the process of learning how they learn.
SPEAKER_0:  and you become.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  potential nightmare person. It's hard to recognize that in a crowd. Feels like.
SPEAKER_1:  One of the...
SPEAKER_1:  significant ways to win or
SPEAKER_1:  as a street fighter is avoided by.
SPEAKER_1:  Sort of sending.
SPEAKER_1:  pacifist signals.
SPEAKER_1:  In every way, meaning avoiding the situation whenever there's like.
SPEAKER_1:  like a hypervigilant.
SPEAKER_1:  people you just kind of
SPEAKER_1:  Avoid signaling the year.
SPEAKER_1:  one of the players of interest. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  If we're talking about counter ambush.
SPEAKER_1:  At which point?
SPEAKER_1:  Do you do that versus shift to the?
SPEAKER_1:  progression.
SPEAKER_0:  I think violence should be always an option, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  Everybody should have that option and you need to be good at that option.
SPEAKER_0:  I think I heard Jordan Peterson talk about the fact that everybody needs to be dangerous, but keep that shit under control.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_1:  I think he was referring to a different context, but...
SPEAKER_0:  I know. I'm referring to the ability of... The little physical conflict as well. There's two cases that I saw of people utilizing social engineering to a beautiful degree to de-escalate shit.
SPEAKER_0:  Right. One guy.
SPEAKER_0:  Somewhere first off if you're in a place where people are grabbing your wife's ass or something like that like what are you doing there? You know there's a load of things that are...
SPEAKER_0:  wrong with everything that you're doing in your life to be in that environment. But let's say you're in an inescapable situation.
SPEAKER_0:  Where was this guy?
SPEAKER_0:  who was in a...
SPEAKER_0:  Compromised position.
SPEAKER_0:  Somebody wanted to fight him
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  legit kick his ass.
SPEAKER_0:  And he said, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's go, but I just, I need to warn you that I have hep C.
SPEAKER_0:  before we go outside.
SPEAKER_0:  And that.
SPEAKER_0:  masterful.
SPEAKER_0:  I was getting my phone out to f-
SPEAKER_0:  filmed this, you know, maybe. And even I was just lowered my phone to give him a slow clap. That was a beautiful move.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And then there was this other man, there was a...
SPEAKER_0:  There was a riot somewhere in Ensenada, the municipality of Ensenada in Baja. They were protesting some of the people that pick those fields down there.
SPEAKER_0:  part of a tribe called Los Tricis.
SPEAKER_0:  very hardy, hardworking people, but...
SPEAKER_0:  nefarious people too. They're pretty good at their thing.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a riot line. They couldn't break.
SPEAKER_0:  And this old man walks in the middle of the riot line and yells, grenade! And throws an avocado in the middle of all the cops.
SPEAKER_0:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'll go.
SPEAKER_0:  that rye line with an avocado.
SPEAKER_0:  your
SPEAKER_1:  That could have gone wrong in so many ways.
SPEAKER_0:  hugs.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know. To me, there's small lessons there.
SPEAKER_0:  there is a case to be made about social engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  about learning about behavior.
SPEAKER_0:  about learning how to lie.
SPEAKER_0:  and how to kind of move your way or navigate your way around situations like that.
SPEAKER_0:  Small things like bartering.
SPEAKER_0:  Knowing how to bribe people in conflict zones is the thing that I show when I talk about or train people to work in hostile environments.
SPEAKER_0:  escalation.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  specifically kind of figuring out what is a value in the environment, what things you shouldn't be doing in an environment that might be considered disrespectful or
SPEAKER_0:  out of place, you know, people have a tendency that didn't grow up in places that are violent to make.
SPEAKER_0:  Continuous eye contact with somebody that might be an issue
SPEAKER_0:  or smiling when there's nothing to smile about. I think, you know, there's a picture I saw somewhere of Russians.
SPEAKER_0:  taking a portrait and there's Americans there and Americans are smiling with the Russians aren't?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Because what are they're just about?
SPEAKER_1:  And of course it's not as simple as smile or not smile this subtlety to it like you said I can't think this is super interesting one because um
SPEAKER_1:  I found in my own life.
SPEAKER_1:  Like not making eye contact is...
SPEAKER_1:  Other people will be joking, but it's a really powerful way to de-escalate.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's such a fascinating thing though, cause you could talk about drunk fights that are just.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... they're harmless
SPEAKER_1:  But I feel like the same dynamic applies to the most violent conflict including wars.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like ego.
SPEAKER_1:  is part of this.
SPEAKER_1:  So to me the question of conflict whether it's a street fight or anything else.
SPEAKER_1:  is the calculus of
SPEAKER_1:  Are you?
SPEAKER_1:  willing to.
SPEAKER_1:  Take an owl.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... in terms of psychology somebody grabs your way sassy mentioned
SPEAKER_1:  Boy, if you let that happen, you go home.
SPEAKER_1:  You're gonna have to pay the price.
SPEAKER_1:  of you were the person who didn't define you, like in your relationship.
SPEAKER_1:  You didn't defend your wife's honor. Why would you do that when your wife is impacted by兩ďegoscarele, just when your life was替 Oracle to take you to the gains?
SPEAKER_1:  You're going to psychologically pay that price yourself?
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Depending on your wife, she might secretly also-
SPEAKER_0:  lose a little bit of respect for you.
SPEAKER_1:  Now...
SPEAKER_1:  How do you play that calculus? Cause now we see the war in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  I would say there is elements of similar posturing in the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  in Europe.
SPEAKER_1:  in Ukraine, Russia, China, leadership.
SPEAKER_0:  at a
SPEAKER_1:  back at a geopolitics.
SPEAKER_1:  It's still somebody grabs somebody's ass.
SPEAKER_1:  and you're not backing me.
SPEAKER_0:  So to take those losses and basically just posture, you know, lower your head and
SPEAKER_0:  live to fight another day type situation.
SPEAKER_0:  The thing with modern violence is, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  the access to weaponry.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I mean, again.
SPEAKER_0:  Nobody owns life but anybody who can hold a frying pan can own death. I've seen people.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, get double leg takedown somebody on the ground. It's a different thing doing in the mats.
SPEAKER_0:  versus concrete.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a good way to kill somebody, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  the most
SPEAKER_0:  The most prolific impact weapon on the planet is...
SPEAKER_0:  the planet itself.
SPEAKER_0:  You can see various videos of people online where they fall and they hit their head or somebody hits their head.
SPEAKER_0:  and they go into.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, the stretched out fit basically.
SPEAKER_0:  And that might not kill you then, but it'll kill you that night.
SPEAKER_0:  or the second night if you don't get checked out. People bleed out internally, get an edema.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, the whole aspect of me showing how some of these things.
SPEAKER_0:  not only some of these methodologies and somehow people prepare for violence and how people
SPEAKER_0:  experience violence, how they make their weapons, how the people fight in the streets and stuff like that.
SPEAKER_0:  it's to recognize that behavior from the inception.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a video I show where there's a bunch of street kids in Rio de Janeiro. I think it's during the Olympics where they're snatching.
SPEAKER_0:  chains and cell phones from people.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's a fun video, you know, see it.
SPEAKER_0:  The first thing you learn about it is how they...
SPEAKER_0:  Target people.
SPEAKER_0:  Now who are they going after? There's a bunch of people there.
SPEAKER_0:  Why are they going after that specific person?
SPEAKER_0:  and you start learning about profiling and how they identify victim mentality, or the perfect victim, lack of awareness.
SPEAKER_0:  they keep on a straight line, avoidance, avoidance of eye contact if they're doing something of areas wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  and how they pick who they're gonna go after, the small people, the women.
SPEAKER_0:  even some of the men.
SPEAKER_0:  and they separate the men that they're perfect victims versus the men that are just gonna turn around and punch them in the face, you know? What are they looking for?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, first off, you notice that the men that are in that environment...
SPEAKER_0:  that look at them and are aware of their presence, the hyper aware, are the ones that are not a good target.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's the first lesson there. So it's probably a good idea not only to be hyper aware.
SPEAKER_0:  but to recognize that hyper wave is another.
SPEAKER_0:  if I want to separate myself from the victim crowd.
SPEAKER_0:  Another thing you notice is these are kids going after some grown adults, and some of these grown adult men are with women.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  you see them kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  getting outside of the grasp of the kids that are trying to rip their chains off their neck or their cell phones.
SPEAKER_0:  and they have no consideration for the women around them.
SPEAKER_0:  You see other men that are with women and you see them grab the women and put them behind them and ba-
SPEAKER_0:  And immediately they'll say, this is the wrong one. Let me move on to the next one.
SPEAKER_0:  So that small little lesson in those videos will show you first how these kids are.
SPEAKER_0:  growing up.
SPEAKER_0:  to profile and target who the perfect victims are. That's a school for them.
SPEAKER_0:  And that is an adversarial school. We should look at that school and-
SPEAKER_0:  apply to ourselves.
SPEAKER_1:  In general, you think conflict...
SPEAKER_1:  Ultimately, the people that are doing conflict are looking forward.
SPEAKER_1:  weakness.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, they're looking for opportunity.
SPEAKER_0:  opportunistic. That's the predators. That's what they do. They look for an opportunity, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  from jumping down from a tree and getting the slowest gazelle to...
SPEAKER_0:  Looking for the opportune moment to pounce on something that's probably big, but the risk is worth it
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like there's several motivations.
SPEAKER_1:  But isn't there also...
SPEAKER_1:  Her
SPEAKER_1:  power hierarchy motivation as well.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you, there's something about the big guy that tempts you to...
SPEAKER_1:  send a message, especially with gangs, aren't they constantly?
SPEAKER_1:  sort of trying to signal
SPEAKER_0:  the third day alpha. Yeah, I mean, there's a different situation. You could be facing a sociopathic predator who is looking for something in you that you're the resource that they're looking after.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe it's a woman.
SPEAKER_0:  It could be a group of people that don't like the fact that you have a specific nationality or your passport is stamped in a specific way or that you prayed to whatever God.
SPEAKER_0:  All these factor in.
SPEAKER_0:  But in the end, they all do the same thing.
SPEAKER_0:  They look for an advantageous position.
SPEAKER_0:  If I were to target you, I would put you in between that wall and me. So you have two avenues of exits.
SPEAKER_0:  and I will step on one of your feet.
SPEAKER_0:  to keep that avenue closed. So you have to go this way. So this is where my knife is going to be.
SPEAKER_0:  you see that behavior mirrored.
SPEAKER_0:  everywhere in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  First off, you look for advantages.
SPEAKER_0:  if it's something that's unavoidable, like you're in between me and my ability to go home.
SPEAKER_0:  Are you in between me and my ability to feed my family?
SPEAKER_0:  or you're in between me and my ability to posture to the people that are behind me, the young guys that I'm in charge.
SPEAKER_0:  I will do everything in my power.
SPEAKER_0:  and you.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  motivations are.
SPEAKER_0:  not my realm.
SPEAKER_0:  the ways they do it are, you know, basically the advantage.
SPEAKER_0:  part of it.
SPEAKER_1:  So desperation is...
SPEAKER_0:  is dangerous.
SPEAKER_0:  a dangerous school. When it's a dangerous school, I mean, the most dangerous people usually come from those.
SPEAKER_0:  desperate environments.
SPEAKER_0:  You can have people in Coronado.
SPEAKER_0:  holding onto logs in the ocean and go through this millions of dollars worth of training and just be professional killers for the government and just be these incredible human beings.
SPEAKER_0:  and then there's a kid that will walk up to one of them when he's off, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  and put an ice pick right into his chest when he's least expecting it.
SPEAKER_0:  And that doesn't mean that one is superior than the other. It just means that there's more than one way to become that.
SPEAKER_0:  Teenagers terrify me.
SPEAKER_1:  It feels like the intensity of desperation.
SPEAKER_1:  like the capacity of a teenager.
SPEAKER_1:  Like 16, 17.
SPEAKER_1:  to be desperate and also not have the
SPEAKER_1:  matured understanding of ethics of the world.
SPEAKER_1:  Like they have this intensity of feeling.
SPEAKER_1:  That I was unlike anything else
SPEAKER_0:  They don't have a volume knob to that. So it's like a garden hose without a nozzle on it, so you can regulate it. They haven't developed that.
SPEAKER_0:  They haven't learned that maybe from somebody else or.
SPEAKER_0:  It used to be warrior cultures. You would be a prentice under somebody or you would learn some of these things from other people. You wouldn't believe it
SPEAKER_0:  Some modern gangs have a little bit of that.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you're not, and you're just this kid that's been playing Call of Duty all of his life, or has been witnessing violence in media, then there's no...
SPEAKER_0:  sense of...
SPEAKER_0:  Probably a bad idea to go off and do this because all of these repercussions. I could see how that could be a-
SPEAKER_0:  danger to society.
SPEAKER_0:  some of the volume knobs, some of the...
SPEAKER_0:  countermeasures the people exploding on somebody else with a
SPEAKER_0:  with a weapon, you know, that you see videos constantly online. I remember seeing this one of these two.
SPEAKER_0:  teenage girls somewhere in the US and one of them just
SPEAKER_0:  There's a.
SPEAKER_0:  Fight.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a hair pulling competition and all of a sudden one of them takes out a knife.
SPEAKER_0:  And it just happens.
SPEAKER_0:  like that.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It's just pure and restrained.
SPEAKER_0:  downward stabbing.
SPEAKER_0:  out.
SPEAKER_0:  You're like, wait.
SPEAKER_0:  Where did that come from?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  She's from an environment where...
SPEAKER_0:  She saw that as an option.
SPEAKER_0:  She didn't see the repercussions of it, and she found herself in a place where she thought that was the only viable option.
SPEAKER_0:  pulling out a weapon.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's the dangerous part of it.
SPEAKER_1:  how do you prepare?
SPEAKER_1:  to win those kinds of situations, to escape those kinds of situations.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you said, this is training.
SPEAKER_1:  It's exposing your mind.
SPEAKER_0:  I always tell people, like, if you don't have a combative bass, you don't have a bass.
SPEAKER_0:  boxing, jiu jitsu.
SPEAKER_1:  And that gives you what, like an awareness of your body?
SPEAKER_0:  It gives you an awareness of your body, it gives you a spatial awareness. If you can't see the points with your peripheral vision.
SPEAKER_0:  if you can't see the points of somebody's feet in your peripheral vision.
SPEAKER_0:  They are in range.
SPEAKER_0:  to stab you in the heart if they wanted to.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's something you learn from boxing that you learn from jujitsu. You learn from a bunch of combat arts where you're-
SPEAKER_0:  you learn about distance and angling people.
SPEAKER_0:  that comes from this experience that you have. Again, a lot of these things were just...
SPEAKER_0:  a horse play when we're growing up in some cultures or.
SPEAKER_0:  rough and tumble with your brothers and shit like that. But some of us are growing up in single kid homes now and we don't get that, we were missing that. And if you don't have it, then you find it in the...
SPEAKER_0:  You find it in a jiu-jitsu gym, you find it in a boxing gym, you find it in a Thai boxing gym, you find it in places where they specialize in...
SPEAKER_0:  focusing on certain aspects of this whole combative whole.
SPEAKER_0:  used to be before UFC.
SPEAKER_0:  Kung Fu man, you know, Kung Fu guy, that's just street lethal shit. You can't use it in the sporting con. He can't show you this because it'll kill you.
SPEAKER_0:  Now we pretty much know that most of that was.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, Flights of Fancy or BS. You know, it pains me too, man. I wanted to learn some of the D-Mock, single punching and killing technique. You know, I remember those books, but that's just not- I'm still on the lookout for that. Maybe somewhere, I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe if you put a pen in your hand, that might turn into that.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the only way, right?
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of these myths are kind of like faded away. Now you see people that have different combative bases.
SPEAKER_0:  combining them all and becoming a fighter now.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a UFC fight, two people fighting each other is one thing.
SPEAKER_0:  you being in the middle of the Portland riots.
SPEAKER_0:  and a bunch of.
SPEAKER_0:  state troopers throwing gas at rioters and then rioters themselves fighting each other.
SPEAKER_0:  and you finding yourself in the middle of that, that's a completely different thing.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you think you're gonna...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, go on the ground and get in a guard with a guy swinging around a piece of a shovel handle, right?
SPEAKER_0:  your guess is going on.
SPEAKER_0:  because you got a...
SPEAKER_0:  stop there and your car was you know
SPEAKER_0:  windows are broken and your family's in the backseat.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, that is a different situation.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  gonna get medical.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  learning about weaponry.
SPEAKER_0:  I personally...
SPEAKER_0:  don't really like.
SPEAKER_0:  fighting on the ground.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's why I forced myself to go to train with different people out there, you know, on the ground. Jiu-Jitsu, catch wrestling. på placing fly
SPEAKER_1:  the bottom.
SPEAKER_1:  Neither, you don't like either.
SPEAKER_0:  I personally, I like being in a car and running everybody over. That would be great, you know, if I could or driving really far away.
SPEAKER_0:  or uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I had this experience and...
SPEAKER_0:  Utah.
SPEAKER_0:  Some friends of mine
SPEAKER_0:  a military...
SPEAKER_0:  some of your best shooters, some of the best shooters in the US, you know, coming from the Marine Corps.
SPEAKER_0:  were showing me how they, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  would shoot something from really far away.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was like...
SPEAKER_0:  You don't even have to be in the same vicinity.
SPEAKER_0:  the scope of violence and how far you can be from it or how close you can be from it.
SPEAKER_1:  Just wait till we get to see what we can do in the cyber attack world.
SPEAKER_1:  who can destroy your whole wellbeing, your whole life, your...
SPEAKER_0:  Identity. That's another aspect.
SPEAKER_1:  of it too.
SPEAKER_1:  And then...
SPEAKER_1:  figure out where you live in terms of ambush.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. Everything about you such that.
SPEAKER_1:  Parting use easy.
SPEAKER_0:  I have a class where we specifically work on social engineering and kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  how you can go about something at a micro level.
SPEAKER_0:  I do a class with a guy named Matt Fiddler who does a
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, he's one of the premier experts on how to get into and
SPEAKER_0:  Bypass locks.
SPEAKER_0:  basically.
SPEAKER_0:  He'll show you how to open up every single bypass, every single commercial lock available in the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, he'll spread it out and-
SPEAKER_0:  and open up everything. And that's it.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  And my part in his class is I talk about how you can.
SPEAKER_0:  some of that off in a public space and not get caught or how you would employ some of these things in a context where it's useful for law enforcement, for the military, stuff like that.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh...
SPEAKER_0:  So we have this exercise in a public space where there's a bunch of padlocks in the environment.
SPEAKER_0:  and we paint them pink.
SPEAKER_0:  So people know it's.
SPEAKER_0:  our bad locks and we're not breaking into anybody else's bad locks if we get approached and asked about it.
SPEAKER_0:  But I asked the students like.
SPEAKER_0:  So you have to gather all these padlocks.
SPEAKER_0:  of this public space, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  So how would you do it? A lot of them are trying to pick them.
SPEAKER_0:  They're very suspiciously picking them and stuff like that, that you get caught.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the whole situation.
SPEAKER_0:  But the smart ones...
SPEAKER_0:  we'll basically develop a social media campaign related to the bad blocks, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  a beautiful example of this. This actually happened here in Texas.
SPEAKER_0:  I did a class out in Dallas.
SPEAKER_0:  We put the padlocks over this public mall.
SPEAKER_0:  And the students basically came up with a breast cancer awareness campaign online that they
SPEAKER_0:  They made Faker.
SPEAKER_0:  They made flyers for it. They did the social media page on a campaign.
SPEAKER_0:  They did this email chain. So when they went there, people were expecting them.
SPEAKER_0:  So they normalized the behavior through social media and they were walking around with bowl cutters in the middle of them all, cutting these things off.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a beautiful solution to a complex problem of that nature.
SPEAKER_0:  the weaponizing part of it. Anything can be, all knowledge can be weaponized.
SPEAKER_0:  If you focus on getting in a street fight with somebody with your fist or a knife, you're missing out on the whole complexity of violence and the way that it's now being utilized.
SPEAKER_0:  So in terms of breaking out.
SPEAKER_1:  locks.
SPEAKER_1:  and in restraints and captivity.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's talk about a dark topic that you're one of the world experts in.
SPEAKER_1:  kidnapping you see these courses on conor kidnapping and terrorism
SPEAKER_1:  I read an estimate that criminal gangs get $500 million a year in ransom payments from kidnapping. Just at a high level, what is kidnapping, who does it, and why?
SPEAKER_1:  What are some?
SPEAKER_1:  Insights that can help.
SPEAKER_0:  us understand what is this problem in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  It happens in different ways in different parts of the world. I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  I just sent off a group of people that trained some of the Ukrainians and some of the stuff that they were showing them with some of the counter.
SPEAKER_0:  custody stuff that I show on the most.
SPEAKER_0:  for the mind name Vince went out there.
SPEAKER_0:  was showing them some of the aspects of how to utilize things like Kevlar cordage and how to infuse it in their uniform. So if they get...
SPEAKER_0:  zip tie to cut them open.
SPEAKER_0:  war setting so it's
SPEAKER_0:  talks about being captive in a war zone.
SPEAKER_0:  but the information or the methodology actually comes from Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  that methodology as far as how I learned it.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of how to escape from it.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So in Mexico you have
SPEAKER_0:  abductions happening where cartels who hold control over a specific place or zone.
SPEAKER_0:  are having a hard time with financial situations as far as maybe they're not making enough money to pay everybody off so they let them freelance basically.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of ways some of these criminal groups freelance or some of these groups actually professionalize in.
SPEAKER_0:  to abduct businessmen, abduct the sons of businessmen or people that have money to...
SPEAKER_0:  Ask for ransoms for them.
SPEAKER_0:  basically.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  They've taken.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, captivity and abduction to like an art form in places like Mexico. And it has a history all over the world, but specifically my experience with it, with it was going to.
SPEAKER_0:  Cartel safe houses is it
SPEAKER_0:  turn into holding places. You would see homemade prison cells and stuff like that, and people being held in captivity for months, if not years.
SPEAKER_0:  as they were milking their family for everything they own.
SPEAKER_1:  So it turns out into a business, they're not actually even interested in hurting the people.
SPEAKER_1:  physically, they're interested in hurting them.
SPEAKER_1:  financially.
SPEAKER_0:  financially and also this if they get hurt they're hurt for a purpose which is to make their family pay up faster or more
SPEAKER_0:  Some of the abduction groups that I've seen out there, professional ones in Mexico, basically make it a living to target people that have abduction insurance or that work for companies that have good abduction insurance.
SPEAKER_0:  It's almost like an ATM for them, you know? It's like, ah, here we go again, huh?
SPEAKER_0:  So there's some of that going on.
SPEAKER_0:  Some not so much.
SPEAKER_0:  Some abductions are express
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I'll grab you with a gunpoint, take you to an ATM.
SPEAKER_0:  You empty it out and then you're on your way. That's an express kidnapping. That might not be worth you doing any.
SPEAKER_0:  thing insane, you know, just go with emotions.
SPEAKER_0:  But some people do get picked up.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Uh-huh.
SPEAKER_0:  I have trained people with prior experiences of abductions in Mexico and here in the United States, people that have spent some time in captivity with loved ones here, like ex-boyfriends or boyfriends that tie them up and beat the shit out of them.
SPEAKER_0:  And the restraints that you utilize are zip ties and handcuffs sometimes, or duct tape, or their own clothing, things of this nature.
SPEAKER_0:  basically what somebody's looking for when they...
SPEAKER_0:  tie anybody up is to convince you that they are in control.
SPEAKER_0:  that they are God and that any hope of you releasing those restraints or getting out of that situation is hopeless.
SPEAKER_0:  from a cartel group picking you up in the middle of a...
SPEAKER_0:  dirt road somewhere and...
SPEAKER_0:  Cancun too.
SPEAKER_0:  Ex-boyfriend showing up at your house and tying you up till you agree to get back with him
SPEAKER_0:  It's the same thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  and some of the restraints that are being utilized come from different places. I mean, I remember...
SPEAKER_0:  An instructor I had way back when told me.
SPEAKER_0:  that the proliferation of zip ties as a restraint in criminal abductions came up after the movie heat came out.
SPEAKER_0:  because everybody wanted to be Robert De Niro zip-tying people in the bank robbery at the end of the movie.
SPEAKER_0:  Criminals saw that and...
SPEAKER_0:  it became a good thing.
SPEAKER_1:  AS
SPEAKER_1:  Is it possible to systematically learn how to escape restraints like handcuffs, rope, zip ties?
SPEAKER_0:  The best at it are not the military. They're not seer program people. They are criminals. I learned how to get out handcuffs from a 15 year old who was in charge of meth sales.
SPEAKER_0:  in La Avenida Revolucion in Tijuana. Is there a system to it?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's not specifically a system. It's usually what happens is they'll buy a set of handcuffs and they will mess around with them in a playing feature.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  One thing I do in a class is first off, I'm honest about the fact that some, all the restraints are temporary.
SPEAKER_0:  even marriage.
SPEAKER_1:  This is like, wait, can we just pause on the deep philosophical?
SPEAKER_1:  You're like the immortal Musashi with that statements all.
SPEAKER_0:  All restraints are temporary, even marriage. I'll just, I just like adding that one in there for last because this is a dark subject.
SPEAKER_1:  Every cage can-
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  All restraints are temporary. You either free yourself from the restraints.
SPEAKER_0:  somebody else takes them off or you're dying, your body rots away around.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, those are the options.
SPEAKER_0:  And I like that first option myself.
SPEAKER_0:  The second option is pretty cool if you can convince somebody to do that for you.
SPEAKER_0:  But that first option is an interesting one.
SPEAKER_0:  you have to deconstruct restraints. Not all restraints are made the same. You can train to get out of handcuffs here in the US and focus on a pair of Smith & Wesson handcuffs, which are kind of the most common brand of handcuffs here.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you find yourself in detention somewhere in Russia, the handcuffs out there are completely different. You know, the key way is different, the mechanism is different, but some of the same.
SPEAKER_0:  ways of bypassing those mechanisms are.
SPEAKER_1:  So in Russia, what kind are they using in Russia?
SPEAKER_1:  I'm gonna travel in there, I need this information.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll send you a specific model and details on how to get out of those. But basically... Just asking for a friend. I'm sorry.
SPEAKER_0:  So what I do is I take.
SPEAKER_0:  I take a pair of Smith and Wesson handcuffs, I put them in the middle of three people in a class, I spread them out.
SPEAKER_0:  and I have them place them on each other in a just playing manner. I have Hank, I have Hank of Keith there and I have a pair of bowl cutters there in case somebody gets stuck, does something stupid.
SPEAKER_0:  So they play with each other as far as putting them on randomly. I show them how to put them on appropriately.
SPEAKER_0:  and then I show them a handcuff key.
SPEAKER_0:  and a handcuff key will open up handcuffs.
SPEAKER_0:  Interestingly enough.
SPEAKER_0:  But the thing about a handcuff key is it's not made to be used by the person that is in those handcuffs.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's the first lesson there.
SPEAKER_0:  If you have a handcuff key, handcuff keys are the most used tool to open up handcuffs in custody situations.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, both.
SPEAKER_0:  criminals escaped from the police to...
SPEAKER_0:  people escaping from criminals.
SPEAKER_0:  Just the standard.
SPEAKER_0:  hidden handcuff key.
SPEAKER_0:  So I show them how to modify the handcuff key so it's more optimal to use on yourself with just basic garbage that you can find. Piece of wire.
SPEAKER_0:  a zip tie piece, basically how to.
SPEAKER_0:  put a leverage arm on the handcuff key.
SPEAKER_0:  So you can actually spin it in the keyway behind your back or in front of you.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm trying to think, I don't think I've ever been in handcuffs.
SPEAKER_0:  Appropriate way to handcuff somebody is palms out.
SPEAKER_0:  How much?
SPEAKER_1:  The restriction is
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of there's a lot if it's a hinge handcuff there's a lot of restriction with no change. Can you reach back? You could try and reach back or you can basically put yourself in a not compromised position and
SPEAKER_0:  feed the most of your palm meat into the handcuff way. So when they shedded on you.
SPEAKER_0:  you have more space to work with.
SPEAKER_0:  so you can spin your hand. we call it a passive resistance.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  Again, you go through a process with them where you deconstruct how people are.
SPEAKER_0:  handcuffed.
SPEAKER_0:  handcuff keys and how to modify handcuff key to be able to use on yourself and these all of these things they're Constructing as we go.
SPEAKER_0:  So they basically, hey, what's a grinding surface? Well, there's concrete outside. So they grind an angle on the key so you can get.
SPEAKER_0:  a key not to go straight into the keyway, but you can get it.
SPEAKER_0:  into the key we had an angle for example.
SPEAKER_0:  something.
SPEAKER_0:  It's something that is out there as far as a method.
SPEAKER_0:  You can't spin a key behind your back because it's small. It's designed to be used by somebody else opening those handcuffs on you. So you put an arm on it so you can leverage our arms so you can spin it behind your back.
SPEAKER_0:  you learn how to...
SPEAKER_0:  Put yourself in not a compromised position. If somebody asks you for your hands that they could be cuffed, you don't do this.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you do that or you put yourself in a cable grip.
SPEAKER_0:  behind your back, which is a pretty strong grip and it's hard to spread those hands apart. That's the thing that people go into.
SPEAKER_0:  automatically when they're in fear.
SPEAKER_0:  So all these things are advantageous for you.
SPEAKER_0:  and you learn.
SPEAKER_0:  and not only people get restrained.
SPEAKER_0:  but you see videos of them because I show a bunch of abduction that's actually happening live.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, the best thing is avoidance, but specifically when you work around restraints is...
SPEAKER_0:  Number one, learn how some of these restraints work.
SPEAKER_0:  Number two is learning how some of the ready-made tools to get out of the restraints look like.
SPEAKER_0:  function.
SPEAKER_0:  And number three, which is the advanced level, is learn how to construct all these things yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  which is I think that is the.
SPEAKER_0:  That is the best.
SPEAKER_0:  thing you can show somebody.
SPEAKER_0:  handcuffs I just use a standard pair of handcuffs and then we deconstruct other very specialized handcuffs that might be out there.
SPEAKER_0:  and you show them if you're gonna travel somewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  Learn what restraints are commonly available in the environment.
SPEAKER_0:  Somebody going to North Sub-Saharan Africa.
SPEAKER_0:  carrying a plastic handcuff key.
SPEAKER_0:  is
SPEAKER_0:  that's going to be useless out there because there's not going to be standard handcuffs out there that would be...
SPEAKER_0:  open with that type of key. Out there you're probably going to be tied up with a chain and a padlock of some sort, maybe a 40 millimeter Chinese padlock with a plastic core that you can open with.
SPEAKER_0:  a lighter if you can burn the core, melt the core open or...
SPEAKER_0:  If you can leverage that open, that's a pretty easy thing to open. Or a bobby pin you can reach all the way in the back and open the latch.
SPEAKER_0:  What about a rope?
SPEAKER_0:  Uhhh...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it is common. This is one of my favorite things for rope.
SPEAKER_0:  Something I-
SPEAKER_0:  usually carry and...
SPEAKER_0:  some places.
SPEAKER_0:  another gift for you if you want.
SPEAKER_0:  the ceramic razor blade.
SPEAKER_0:  Is it capable of cutting?
SPEAKER_0:  Nice.
SPEAKER_0:  Alright, small.
SPEAKER_0:  You can put it behind a label. I've seen some students put the Levi's label on there and just...
SPEAKER_0:  So we pack on.
SPEAKER_0:  Um,
SPEAKER_0:  It is non-magnetic, non-ferrous, so in and out of...
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  that type of situation. You can get in and it's something you can have with you.
SPEAKER_0:  everywhere.
SPEAKER_0:  This is a pretty fancy one, or you can just grab a simple razor blade. Actually learning how to use or leverage a razor blade.
SPEAKER_0:  between your palms.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  know how to go up and down with it to be able to cut yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's just practice to do that well.
SPEAKER_0:  It's practice and it's also exposure to just this is a possibility. This is how you could hide it. Again, the whole smuggling aspect comes from a criminal.
SPEAKER_0:  a criminal mindset type setting.
SPEAKER_0:  So how things are hidden, where they're hidden.
SPEAKER_0:  And when I talk about concealing objects of this nature, it usually comes from...
SPEAKER_0:  smuggling.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, the fact that I have something in a notebook comes from heroin smuggling.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're not looking at the school of criminality, you're missing out on a big...
SPEAKER_0:  part of the uh...
SPEAKER_0:  equation.
SPEAKER_1:  So for people who want to learn.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, this D. Do you teach courses on this? Do you know what's the right? What's the rec?
SPEAKER_1:  How do you get in touch with you or learn from you? Do you have stuff online or is it all online?
SPEAKER_0:  So I have some stuff on my patreon specifically I have a patreon where I share a lot of the
SPEAKER_0:  Online material, basically a bunch of, this is my notebook, I have a bunch of stuff that I just met somebody in Philadelphia that showed me a pretty unique way of...
SPEAKER_0:  utilizing a box cutter as a weapon. So I wrote some of that down.
SPEAKER_0:  I filmed some of it.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's not for any other reason. I'm not trying to create dangerous people out there. It's like, hey, look at this. This is something that's out there.
SPEAKER_0:  So a lot of that information, some of those notes and stuff like that, I keep on my Patreon.
SPEAKER_0:  I used to share it openly on Facebook and Instagram, but that...
SPEAKER_0:  That has not, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  been.
SPEAKER_0:  possible anymore.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I'm a member of your Patreon and I recommend people sign up. It's really great because you also have philosophy.
SPEAKER_1:  You're the...
SPEAKER_1:  You're the, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  the Mexican Miyamoto Musashi.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not just these skills, it's also the philosophy around it.
SPEAKER_0:  Like I got that book of five rings before I went into training. Like I took that with me through training.
SPEAKER_0:  the whole aspect of, you know, go to places frightening to the common brand of men, you know, be put in jail and extricate yourself with your own wisdom.
SPEAKER_0:  I think he was speaking about experiencing experience, you know, the whole warrior's journey, the hero's journey of going out there and actually risking.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's a pretty...
SPEAKER_0:  big basis and aspect of what the work I do and showing some of these things.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a tendency to people say, hey, I'm afraid to go to Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  What do I need to know? Like, well, if you're afraid to go to Mexico, go to Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I was in Detroit. I was pretty afraid when I was in Detroit, in some parts of Detroit and the South Side of Chicago.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, but, uh,
SPEAKER_0:  I don't want to be dictated.
SPEAKER_0:  where I can go and where I can't go because of safety. I want to take responsibility for that myself and figure out ways of being more capable and an asset to the people around me and myself.
SPEAKER_0:  And that comes through experience.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  and people don't want to risk getting a shoulder injury, rolling a jujitsu, or don't want to risk getting a bloody nose in boxing, but that is the way.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, there's some aspects.
SPEAKER_1:  to fitting in.
SPEAKER_1:  You quote.
SPEAKER_1:  Katori Hanzo on imitation.
SPEAKER_1:  The most important thing you should keep in mind when you go on a shinobi mission is to imitate well the language of the target province.
SPEAKER_1:  and the ways of the local people.
SPEAKER_1:  This includes their appearances.
SPEAKER_1:  the way of wearing clothes.
SPEAKER_1:  The way of shaving their head.
SPEAKER_1:  way of making up their hair.
SPEAKER_1:  the way of making up a sword or short sword, and the way of refinement and luxury.
SPEAKER_1:  So how do you fit into some of those?
SPEAKER_1:  places.
SPEAKER_1:  You know Mexico, but a person like me that doesn't know anything about Mexico and Sam interviewing somebody in a leadership position in a drug cartel.
SPEAKER_1:  How quickly do you?
SPEAKER_0:  learn how to fit in.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's not about fitting in, it's about coming up with a narrative for yourself. What that book is talking about, that's a quote from the book called A Shoninki.
SPEAKER_0:  which is like a...
SPEAKER_0:  an actual legit ninja manual from the 1500s or something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  and they're not talking about blending in.
SPEAKER_0:  They're talking about creating a narrative or a lie through your appearance and your behavior and your knowledge base. That's what they're talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say first.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're going to go to a place like that, first off, learn what is common there.
SPEAKER_0:  What type of common restraints might be placed on you? What criminal groups work out there? What type of guns they have?
SPEAKER_0:  not only what type of guns they have, but go to the gun range in Vegas and learn how to fire some of these firearms yourself so you know how to load them in case you run into a bad situation.
SPEAKER_0:  how they tie the sword, how they wear their sword swords.
SPEAKER_0:  could equate to how, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  if you run into some issues. Also, it will give you a good idea how many rounds those hold so you can run at the right moment. I like how you f-
SPEAKER_1:  focusing on the tools of violence. But there's also the social engineering de-escalation, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So if you are in an environment like that and you are carrying around a camera
SPEAKER_0:  that might be an issue.
SPEAKER_0:  Or the opposite and not be an issue. Well, if you're asked like.
SPEAKER_0:  Who are you with? Am I with a news organization or am I with a Christian aid group here?
SPEAKER_0:  And if you are with a Christian aid group, it's probably a good idea to learn some of the Bible.
SPEAKER_0:  if you want a quick way of having a.
SPEAKER_0:  somebody out there try and stop talking to you. You're gonna start talking about Jesus in the middle of a little cartel territory when they approach you and take out the Bible. That'll quickly deescalate...
SPEAKER_1:  prefer to do is I find somebody from the New York Times and the Wall Street Journal and beat them up in front of the...
SPEAKER_1:  just to send a signal to journalists and I too don't.
SPEAKER_0:  like journalists. That could be a way, but...
SPEAKER_0:  to send a message. I think a lot of us miss the fact that we are capable of taking control of our own narrative and what we communicate to people around us.
SPEAKER_0:  I can show up here drinking a Monster Energy drink.
SPEAKER_0:  dumping it on the ground, scratching you know what, then just sit down and just be a rude motherfucker. That's not who I am, but I can do that.
SPEAKER_0:  and you will believe me if I am good at it.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of us miss the, some of us don't know this aspect because it's something we consider predatory or something that is wrong or negative or bad.
SPEAKER_0:  And some of these aspects are actually, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  They're pretty useful.
SPEAKER_0:  I learned most of my tradecraft and skill craft from panhandlers and
SPEAKER_0:  street performers.
SPEAKER_0:  when I had.
SPEAKER_0:  some training related to social engineering. Those were the people that I learned from.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember.
SPEAKER_0:  we were doing surveillance and there was a guy there that showed us how to do surveillance, you know, on the street.
SPEAKER_0:  And he said.
SPEAKER_0:  if you can find a way for somebody to smell you before they see you.
SPEAKER_0:  you'll become invisible.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was like, that's bullshit.
SPEAKER_0:  If you can find a way of somebody smelling you before they see you become invisible, I didn't understand what that meant.
SPEAKER_0:  So we went on a three day bender, didn't take a shower, smelled like shit.
SPEAKER_0:  No deodorant.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you smell like a homeless person, you look like a homeless person.
SPEAKER_0:  and you approach somebody asking for the time and they smell you before they see you.
SPEAKER_0:  and you are not there. You're not a human. You don't exist.
SPEAKER_0:  So that was a pretty valuable lesson that I got there. Yeah, this is a good one.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's interesting, but like...
SPEAKER_1:  I have this belief.
SPEAKER_1:  It has to do with the way I operate in this world, I suppose.
SPEAKER_1:  If you come off as a person legitimately, I guess you could fake it, but I think it's...
SPEAKER_1:  It just feels like...
SPEAKER_1:  you can be extremely good.
SPEAKER_1:  possibly the best in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  if you practice it your whole life at being you.
SPEAKER_1:  You being authentic, being.
SPEAKER_1:  It's showing like you have nothing to hide.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_0:  a true believer.
SPEAKER_0:  is what I true.
SPEAKER_1:  So like yes, you can come up with a fake narrative, but then
SPEAKER_1:  What I mean is like live that narrative your whole life then.
SPEAKER_1:  We'll be...
SPEAKER_0:  like, I understand.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I understand. And then never falter from that.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you are this person. That's what I'm trying to have nothing.
SPEAKER_0:  to hide. I consider that a true believer and yeah that is a unique person when you meet them and they are out there. There are people that will fucking walk into places.
SPEAKER_0:  This is why I am I don't give a fuck
SPEAKER_0:  This is who I am. If you don't trust me, well, shoot me. Fuck it.
SPEAKER_0:  This is my honesty and if you don't trust me, well look at all these people that I've interacted with in the past and you can ask them about it or you can see my effects on other people.
SPEAKER_0:  That's going to be my presentation card. That's the way you said it.
SPEAKER_1:  it now is using words in its blunt.
SPEAKER_1:  Usually if somebody's blunt like that.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I'm a no bullshit person that means they're not.
SPEAKER_1:  That means there are fellowships.
SPEAKER_0:  actually. But you do that through, I mean I'm saying I'm verbalizing your behavior, you know, just walking somewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's say you're going to interview.
SPEAKER_0:  somebody very dangerous down there.
SPEAKER_0:  and you walk into a room without worry.
SPEAKER_0:  That is.
SPEAKER_0:  That is a presentation to you. I know that's a pretty interesting introduction.
SPEAKER_0:  You're not a threat because...
SPEAKER_0:  You don't consider yourself a threat and you're walking in there with the confidence that you don't consider yourself a threat.
SPEAKER_0:  which is an interesting way of going about it.
SPEAKER_0:  my life experiences has been different.
SPEAKER_0:  I was in program that way from an early age and it's hard for me to go into that line.
SPEAKER_0:  Although more and more as I get older and as I learn more about the world and I've failed a few more times, I can understand or more cognizant of the fact that...
SPEAKER_0:  You don't really have to try that much if you believe.
SPEAKER_0:  in yourself and who you are. If you know yourself, I think that is...
SPEAKER_0:  at the core of it. If you know yourself enough.
SPEAKER_0:  to be able to kind of communicate that to people around you.
SPEAKER_1:  and you're not hiding from yourself or from the world your flaws.
SPEAKER_1:  That was the other thing you spoke to.
SPEAKER_1:  that is probably inspiring to others is.
SPEAKER_1:  being honest about your flaws, about your weaknesses as a human being.
SPEAKER_0:  You can't pick pocket or naked man. Yeah, that's right. That's really brilliant. If you can.
SPEAKER_0:  if you know how to be naked. And again, I'm not there. I think I'm working towards that.
SPEAKER_0:  Just bye.
SPEAKER_0:  Hopefully going through shit and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  showing people not telling them.
SPEAKER_0:  is a show me don't tell me is another.
SPEAKER_0:  valuable lesson that I got long ago.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I travel across the country and I not only get to show people what I know how to do, but I give examples of it through things that I do out there.
SPEAKER_0:  I say this a lot, you know, when I travel out there, I'm never alone. You know, there's couches out there waiting for me. You know, there's homes that I can go and stay at.
SPEAKER_0:  friends that I have out there that I have never even met.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's been about me not only wearing some of those mistakes and past failures on my sleeve, but also turning them into lessons for people.
SPEAKER_0:  and...
SPEAKER_0:  just telling people the fact that I know how to do all this.
SPEAKER_0:  weird stuff, you know, and I show people how to do it. weird stuff, you know, and I show people how to do it.
SPEAKER_0:  But here's a bunch of weird memes that are very humorous about my culture and about
SPEAKER_0:  being it through going through therapy and.
SPEAKER_0:  This is me doing something goofy and this is me being an idiot in front of all you guys as well. You know, this is me being the fool. I think that is another aspect of it.
SPEAKER_1:  I love that as part of that journey you made enemies with the rodeo clown and made up with them afterwards.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, we're still, let's hope.
SPEAKER_0:  We're in a very toxic relationship. You know, he knows who he is. He's probably out there listening. He's a lovin'
SPEAKER_1:  hate.
SPEAKER_0:  We, we, we, we stopped talking to each other for months and then, you know, just send up.
SPEAKER_0:  message of some sort and just you know we're back at it.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, back, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Love expressed through anger. I love it. Therapeutic.
SPEAKER_1:  You have both very interesting career paths. If we can just.
SPEAKER_1:  jump back to a really interesting topic that
SPEAKER_1:  I wanted to mention.
SPEAKER_1:  on narco-ecultism.
SPEAKER_1:  What are narco cults?
SPEAKER_1:  What's the relationship between you kind of mentioned religion a little bit. Yeah. What's the relationship between.
SPEAKER_1:  religious culture.
SPEAKER_0:  drug culture. First off, Mexico is one of the most Catholic countries on the planet.
SPEAKER_0:  if not the most Catholic country on the planet.
SPEAKER_0:  Not only that, it is a country that has.
SPEAKER_0:  a root in spirituality.
SPEAKER_0:  through its ethnic culture.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  other parts of the world got most of that taken away and or suppressed or killed or...
SPEAKER_0:  taken away.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  when the Spanish came to Mexico, they were...
SPEAKER_0:  a product of a...
SPEAKER_0:  recently.
SPEAKER_0:  liberated.
SPEAKER_0:  group of people. They just got done being invaded by the Moors, basically.
SPEAKER_0:  and they brought with them the image of La Virgen de Guadalupe.
SPEAKER_0:  the version of Guadalupe.
SPEAKER_0:  Anon Cortez's vision of that or version of that was a lady holding a crystal scepter.
SPEAKER_0:  Baby Jesus.
SPEAKER_0:  and standing on a crescent moon.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what he brought with him.
SPEAKER_0:  to the Americas.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh...
SPEAKER_0:  when the conquest happened.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of people say that Spanish came and conquests the Aztec Empire.
SPEAKER_0:  The enemies of the Aztec allied themselves with the Spanish and they took them down.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what happened. And then the rest was.
SPEAKER_0:  famine and sickness.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what killed most of them.
SPEAKER_0:  they realized that it was gonna be hard to suppress some of the spiritual practices in Mexico. So they decided to...
SPEAKER_0:  mill them with Catholic iconography.
SPEAKER_0:  So you see this cult to...
SPEAKER_0:  one I'd seen which is like a
SPEAKER_0:  fertility variant of...
SPEAKER_0:  a mother goddess in the athletic culture.
SPEAKER_0:  and they turn her into La Virgen de Guadalupe, which is the icon that a lot of Mexicans venerate as the-
SPEAKER_0:  La Virgen the Virgin.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  but in her she conceals.
SPEAKER_0:  cultural elements from the past.
SPEAKER_0:  She has a black sash across her stomach, which means she's pregnant. Common in the Aztec culture and the Mejica culture.
SPEAKER_0:  She's standing on a chair that has eagle wings.
SPEAKER_0:  that is a war god.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the symbol of the war god down there.
SPEAKER_0:  She has stars on her, which is a...
SPEAKER_0:  There's a veil of certain stars that are related to some of the spiritual practices from before.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, they hid these things in that setting. That's how you skip forward.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, hundreds of years.
SPEAKER_0:  and you start seeing things like...
SPEAKER_0:  Malverde
SPEAKER_0:  who was a bandit that lived in Zinaloa way back in the day.
SPEAKER_0:  he would rob rich farmers that would go through the...
SPEAKER_0:  the countryside.
SPEAKER_0:  One time he was almost caught and he was shot and injured.
SPEAKER_0:  and he was wanted by the government. So he told one of his friends to
SPEAKER_0:  tell them where he was and to give them money.
SPEAKER_0:  the reward money to the townspeople.
SPEAKER_0:  So we did that.
SPEAKER_0:  He was hung from a tree and the order was not to bury him, just to let his body rot.
SPEAKER_0:  His body rotted away until it fell onto the ground bones.
SPEAKER_0:  and each of the townspeople would go over and put a rock on top of his.
SPEAKER_0:  until it became a pile of rocks.
SPEAKER_0:  And then he started granting miracles.
SPEAKER_0:  So again, this whole aspect of these criminals become insates.
SPEAKER_0:  and also the middle finger from the...
SPEAKER_0:  downward local populace to the.
SPEAKER_0:  the church in a way because he's not a recognized saint, but he has an altar and people venerate the church in a way because he's not a recognized saint, but he has an altar and people venerate
SPEAKER_0:  then you have...
SPEAKER_0:  cartels that have a spiritual practice or spirituality behind what they do, which is part of their culture, but is also like a tool.
SPEAKER_0:  They used to.
SPEAKER_0:  ingratiate themselves with the local population or the population around them. icons of power and sometimes of
SPEAKER_0:  I'm almost a symbol of rebellion.
SPEAKER_0:  You see El Chapo's son, when he was arrested, had a Santo Niño de Tocha on his chest.
SPEAKER_0:  which is a.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a holy kid of a daughter.
SPEAKER_0:  Spanish legend.
SPEAKER_0:  During the Morris conquest, they said that a statue of that saint would go around and feed some of the hungry. That was the legend.
SPEAKER_0:  and he's a saint of the persecuted. So.
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that when he was arrested, you see him wearing that and then he was liberated is a-
SPEAKER_0:  miracle in and of itself.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's proof.
SPEAKER_0:  that that works.
SPEAKER_0:  you see that was, you can find one of those scapularios anywhere in Mexico that was the most
SPEAKER_0:  At least the sold one.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So you see them utilizing some of these aspects in their own.
SPEAKER_0:  belief system as similar as iconography for some of the things they do.
SPEAKER_0:  then you go into some of the other aspects of it that are out there like Santa Muerte.
SPEAKER_0:  which is actually a faith that I grew up in.
SPEAKER_0:  Mexico has a weird relationship to death.
SPEAKER_0:  We have parties at the cemetery on Day of the Dead, and I just went through one recently. This is November the 2nd.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So we celebrate our dead.
SPEAKER_0:  and we celebrate death in a way that I don't think a lot of cultures out there do.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's a joyful occasion. It is a celebration, yeah. My eight year old.
SPEAKER_0:  put two beers on an altar, one for my mom, one for my brother.
SPEAKER_0:  She bought a Snickers bar for my mom and a bag of pops for my...
SPEAKER_0:  brother.
SPEAKER_0:  flower petals and marigolds and pictures of them on an altar. This is amazing. What kind of beer?
SPEAKER_0:  Tecate. Tecate Roja for my mother because she was hardcore and Tecate Light for my brother. You know, he was more of an endurance drinker.
SPEAKER_0:  Um,
SPEAKER_0:  And it's also for me.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, the relationship to death down there is different
SPEAKER_0:  So there's an icon in Mexico. It's actually one of the
SPEAKER_0:  fastest rolling.
SPEAKER_0:  alternative spiritual practices in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  And not only in Mexico, but here in the US, I've been to Santa Marta temples across the country.
SPEAKER_0:  I found one in Connecticut out of all places.
SPEAKER_0:  how I grew up with it or I saw it is...
SPEAKER_0:  My family was on Guadalupe Anas.
SPEAKER_0:  We were Catholic and we venerated the Virgin of Guadalupe specifically.
SPEAKER_0:  the icon of the region of Guadalupe.
SPEAKER_0:  But every now and then there are winks and nods to a skeletal saint in family practices.
SPEAKER_0:  even when I went to work.
SPEAKER_0:  The older guys that I was working with would tell me like, okay, we gotta go ask a...
SPEAKER_0:  Ask for protection.
SPEAKER_0:  So they would drive me over to the church and I thought I was going to the cathedral and then we made our
SPEAKER_0:  left turn and it wasn't the cathedral, it was the
SPEAKER_0:  market next to the Cathedral in Tijuana.
SPEAKER_0:  and.
SPEAKER_0:  In the little corner, there was a big...
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  Santa Marta Reaper refugee.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  And then I knew why I had to bring a bottle of tequila. It's like, why am I bringing a bottle of tequila to the church?
SPEAKER_0:  It was for her.
SPEAKER_0:  Death, la muerte.
SPEAKER_0:  It was partly hazing.
SPEAKER_0:  And also...
SPEAKER_0:  they did believe that they were basically imbued with.
SPEAKER_0:  the being agents of death in a way.
SPEAKER_0:  So it was like a cultural thing as well, something that they wore on them as.
SPEAKER_0:  not only protection but also like a samurai would wear.
SPEAKER_0:  this death iconography on them or how...
SPEAKER_0:  the Maori would do haka dances.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, to some of these guys and their kind of warrior culture that they were growing up with or trying to view on us the young guys.
SPEAKER_0:  They would take us there and they would envieu us with iconography of Santa Marta to be like a psychological thing.
SPEAKER_1:  So that gives you strength and meaning in the face of struggle.
SPEAKER_1:  Like in the face of difficulties in life?
SPEAKER_0:  I think closeness to death and having a relationship to death in the form of a symbolic representation of it like something where there were an icon like that.
SPEAKER_0:  makes it not as scary, I guess. Or not only that, but it's also something that the other side.
SPEAKER_0:  the enemy.
SPEAKER_0:  the cartels groups, they would venerate it as well.
SPEAKER_0:  So when they would see it on you, it was almost debilitating.
SPEAKER_0:  them. They were like, oh, are you guys cops? Are you guys? Why are you wearing that?
SPEAKER_0:  So there was an aspect of that to it.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm a mental moody.
SPEAKER_0:  Morty type thing where you remember death, you know type thing
SPEAKER_1:  There's some aspect in which you don't want to mess with a person who meditates on death.
SPEAKER_0:  There was some of that, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a saying, I think they probably took it from a movie or something like that, but I don't know where they got it.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  May I earn your need and be your wrath.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a good line. I would say that.
SPEAKER_0:  the statue.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Santa.
SPEAKER_0:  Another thing people, it's not a cartel specific saint though. It's like everybody, like at all levels, from the lady that sells tortillas.
SPEAKER_0:  to the arm.
SPEAKER_0:  to the cops, to the military. There's some people in the military that have been raided. There's a very specific symbol of how this is like a weird.
SPEAKER_0:  relationship specifically in Santa Marta and Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a shrine.
SPEAKER_0:  outside of Tijuana.
SPEAKER_0:  right across the.
SPEAKER_0:  La Presa, it's like a water reservoir right outside Tijuana.
SPEAKER_0:  and there was a big Santa Muerte altar there.
SPEAKER_0:  like on the roadside.
SPEAKER_0:  and my former boss, Leiza Ola, ordered that thing destroyed.
SPEAKER_0:  So he ordered a truck to destroy it.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a famous thing.
SPEAKER_0:  and it was rebuilt the next night.
SPEAKER_0:  And I know for a fact that some of the people that rebuilt that were some of the same guys that were destroying it.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh man, that's pretty symbolic. So it's just, it's not something that can be killed. It's a part of the-
SPEAKER_1:  The Spirit of the People.
SPEAKER_0:  It keeps getting destroyed by...
SPEAKER_0:  ultra-Christian groups or Catholic groups and it keeps getting rebuilt.
SPEAKER_0:  personally for me as a
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  I don't believe that there's a...
SPEAKER_0:  a Reaper skeleton in the sky protecting me.
SPEAKER_0:  But I do believe in the...
SPEAKER_0:  aspect of an ending.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, and how it's important to, you know, the ending is important in all things and death should be present in life and if it's not then you're delusional about
SPEAKER_0:  Thanks.
SPEAKER_1:  So do you have some mechanism to meditate on death?
SPEAKER_0:  and having my daughter who's eight.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Beware as a...
SPEAKER_0:  benevolent.
SPEAKER_0:  playing.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  She's a kid and she sees a skeleton that represents death and she just does.
SPEAKER_0:  I think...
SPEAKER_0:  in a way Mexicans have.
SPEAKER_0:  take in some of those aspects.
SPEAKER_0:  be it Day of the Dead.
SPEAKER_0:  some of these practices related to some occultism aspects around.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, St. Judas, you know, St. Kudas.
SPEAKER_0:  St. Judas is the...
SPEAKER_0:  the patron state of lost causes.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's one of the most venerated saints in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  Jesus probably the fourth or fifth you pray to which is pretty
SPEAKER_0:  funny and ridiculous but...
SPEAKER_0:  The reason why
SPEAKER_0:  And this is something I heard from somebody that was actually...
SPEAKER_0:  We found them.
SPEAKER_0:  with a gun and on his gun he had a
SPEAKER_0:  St. Judas effigy.
SPEAKER_0:  And he said, oh, like, why San Judas? What is this that is sogening why
SPEAKER_0:  And he's like, well, he's the last saint you pray to.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you mean?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, on the list of saints you pray to, he's the last one because when you pray to Judas, you might get the other Judas on the line.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the last one you pray to. That's why he's like the lost cause of saints.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember like
SPEAKER_0:  even how we...
SPEAKER_0:  try and bribe or maneuver our way, even in spirituality, in spiritual practices.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, such a fascinating culture.
SPEAKER_1:  That's unlike anything else.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's right next door.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's here too, again.
SPEAKER_0:  I found an alter in...
SPEAKER_0:  Connecticut.
SPEAKER_0:  which is pretty fascinating. There's one in Arizona.
SPEAKER_0:  against one of the
SPEAKER_0:  fastest-growing spiritual practices.
SPEAKER_0:  and not only in the US, but like...
SPEAKER_0:  across those.
SPEAKER_0:  Somebody from Russia reached out. There's an altar out there and there's a group of people praying to Santa Marta. I've been posting and writing a lot about it recently just from my own experience and some of the stuff that I gathered for myself.
SPEAKER_0:  All the way out there.
SPEAKER_0:  Those people are fascinated by some of those aspects.
SPEAKER_1:  So I gotta ask you about the dark turn of the-
SPEAKER_1:  of that spirituality.
SPEAKER_1:  Or maybe you will place this elsewhere, but who was Adolfo?
SPEAKER_1:  Kastanza.
SPEAKER_1:  Alpadrino.
SPEAKER_0:  This is a guy that comes...
SPEAKER_0:  up in a period I think he's...
SPEAKER_0:  He's at that initial period of cartels. This is before my time and I've-
SPEAKER_0:  I've talked to some of the people that were there for some of that. I mean, he killed a lot of people.
SPEAKER_0:  He was exposed.
SPEAKER_0:  and learned through his family ties about some of the Afro-Caribbean spiritualities that are now also exploding as far as influences across the world.
SPEAKER_0:  and in the US.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm going to talk about that. I mean, Santeria.
SPEAKER_0:  Palo Mayombe.
SPEAKER_0:  basically some old
SPEAKER_0:  spiritual practices coming out of Africa.
SPEAKER_0:  that uh...
SPEAKER_0:  utilize things like Ngangas, which are basically spiritual vessels that have to be loaded with
SPEAKER_0:  Human remains, in some cases.
SPEAKER_0:  he was basically a spiritual practitioner that certain cartel groups would hire for them to
SPEAKER_0:  Curse the other side.
SPEAKER_0:  to enviw them with invisibility to be able to transport their drugs or protection spells and stuff like that.
SPEAKER_0:  He was very successful at it apparently, or at least that is the experience of the people paying for some of these practices.
SPEAKER_0:  as his spells and his work.
SPEAKER_0:  getting bigger and bigger and more and more and complicated, the...
SPEAKER_0:  ingredients he needed for these Ngangas or these spells, these cauldrons that he would fill with.
SPEAKER_0:  certain elements grew in comp.
SPEAKER_0:  complexity.
SPEAKER_0:  until finally he said he needed the brain of a highly educated American of some sort.
SPEAKER_0:  which led to his eventual downfall.
SPEAKER_0:  He was basically...
SPEAKER_0:  responsible for abducting and murdering a young American who was a university college student I think.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think he believed?
SPEAKER_1:  Duh.
SPEAKER_1:  So this guy's murdering people to create what? Magical potions?
SPEAKER_0:  the vessels get vessels
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think he...
SPEAKER_0:  truly believe that he was capable of doing what he was doing, I guess.
SPEAKER_1:  there's a culture
SPEAKER_1:  that spiritually inclined that.
SPEAKER_1:  Hannah.
SPEAKER_1:  was on the same wavelength.
SPEAKER_1:  as him.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it jived.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, some of these spiritual practices, again, there's.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a ritualistic cannibalism done by some of these cartel groups out there. Was he involved?
SPEAKER_1:  in cat- in catablysm.
SPEAKER_0:  He wasn't involved in cannibalism that I know of, but most of the things that he was kind of known for was basically
SPEAKER_0:  requesting human body parts for some of the spell works he was doing.
SPEAKER_0:  And then.
SPEAKER_0:  going to such a level where he needed a specific brain or head of somebody that was educated and American.
SPEAKER_0:  So that.
SPEAKER_0:  again, led to his eventual downfall. His ranch was raided, they found.
SPEAKER_0:  the body parts inside of these cauldrons that he was preparing.
SPEAKER_0:  That's an interesting example of somebody. There's a.
SPEAKER_0:  cartel head somewhere in central Mexico as well.
SPEAKER_0:  El Mas Loco was his nickname.
SPEAKER_0:  And he basically forced the citizenship around him to turn him into a saint.
SPEAKER_0:  So he made a statue of himself. He was very big into, uh,
SPEAKER_0:  Christianity, specifically kind of like the Crusader.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, mentality and all of that.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of envied himself and some of the people that were around him with that.
SPEAKER_0:  and there's still alters to his death, to him after he died. He died two times. One time the government declared him that he was killing a shootout and turns out he wasn't dead.
SPEAKER_0:  So that was his first miracle, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  And then when he was really dead, some of his people and his loyal followers were gunpoint kind of still forced to go and get flowers and venerate these effigies and statues of him as a saint.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a powerful weapon, spirituality in Mexico is a powerful weapon and
SPEAKER_0:  You know, the church, Catholic Church in Mexico, was a pretty bad track record.
SPEAKER_0:  but as far as that being used to control populace and stuff like that.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think...
SPEAKER_0:  It's just another aspect that is being exploited in Mexico in some communities as far as the spirituality and the desperate need for people to believe in something.
SPEAKER_0:  and how that leads for some people to go into some horrible predatory behavior around it.
SPEAKER_1:  It was a fascinating...
SPEAKER_1:  Dynamica play here.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's not just the United States and Mexico, it's also China that you talk about.
SPEAKER_1:  China is the primary source of fentanyl in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  So fentanyl is an opioid.
SPEAKER_1:  that leads to 70,000.
SPEAKER_1:  plus or minus.
SPEAKER_1:  overdose deaths in the US every year.
SPEAKER_1:  So reading from Wikipedia.
SPEAKER_1:  quote, compared with heroin, it is more potent, has higher profit margins.
SPEAKER_1:  And because it is compact, has simpler logistics. It can be cut into or even replaced entirely Supply of heroin and other opiates.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think is important to understand about fentanyl as a drug?
SPEAKER_0:  there was a prescription.
SPEAKER_0:  op je epidemic in the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  that kind of
SPEAKER_0:  went down or stopped, well, still out there, but the epidemic-specific around it kind of
SPEAKER_0:  computer it out.
SPEAKER_0:  and there was also marijuana legalization.
SPEAKER_0:  happening at kind of the same time period.
SPEAKER_0:  which people talking about marijuana legalization thought it was gonna hit the cartels in their pockets and it was gonna be like a...
SPEAKER_0:  a death blow to these criminal groups.
SPEAKER_0:  Well now there's a illegal
SPEAKER_0:  pot grows in the United States being run by cartels in federal lands.
SPEAKER_0:  There's
SPEAKER_0:  the legal pot grows that are in some way, shape or form.
SPEAKER_0:  Influenced and or run or owned by some criminal groups and they're kind of utilizing that
SPEAKER_0:  The marijuana fields in Mexico turned into...
SPEAKER_0:  Poppyfield.
SPEAKER_0:  once again.
SPEAKER_0:  The problem is that some of these lands were leached of all the nutrients and they're not as good as something you would find somewhere in Afghanistan. So the yield and the quality of it wasn't as strong as it could be.
SPEAKER_0:  So somebody thought about the bright idea of putting fentanyl into the mix.
SPEAKER_0:  and...
SPEAKER_0:  not only that, but also figuring out a get-
SPEAKER_0:  fentanyl into Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  Mexico has a GI and pharmaceutical industry.
SPEAKER_0:  that people kind of also don't kind of know or factor into this equation.
SPEAKER_0:  which leads into...
SPEAKER_0:  the free ability of...
SPEAKER_0:  chemicals going in and out of the country and legal means of it happening.
SPEAKER_0:  So not only the precursors to make it, but also the chemists and the industry to create it in Mexico as well.
SPEAKER_0:  Some clandestine.
SPEAKER_0:  factories of fentanyl have been found in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  But realistically, it's not needed with the ways that the ports and the borders are down in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  stay engaged and stay dried.
SPEAKER_0:  started seeing an influx and a flood of fentanyl into Mexico specifically related to infusing it into a harrow.
SPEAKER_0:  and not only using that to feed local drug markets, but send it up into the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  which started off this process that we're kind of going through still.
SPEAKER_1:  Are these like similar highs?
SPEAKER_1:  And drug-wise, why do you infuse?
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, probably you're not the right person to have this biochemical discussion.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know about the biochemical aspect of it, but like speaking to
SPEAKER_0:  You guys that do Chiva down there, that's what we call heroin down there. That's like a nickname for it.
SPEAKER_0:  having them describe.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of the older stinkier darker heroin they used to get
SPEAKER_0:  before this whole Fentanyl thing.
SPEAKER_0:  and the highs I would get and how much they would have to take versus some of the stuff loaded with fentanyl.
SPEAKER_0:  They have to.
SPEAKER_1:  Also, there is more at higher potency. You
SPEAKER_0:  There's a higher potency to it and also there's a, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  more money to be made, easier to transport.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  But then...
SPEAKER_1:  Is this how China starts becoming?
SPEAKER_0:  part of the picture.
SPEAKER_0:  One aspect to it that people kind of miss is that, you know, there's no
SPEAKER_0:  Chinese cartel.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there's no criminal.
SPEAKER_0:  Chinese organization working unseen.
SPEAKER_0:  getting around government oversight in China.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know of any such.
SPEAKER_1:  Anything that could be labeled as a criminal organization is deeply integrated with the government.
SPEAKER_0:  I've never heard of a giant criminal enterprise in China operating. We have to assume that...
SPEAKER_1:  Independent added skips
SPEAKER_0:  of the state.
SPEAKER_0:  I would have to assume that some of these things are happening with the know-how and inaction of the government out there.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  when COVID hit.
SPEAKER_0:  there was a shortage of fentanyl.
SPEAKER_0:  on the northern side of Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  specifically related to the Xenolawa cartel. These guys were actually-
SPEAKER_0:  trafficking fentanyl from the US down to Mexico to infuse their product.
SPEAKER_0:  but not the new generation cartel which operates out of the central part of Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  Kolyma area which have access to the seaside ports.
SPEAKER_0:  So even during the shutdown, they were getting supplied.
SPEAKER_0:  which means to me, at least, or for anybody observing it, that the supply chain was not cut.
SPEAKER_0:  and whatever was coming out of China was...
SPEAKER_0:  being let.
SPEAKER_0:  out of China.
SPEAKER_0:  by whatever official channels would be able to shut down or stop it.
SPEAKER_1:  God, I would love to know the organizational structure, the governmental structure.
SPEAKER_1:  of China.
SPEAKER_1:  how they enable it.
SPEAKER_1:  because I can't imagine.
SPEAKER_1:  at the very top.
SPEAKER_1:  there's like a portfolio of things we're doing one of them is
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's more in action or just the know how that is happening, but just like hands off. Just let this
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  If I were to understand.
SPEAKER_1:  how large bureaucracies work.
SPEAKER_1:  It's looking the other way.
SPEAKER_1:  You.
SPEAKER_0:  are now seeing.
SPEAKER_0:  pill presses brought to Mexico, industrial-level pill presses found in clandestine laboratories.
SPEAKER_0:  where they're not only...
SPEAKER_0:  Infusing.
SPEAKER_0:  the yields that they're doing with fentanyl, but also making.
SPEAKER_0:  fake pain medication.
SPEAKER_0:  that is flooding.
SPEAKER_0:  US markets everywhere, less far as.
SPEAKER_0:  Is that pain medication or is that
SPEAKER_0:  who knows? That's how you see a lot of people dying from ODs that are...
SPEAKER_0:  supposedly taking pain pills and that's not what they're doing.
SPEAKER_0:  So the evolution right now you're seeing is.
SPEAKER_0:  making something.
SPEAKER_0:  look legit as far as pain medication that it isn't. And yeah, I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  Fentanyl is-
SPEAKER_0:  everywhere they're infusing cocaine with it.
SPEAKER_0:  been getting stories from the US of people buying it through Alibaba or just weird online sources and it coming in different packages and it just...
SPEAKER_0:  infusing it into whatever is out there.
SPEAKER_0:  It is killing off a whole generation of people.
SPEAKER_0:  Um,
SPEAKER_0:  and it comes from one place.
SPEAKER_0:  or it's manufactured somewhere where it's being.
SPEAKER_0:  manufactured with the precursors and the elements and know-how that comes from one place.
SPEAKER_0:  Who ever done it in my China?
SPEAKER_0:  about China.
SPEAKER_1:  because Mexico seems to have what's the role of this is such a complicated and how do you start to talk about the drug war
SPEAKER_1:  and more and more and more.
SPEAKER_1:  China
SPEAKER_1:  is the source of the drug.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there a drug war going on with China?
SPEAKER_0:  there's probably an economic war. While you talk about this and other sides of China.
SPEAKER_0:  Most, and this is something that's come out recently, a few years back, I think, but basically.
SPEAKER_0:  The ways you would move money back into Mexico after you have a load up here is that you would give it to a Chinese money broker.
SPEAKER_0:  they would put into Chinese banking system and it immediately would just disappear from American eyes.
SPEAKER_0:  and then another money broker in Mexico would receive it through a money transfer from China.
SPEAKER_1:  So China's incredibly good at money laundering.
SPEAKER_0:  That's another aspect to their, I mean, their banking system is invisible to the U.S.
SPEAKER_0:  basically, which allows the monies to move from one point to another.
SPEAKER_0:  So money brokers and people moving money for the groups down there are Chinese. So that's another aspect or element of China.
SPEAKER_0:  as far as its presence.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the role of intelligence in all of this?
SPEAKER_1:  FBI, CIA, the Chinese.
SPEAKER_1:  intelligence.
SPEAKER_0:  agencies.
SPEAKER_0:  Right now Mexico is going through a...
SPEAKER_0:  a nationalistic resurgence and left this presidency.
SPEAKER_0:  which is not friendly to US interest in a lot of ways.
SPEAKER_0:  The US has had a pretty bad track record with its foreign policy in Mexico, with a lot of damage being done by the last president as far as his rhetoric.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Donald Trump.
SPEAKER_0:  which has been weaponized and utilized by the by.
SPEAKER_0:  left down in Mexico.
SPEAKER_1:  So America is not seen positively.
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  Every now and then I post something about Mexico, some horrible thing happening down there. I was like, why doesn't USN people down there like-
SPEAKER_0:  aren't Mexicans looking for like US intervention? I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  That is beyond what anybody in Mexico would want. Specifically, you see that sentiment out there.
SPEAKER_0:  They don't view the US as somebody that's going to come in and fix anything or somebody that's going to help or as a friend.
SPEAKER_0:  with it when the Ukrainian conflict happened.
SPEAKER_0:  Mexico basically is
SPEAKER_0:  abstained from saying anything.
SPEAKER_0:  which is a wink and a nod to Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  It has openly been pro-Maduro and openly celebrated some of these regimes popping up.
SPEAKER_0:  across Latin America.
SPEAKER_0:  you know.
SPEAKER_0:  which is.
SPEAKER_0:  That is what people voted for. That is sentiment down there. They're going towards the left of the political spectrum because they've been...
SPEAKER_0:  basically violated over and over again by all these different presidencies that have promise changed.
SPEAKER_0:  brought corruption with them and they are our choices. So this is the best we have right now.
SPEAKER_0:  Ah.
SPEAKER_0:  And all of the enemies of the United States are taking full advantage of that. We recently had a general kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  address the Senate committee hearing, I think. He was talking about the...
SPEAKER_0:  prevalence of foreign intelligence services in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  and why that is.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you know, it has Mexico as.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of the minable lithium on the planet underneath the.
SPEAKER_0:  parts of it, specifically in the north.
SPEAKER_0:  It is going through a process. They call it the Cuarta Transformacion. The fourth transformation is what the president of Mexico calls it.
SPEAKER_0:  which is a
SPEAKER_0:  In a way, it's basically we're here to stay type thing.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, they just nationalized mining lithium.
SPEAKER_0:  and taking control of that and using that as leverage. If the United States ever wants to go to Mexico, that's probably not going to be related to.
SPEAKER_0:  cartel issues is going to probably relate to energy, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Thinking ahead, I guess.
SPEAKER_1:  Or what about also?
SPEAKER_1:  Just imagine a world.
SPEAKER_1:  what India and China are doing.
SPEAKER_1:  Phantom
SPEAKER_1:  trade with Mexico or whatever transport.
SPEAKER_1:  Imagine Chinese military.
SPEAKER_1:  moves.
SPEAKER_1:  makes an agreement, a NATO type of agreement with Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  That's pretty possible.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, we're seeing militarized Mexico. That's another aspect of Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  Mexico that again I haven't seen talked about a lot here in the US.
SPEAKER_0:  The main problem is that the current president had was he was going to make the federal police and the
SPEAKER_0:  the security issues in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  Civilian. He was gonna-
SPEAKER_0:  do exactly the opposite as his main rival, Felipe Calderon, the guy that started off the drug war efficiently.
SPEAKER_0:  And what does he do?
SPEAKER_0:  He dissolves the civilian leadership of the federal police. Dissolves the federal police.
SPEAKER_0:  creates the National Guard, which is a military unit.
SPEAKER_0:  and he puts the military in charge of that.
SPEAKER_0:  Now the military has a full monopoly over all.
SPEAKER_0:  federal policing.
SPEAKER_0:  When you cross into Mexico, you'll see them wearing these white camouflage uniforms. See the link above for the details on our channel.
SPEAKER_0:  Those are National Guard.
SPEAKER_0:  people.
SPEAKER_0:  but they're.
SPEAKER_0:  the military. So you're now seeing a militarized Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  with some of these leaks that happened during the Wacamaya leaks.
SPEAKER_0:  You're now seeing that Mexico has been hosting members of the Haitian military, and they've been training them up.
SPEAKER_0:  Doom.
SPEAKER_0:  Go back.
SPEAKER_0:  to police their country.
SPEAKER_0:  That's not something that Mexico has been known for, hosting other nations and training them in such a way.
SPEAKER_0:  It's an interesting maneuver. Mexico has been historically neutral about getting involved in foreign conflicts.
SPEAKER_0:  about voting and resolutions as far as invading or not invading or doing all these things.
SPEAKER_0:  Mexico has been historically kind of neutral when it comes to some of these things and now we're
SPEAKER_0:  training foreign military forces to go and do that role somewhere else.
SPEAKER_0:  We have the military building airports and building infrastructure in Mexico and a lot of their higher ups getting very
SPEAKER_0:  you know, wealthy around it, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  and they basically have a monopoly over.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, who gets to have guns down there? You know, there's one gun store in all Mexico and it's run by the military.
SPEAKER_0:  and the only way you can buy a gun there is if you can buy a plane ticket to fly there.
SPEAKER_0:  and have enough money to sustain that right or that privilege.
SPEAKER_0:  So you're seeing the military not being.
SPEAKER_0:  in its traditional role of just being the security force. Now it's policing.
SPEAKER_0:  it's involved in.
SPEAKER_0:  It's getting involved in politics in a big way. It's legislation that has passed to keep it on the streets and the policing role for more years now.
SPEAKER_0:  that should be looked at closer by anybody observing it from afar, the militarization of Mexico and where it's going.
SPEAKER_1:  because of you.
SPEAKER_1:  move towards a world where a world war three happens it feels like mexico
SPEAKER_1:  will be the center.
SPEAKER_1:  Because...
SPEAKER_1:  A hot war would be fought on the ground.
SPEAKER_1:  And so you have a very...
SPEAKER_1:  Difficult parallel between Mexico and Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  Both don't have nuclear weapons.
SPEAKER_1:  both have relationships. So Ukraine has a relationship.
SPEAKER_1:  or a pull towards the European Union and NATO.
SPEAKER_1:  Mexico, at least currently, has a
SPEAKER_1:  kind of slow pull towards.
SPEAKER_1:  China.
SPEAKER_1:  india potentially and russia you have this divide between
SPEAKER_1:  power centers in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  And in terms of.
SPEAKER_1:  Just imagine.
SPEAKER_1:  Hundreds of thousands of Mexican troops.
SPEAKER_1:  hundreds of thousands of Chinese troops on the border.
SPEAKER_1:  on the US border.
SPEAKER_0:  on the Mexican side. And also the fact that
SPEAKER_0:  that border doesn't mean anything to any sort of conflict that would happen regionally.
SPEAKER_0:  because that
SPEAKER_0:  It's very easy to cross border. Doesn't matter how many walls you put across it.
SPEAKER_0:  people are already here.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  This is not going to be a war fought off in some overseas place.
SPEAKER_0:  Like you're not gonna...
SPEAKER_0:  This is something if it happens.
SPEAKER_0:  if destabilization is utilized in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  to cause a conflict there and it turns into a Vietnam or a proxy war down there.
SPEAKER_0:  of a sword.
SPEAKER_0:  which I think...
SPEAKER_0:  In a way, you're already kind of seeing some of that.
SPEAKER_0:  through some of the conflicts going on down there. You have a
SPEAKER_0:  a new generation cartel.
SPEAKER_0:  that is being fed fentanyl from the Pacific side ports.
SPEAKER_0:  And suspiciously, you want to think that maybe it's favored by a foreign government of some sort, in some way, shape, or form, who knows?
SPEAKER_0:  And then you have a historically in control Sinaloa cartel that may or may not be favored by the US in some way, shape or form.
SPEAKER_0:  You can imagine.
SPEAKER_0:  a further conflict down there and people fostering it.
SPEAKER_0:  and seeing the effects of.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically...
SPEAKER_0:  setting a fire on the feet of the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  Its second largest consumer of US products is Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  the massive
SPEAKER_0:  wave of immigration that is going to be basically weaponized.
SPEAKER_0:  You know you saw the collapse of the border security structure with the
SPEAKER_0:  contingent of 3000.
SPEAKER_0:  Honduran
SPEAKER_0:  Guatemalan immigrants in that first wave of caravans coming to Tijuana. UPBEAT MUSIC.
SPEAKER_0:  It was pretty bad.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  It was pretty bad and it could have gotten worse.
SPEAKER_0:  Now, what is going to happen when that wave is no longer 3,000, but a million people being displaced by violence or being...
SPEAKER_0:  in fear of whatever conflict might originate down there. And just.
SPEAKER_0:  that massive wave of migration and move.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's an interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  thing that people should look at and, you know, how can you?
SPEAKER_0:  effect change to try and stop some of these things to happen.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, let me ask you at a philosophical, at a human level, what do you think about immigration?
SPEAKER_1:  illegal and legal immigration.
SPEAKER_1:  From
SPEAKER_1:  the direction of Mexico to the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  So we have an estimated.
SPEAKER_1:  11 million illegal immigrants in the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  And uh...
SPEAKER_1:  estimated 45 million legal.
SPEAKER_1:  immigrants in the US.
SPEAKER_0:  a few things about that.
SPEAKER_0:  When COVID hit, there was no shortages of produce.
SPEAKER_0:  and in the supermarkets.
SPEAKER_0:  Which means that...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, illegal immigration is pretty much the backbone of all produce and some of the farming industries out there, you know, most of it.
SPEAKER_0:  So illegal immigration.
SPEAKER_0:  and illegal.
SPEAKER_0:  illegal workers in those fields are essential workers in a way.
SPEAKER_0:  I think there's a weird relationship in the United States with some of these workers and how they're demonized and how they're called criminals. I think there's...
SPEAKER_0:  There was a state out there that passed anti-illegal immigrant worker legislation.
SPEAKER_0:  The farmers had to look elsewhere for people to show up to work in some of these fields, which basically caused...
SPEAKER_0:  millions of dollars worth of losses for some of these.
SPEAKER_0:  Farms.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Anywhere you go out there in the United States, you go into the kitchens and there's going to be paisanos there, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  French high level French restaurants.
SPEAKER_0:  You'll see people from Puebla there that...
SPEAKER_0:  made their way illegally and might have legalized or regularized their way.
SPEAKER_0:  into the country or.
SPEAKER_0:  or in a sanctuary city.
SPEAKER_0:  You go to the service industry hotels, you know, those are the people changing the blankets. Those are the people in the washrooms.
SPEAKER_0:  You have them doing jobs that no American wants to do, realistically. And they're everywhere in this country. They are.
SPEAKER_0:  the backbone of some of these industries that are essential in this country.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think there's a deep sense in which they are American?
SPEAKER_0:  I think they're indispensable and anybody that says they aren't.
SPEAKER_0:  is.
SPEAKER_0:  Delusional.
SPEAKER_0:  if you take every single legal worker out of the industry in the United States and send them back
SPEAKER_0:  Like, there's a movie out there called like that, the Mexicanas a day without Mexicans.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  everything would stop.
SPEAKER_0:  So the relationship is there. People talk about the history of slavery in this country.
SPEAKER_0:  like it's a thing that's in the past.
SPEAKER_0:  There's endangered slaves in the country right now, people that are paying off their
SPEAKER_0:  They're people smugglers because they brought them into this country and they haven't been able to pay that fine or that fee yet.
SPEAKER_0:  and are basically being held hostage by that here in the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  So they're slaves right now in the United States. People are talking about it's a historical context.
SPEAKER_1:  What do we do about it? How are we supposed to think about it?
SPEAKER_0:  We're going to have to rethink how we look at immigration, illegal or illegal or illegal immigration from Mexico and how we view Mexico as a foreign country.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Your relationship to Canada is one thing, your relationship to Mexico is another.
SPEAKER_0:  Um,
SPEAKER_0:  foreign policy towards Mexico has been.
SPEAKER_0:  pretty nefarious as far as the United States in a lot of ways.
SPEAKER_0:  You can go back.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a student massacre during the Olympics.
SPEAKER_0:  And the president in turn at that time was on the CIA payroll. And it was a counter.
SPEAKER_0:  communist type maneuver that we're doing down there.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  There are some bloody hands on the US side of some of the things that have been happening in Mexico as far as destabilization and influencing.
SPEAKER_0:  meddling in foreign policy out there.
SPEAKER_0:  most of the guns that are used down there come from the US. And that's another interesting aspect and responsibility that people...
SPEAKER_0:  shouldn't kind of think about up here.
SPEAKER_0:  So there is.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm the drug war side a machine that's.
SPEAKER_1:  fueling the drug war.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, there's a giant drug habit up here, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  but also a governmental intelligence and military support through the sale of weapons.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know about the sale of weapons, but you know.
SPEAKER_0:  There's some birdie.
SPEAKER_0:  We talk about poorest borders.
SPEAKER_0:  coming up. There's porous borders also going down, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a flow of guns going down.
SPEAKER_0:  and munitions.
SPEAKER_0:  which again, they don't kill anybody by themselves. They get put in the hands of the desperate that are trying to feed a giant drug market.
SPEAKER_0:  to the south, to the north. You know, Mexico has a saying.
SPEAKER_0:  Mexico, Mexico far from God, but close to the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's a...
SPEAKER_0:  There's definitely a responsibility on both sides. This is no longer a Mexico problem, a US problem.
SPEAKER_0:  This is a regional problem.
SPEAKER_0:  And if we don't think of it as a regional problem with our brothers on the southern side of it.
SPEAKER_0:  And with family, we're related in blood. There's like, we are, we are.
SPEAKER_0:  Mexico and the United States are like this.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's become popular in politics, they just throw a line.
SPEAKER_0:  All right.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think we need to get to a place where we can figure out how to make those connections and repair some of the damage done by just years and years of bad policy on both sides of the border.
SPEAKER_1:  policy and rhetoric, the way we talk about it, the way we think about it, not just the actual policy, but 92 Bio
SPEAKER_1:  seeing the humanity and the people that are here.
SPEAKER_0:  It's an easy thing. They're coming to take our jobs is something you hear.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a state out there that passed them.
SPEAKER_0:  anti-
SPEAKER_0:  anti-legislation as far as illegal workers on fields. And it led to
SPEAKER_0:  massive losses, nobody wanted to show up for those jobs, basically. People would show up one day and they wouldn't come back and they were doing jobs that people just don't want to do.
SPEAKER_0:  Are they taking that from the locals?
SPEAKER_0:  Or are they filling an essential role?
SPEAKER_0:  that we feel guilty about.
SPEAKER_0:  and the rhetoric around it is more about guilt.
SPEAKER_0:  than anything.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I am an immigrant myself. You know, I've gone through the experience of...
SPEAKER_0:  doing it legally.
SPEAKER_0:  I've seen people not do it legally and are in way better places than I am basically.
SPEAKER_0:  by going around some of the system.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the Moonsault Deep.
SPEAKER_0:  immigration system here in the US.
SPEAKER_0:  there's something wrong, you know, it's kind of broken.
SPEAKER_0:  Um,
SPEAKER_0:  And people coming here illegally are not only...
SPEAKER_0:  They're looking for a better life for themselves, a better life for people.
SPEAKER_0:  this whole aspect of vilifying them and they're like, oh, this immigrant did this horrible thing, this immigrant did that horrible thing.
SPEAKER_0:  and people saying, go back to your country.
SPEAKER_0:  At the same time, they go to a hotel where all the service staff is from that part of the world and they're here irregularly.
SPEAKER_0:  or they go to the Whole Foods and they get some produce there and it's...
SPEAKER_0:  picked by some of the same people that are realifying.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, we need to kind of like...
SPEAKER_0:  think about that and analyze that for ourselves.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, the idea of go back to your country and finding the other and having a disdain and a hate towards the other.
SPEAKER_1:  Ever since I had a recent conversation with Yay.
SPEAKER_1:  formerly known as Kanye West, I got to.
SPEAKER_1:  hear a few things from.
SPEAKER_1:  let's say unfriendly messages from white nationalists.
SPEAKER_1:  and I got to learn about this world.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I continue on the journey of learning.
SPEAKER_1:  which is the idea that the United States, this country...
SPEAKER_1:  should look a certain way, should have a certain skin color, should have a certain religion.
SPEAKER_1:  and everything else is a pollution, is a poison.
SPEAKER_1:  to this.
SPEAKER_1:  I made it sound hateful right now.
SPEAKER_1:  but they usually frame it in a positive way.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, like the purity.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm sure Hitler also phrased everything in a positive way, especially in the 1930s about the purity of Germany.
SPEAKER_1:  But the reality of the United States and one of the things that makes it
SPEAKER_1:  At least the idea of the United States is the soup, the mix.
SPEAKER_1:  unlike so many nations I've traveled to.
SPEAKER_1:  The diversity, the good kind of diversity is what makes.
SPEAKER_1:  country great.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's so I think it needs to be based on the.
SPEAKER_1:  accepting the different subgroups that make up the United States versus trying to purify it.
SPEAKER_1:  Mexican immigrants is just another flavor.
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  saying this is the other, let's reject the other.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I saw that interview by the way that was.
SPEAKER_0:  that you showed abasing restraint in that interview.
SPEAKER_0:  My experience when I came up here, again, Trump was elected when I came up here. So it was a weird.
SPEAKER_0:  time for me as far as being an American and the immigrant experience for myself.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  by both being, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  basically the ones that were, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  talked about in that way.
SPEAKER_0:  and also having a bunch of my friends who were very conservative and
SPEAKER_0:  you know, wearing some of those MAGA hats around me and like, Hey at like.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you know, I'm a guest here so I have to, you know, but uh...
SPEAKER_0:  It's a balancing act is what I've been looking at it as.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, on one side...
SPEAKER_0:  There's the woke.
SPEAKER_0:  side of it, which everything goes. And then the other side is like, let's hold on to some of these things that make us who we are.
SPEAKER_0:  On my end, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  I want to get to a place where I can smoke a joint.
SPEAKER_0:  Conceal, carry, or firearm. Be at my gay best friend's wedding.
SPEAKER_0:  And I want the government not to say anything about it. And I think there's parts in the United States here that kind of feel the same way.
SPEAKER_0:  but there's extremes on both sides that are pulling you to one side or the other.
SPEAKER_0:  And I've seen more of the United States than most Americans. I'm in a different state every weekend.
SPEAKER_0:  So I get to go to TIFF.
SPEAKER_0:  going to Tampa tomorrow.
SPEAKER_0:  Then I'm going back to California, then I'm going to drop to Tennessee later.
SPEAKER_0:  Kentucky, so I get to see all types of people and all types of mentalities and ways that people live and this country is more diverse than...
SPEAKER_0:  most would think, you know, if you only see it through the lens of television or media.
SPEAKER_0:  What I keep seeing out there that for me is like a...
SPEAKER_0:  the reason I came here, I guess, and a lot of the reasons that I feel a vested interest in this country, not just because my kid's American.
SPEAKER_0:  So I have a very, very big interest in this country doing well.
SPEAKER_0:  But the thing I see is they're still...
SPEAKER_0:  the opportunity and the ability to do something with yourself and opportunities out there for people like me that come here with nothing. I came here with.
SPEAKER_0:  an experience base.
SPEAKER_0:  A truck.
SPEAKER_0:  And some demons and yeah, a bunch of demons in a bag.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I'm here with you talking right now about some of those experiences. Another immigrant.
SPEAKER_0:  to another immigrant and both of us are reaching.
SPEAKER_0:  people out there that might not have, might haven't heard a voice of people like us that come here.
SPEAKER_0:  with our own.
SPEAKER_0:  bag of demons, but...
SPEAKER_0:  Where else in the world can two people like us have a conversation with an audience like us and not be shot outside of this because of the stuff we're saying?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, listen to with love and respect, not.
SPEAKER_1:  Not derision.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask you for advice. What would you say to young folks?
SPEAKER_1:  wherever they come from.
SPEAKER_1:  So in high school and college, they're thinking of how to live.
SPEAKER_1:  a life.
SPEAKER_1:  have a career they can be proud of.
SPEAKER_1:  And especially if they're struggling, especially if they're at a low point like you are when you came.
SPEAKER_1:  here.
SPEAKER_0:  ice.
SPEAKER_0:  Travel is one of the biggest things in the world that I would ask people to kind of go out to.
SPEAKER_0:  how other people live. Don't go there with your own preconceived notions or trying to make people act like you act. Go out there and travel and actually experience the world.
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't have to be another country.
SPEAKER_0:  Going from Tennessee to Seattle, it's a pretty interesting change of scenery.
SPEAKER_1:  Who's better at knife fighting? Just kidding, you don't have to answer that.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Tennessee. But the traveling is one and knowing how other people live is one aspect of it that I would tell people.
SPEAKER_0:  It's risky, it's dangerous, but that is part of the journey is one of the things I would ask people, young people to kind of consider.
SPEAKER_0:  Service is essential.
SPEAKER_0:  and it should be at the basis of all of our lives.
SPEAKER_0:  service. Start there. Start with service.
SPEAKER_0:  In any industry, you're going to go start your own restaurant, you have to work in the kitchen for service.
SPEAKER_0:  We're going to be a part, a productive member of this country. Service. And I'm not talking just about the military because the military, it's a process and it's a lifestyle and it's a thing for some people out there.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not even a choice for other people if they want an education and I get that.
SPEAKER_0:  Community service of any kind is an essential thing.
SPEAKER_0:  the ability to go out there and interact with the people that you would normally not interact with the homeless population that there is in this country.
SPEAKER_0:  of the older population that die in Mexico, our old die in our homes, you know, but here you send them off somewhere else to die.
SPEAKER_0:  which is an interesting weird detachment that I've seen in the US as far as
SPEAKER_0:  how the elders are.
SPEAKER_0:  or cast aside.
SPEAKER_0:  If I can...
SPEAKER_0:  say anything to young people is to.
SPEAKER_0:  start figuring out our lives of service and that's gonna expose you to a bunch of experiences to a bunch of people out there you might not regularly kind of meet and see and realities.
SPEAKER_0:  Education.
SPEAKER_0:  is
SPEAKER_0:  out there.
SPEAKER_0:  It is expensive, but I've sat through a bunch of really expensive classes that I've
SPEAKER_0:  managed to see on YouTube and learned a lot from them.
SPEAKER_0:  So education is out there, but it doesn't have to be as expensive as they make it. It's all about the individual and what he does with that education.
SPEAKER_0:  The dream is free and the hustle is sold separately.
SPEAKER_0:  but the ability to take information, process it, and use it.
SPEAKER_0:  We're expecting everything to be safe.
SPEAKER_0:  process and given to us in a platter.
SPEAKER_0:  taking that and digesting it and thinking that's going to make us somebody that's going to be productive or valuable in society.
SPEAKER_0:  What's up to us?
SPEAKER_0:  The US talks a lot about freedoms, but doesn't talk a lot about responsibilities.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's a big part of it.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, take responsibility for like, I came here without anything. And the first thing I thought was.
SPEAKER_0:  I have a responsibility for the people that I've.
SPEAKER_0:  work with and the people that are going through the same problems than I am, how can I figure out a way to help?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, the dark side of thinking a lot about freedom is...
SPEAKER_1:  thinking too individualistically.
SPEAKER_1:  meaning thinking about me, how to optimize my situation getting
SPEAKER_1:  the deepest growth.
SPEAKER_1:  you can do as an individual is by taking care of others, by helping others, by being of service, by being useful to your community locally.
SPEAKER_1:  and then hopefully also a scale.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's how you grow.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's responsibility of like helping those around.
SPEAKER_0:  There's an isolationist aspect to culture now.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like we...
SPEAKER_0:  we are separate, there's almost like a spiritual or cultural amputation in a way where...
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  When I was a kid, the house where all the bikes outside of it, that was where all the kids were hanging out.
SPEAKER_0:  And now everybody's on their phone, you know, and they're separate houses, I.
SPEAKER_0:  chatting on whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a detachment to there. That's a weird aspect to it. And also the aspect of I need to be safe. I can't be offended.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't hurt me, say spaces. This is my right, this is my, this is my right, this is my reality, you need to respect it.
SPEAKER_0:  Respect is earned.
SPEAKER_0:  and where I come from, respect to Zerun.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  There's freedoms, but there's dangerous freedoms.
SPEAKER_0:  Any freedom you have in Mexico is a dangerous freedom in a way.
SPEAKER_0:  you know?
SPEAKER_0:  You can drive home drunk in Mexico.
SPEAKER_0:  You can.
SPEAKER_0:  the few.
SPEAKER_0:  bribe a cop on your way there and if you don't die or crash into somebody else.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a dangerous aspect of freedom.
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  but there's a responsibility to all of it.
SPEAKER_0:  It is a twisted responsibility in a twisted way to talk about it and describe it.
SPEAKER_0:  the aspect of...
SPEAKER_0:  people.
SPEAKER_0:  screaming for freedom up here or their rights or their...
SPEAKER_0:  privilege.
SPEAKER_0:  without the responsibility.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  What are you doing for your community?
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  You're complaining about this, what are you doing about it?
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  Another thing I've noticed in traveling around, it's scary, is the whole people.
SPEAKER_0:  people getting shouted down or cancelled because of what the expressors say.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of the creepiest experiences I've had in the US has been through universities, or just seeing young people that have an opinion that is completely outside of reality.
SPEAKER_0:  Um,
SPEAKER_0:  people telling me how things are in Mexico, because they learned it through...
SPEAKER_0:  college course.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  seeing sons of immigrants.
SPEAKER_0:  criticizing me because of my opinion.
SPEAKER_0:  of Mexico or what I have to say about it.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you want to encounter the worst enemy of a Mexican, there's usually a second, third generation Mexican up here that shouts you down for what you're saying.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean in general entitlement, all of those kinds of things.
SPEAKER_1:  I, I, some of that comes with just being young in general, but yes, humility.
SPEAKER_1:  Humility at a societal scale would benefit significantly.
SPEAKER_1:  especially the young.
SPEAKER_1:  I would say some of the service that you're speaking to.
SPEAKER_1:  is
SPEAKER_1:  comes with being humbled.
SPEAKER_1:  And that is one of the-
SPEAKER_1:  best things you can do as a young person.
SPEAKER_1:  while maintaining the dream and the ambition.
SPEAKER_1:  humble yourself to the reality of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  one small example, a micro example of this.
SPEAKER_0:  My kid.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a homeless guy.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  She was out with some family members.
SPEAKER_0:  It's Homeless Guy.
SPEAKER_0:  showed up he was erratic, mentally disturbed.
SPEAKER_0:  Create a scene.
SPEAKER_0:  she was upset.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a little bit of trauma there, so you're like, Oh, now all homeless people are bad.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  with her.
SPEAKER_0:  She does art pieces sometimes for me and helps me make designs for the clothing brand that I have.
SPEAKER_0:  and we take some of that money and we buy socks and underwear.
SPEAKER_0:  And sometimes I have them in the car, sometimes I drive around and see somebody need something and I give it to her.
SPEAKER_0:  and says, you helped me earn this money that's going to help these people.
SPEAKER_0:  So you should just give them these.
SPEAKER_0:  And she's like.
SPEAKER_0:  Peace!
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm like, ah, thank you. She's like, cool. Surreal Da Duenda.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  She used to roll up the window really quick, now she doesn't.
SPEAKER_0:  They cease to be.
SPEAKER_0:  Scary.
SPEAKER_0:  Because now some of them have names.
SPEAKER_0:  Now some of them know her name, you know, when they when she crosses by there. So she's.
SPEAKER_0:  There's contact there.
SPEAKER_0:  She's more connected than I am in some of these places now. She has friends in low places.
SPEAKER_0:  and in high places. That comes later, I guess.
SPEAKER_0:  but she is learning about service. She's learning about.
SPEAKER_0:  Not everybody out there is an enemy or...
SPEAKER_0:  Bad.
SPEAKER_0:  Scary
SPEAKER_0:  you learning about service?
SPEAKER_0:  And she's basically learning that lesson that I got from my mom long ago. Nobody's against you, they're for themselves. Don't take anything personal.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you're not doing something for other people while you're working, then you're not doing anything.
SPEAKER_1:  So when you were young, you were pretty sure you were gonna die.
SPEAKER_1:  your 30. What's your relationship with death today?
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think about your mortality? Are you afraid of it?
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not afraid of it. If anything, I'm afraid of the...
SPEAKER_0:  meaningless.
SPEAKER_0:  death or at least a meaningless
SPEAKER_0:  walk.
SPEAKER_0:  towards it.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm afraid of losing use of my legs, I guess. I'm afraid of not being able to go out there and do things anymore. I'm afraid that I'm...
SPEAKER_0:  not physically capable of doing the job that I used to do.
SPEAKER_0:  So if anything, I'm afraid of stillness. You know, something I always quote a lot in my writing, stillness is death.
SPEAKER_1:  So you always want to be challenging yourself moving.
SPEAKER_1:  growing.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you're traveling, so you get all these experiences and filling your life with all these experiences.
SPEAKER_1:  And if it ends...
SPEAKER_1:  When it ends.
SPEAKER_1:  Are you ready for it? Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not afraid of the end. The ending is important in all things.
SPEAKER_0:  First time I got a promotion, I got two silver coins handed to me.
SPEAKER_0:  Here's a silver coin and this is another silver coin.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll give you the other one when your job ends.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  It depends on you if you wanted to have it over your eyes or in your pocket.
SPEAKER_0:  And the lesson there is that this job you're getting, it's pretty cool and you're gonna be in charge of all these people and it's pretty important, but it's gonna end.
SPEAKER_0:  So you always have to, the ending is important in all things.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  If we don't keep that in mind, then if you think we're immortal and nothing's going to end, I think there's an atrophy, a spiritual atrophy in that.
SPEAKER_1:  for the sake of spiritual flourishing.
SPEAKER_1:  This conversation too must come to an end.
SPEAKER_1:  So I think a beautiful way to end it. And I'm a huge fan of yours.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for.
SPEAKER_1:  Being a man with a life well lived.
SPEAKER_1:  and for talking with me today is an honor man. This is an awesome conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you for having me on.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with Ed Calderon.
SPEAKER_1:  support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now...
SPEAKER_1:  Let me leave you with some words from Al Pacino's character in Scarface.
SPEAKER_1:  Tony Montana.
SPEAKER_1:  You don't have the guts to be what you want to be.
SPEAKER_1:  You need people like me so you can point your fingers and say
SPEAKER_1:  That's the bad guy.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for listening.
SPEAKER_1:  I hope to see you.
SPEAKER_1:  next time.