SPEAKER_1:  The following is a conversation with Michael Malus.
SPEAKER_1:  This is a special holiday episode.
SPEAKER_1:  and it is made extra special.
SPEAKER_1:  because it's announcing the release of Michael's new book called
SPEAKER_1:  white pill.
SPEAKER_1:  A tale of good and evil.
SPEAKER_1:  Michael and I disagree on a lot of ideas in politics and philosophy.
SPEAKER_1:  and we'll have a lot of fun disagreeing.
SPEAKER_1:  There's no question.
SPEAKER_1:  that he has a deep love for humanity.
SPEAKER_1:  and puts his heart and soul into his work.
SPEAKER_1:  especially into this heart-wrenching, deeply personal book.
SPEAKER_1:  So I ask.
SPEAKER_1:  that you support him.
SPEAKER_1:  by buying it at whitepillbook.com.
SPEAKER_1:  That should.
SPEAKER_1:  Hopefully forward to the Amazon page.
SPEAKER_1:  As always, we eat stressed up.
SPEAKER_1:  in a ridiculous outfit.
SPEAKER_1:  without coordinating.
SPEAKER_1:  for the chaos.
SPEAKER_1:  that makes life so.
SPEAKER_1:  Damn interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  This episode is full of humor.
SPEAKER_1:  Darkness
SPEAKER_1:  and love.
SPEAKER_1:  which is the best way to celebrate the holidays.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the Lex Freedman Podcast. To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now, dear friends.
SPEAKER_1:  Here's Michael.
SPEAKER_1:  mouse.
SPEAKER_1:  We probably should have coordinated this better, shouldn't we? Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Have you?
SPEAKER_1:  since this is a Christmas special.
SPEAKER_1:  A holiday special, have you been a good or?
SPEAKER_1:  A bad boy, Michael.
SPEAKER_1:  this year.
SPEAKER_0:  Well that's interesting one of the
SPEAKER_0:  People in the book, Granville Hicks, his autobiography starts with, I was a good boy.
SPEAKER_0:  and he wasn't a very good boy.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  On a scale of 1 to 10.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm trying to think of what bad things I've done.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, okay, there's that. Okay, wait. That's not that was not that that's all right. I would say nine
SPEAKER_0:  Nine! yeah
SPEAKER_0:  I try to do the right thing.
SPEAKER_0:  What about you? Is it going to be 1 or 0?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, no, I'm extremely self-critical. I push to zero. Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  I reach for the zero.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, mission accomplished.
SPEAKER_1:  So this episode.
SPEAKER_1:  is announcing the release.
SPEAKER_1:  of The White Pill, a book you wrote.
SPEAKER_1:  I've gotten
SPEAKER_1:  the honor, the privilege, the pleasure of being one of the first people to read it.
SPEAKER_0:  So I'm really, I don't know if nervous is the word, but you are the first.
SPEAKER_0:  person who has read it that I am speaking to about it.
SPEAKER_1:  My first, my last, my everything. Yes. I'm gonna say that to all the girls.
SPEAKER_0:  but I'll take it. All the fembunts?
SPEAKER_1:  Oh the fun buds.
SPEAKER_1:  But yeah, it was a truly incredible book.
SPEAKER_1:  It's basically a story of evil in the 20th century.
SPEAKER_1:  and throughout.
SPEAKER_1:  it.
SPEAKER_1:  you reveal a thread that gives us hope.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's the idea of the white pill.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's the blue pill and the red pill.
SPEAKER_1:  There's the black pill, which is a kind of deeply cynical.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe apathetic, just giving up on the world.
SPEAKER_1:  given that you see behind the curtain and you...
SPEAKER_1:  Given that you don't like what you see, given that there's so much suffering in the world, you give up. There's a science in slaughter of life, I was a fight of life silicon, having to have
SPEAKER_1:  I suppose is even though you acknowledge that there's evil in the world, you don't give up.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  If you're listening to this and you're a fan of this podcast.
SPEAKER_0:  You go to whitepillbook.com and it'll go to it.
SPEAKER_1:  white pill book.com and if you don't know how to spell, we'll probably have a link that you can click on.
SPEAKER_1:  So for people who also don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  My Komalis.
SPEAKER_1:  is not just a troll.
SPEAKER_1:  Not just a hilarious, comedic.
SPEAKER_1:  genius.
SPEAKER_1:  who hosts his own podcast, but he is an incredible, brilliant author. Dear reader, the uh...
SPEAKER_1:  unauthorized autobiography Kim Jong Il.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's a story of North Korea, the new right to journey to the fringe of American politics.
SPEAKER_1:  That's...
SPEAKER_1:  The story.
SPEAKER_1:  of the extremes.
SPEAKER_1:  of the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  political movements and then the anarchist handbook that's talking about the ideologies, the different flavors of ideologies of anarchism.
SPEAKER_1:  But on top of that, you're now rev-
SPEAKER_1:  going in.
SPEAKER_1:  going into the darkest.
SPEAKER_1:  aspects of the twentieth century with the soviet union and uh... communism with white pill song
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask you, let's start at the beginning.
SPEAKER_1:  At the end of the 19th century, as you write, the terms socialist, communist, and anarchist were used somewhat loosely and interchangeably.
SPEAKER_1:  because the prophesied Marxist society was one in which the state had famously withered away.
SPEAKER_1:  There was a great disagreement about what a social system would do.
SPEAKER_1:  looked like in practice, but two things were clear.
SPEAKER_1:  First, that socialism was both inevitable and scientific.
SPEAKER_1:  the way of the future and second.
SPEAKER_1:  that the capitalist ruling class were not going down without a fight. So what are the key points?
SPEAKER_1:  of disagreement between.
SPEAKER_1:  the socialists, the anarchists, the communists along that.
SPEAKER_1:  at that time.
SPEAKER_1:  at the end of the 19th century, at the beginning of the 20th century.
SPEAKER_1:  The possibility of the century laid before us that eventually led to the first and the second world war.
SPEAKER_0:  The idea when the Industrial Revolution came and Marx was very much a product of Industrial Revolutionary thinking was, okay, now that we have technology, now that we have science, we can scientifically manage society.
SPEAKER_0:  We saw this very much with Woodrow Wilson.
SPEAKER_0:  and this kind of idea of progressivism that, you know, we could use some,
SPEAKER_0:  technology and kind of not.
SPEAKER_0:  capitalism in their view unfettered capitalism was wasteful you're making too much stuff you have surpluses you have
SPEAKER_0:  shortages if we produce just exactly what we need and you have these people engineers, your engineering society...
SPEAKER_0:  then everyone will be happy and you won't have to have any suffering or waste.
SPEAKER_0:  So socialism at that time was used as a broad umbrella.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not using the term that it means today of.
SPEAKER_0:  necessarily state socialism. It just meant the idea of having society scientifically run.
SPEAKER_0:  So you had a huge argument, they're different wings, you even had it from the beginning with Marx versus Bakunin because Marx was for...
SPEAKER_0:  obviously state socialism, the absolute state running everything. Even with
SPEAKER_0:  marks and angles.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a means to an end after man is remade.
SPEAKER_0:  in his very nature, then the state withers away and everyone's equal and then you have this kind of heaven on earth situation. Bakunin was the opposite. He regarded the state as inherently immoral.
SPEAKER_0:  and wanted to have kind of like.
SPEAKER_0:  workers collectives and things like that and ultra localized control.
SPEAKER_1:  So the end was always stateless. It's just that some people viewed the state as.
SPEAKER_1:  a convenient effective intermediate.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I think at least Mark some process.
SPEAKER_0:  plenty of others who just regarded it, you know, have the state owner, have the workers you know, control.
SPEAKER_0:  the production via the state.
SPEAKER_1:  By the way, how does my hat look?
SPEAKER_0:  It looks great festive.
SPEAKER_1:  Is this side better?
SPEAKER_0:  than the other side. I think you want it on this side so people can see you.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh no.
SPEAKER_1:  You know like, um...
SPEAKER_1:  when you have like hair.
SPEAKER_0:  Peekaboo hair, it's called. Veronica Lake, I think was her name.
SPEAKER_1:  And then I just glance flirtatiously towards the camera sometimes. I'll get 말이 on the next two over Foran,
SPEAKER_0:  Wow
SPEAKER_0:  No glove, no love.
SPEAKER_0:  The bad.
SPEAKER_1:  The bad aspect of white gloves is...
SPEAKER_1:  The blood stains them.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to get new ones every time.
SPEAKER_1:  And now I glance flirtatiously after that.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm sorry, okay, Bakunin and Marx, go ahead.
SPEAKER_0:  So there were other...
SPEAKER_0:  socialists who did not regard this kind of end times where the state would do it the way at all.
SPEAKER_0:  And there are, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  various strains in between where you'd have some capitalism and some socialism.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... you know the concept of a safety net
SPEAKER_0:  came out of socialist thinking, the Labour Party came out, the Fabian Socialists in Great Britain, their logo was a wolf in sheep's clothing.
SPEAKER_0:  And then when that was too on the nose, they changed it to a tortoise, meaning we're going to get to socialism.
SPEAKER_0:  slowly in the sense of either...
SPEAKER_0:  uh... gradualism or boiling a frog
SPEAKER_0:  And also the big part of this thinking at the time, this is again, the late 19th century.
SPEAKER_0:  is the idea that there's going to be a worldwide workers revolution. It wasn't going to be that.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, in one country, you know, it was gonna happen and then all the other countries would be capitalists. The idea was, all right.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh
SPEAKER_0:  like the workers in Germany have more in common with the workers in America.
SPEAKER_0:  than the workers in Germany have with the capitalists in Germany. So the idea is, alright, like they're the working class all over the world, at one point they're going to be like...
SPEAKER_0:  We're being exploited.
SPEAKER_0:  It's getting worse and worse for us. We can't feed our families. We're getting injured and so on and so forth and there's no compensation for this.
SPEAKER_0:  We're just going to overthrow our chains and we're going to run everything ourselves. We're the ones running it already anyway.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and you know, the
SPEAKER_0:  This was their doing all the work.
SPEAKER_0:  And we're doing all the work, so why shouldn't we be getting all the benefits?
SPEAKER_1:  What's the role of violence in all of this?
SPEAKER_0:  So this was a big.
SPEAKER_0:  source of contention.
SPEAKER_0:  So the Fabians, for example, in Britain, who are all socialists, they were very heavily
SPEAKER_0:  of the idea that we can do this through the ballot box.
SPEAKER_0:  We can.
SPEAKER_0:  advocate and
SPEAKER_0:  have.
SPEAKER_0:  agitate and get the people to be voting for their own self-interest and furthering the state.
SPEAKER_0:  at the expense of the capitalist class.
SPEAKER_0:  Then there were the people who were the hardcore anarchists who were like...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  If voting changed anything, they wouldn't let us do it.
SPEAKER_0:  And the only way to have a revolution is to have a revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  too.
SPEAKER_0:  Kill to...
SPEAKER_0:  Overthrow?
SPEAKER_0:  to seize these factories.
SPEAKER_0:  And this was a big argument and it also.
SPEAKER_0:  fed into the idea of...
SPEAKER_0:  Where does free speech end?
SPEAKER_0:  Is it legal to be giving speeches advocating for violence and revolution? Is it legal? Is it legal to be giving speeches advocating for violence and revolution?
SPEAKER_0:  He published a book?
SPEAKER_0:  uh... in the eighteen hundreds about how to build dynamite and how to build bombs
SPEAKER_0:  And this is a big.
SPEAKER_0:  free speech concerned the time because now anyone in their own house
SPEAKER_0:  can make a bomb and...
SPEAKER_0:  kill lots of people. And this is something that was happening with enormous frequency at the time. And people tend to think, you know, because we have these kind of prejudices.
SPEAKER_0:  or we only remember what's happening now but
SPEAKER_0:  This was World War I and got started with the assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand.
SPEAKER_0:  There were lots of people, McKinley is another one who I discussed in the book, his assassination.
SPEAKER_0:  There was lots.
SPEAKER_0:  of violence happening very regularly. And with the creation of dynamite, it kind of exponentially became more dangerous and threatening. Even now on Wall Street, there was a bomb that went off, I think in the 1920s.
SPEAKER_0:  And the shards of shrapnel are still in the JP Morgan building, I believe.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you ever think?
SPEAKER_1:  if you were alive during that time, what you would be doing?
SPEAKER_1:  You think of yourself as an anarchist?
SPEAKER_1:  Would you be, where would you be? Would you be a socialist, a communist? Which parties would you attend?
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  figuratively and
SPEAKER_0:  The thing that was so interesting back then is there was a woman named Mabel Dodge Lujan and she ended her days in Taos, New Mexico. She found an artist colony.
SPEAKER_0:  and she had an apartment on 9th street and 5th avenue in Manhattan.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... shuttle salon
SPEAKER_0:  and everyone got together and talked and you have Emma Goldman who's an anarchist, Margaret Sanger who invented Planned Parenthood and advocated for birth control.
SPEAKER_0:  and you'd have the people from the Wobblies, the hardcore labor unions, and everyone kind of, Ed Shellmanekin didn't attend, but he was friends with them all.
SPEAKER_0:  So there was this very weird...
SPEAKER_0:  with the birth of modernism in art and in kind of modernist thinking.
SPEAKER_0:  There was this idea of like, all right.
SPEAKER_0:  Like this was the first time where you could be intellectual as a class, where there really was this space for people who are thinkers.
SPEAKER_0:  And they just sat around being like, all right, like, what are we gonna do with ourselves? And you had it in modern art.
SPEAKER_0:  You had it in literature, you had it in politics.
SPEAKER_0:  So it was a very exciting time.
SPEAKER_0:  where people were like, all right, like everything is now on the table.
SPEAKER_0:  What are we gonna do with this? And they very much were aware that this was a break.
SPEAKER_0:  with the pre-industrial revolution kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  farmer labor era.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you see?
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think for you violence would be compelling?
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  First of all, I'm just too small.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, but second, I just dynamite.
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't care about your size.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, but I mean retribution does and I think
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, but to me violence is the kind of thing where...
SPEAKER_0:  You think you're running it, but it's running you?
SPEAKER_0:  Once you
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  that line, you know, violence sings its own song.
SPEAKER_0:  So whenever I hear even contemporary times where people are advocating for, you know, violent actions, it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  When you start a fire, you're not like, I'm just going to burn down this house. You know, it's, it's, it's, and there's many.
SPEAKER_0:  cases over and over of people who are building bombs.
SPEAKER_0:  or trying to assassinate someone or things like that, and it ended up literally.
SPEAKER_0:  Literally literally blowing up in their own face.
SPEAKER_0:  So, and violence doesn't
SPEAKER_0:  Really?
SPEAKER_0:  work necessarily because you know if you have an assassination you're not assassinating the presidency.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, if you take out, you know, a president.
SPEAKER_0:  There's another president instantly there. So what have you accomplished? So
SPEAKER_0:  husband.
SPEAKER_0:  Dad is gone.
SPEAKER_0:  You replace them with someone who now is in a position to crack down.
SPEAKER_0:  and retaliate with even more violence. So it's a-
SPEAKER_0:  the calculus for me isn't there. Would I be advocating for then?
SPEAKER_0:  Who knows?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  But I mean, I don't know if I'd be able to have the space to be.
SPEAKER_0:  I certainly wouldn't have the space to be a podcaster or like a media personality. That wasn't really a thing. To some extent, it was in the 1920s.
SPEAKER_0:  with the Algonquin roundtable and all the people from the New Yorker magazine.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, but they were all drunks, you know, it was very much, uh,
SPEAKER_0:  uh, a weird
SPEAKER_0:  kind of situation to be a thinker.
SPEAKER_1:  What would you think you'd do? Work at a carnival? You look good in lipstick, so...
SPEAKER_0:  Well, thank you. Um, I looked at anything. Um, what would I, I don't know. I mean, you're not building robots. I mean, you could have been a Tesla, right? Okay. I didn't mean a car. I meant the person. Like I understand.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, thank you for explaining the witty comments to me.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't witty at all. Cause you wouldn't get Einstein, cause he was an immigrant.
SPEAKER_1:  So I wouldn't work with an immigrant, what is that even?
SPEAKER_0:  No, you would have been a Tesla-like figure. There's already a Tesla, so you wouldn't literally be Tesla. That's why I said a Tesla.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, Tesla. Okay. So, all right. So, thank you for the explanation.
SPEAKER_1:  See, Michael doesn't only make funny things, he also explains them for you. It wasn't fun, man.
SPEAKER_0:  It wasn't funny at all. That I agree with.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so yes, when you...
SPEAKER_0:  She this is like I didn't like you. It's this
SPEAKER_0:  Alright.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm downgrading it from a 9 down to an 8.
SPEAKER_1:  if you keep talking like this
SPEAKER_1:  A five is a real possibility. All right. So, uh, vacuum is the kind of vacuum that's created with violence is, is usually.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  filled with like a
SPEAKER_1:  with a harsher figure.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  So you don't think violent revolution ultimately leads to positive progress in the short term.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, sometimes it does. The American Revolution, I think, was a positive example. And overthrowing the Tsar, which was done peacefully.
SPEAKER_0:  was a positive example, but again,
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, when-
SPEAKER_0:  violence happens, people get scared.
SPEAKER_0:  and they want the violence stopped immediately. And that's a call for authoritarianism.
SPEAKER_0:  and you see it time and time again. And they also want retribution. They were like, bring this back to normal.
SPEAKER_0:  and they don't really worry about things like civil liberties or things like that. It's a very, uh, uh,
SPEAKER_0:  and then it also.
SPEAKER_0:  creates this space for invasion from.
SPEAKER_0:  foreign sources or demagogues, you know, like, oh look, they're killing us in the streets. Now you got to support me.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a very...
SPEAKER_0:  Deadly game, obviously.
SPEAKER_1:  I remember somebody told me.
SPEAKER_1:  that I forget where it was, but they told me that from the very beginning it was obvious that communism is an evil system.
SPEAKER_1:  or a system that leads to evil.
SPEAKER_1:  And to me, at least that's not.
SPEAKER_1:  If I had to put myself in the beginning of the 20th century at the end of the 19th century, it would be Asia.
SPEAKER_1:  They are.
SPEAKER_1:  trying to elevate humanity.
SPEAKER_1:  the basic worth of a human being.
SPEAKER_1:  of a hard working human being, of the working class, of the people that are doing the work and are striving and...
SPEAKER_1:  just really trying to build up society with their own hands. which seems like a beautiful ideal.
SPEAKER_1:  So I guess the question is
SPEAKER_1:  Can you see yourself?
SPEAKER_1:  believing that.
SPEAKER_1:  in the ideas of socialism and communism.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, let's say if you were living.
SPEAKER_0:  in Russia. Oh yeah, easily. First of all, I don't think anything is obvious in politics.
SPEAKER_0:  it's not obvious that you know
SPEAKER_0:  humans have rights, it's not obvious that liberty is better or the markets either.
SPEAKER_0:  whether you're four.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, welfare state or your four more free markets, not that those is obvious. Both of them involve enormous amount of thought.
SPEAKER_0:  and background information. So when someone says something is obvious,
SPEAKER_0:  politics, they really mean something's apparent. Well, it's not apparent on its face that if we all get together.
SPEAKER_0:  and promote a society based on equality.
SPEAKER_0:  and we all chip in that it's going to really be good for everyone. I mean that to me is the promise.
SPEAKER_0:  of communism.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was also very appealing to many people because
SPEAKER_0:  It was new.
SPEAKER_0:  So the idea was, all right.
SPEAKER_0:  We've tried it these other ways.
SPEAKER_0:  There's all these negative consequences, you have all these slums.
SPEAKER_0:  You have people getting, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  fired and then they have no recourse.
SPEAKER_0:  You have women with ten kids.
SPEAKER_0:  and they can't feed their kids, infant mortality, you don't have sanitation, you don't have food, everyone's illiterate and uneducated.
SPEAKER_0:  And then here's saying, look.
SPEAKER_0:  If we all chip in together, everyone will have clothes, everyone will have food, everyone will be educated, everyone will do their part. It's going to be rough in the short period.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a very compelling...
SPEAKER_0:  case to be made for communism. It's really easy in many ways.
SPEAKER_0:  when something hasn't been tried.
SPEAKER_0:  to make it sound.
SPEAKER_0:  compelling.
SPEAKER_0:  because you just talk about how great it's gonna be.
SPEAKER_0:  And then no one.
SPEAKER_0:  No one f-
SPEAKER_0:  You know, people are always arguing about how like Venezuela and Sweden, like, oh, you want democratic socialism to be like Sweden, you don't want it to be like Venezuela. The Venezuelans didn't vote for Venezuela, they voted for Sweden. They ended up with Venezuela.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  And the thing with communism, especially at that era.
SPEAKER_0:  It was very much a-
SPEAKER_0:  correlated.
SPEAKER_0:  with people who are too smart for their own good.
SPEAKER_0:  because they had the idea that.
SPEAKER_0:  if we are just put in charge.
SPEAKER_0:  instead of these like.
SPEAKER_0:  business for people or these heirs to great estates.
SPEAKER_0:  if the people who are smart and get it, like us.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't mean you and me, the people at the time who are advocating for it.
SPEAKER_0:  Once we're in charge, since we're good people and we want what's best for everyone, um, we're going to make sure everyone's taken care of. And, you know, they always talked about how much they cared about the little guy.
SPEAKER_0:  So I'm sure some of them meant it a lot and like, look, if the guy in charge.
SPEAKER_0:  is very much concerned with the little guy. He's not going to slip between the cracks.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's just going to be absolutely great.
SPEAKER_0:  and we don't have to worry about.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  the capitalist class just basically exploiting people and having these huge estates.
SPEAKER_0:  while these people can't even feed their own families.
SPEAKER_1:  Since we have a little bit of momentum, can you steal me on the case for socialism?
SPEAKER_1:  At that time...
SPEAKER_1:  and even today.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if it's...
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if there's a rhyme and a...
SPEAKER_1:  similarity to those.
SPEAKER_1:  to socialism was implemented at that time and what could possibly be implemented today, but maybe you can dance between the two.
SPEAKER_0:  The Steelman argument for socialism is...
SPEAKER_0:  if you have everything up to private industry.
SPEAKER_0:  You do not have a guarantee.
SPEAKER_0:  that someone won't fall between the cracks.
SPEAKER_0:  And the other concern is...
SPEAKER_0:  in any other context if someone is let's suppose mentally ill.
SPEAKER_0:  right? Through no fault of their own.
SPEAKER_0:  And they are, or someone's handicapped, you know, they can't.
SPEAKER_0:  feed themselves or mentally disabled or something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  if you have everything up to charity.
SPEAKER_0:  some.
SPEAKER_0:  if you see this with endangered species, right?
SPEAKER_0:  the species that are cute.
SPEAKER_0:  It's easy to raise money for them and protect them.
SPEAKER_0:  Some weird.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of frog somewhere that no one cares about.
SPEAKER_0:  You can't raise money for it. There's people's interests are to what they find interesting. So if someone is.
SPEAKER_0:  someone who's like not socially appealing in some way, whatever capacity.
SPEAKER_0:  they're going to fall between the cracks.
SPEAKER_0:  and they're screwed.
SPEAKER_0:  Under socialism, if you have a government taking care of everything,
SPEAKER_0:  No one is left behind.
SPEAKER_0:  You are guaranteed.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  The lowest of the low and the worst of the worst are still going to make sure that they're not starving the street.
SPEAKER_0:  or just left behind. So that is a big moral case.
SPEAKER_0:  to be made for having the state.
SPEAKER_0:  running everything. In terms of economics, it's a lot harder.
SPEAKER_0:  But the argument there would be
SPEAKER_0:  It's why it's not fair.
SPEAKER_0:  a term which.
SPEAKER_0:  in my view does not actually have a good meaning.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's not fair that...
SPEAKER_0:  because you were born a Rockefeller.
SPEAKER_0:  and I was born in Poland.
SPEAKER_0:  that you never have to worry about food for the rest of your life.
SPEAKER_0:  whereas I have to worry about...
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  paying for a doctor for my kid. Like you just, you won this lottery when you were born and now I have to be screwed and have to respect all your property. Why?
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  That is another strong argument to be made for socialism.
SPEAKER_0:  And the other argument is...
SPEAKER_0:  If you have a...
SPEAKER_0:  media apparatus.
SPEAKER_0:  that is operated under
SPEAKER_0:  profit-seeking principles.
SPEAKER_0:  It is going to feed into people's worst.
SPEAKER_0:  qualities, most basic animal-like qualities and sensationless qualities.
SPEAKER_0:  and will be used as a mechanism for capitalist control, whereas if the government, which represents all of us, goes higher, the government will stop.
SPEAKER_0:  is running things.
SPEAKER_0:  then everyone will have a right.
SPEAKER_0:  have their voice heard and won't be manipulated. That's the argument.
SPEAKER_1:  the reaching towards the stateless version.
SPEAKER_1:  sort of because you espouse ideas of anarchism.
SPEAKER_1:  it kind of has the same conclusion.
SPEAKER_1:  which is reaching towards the removal of the state to where we, I guess, have.
SPEAKER_1:  some distributed reallocation of resources that are...
SPEAKER_1:  quote unquote, fair.
SPEAKER_0:  thing is the Marxist vision of the state withering away and becoming anarchism.
SPEAKER_0:  It's really kind of like the underpants gnomes.
SPEAKER_0:  Because it's like, step one.
SPEAKER_0:  You have marks. I missed the You have marks.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  Unsay.
SPEAKER_0:  You have full.
SPEAKER_0:  communism, the states running everything, including education.
SPEAKER_0:  Step 2? Step 3?
SPEAKER_0:  So their idea was that after enough time...
SPEAKER_0:  the nature of man himself.
SPEAKER_0:  was going to change. And then the government would be superfluous because we would all be.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, equal.
SPEAKER_0:  and we would all naturally or socially, whatever term they would use.
SPEAKER_0:  want to.
SPEAKER_0:  act the part that we would need to.
SPEAKER_0:  And in fact, Reagan...
SPEAKER_0:  had a great joke about this where there were two commissars, I think, in Moscow.
SPEAKER_0:  And when they're walking around, they're going, is this it? Have we done it? Have we reached full communism? Oh no, it's going to get a hell of a lot worse.
SPEAKER_0:  So, you know, that's kind of the counterargument to that.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think?
SPEAKER_1:  Culture, society can't change the nature of man.
SPEAKER_1:  No.
SPEAKER_1:  So no matter...
SPEAKER_1:  You don't think this idea that, for example, America has been founded on that all men are created to equal.
SPEAKER_1:  that that idea...
SPEAKER_1:  can't permeate the culture and
SPEAKER_1:  Thereby...
SPEAKER_1:  change how we see each other.
SPEAKER_1:  Howie.
SPEAKER_1:  Think of the basic worth of a human being, and thereby change our nature.
SPEAKER_0:  Doesn't change, that's epigenetic, I don't-
SPEAKER_0:  Think the-
SPEAKER_0:  that changes the nature of man.
SPEAKER_0:  I think, for example.
SPEAKER_0:  If I say someone at which I agree with that someone is innocent until proven guilty.
SPEAKER_0:  They're not literally innocent.
SPEAKER_0:  They're regarded in a legal context as innocent, but that person is or is not a murderer or thief or so on and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  so we can.
SPEAKER_0:  legally and ethically regard everyone as equal.
SPEAKER_0:  But as Thomas Sowell pointed out, a human being isn't even equal to himself over the course of a day. Twins who were genetic clones are not equal to one another. So it is a- EXמע Quran
SPEAKER_0:  important thing legally.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's a good yardstick, but it's not.
SPEAKER_0:  Literally true. Im pain 100 boil, the
SPEAKER_1:  think that law becomes ethics so we
SPEAKER_1:  Um,
SPEAKER_1:  That idea of justice starts to like...
SPEAKER_1:  We start to internalize it.
SPEAKER_1:  that we just...
SPEAKER_1:  the way we behave, the way we think about the world.
SPEAKER_0:  No, I think it's a complete-
SPEAKER_0:  red herring.
SPEAKER_0:  because
SPEAKER_0:  No one is.
SPEAKER_1:  No, you're right, Harry.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  See what I did there.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  because
SPEAKER_0:  people are still going to always prefer their family to strangers.
SPEAKER_0:  or they're in group to out group.
SPEAKER_0:  So in terms of if you're going to have equality, that means it's going to not matter to you whether someone is your mom.
SPEAKER_0:  where someone is, you know, someone down the street, and I don't see how that will ever become the case.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you think it would?
SPEAKER_1:  it would be possible.
SPEAKER_1:  if you weren't intellectual.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you are at the beginning of the 20th century. Would you be able to predict?
SPEAKER_1:  the rest of the 20th century.
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think at all. I think there were so many
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Out of nowhere turns.
SPEAKER_0:  that no one would have seen them coming. And as an example,
SPEAKER_0:  Lenin seizing power.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  making the Bolshevik revolution a reality.
SPEAKER_0:  was regarded as utopian and insane.
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that he pulled it off is...
SPEAKER_0:  close to miraculous, and it was quite literally unprecedented.
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that so that's a very big one.
SPEAKER_1:  Which aspect of it sorry to interrupt?
SPEAKER_1:  which aspect was hard to predict, that a singular figure with just some ideas would be able to take so much power.
SPEAKER_0:  and maintain that power and remake that society so drastically, so quickly, despite such opposition.
SPEAKER_1:  Also, not just a set of temporary protests by hooligans that lead to
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  the short term but then stabilizes but literally changes the entirety of the system.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, Ludendorff, who was the German general, he's like, all right, we got to get the Russians out of World War I.
SPEAKER_0:  He's the one who's like, all right, let's get this lunatic Lenin who already tried and failed.
SPEAKER_0:  to have a revolution in Russia. Let's send him back there.
SPEAKER_0:  And he's just going to cause problems to everybody. And it's going to be great because it's going to weaken Russia and then our Eastern Front.
SPEAKER_0:  isn't going to have to be a problem.
SPEAKER_0:  And then to his surprise and.
SPEAKER_0:  everyone else is including, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  anarchists and communists worldwide.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, they pulled off this, you know, October revolution and then for a while it's like, all right. I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I think my understanding is even people at the time...
SPEAKER_0:  in St. Petersburg and in Moscow were like.
SPEAKER_0:  What does this even mean, right? Like no one took it seriously?
SPEAKER_0:  And then very quickly you had the CHECA and the secret police and all these other kind of implementations.
SPEAKER_0:  of the communist state and people are like, oh.
SPEAKER_0:  They're not messing around.
SPEAKER_0:  But they're like, all right, this is not going to last for long. And you know, the USA, the US and day.
SPEAKER_0:  We didn't even recognize the Soviet Union's legitimacy for a very long time. There were no diplomatic relations. And after a certain point, it's like...
SPEAKER_0:  who's the, if you don't recognize Lenin and Stalin's government, who's the government of this, of Russia or the Soviet Union? Is it the Tsar? Like you have to recognize it. It's just, they're not going anywhere. So that was something that was not.
SPEAKER_0:  I think very...
SPEAKER_0:  predictable. The Great Depression.
SPEAKER_0:  In retrospect, there were certain things that were predictable, but...
SPEAKER_0:  It was not at all the case that it needed to last as long as it did in the states as FDR made it do. So there's all sorts of things. I mean, if they...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, um,
SPEAKER_0:  F
SPEAKER_0:  fought Germany's remilitarization near World War II could have been prevented if you didn't have the Treaty of Versailles.
SPEAKER_0:  Would you have the hyperinflation? Would you have Hitler? These are all, I think-
SPEAKER_0:  choose your own adventure moments where things could have gone in other directions. I don't believe this kind of idea. This is a very Marxist idea.
SPEAKER_0:  that history is inevitable and once you start with certain premises the contradictions kind of unfold. I think it's ridiculous.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel there's power in the Santa Claus outfit.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah?
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, it's a fundamentally communist.
SPEAKER_1:  idea, right?
SPEAKER_1:  How?
SPEAKER_1:  Arbitrary redistribution of wealth.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not redistribution.
SPEAKER_1:  At least I decide who's good and bad. Only I, only I know.
SPEAKER_1:  This.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I am somehow getting funding from someone, right? No?
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, listen, I have so much to teach you, little Michael.
SPEAKER_1:  Workshop.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. And how many people do you think are employed?
SPEAKER_1:  in this workshop. The
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  i don't know how many of them the workshop uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I think the rest of you are gonna have to look into it. No, anyway, and the red colors and everything. Is that the biggest holiday of all time, Christmas? Like just in terms of.
SPEAKER_1:  the intensity of the festivities.
SPEAKER_0:  No, I think Christmas is a very recent-
SPEAKER_0:  phenomenon. I think historically it was not a big deal.
SPEAKER_1:  Now I know in historical case it has not been, but in terms of...
SPEAKER_1:  how much it captivates.
SPEAKER_1:  how intense it is.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess from a capitalist perspective, like how much is going on, how visual it is, how intense it is, how it grabs a whole.
SPEAKER_0:  population. I think it's because the idea of Christmas is
SPEAKER_0:  probably one of the most powerful holiday ideas.
SPEAKER_0:  Easter is probably up there. Easter is obviously up there because you have Christ dying, his resurrection. So that's kind of a big one.
SPEAKER_0:  But Christmas is the symbol of
SPEAKER_0:  brotherhood and kindness and magnanimity. You know, one of the things I despise
SPEAKER_0:  about our culture is this glory and something I'm fighting very heavily with this book or at least attempting to.
SPEAKER_0:  Is this glorification of cynicism?
SPEAKER_0:  This kind of like, oh you like this song, that's cute, stupid.
SPEAKER_0:  Whereas Christmas is the one time of year
SPEAKER_0:  where you could be happy.
SPEAKER_0:  Enjoy us!
SPEAKER_0:  and kind.
SPEAKER_0:  People don't get to roll their eyes at you.
SPEAKER_0:  They get to stop being too cool for school.
SPEAKER_0:  and they get to be like, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  I enjoy your friendship, your...
SPEAKER_0:  my sister, my brother, my dad, my mom, whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  And...
SPEAKER_0:  It was Ayn Rand's favorite holiday.
SPEAKER_0:  I adore it.
SPEAKER_0:  especially Christmas in New York.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's just this idea of like...
SPEAKER_0:  Even though we're called.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's dark outside, you know, it's still this kind of like, it's still cozy.
SPEAKER_0:  And you, and the next, let's hope the next year is, because with, with, with Russians, Dmitrovskaya Sena comes on New Year's.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's kind of like, let's make this next year an even better one. So it's very much the holiday of hope.
SPEAKER_1:  Enjoy.
SPEAKER_1:  and like love for family for.
SPEAKER_0:  Friendship and kindness and benevolence. Yeah
SPEAKER_1:  like almost the whole.
SPEAKER_1:  that whole rat race of...
SPEAKER_1:  Chasing material possessions and all that gets put on hold for beef moment. It's just all goes quiet
SPEAKER_0:  But it's also about giving people material possessions like here, like I value you. This is something that brings you joy.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, you're right in the book, which by the way...
SPEAKER_1:  people should go get buy it right now.
SPEAKER_1:  if you support this podcast.
SPEAKER_1:  Or if you support the ridiculous outfits that Michaels wear.
SPEAKER_1:  Where's?
SPEAKER_1:  The more books you buy, the more outfits he is going to wear.
SPEAKER_0:  I've got two.
SPEAKER_0:  my next two appearances in the show assuming I don't burn this bridge.
SPEAKER_0:  I've got some good one. This bridge.
SPEAKER_1:  It has been burning for a long time.
SPEAKER_1:  We've been going across the road by canoe at this point.
SPEAKER_1:  Next time we're going to be swimming.
SPEAKER_0:  How the hell are you gonna swim? You're made out of lead!
SPEAKER_1:  That's true.
SPEAKER_1:  Sink to the bottom, get dragged across by rope.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, you write in the book, cynics like to lie and call themselves realists.
SPEAKER_1:  Hoping for positive outcomes can thus be dismissed as being naive.
SPEAKER_1:  or utopian.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you elaborate on this point? Just like you said right now, I mean,
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like a-
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if it's a fundamental-
SPEAKER_1:  characteristic of our society today or just
SPEAKER_1:  societies throughout history.
SPEAKER_1:  But there is a cynicism.
SPEAKER_1:  you write in Soviet Union or Zemun.
SPEAKER_1:  Really.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a deep cynicism.
SPEAKER_0:  That was good at the end, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  But there is a cynicism today as well, at least in public discourse. Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  Why does it happen in a-
SPEAKER_1:  How can we fight it?
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it is.
SPEAKER_0:  Easy.
SPEAKER_0:  to be like, eh, everything sucks.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I had my friend Lux, she was a blogger, she was an author.
SPEAKER_0:  She had this great line because we worked in media.
SPEAKER_0:  And she's like, if you're at a party and someone starts talking about a new app or website.
SPEAKER_0:  and you don't know anything about it, just say, Oh, I was on that for a while, it sucked.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's all you need to say. I'm like, Lex, that's a great line. But I think-
SPEAKER_0:  It is.
SPEAKER_0:  And especially, I'm sure you had to, you experienced this as well with your family. I certainly did with mine.
SPEAKER_0:  There is this.
SPEAKER_0:  idea especially in Russian culture but in American culture to some extent as well.
SPEAKER_0:  where if you have aspirations...
SPEAKER_0:  I remember there was this show called Russian Dolls.
SPEAKER_0:  It was.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, I just got it, like the Matryoshka. Okay, I just got it, that's the name, okay. The show is called Russian Dolls. It was about Brighton Beach, which is the Russian Jewish neighborhood in Brooklyn. It was supposed to be their version of Jersey Shore. It was on Lifetime and it had no ratings. And I remember the last four episodes, they had to burn them, so they just ran it through like 8 a.m. to 10 a.m. one day.
SPEAKER_0:  And there was this one scene where the, when the girls, I forget her name, probably Natalia.
SPEAKER_0:  and she'd been in college.
SPEAKER_0:  and she had been.
SPEAKER_0:  wondering which one to major in.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? And this story was so perfect, I'm sure I've told it before.
SPEAKER_0:  and she took an aptitude test.
SPEAKER_0:  and she went with her mom to get like mani-pedis or something.
SPEAKER_0:  And she goes, mom, you know, I've had like 80 majors. I didn't know what I wanted to do.
SPEAKER_0:  And she goes, I took this app to test. It really made sense to me.
SPEAKER_0:  I am going to go to law school. I want to be a lawyer. This is something I enjoy. And the first thing out of her mom's mouth is how are you going to pay for it?
SPEAKER_0:  And the girl, and I really relate it, because if you didn't have this Russian upbringing, you watched it, you would think her reaction was completely insane. She just lost it.
SPEAKER_0:  Just screaming. She's like.
SPEAKER_0:  People pay for law school all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll figure out a way. Why is your first reaction to look for a problem?
SPEAKER_0:  Why is your first response to be like...
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, wait, are you sure you've thought this through? I have been struggling with one problem for years, what I wanted to do for a living. And now like, as soon as I solve this one big problem of identity, your first reaction is like, let's find a new problem. Why is that your instead of let's figure out how we're going to pay for it.
SPEAKER_0:  and that kind of approach.
SPEAKER_0:  Is so.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  deadly and it gnaws at you. I don't like giving people advice because-
SPEAKER_0:  Who the hell am I? And also if I don't know the context of the problem, I'm not informed enough to give advice. But this is a piece of advice that I do for comfort giving. If you are someone who has around you, then you should be aware of the context of the problem.
SPEAKER_0:  people who as soon as you have any accomplishment or any hope
SPEAKER_0:  that their first reaction is to be like, well, what about this?
SPEAKER_0:  you have to get rid of them or sit them down, maybe give them a chance.
SPEAKER_0:  because that is something that is such so-
SPEAKER_0:  demoralizing.
SPEAKER_0:  and it drains you and it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, the example I've used all the time, all the time, all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  I say if you want to be an author.
SPEAKER_0:  You can go to any bookstore.
SPEAKER_0:  and look at all the shitty, shitty books, like The White Pill.
SPEAKER_0:  And you could say to yourself,
SPEAKER_0:  I could be the shitty author.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't have to be Hemingway.
SPEAKER_1:  So people should buy your book just to know.
SPEAKER_1:  It doesn't take much.
SPEAKER_0:  It really does not take much. What shitty writing is all about.
SPEAKER_0:  and boring.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  You could just pick a random-
SPEAKER_1:  random period in history and just write a bunch of crap about it and put a pretty stamp on the cover and just go
SPEAKER_0:  It was pretty. Yeah. Yeah
SPEAKER_0:  But I mean, like for you, right? Like not.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't, I don't mean you let, but. I was raised by the wolves.
SPEAKER_1:  If you
SPEAKER_0:  You
SPEAKER_0:  The wolf bots.
SPEAKER_0:  There's lots of stand-up comedians.
SPEAKER_0:  who aren't.
SPEAKER_0:  Jerry Seinfeld. Yeah. Right? You don't have to be Joe Rogan.
SPEAKER_0:  You could be someone who's got a medium audience.
SPEAKER_0:  and are enjoying it. So like the idea that like something has to be
SPEAKER_0:  You have to be a massive superstar or your failure is also ridiculous, but that's cynicism.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, you can even be a failed comedian like Dave Smith.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I don't this is generic name I came up with as an example.
SPEAKER_1:  I think he has a podcast of some kind. Maybe so...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Not very funny, I don't know why he would call himself a comedian, but-
SPEAKER_0:  UB is being ironic.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm sorry.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, don't you think?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so even then you could do...
SPEAKER_0:  something special. Remember what you did with me in the movie theater.
SPEAKER_1:  What's that?
SPEAKER_1:  I don't, is, oh, you continue. Can you explain the jokes? Cause I can't.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not explaining jokes, I'm wearing lipstick. That's not enough.
SPEAKER_1:  Now I remember what you did to me in a movie theater.
SPEAKER_1:  And you wore lipstick that night too.
SPEAKER_0:  not when I was done.
SPEAKER_1:  People for sure will think this feels like a gay porn.
SPEAKER_0:  Like a very long intro. Because we're not wearing pants.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  There's many reasons why this feels like this and the outfits.
SPEAKER_1:  and just everything about this.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. How would you know?
SPEAKER_1:  I, my friend, I have stories.
SPEAKER_0:  I thought I don't have friends.
SPEAKER_0:  I- this is-
SPEAKER_1:  They're all suspiciously named either Lex or Lux.
SPEAKER_0:  or stuff like that. Like you lack complete creativity.
SPEAKER_0:  just like in the writing of your book. Yeah,
SPEAKER_1:  It's like you didn't even use like a thesaurus for your book. The same words over and over and over.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, the sad thing about the cynicism is like...
SPEAKER_1:  I don't think it's just a Russian thing.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the people... No, let me interrupt you because I didn't finish what you were saying earlier. In America, it's not just a Russian thing. In American culture...
SPEAKER_0:  If you have like a
SPEAKER_0:  sitcom or a musical.
SPEAKER_0:  It's regarded as less legitimate.
SPEAKER_0:  than a drama.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Like if something's got to be about someone struggling.
SPEAKER_0:  or someone's suffering, whereas this is like a joyous, happy story, like maybe something like Pixar, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Like sure they have conflict and they're going for something, but it's overall the
SPEAKER_0:  background the universe is taking in is very joyous and happy. What is regarded?
SPEAKER_0:  artistically.
SPEAKER_0:  as less legitimate.
SPEAKER_0:  than something which is dark and the background is despair.
SPEAKER_0:  And that very subtly.
SPEAKER_0:  sends a very, to me,
SPEAKER_0:  pernicious message.
SPEAKER_0:  that the, you know, that.
SPEAKER_0:  What's real is despair.
SPEAKER_0:  and happiness is the aberration. And I think if you have that as your mindset, you're setting yourself up for maybe not failure, but certainly not happiness.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's in a...
SPEAKER_1:  the figures, the ideas that the culture elevates, but at the local.
SPEAKER_1:  personal life of parents and teachers, that still happens a lot. in russia and here just
SPEAKER_1:  My whole...
SPEAKER_1:  life especially because I'm a weirdo.
SPEAKER_1:  I've been.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of told to...
SPEAKER_1:  Basically be less weird.
SPEAKER_1:  be, uh...
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  There's a kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  sense in where there's a certain path you're supposed to take in life.
SPEAKER_1:  And every time you have a little bit of success on those very specifically defined paths.
SPEAKER_1:  you're pushed to do more and more and more on those paths.
SPEAKER_1:  as opposed to celebrating the full complexity of the weirdo that each one of us is, and I certainly am.
SPEAKER_1:  And I just.
SPEAKER_1:  Teachers.
SPEAKER_1:  even friends.
SPEAKER_1:  and certainly family.
SPEAKER_1:  have constantly been...
SPEAKER_1:  very cynical about
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  my aspirations, my dreams and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  I think that actually created a deeply self-critical...
SPEAKER_1:  Engine in my brain?
SPEAKER_1:  that I think it ultimately was.
SPEAKER_1:  Productive.
SPEAKER_1:  because it was also
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  balanced by just an internal maybe through genetics.
SPEAKER_1:  I have of optimism about the world, of just seeing the beauty in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  It is weird looking back.
SPEAKER_1:  How much do?
SPEAKER_1:  how much people that love me were trying to...
SPEAKER_1:  Bring me down.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. So strange. It's also very hurtful for me because when I graduated college, it was important for me to be self-made and not take money from my family.
SPEAKER_0:  And I remember my grandma, this was a huge argument, an ongoing argument.
SPEAKER_0:  And one time she, you know, as we were leaving, as she was leaving my house, she slipped money in.
SPEAKER_0:  under the door and I threw it out and it made me so angry.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, or like one year for my birthday, she gave me, I think like $500, which was a lot of money, you know, when you're like 22 or 23 and I was so pissed.
SPEAKER_0:  because that.
SPEAKER_0:  told me.
SPEAKER_0:  that they didn't believe that I'd be able to feed myself or make it on my own.
SPEAKER_0:  And I understand their mindset, but it's like...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not.
SPEAKER_0:  I wasn't, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  I never was never hungry. Like maybe I couldn't.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember I'd have to wait on the subway because I couldn't afford a cab.
SPEAKER_0:  But that was a sacrifice I had to make. I had to wait that half hour.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a huge source and remains a source of enormous tension and contention. And I think also...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm sure speaking to your upbringing.
SPEAKER_0:  in their minds, unless you're going into an office, you can't pay the rent. It doesn't make sense.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, so, but there's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just like you said forget the office forget all that
SPEAKER_1:  No matter what.
SPEAKER_1:  There's.
SPEAKER_1:  Always.
SPEAKER_1:  Whatever you accomplish in life, you always do.
SPEAKER_1:  You're always, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Negative.
SPEAKER_1:  about your current position.
SPEAKER_1:  you always come up with another problem.
SPEAKER_1:  Just like you said, I was always, is a self generating problem.
SPEAKER_0:  box.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I remember I-
SPEAKER_0:  didn't speak to my dad for a few years, then I'm like, let me give this guy another chance.
SPEAKER_0:  And in that time period, Harvey Picar, the...
SPEAKER_0:  author of subject of American splendor the movie and author of the series comic books
SPEAKER_0:  He and I became friends and he was writing a graphic novel about me.
SPEAKER_0:  And when I met with my dad, I'm like, oh.
SPEAKER_0:  Someone's writing a book about me. He goes, I know so
SPEAKER_0:  And it was one of those moments where I'm like, wow, you're an asshole.
SPEAKER_0:  and not the kind of asshole I am. You're just like not a good-
SPEAKER_0:  person and I don't know or really at this point care.
SPEAKER_0:  but.
SPEAKER_0:  motivation or if there was no motivation with the visceral emotional reasoning for that.
SPEAKER_0:  but that kind of thing is something I...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, much later now in life.
SPEAKER_0:  have absolutely no.
SPEAKER_0:  tolerance for.
SPEAKER_1:  in my own.
SPEAKER_1:  private life.
SPEAKER_1:  I try to forgive and love those people.
SPEAKER_1:  but it is, there have been a few.
SPEAKER_1:  in my life like this?
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  I think they are incredible people if you allow yourself to see it, but they're flawed.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  I tried to forgive them.
SPEAKER_1:  That said, it is true that-
SPEAKER_1:  uh... the people that are close to you special family have uh... disproportionately psychological effect on you so you have to be very careful
SPEAKER_1:  having them in your life too much.
SPEAKER_1:  Like one thing is to love them.
SPEAKER_1:  and the other is to actually, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Allow yourself to flourish. Surround yourself with people that help you flourish. And like you said, the advice there is really powerful.
SPEAKER_1:  especially early on to have
SPEAKER_1:  people that believe in you.
SPEAKER_1:  in whatever crazy big dreams you have.
SPEAKER_1:  They pat you on the back and say, you got this kid.
SPEAKER_0:  And here's the other thing.
SPEAKER_0:  If you try...
SPEAKER_0:  and you don't make it to that roguin level.
SPEAKER_0:  It's okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, I have several books that I've written.
SPEAKER_0:  that are on my hard drive that have not been published.
SPEAKER_0:  and there were a lot of work.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was really disappointing when they went out and no publishers were interested in it. Maybe I'll publish it one day, maybe I won't.
SPEAKER_0:  point being.
SPEAKER_0:  It's fine, I tried.
SPEAKER_0:  Is it a romance novel? One is, one is a- Circe, Ooo, Ma-
SPEAKER_1:  No
SPEAKER_1:  Does he have a Santa, a guy in a Santa outfit?
SPEAKER_0:  Can you please?
SPEAKER_0:  Stop asking me to send you gay pornography!
SPEAKER_0:  He's calling me up all hours of the night. I need more gay porn. I need some ones. I only have zeros. Yeah. Never enough. Never enough. This one almost got a book deal. This would have been 16 years ago. It was a ladlet novel.
SPEAKER_0:  ah, no one can evacuate
SPEAKER_0:  Ladlet.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like the corn bee.
SPEAKER_0:  What? Nicorn Bee?
SPEAKER_0:  about a boy. So there was a little mini-genre of these books about young men trying to struggle their way through this whole little series of them. Fight Club.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... it is adjacent to that
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, it's not literally lad lit.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like you would write.
SPEAKER_1:  great fight club type novel.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, Fight Club is much, and Chuck Pollin, as my understanding, admitted this, Fight Club is one of the few.
SPEAKER_0:  things where the movie is better than the book.
SPEAKER_1:  all since then.
SPEAKER_1:  But the movie is so iconic.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, for sure.
SPEAKER_1:  but...
SPEAKER_1:  but still isn't there a deeply like philosophical.
SPEAKER_1:  It's kind of like David Foster Wallace novels. Doesn't doesn't it doesn't fight club capture some moment in time?
SPEAKER_0:  That's very kind of... I was hanging out with Kurt Metzger a couple weeks ago, comedian, very failed comedian. Name drop. Yeah, Kurt. Watch out. And he had this great story. He was hanging out with Patrice O'Neill, the late comedian. Name drop. With the great comics of all.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I think Patrice goes, Kurt was talking about how much she liked the book or the movie Fight Club and Patrice is like-
SPEAKER_0:  That is the whitest book on earth. He goes, your problem in life is you don't have enough violence. Your proper life. You need someone to beat you up?
SPEAKER_0:  That's not a problem for me.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it wasn't, I mean, but-
SPEAKER_1:  still it's it is a very white book but it still captures a kind of anger and angst
SPEAKER_1:  and a certain subculture in society. That's really powerful. Probably led to.
SPEAKER_1:  in some part of the thing you wrote about and then you write.
SPEAKER_0:  Sure. I mean, it was this kind of like, there's that line in the movie where...
SPEAKER_0:  Edward Norton says I'm a 30 year old boy.
SPEAKER_0:  this kind of question of what is it, sorry to be Matt Walsh, but what does it mean to be a man, right? What does masculinity mean? Why are so many men so at such a young age?
SPEAKER_0:  Feeling so lost?
SPEAKER_0:  this idea that like if I fill my house with nice furniture, that's still not going to be fulfilling to anyone.
SPEAKER_0:  Matt what was Matt what?
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_0:  He's from the Daily Wire, he just did a documentary called What is a Woman?
SPEAKER_0:  Can you explain? I don't know who he is. So Matt Walsh is someone who works with Daily Wire. Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  And he just recently did a documentary called, What is a Woman? I think it was called. And he went out to lots of people working in gender theory and that's the thing. And he asked them to define, and he went to the Messiah.
SPEAKER_0:  in Africa, the tribe.
SPEAKER_0:  and to talk to people about transgenderism, non-binary, which is a word I know you hate. And the documentary was a...
SPEAKER_0:  Surprisingly well done.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that like a...
SPEAKER_1:  passive aggressive compliment.
SPEAKER_1:  Surprisingly well done.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, because Matt is very, um...
SPEAKER_0:  aggressive on Twitter. We follow each other.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  There was a lot of opportunities.
SPEAKER_0:  in this film.
SPEAKER_0:  for him to really be like, oh.
SPEAKER_0:  And instead, to his credit, he let the people speak.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's possible to edit a certain way of course, it was obviously edited.
SPEAKER_0:  When he just asked them, can you just define woman for me and playing dumb? We're not playing dumb, just saying, what's your opinion? A lot of the people he was speaking to were getting extremely...
SPEAKER_0:  uh... agitated so it worked in that kind of
SPEAKER_0:  context as well.
SPEAKER_0:  It was not his usual style.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of which.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you ever regret your behavior on Twitter?
SPEAKER_0:  There were a couple of times.
SPEAKER_0:  but very rarely.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you describe the big strategy before we dive back into the October Revolution?
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  My strategy of-
SPEAKER_1:  strategy or is it?
SPEAKER_1:  Does it come from the heart?
SPEAKER_1:  or does it come from the brain?
SPEAKER_0:  It comes from...
SPEAKER_0:  I want to have fun.
SPEAKER_0:  That's literally what it comes down to. It's like this is-
SPEAKER_1:  Girls just wanna have fun.
SPEAKER_0:  Are you drunk? What is in there?
SPEAKER_0:  Thanks for watching!
SPEAKER_0:  I'm very cheeky.
SPEAKER_1:  Have the holiday spirit, even though it's not the holidays.
SPEAKER_0:  That's eggnog. Delirious. I did not.
SPEAKER_1:  sleep much last night. I've been, uh, which is I think the second time we talk or the third time the second time.
SPEAKER_1:  I stayed up almost.
SPEAKER_0:  all night.
SPEAKER_0:  so I know when you're leaving or coming home.
SPEAKER_1:  My camera points at your bedroom.
SPEAKER_1:  from the inside. So you can see where it's wrinkling. I'll close you that now.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Let me ask you this because this is something that's been bothering me. There was a chair that you threw out.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm broken.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was looking at my camera and I'm like, let me see when he threw this out.
SPEAKER_0:  And then one time you went to the garbage and you adjusted it to make it stick out of the garbage even more. What were you doing there?
SPEAKER_0:  Was I? Oh, to-
SPEAKER_1:  to make sure that people know there's a chair in there.
SPEAKER_0:  Is that really what you- what? Well, like the garbage person-
SPEAKER_1:  they'd notice the chair so they don't get.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I always think I don't want them to get like hurt.
SPEAKER_0:  or whatever. Oh, OK.
SPEAKER_1:  they open the thing it's like
SPEAKER_0:  Duh chair.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know what I was thinking.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, it was really odd.
SPEAKER_1:  know how to get rid of a chair it was broken it was cracked and I didn't it was
SPEAKER_0:  So Twitter for me, I-
SPEAKER_0:  My point is to have fun.
SPEAKER_0:  It's also fun to kind of smack down people who I regard as bad actors.
SPEAKER_0:  And also kind of to promote news that I find interesting that maybe isn't as prominently part of the culture as it might otherwise be.
SPEAKER_1:  You think sometimes you draw.
SPEAKER_1:  too broadly the category of people that are bad actors and then some
SPEAKER_1:  Thereby
SPEAKER_1:  sort of adding to the.
SPEAKER_1:  the mockery and the cynicism in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think mockery and cynicism are at all synonymous.
SPEAKER_0:  I think cynicism means everyone sucks. I don't think everyone sucks. I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  It is.
SPEAKER_0:  undeniable that a lot of people suck.
SPEAKER_1:  What if I told you...
SPEAKER_1:  Most people don't suck.
SPEAKER_1:  Could you?
SPEAKER_1:  Could you steal me on the case that most people don't?
SPEAKER_0:  I can do it in a cynical way, honestly. It's a quasi-cynical way. I think most people are neither here nor there.
SPEAKER_0:  Most people just kind of go with the flow.
SPEAKER_0:  They're amiable.
SPEAKER_0:  human beings are social creatures. They want to get along.
SPEAKER_0:  They don't want to cause problems. They don't have the capacity to be the target of a problem.
SPEAKER_0:  So, most people, I mean, if most people sucked...
SPEAKER_0:  then going anywhere would be an excruciating ordeal, right? like literally any like
SPEAKER_0:  The airport's annoying, but if most people sucked, it would really be annoying. Going to the supermarket would be really annoying. So I don't think most people suck.
SPEAKER_0:  but I do think that in...
SPEAKER_0:  public discourse.
SPEAKER_0:  There are lots of people.
SPEAKER_0:  Who are?
SPEAKER_0:  Dishonest.
SPEAKER_0:  about their agenda. For example, if I'm, you know, I could be a
SPEAKER_0:  someone who has promoting a certain ideology.
SPEAKER_0:  But I'm-
SPEAKER_0:  in the payroll of a candidate.
SPEAKER_0:  Or, you know, my think tank needs this to happen or I'm being paid for something like that. So that sort of thing, I think, happens all the time. There's the line I have in the book, Upton Sinclair.
SPEAKER_0:  I forgot how he exact- he word exactly, but it's very hard to convince someone of something if his payroll depends on him not being convinced of it, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So I think things like that are... The thing I'm really excited about with what Elon's doing with Twitter...
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm just ecstatic about this.
SPEAKER_0:  is
SPEAKER_0:  to have the context now.
SPEAKER_0:  So you'll have a politician making a claim and they're going to award it in certain ways. This is like my favorite example.
SPEAKER_0:  is when people are like, if you look at the years 2002 to 2020, terrorism in America, it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  Did anything happen in 2001?
SPEAKER_0:  Is there a reason you just coincidentally started in 2002? Like things like that.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  When people are manipulating things to force an outcome that they want and to promote an idea that they want disingenuously, to have that underneath that in Twitter now where the audience provides context, I think is something extremely useful and it's a great way to nip propaganda in the bud.
SPEAKER_0:  and propaganda group.
SPEAKER_0:  pervades the entire political spectrum, of course.
SPEAKER_1:  The interesting thing about Twitter is also the discussion about free speech and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  Interesting to discuss free speech.
SPEAKER_1:  and the freedom of the press from the context of the Soviet Union. Sure.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's return to the October Revolution at Lenin.
SPEAKER_1:  what was the actual revolution what uh... who was when it was some interesting aspects of this
SPEAKER_1:  this human being and also this moment in history that stand out to you that are important to understand
SPEAKER_0:  I think the...
SPEAKER_0:  Interesting thing about Lenin.
SPEAKER_0:  Is he?
SPEAKER_0:  Was this zealot?
SPEAKER_0:  And he was a visionary?
SPEAKER_0:  and he really kinda meant it.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I'm skipping ahead a little bit, but Lenin...
SPEAKER_0:  also with someone who was strategic.
SPEAKER_0:  So at a certain point when they were trying to advance communism throughout the Soviet Union
SPEAKER_0:  and the costs were outweighing the benefits. He did a strategic retreat. He did the new economic policy. He had a rise of kind of these.
SPEAKER_0:  small capitalists coming back, you could hire people again.
SPEAKER_0:  And for the hardcore...
SPEAKER_0:  people in the Soviet Union, hardcore communists. This was a huge betrayal. It's a step back.
SPEAKER_0:  He didn't do it because he was some kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  crypto capitalist, he did it because he's like, all right, we know where we got to get to, but we have to go at a certain pace and we have to adjust as we go along. So to have someone who is that much of an ideologue.
SPEAKER_0:  and that much of a visionary.
SPEAKER_0:  but still to have any.
SPEAKER_0:  element of pragmatism to him.
SPEAKER_0:  is I think a very rare.
SPEAKER_0:  combination.
SPEAKER_1:  And that pragmatism, do you think that's ultimately where things go wrong?
SPEAKER_1:  Sort of, um...
SPEAKER_1:  That's where you sacrifice the ideas.
SPEAKER_0:  Pragmatism in this case was good because by taking a step back
SPEAKER_0:  You know, he kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll give himself some breathing room.
SPEAKER_0:  to allow the revolution to continue to win the civil war. There was a big moment where Germany, it's just there's lots of like funny anecdotes that I learned while researching this book. So, you know, they were.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, Germany and Russia, they were negotiating, uh, stale, a ceasefire because they wanted Germany wanted Russia out of the war. And basically Germany was like, all right, you will let you leave.
SPEAKER_0:  but you have to sign this treaty and basically hand over all this land that we're currently occupying.
SPEAKER_0:  It was just parts of Ukraine, parts of Poland.
SPEAKER_0:  And Lenin tells Trotsky to stall. He's just run the clock because he was of the belief.
SPEAKER_0:  that now that they've taken power in Russia, you're gonna have a worldwide workers revolution. Just like, just stall them.
SPEAKER_0:  And he stalled, he stalled and at a certain point Germany's like, all right, you're signing this tomorrow or we're invading.
SPEAKER_0:  And Trotsky basically said, yeah, so we're leaving the war.
SPEAKER_0:  But we're not signing anything and the Germans are like...
SPEAKER_0:  What? I can't well that's what we're doing so hey
SPEAKER_0:  And basically, eventually he had to sign the treaty and cede.
SPEAKER_0:  huge parts of land and a lot of money.
SPEAKER_0:  And this was a very.
SPEAKER_0:  a precarious moment for him to maintain control of Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  And people were telling him like.
SPEAKER_0:  You've lost huge amounts of territory.
SPEAKER_0:  blown it, you should be in jail, and he's like, watch your mouth.
SPEAKER_0:  Because if you look for the future, it'll be clear which one of us is more likely to be the one ending up in jail. And he was absolutely right.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, this was Trotsky or Lenin saying- This was Lenin saying this to Karl Raddick.
SPEAKER_0:  So who are these?
SPEAKER_1:  Who is Trotsky? Who is Lenin?
SPEAKER_1:  Who's Stalin? What is some interesting...
SPEAKER_1:  aspects of all of this. What it sort of just to linger on it.
SPEAKER_1:  the personalities, the ideas that are important.
SPEAKER_0:  Well Trotsky came late to Bolshevism. He was really the brains.
SPEAKER_0:  in many ways of the October Revolution. He was an amazing strategist.
SPEAKER_0:  He never forgot.
SPEAKER_0:  that he was an amazing strategist, had a very high opinion of himself.
SPEAKER_1:  And by the way, the October revolution, 1917.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a key moment.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Of course, the Russian Revolution lasted a long time.
SPEAKER_1:  but...
SPEAKER_1:  This was a key moment.
SPEAKER_1:  of uh...
SPEAKER_1:  but a phase shift towards success.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Bolsheviks. Well, that was the moment. That was like, all right, we are the government now. And now we have to make it's, you know, like Thomas Jefferson said, I think it was Thomas Jefferson or no, it's Ben Franklin, a republic, if you can keep it, it's like, all right.
SPEAKER_0:  We've made our own kind of government if we can keep it, because that was the big question. You had an international blockade. You had the white armies, the czarist forces who want to restore czarism, or at least the parliament from right before Lenin took over. So this was a big kind of no one's.
SPEAKER_0:  was, you know, in some ways it was like the 2016 election. It's like, all right.
SPEAKER_0:  We vote in Trump.
SPEAKER_0:  What's this gonna look like? Like no one, no one!
SPEAKER_0:  had any idea what a Trump presidency was going to look like. All we knew was this guy's on Twitter running his mouth, he's insulting people, and he's had all these views, some are over here, some are over there.
SPEAKER_1:  And the funny thing is the Russians hacked both elections.
SPEAKER_0:  See
SPEAKER_0:  It was Putin and the gremlin.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Trotsky was, you know, Lenin's right-hand man.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and he was, you know, enormous. And to this day, he remains this kind of figure.
SPEAKER_0:  Who is?
SPEAKER_0:  supposedly.
SPEAKER_0:  AIN'T
SPEAKER_0:  less authoritarian.
SPEAKER_0:  anti-Stalinist version of communism that people can endorse.
SPEAKER_0:  And Stalin of course was Lenin's successor. At first there was a triumvirate.
SPEAKER_0:  running Russia as Lenin was recuperating from strokes.
SPEAKER_0:  then very quickly, not very quickly, but gradually, then suddenly, Stalin.
SPEAKER_0:  became an absolute dictator and he had a series of
SPEAKER_0:  and so on and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  which solidified his control over the country.
SPEAKER_1:  And of course for Stalin.
SPEAKER_1:  Trotsky later but throughout.
SPEAKER_1:  as you write seem to almost take on a supernatural character.
SPEAKER_1:  wherein everything that went wrong in the USSR was due not just.
SPEAKER_1:  to his views, but to his direct orders from abroad.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  Of course, George Orwell brilliantly in probably my favorite book of his, which is Animal Farm and also 1984.
SPEAKER_1:  portray Trotsky as a-
SPEAKER_1:  as snowball and animal farming.
SPEAKER_1:  Immanuel Goldstein in 1984.
SPEAKER_1:  is this embodiment of this evil that the woes have to be fighting?
SPEAKER_1:  then you need that in order to hold.
SPEAKER_1:  Hold on to power, you always have to have that enemy.
SPEAKER_0:  Right. So that, I mean, that's something I talk about in the white pill as well. When things start going wrong, they always have to have scapegoats. Right? And there's this Russian, you know, what the Russians like to do is you can't say things out loud, but if you make jokes, you can say unspeakable truths.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's this one anecdote where there's a Russian leader.
SPEAKER_0:  and things are going bad.
SPEAKER_0:  and he looks in his drawer and there were two letters from his predecessor.
SPEAKER_0:  And he opens the first letter in a panic and the letter says, you know, for advice and the letter says blame everything on me.
SPEAKER_0:  So he goes out there and he's like, oh, my predecessor sucked, he was terrible, blah, blah, it's his fault. And everyone's like, okay. And then there's a calamity again. And he's like, oh crap.
SPEAKER_0:  So he goes back at his desk.
SPEAKER_0:  And he reads the second one and it says, sit down and write two letters.
SPEAKER_0:  So when things start going wrong as they...
SPEAKER_0:  constantly did throughout the history of the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, or any.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, totalitarian, authoritarian country.
SPEAKER_0:  it's someone has to be to blame. since we know.
SPEAKER_0:  that our ideology is true.
SPEAKER_0:  scientifically true. If it's not working in reality given the perfection of the ideology, someone must be intentionally
SPEAKER_0:  undermining it and causing the disconnect.
SPEAKER_0:  between thought and reality. And in the Soviet Union, there were, I think it was the Kulaks at one point, then it was the Wreckers.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, the doctors, it was just different. The capital, there was always someone to Antrock ski, uh, was called a fascist and was accused of plotting with Hitler and all this other stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  And you also write, the problem with communism is that eventually you run out of possible scape boats.
SPEAKER_1:  Skip boats.
SPEAKER_1:  Kip boats, you run out of boats.
SPEAKER_1:  You two are out of boats. Who's going to carry them?
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, eventually run out of possible skeg.
SPEAKER_1:  Goats.
SPEAKER_1:  It's my second language, this English thing.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm a failed podcaster. I'm a failure.
SPEAKER_1:  Eventually you run out of possible escape goats for failure, at which point acknowledging or even noticing that something was wrong itself becomes a form of treason.
SPEAKER_0:  I saw that in North Korea, right? Wherever you went in North Korea.
SPEAKER_0:  something was wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  So if you have four buttons for the elevator, one will be mismatched.
SPEAKER_0:  Every wall had a crack.
SPEAKER_0:  Every floor had a stain.
SPEAKER_0:  The bathroom would be rusted through when you want to flush the urinal.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you are someone who points this out...
SPEAKER_0:  Your troublemaker.
SPEAKER_0:  And you're, oh, you're, oh, you're saying something's wrong. You're criticizing the operation. You're, you're first of all, you're, you're threatening the person who's in charge because now they're incompetent and now that's a big red flag for them.
SPEAKER_0:  But second, if you're just going around...
SPEAKER_0:  saying this is wrong, this is wrong, this is wrong, even if it's objectively true.
SPEAKER_0:  You're a troublemaker and you're a counter-revolutionary. So at a certain point, everyone just has to put on blinders.
SPEAKER_0:  and pretend that everything is fine. One example I use in the book, an extreme example, was there was a photography professor.
SPEAKER_0:  and he pointed out his class.
SPEAKER_0:  and he was an older man, that before the revolution, the quality of photographic paper was better and he was, I think, executed.
SPEAKER_0:  for this heresy. So yeah, you have to pretend there was, I just, I'm reading a book right now about the Chinese.
SPEAKER_0:  Cultural Revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  And there was an academic, I forget his name, Hugh Shee, I think, and he points out that in these countries...
SPEAKER_0:  not only do you not have freedom of speech.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't have freedom of silence.
SPEAKER_0:  You can't just sit there quietly. You have to say how great things are and how much you're enjoying and how wonderful they are instead of just keeping quiet because if you keep quiet that's suspicious.
SPEAKER_0:  I had those, um...
SPEAKER_0:  They're always singing those songs about how happy they are and how great everything is. And if everyone else is singing, who are you to not sing?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, those pictures, especially when, you know, when it's Stalin giving speeches and everyone is applauding.
SPEAKER_1:  any dictator and you don't want to be the...
SPEAKER_1:  The first person that stopped.
SPEAKER_0:  stops applauding.
SPEAKER_0:  And why'd you stop clapping? You don't like Stalin?
SPEAKER_1:  Just imagine being one of those people clapping.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's the thing. They always had a sword over their head and they had, but they all had a lot of blood on their hands too. It's a very, very precarious life.
SPEAKER_1:  But there's also...
SPEAKER_1:  I mean 1984 does a good job of this.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  What is that, like two minutes of hate or something like this?
SPEAKER_1:  You lose yourself in the hysteria of it. There's some level of which...
SPEAKER_1:  At first.
SPEAKER_1:  It's, you're sacrificing your basic individualistic.
SPEAKER_1:  ability to think.
SPEAKER_1:  but then you get lost in this kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  wave of emotion.
SPEAKER_1:  and you give into it.
SPEAKER_1:  You allow yourself, it's like a mix of fear.
SPEAKER_1:  and then anger, and then you direct that anger towards.
SPEAKER_1:  like Snowball or Trotsky or whoever the-
SPEAKER_1:  And like.
SPEAKER_0:  What is that? You're also losing yourself in the crowd. Yeah, you're losing- Because you're like, it's not just I'm angry, everyone I know, we're all angry together, so you really are becoming a part of something bigger than yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  and having this kind of communal very-
SPEAKER_0:  emotional experience.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like the opposite of thanks of Christmas, right? Christmas, we're all together.
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone's sharing their joy, everyone's sharing their love.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the opposite, literally the opposite. Like everyone's together sharing their hate and anger and rage.
SPEAKER_0:  but you're all kind of having a mind meld.
SPEAKER_1:  but I wonder what it's like to be an independent thinker in those moments.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, allow yourself to-
SPEAKER_0:  Well, we know.
SPEAKER_0:  Because there were a lot of them and they were all...
SPEAKER_0:  hudnished enormously.
SPEAKER_0:  so they can be noticed.
SPEAKER_0:  You can notice them. Oh yeah. You even notice it in America. America is a free country, but when people start asking too many questions, it's like, where are you going with this?
SPEAKER_0:  You know, like if you're in an office even in a corporate setting.
SPEAKER_0:  You're a troublemaker. You're just, you know, you're making problems for everyone. Why can't you be normal?
SPEAKER_0:  Why can't you be just like everybody else?
SPEAKER_0:  So people do not like having to be made to think.
SPEAKER_0:  And they certainly...
SPEAKER_0:  despise having to be made to justify themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  because that's a threat to their status and to their power and this applies in totalitarianism or applies to
SPEAKER_0:  You know, Dunder Mifflin.
SPEAKER_1:  I still can't believe you're wearing lipstick.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... goes to show you can
SPEAKER_1:  lipstick on a pig.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like a snowball.
SPEAKER_0:  I think you've just been on a bender, that's what I think.
SPEAKER_1:  It's been rough. It's been rough. It's been rough.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel kind of...
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like I can be myself in this outfit. I honestly feel like I could just go around in this outfit and um...
SPEAKER_1:  Just be weird.
SPEAKER_1:  because everyone will accept you if you're wearing a Santa outfit.
SPEAKER_1:  You can say anything in a Santa outfit, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Have you seen Bad Santa?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that's it. Exactly. You can't say anything. My Fox, Dick.
SPEAKER_1:  How did Stalin come to power?
SPEAKER_1:  If we return back to.
SPEAKER_1:  those early days.
SPEAKER_1:  post the October Revolution with Lenin and Trotsky.
SPEAKER_1:  and Stalin.
SPEAKER_1:  How did he come to power?
SPEAKER_0:  So what Stalin did very cleverly, Stalin was, you know, he worked the system.
SPEAKER_0:  he was very much in the background.
SPEAKER_0:  And what he did better than Trotsky is he was much more a politician.
SPEAKER_0:  He was a gladhander.
SPEAKER_0:  He made friends within the party. He made people feel respected and appreciated.
SPEAKER_0:  and Len entrusted him.
SPEAKER_0:  When after Lenin's stroke, Stalin was basically the one who was keeping track of him. Lenin asked Stalin at one point to kill him.
SPEAKER_0:  because after the strokes using capacitated style and talked him out of it, but...
SPEAKER_0:  At the same time Len was like, if I need someone killed, like this is who I need to talk to. You know, Stalin, if you look up photos of him when he was young, he was a stud, he was a gangster, he was a bank robber.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, and.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, he basically worked the system and you had the Trotskyites on one hand, who are much more to the left.
SPEAKER_0:  Stalin's big.
SPEAKER_0:  I would guess I would call it a heresy.
SPEAKER_0:  was he put forth the idea of socialism in one country.
SPEAKER_0:  Whereas, like, we're just going to make it work here in what became the Soviet Union. The Trotsky idea.
SPEAKER_0:  and this is really kind of the Marxist idea, is that the workers revolution has to be worldwide.
SPEAKER_0:  This is just a worldwide kind of new era of humanity.
SPEAKER_0:  where Stalin's like, no, no, no, we're just gonna make it here and then later.
SPEAKER_0:  behind what became the Iron Curtain.
SPEAKER_0:  But this was
SPEAKER_0:  sure this was an ideological division between the two.
SPEAKER_0:  What happens in totalitarian countries, it happens in any kind of like, you know, when you have intermingling of like religion and government.
SPEAKER_0:  things that are.
SPEAKER_0:  like ideological disputes, like the Aryan heresy. The Aryan heresy in Christianity is that Christ is subordinate to God the Father, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Whereas the contemporary Orthodox version, it's one God and three persons, excuse me. So they're all co-equal aspects of God in heaven.
SPEAKER_0:  but that was an excuse to be like, you guys are evil, you're on the side of the devil, we're going to kill you.
SPEAKER_0:  These little-
SPEAKER_0:  disputes about ideas are often a convenient cover.
SPEAKER_0:  for people to have a power struggle.
SPEAKER_0:  in the guise of being like, it's not that I'm about wanting to be more powerful, I'm just on the side of the truth and you're speaking lies and that's dangerous to the revolution or to the true faith.
SPEAKER_0:  So he squeezed.
SPEAKER_0:  But the thing is Trotsky had the seeds of his own defeat.
SPEAKER_0:  because per Trotsky
SPEAKER_0:  The party is always right.
SPEAKER_0:  You cannot be right against the party, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So if you have this kind of party structure...
SPEAKER_0:  And the.
SPEAKER_0:  Hardy is saying...
SPEAKER_0:  You're wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  As an individual, you are wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  Because the collective is what makes decisions. The collective, the workers, are who have the knowledge.
SPEAKER_0:  and the information and it is important for you to.
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  Subordinate.
SPEAKER_0:  your selfishness, your individualism to this greater good. in so that, just to summarize.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of set himself up in many ways.
SPEAKER_0:  Is it clear to you why tra-
SPEAKER_1:  You just explained that he set himself up, but you can see how.
SPEAKER_1:  Different ideologies can be used.
SPEAKER_1:  to achieve different ends.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there another alternative possible trajectory where Trotsky could have been?
SPEAKER_1:  of the head of the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  It would be very hard because he was Jewish. So when they were seizing power,
SPEAKER_0:  Trotsky explicitly said, I can't be in charge, I'm Jewish.
SPEAKER_0:  So the Soviet Union remained extremely anti-Semitic.
SPEAKER_0:  One, the reason so many Jews became communists in the Soviet Union because the promise was once the communists took over, we're not going to have pilgrims anymore. Because once you had these Jewish ghettos, you were going to be a Jew.
SPEAKER_0:  and under the permission or encouragement of the Tsar,
SPEAKER_0:  Just gangs of people go through killing, raping, robbing, stealing, rioting for days. And just a complete massacre. And the idea is like under communism, everyone's going to be equal. We're not going to have this anymore. They still had it, but-
SPEAKER_0:  to a lesser extent.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Since Trotsky was Jewish, his real name is Lev Bronstein.
SPEAKER_0:  You can't you-
SPEAKER_0:  It was almost impossible.
SPEAKER_0:  to have a scenario where he was going to be in charge. And Stalin fed into that to some extent.
SPEAKER_0:  Also this kind of idea of Jewish internationalism. It's like, okay, he doesn't really have loyalty to Russia. And many of the people who were Jewish.
SPEAKER_0:  who were high up in Stalin's.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  government administration.
SPEAKER_0:  They very much had to prove their loyalty.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... to communism as opposed to judaism
SPEAKER_1:  Throughout the 20th century, what was the relationship?
SPEAKER_1:  between communism.
SPEAKER_1:  And, um...
SPEAKER_1:  Jews in the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_1:  What?
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of antisemitism, the ups and downs of antisemitism. It seems like it lessened
SPEAKER_1:  It was lesser and greater.
SPEAKER_1:  in different parts of the 20th century.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it's the kind of thing where...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  If something was bad, there's this Russian rhyme.
SPEAKER_0:  If there is no water in the tap, who drank it?
SPEAKER_0:  Like, if there's no water in the sink, who drank it? Did you call the Jews?
SPEAKER_0:  So if something goes wrong, there's just a convenient historical scapegoat. It's the juice vault.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  This is something that's towards the end of his life very much, and this was after World War II.
SPEAKER_0:  Stalin was getting ready for another kind of series of programs. All these Jews were getting kicked out of their jobs.
SPEAKER_0:  Jewish doctors were getting sent to the Far East instead of being in cities.
SPEAKER_0:  the newspapers started talking about rootless cosmopolitans, which was a term the Nazis also used.
SPEAKER_0:  to kind of regard Jews as others or as aliens.
SPEAKER_0:  And this was going to be, and they were very clever about it.
SPEAKER_0:  Improvda, they would, and I talk about this in the white pill.
SPEAKER_0:  improv that there were articles, letters to the editor. They were like.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, things are getting so anti-semitic.
SPEAKER_0:  We really should round up all the Jews and send them elsewhere for their own safety. So they were kind of setting the the
SPEAKER_0:  ground rules or the...
SPEAKER_0:  basis.
SPEAKER_0:  to have this sort of program come back, but.
SPEAKER_0:  spoiler alert, Stalin dies.
SPEAKER_0:  and immediately.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  All of this gets reversed and the new administration...
SPEAKER_0:  rehabilitates the doctors who were accused of trying to hurt him and all this other sort of thing.
SPEAKER_1:  What is it about the scapegoat?
SPEAKER_1:  in society. Are we always going to be looking for scapegoats?
SPEAKER_1:  What do you learn from human nature that this seems to keep happening?
SPEAKER_0:  I think there's a book called The Nurture Assumption.
SPEAKER_0:  and I discussed this in the new write and what the author learned
SPEAKER_0:  is that humans define themselves by opposition.
SPEAKER_0:  So if you have a group of.
SPEAKER_0:  and its kids and adults.
SPEAKER_0:  The kids will see themselves as kids because we're as opposed to adults.
SPEAKER_0:  If the adults leave.
SPEAKER_0:  the kids see themselves as boys and girls.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not a girl, I'm a boy, I'm not a boy, I'm a girl. So they divide.
SPEAKER_0:  So this idea.
SPEAKER_0:  which is a very lefty idea.
SPEAKER_0:  that human beings naturally all get along is not accurate. The best example of this is
SPEAKER_0:  Look after 9-11. Look where there's a war.
SPEAKER_0:  Nothing unites a popula- it's not like when times are thriving.
SPEAKER_0:  that everyone's all working together when things are bad and there's an enemy.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it's the Japanese of Pearl Harbor. It's Al-Qaeda.
SPEAKER_0:  That's when everyone really comes together because now we have someone to be against.
SPEAKER_0:  So there will always be.
SPEAKER_0:  someone has to be the out group.
SPEAKER_0:  and we have to be the in-group as opposed to them.
SPEAKER_1:  BUT
SPEAKER_1:  There's a viciousness.
SPEAKER_1:  to the actions you take.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... towards the outgroup
SPEAKER_1:  that varies throughout history. Yes
SPEAKER_1:  Some.
SPEAKER_1:  like the degree of viciousness can cross.
SPEAKER_1:  the line towards atrocities, towards genocide. Right. And that's the question of in.
SPEAKER_1:  Why does this sometimes do that?
SPEAKER_1:  Why does it sometimes cross into genocide?
SPEAKER_1:  I understand it's a useful thing to have the other to blame in this world.
SPEAKER_1:  especially when times are rough.
SPEAKER_1:  but why does that sometimes?
SPEAKER_1:  Letus of action.
SPEAKER_1:  that says I'm going to murder.
SPEAKER_1:  well to torture
SPEAKER_0:  together.
SPEAKER_0:  question really is why sometimes it doesn't.
SPEAKER_0:  Right. One of the things I learned when I was doing the new write.
SPEAKER_0:  is a lot of the uh
SPEAKER_0:  Nazis, using that term loosely speaking, you're Nazis, they make the point that like, oh...
SPEAKER_0:  When the Holocaust happened, it really wasn't that big of a deal, and that only became a big deal in the decades later.
SPEAKER_0:  And this just shows the power of Jewish influence. And I'm like.
SPEAKER_0:  This to me is.
SPEAKER_0:  a great thing. It's a great thing that we sat down.
SPEAKER_0:  pretty recently historically.
SPEAKER_0:  And we're like, wait a minute.
SPEAKER_0:  Guys
SPEAKER_0:  When we have a war.
SPEAKER_0:  or we have Conquest.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't have to just...
SPEAKER_0:  start killing everyone. Like this is something that's bad and wrong and-
SPEAKER_0:  Certainly in the last.
SPEAKER_0:  60 years, 70 years, this is something that people have come to take for granted. But that wasn't the case before, it would always be.
SPEAKER_0:  or not always, but often if you conquer, you just.
SPEAKER_0:  go wild and just start slaughtering.
SPEAKER_0:  Massive people.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, it's, um...
SPEAKER_0:  Who's the guy from, um...
SPEAKER_0:  Harvard, and he- Steven Pinker. Sorry, I forgot his name.
SPEAKER_0:  So he just talks about like, you know, we know.
SPEAKER_0:  This is one of the reasons also why.
SPEAKER_0:  There was so much skepticism.
SPEAKER_0:  when the Holocaust started because this was regarded as something that was barbaric. This is from the Middle Ages, from the biblical times. We don't do this anymore. We're civilized now.
SPEAKER_0:  So genocide is.
SPEAKER_0:  historically the norm.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's also harder to pull it off.
SPEAKER_0:  emotionally.
SPEAKER_0:  when you have the visuals.
SPEAKER_0:  and when you have the audio.
SPEAKER_0:  and when you have the voices.
SPEAKER_0:  of the people being slaughtered. We don't know, you know, if this was 2000 years ago and people, you know, in the Bible, they go kill this group, go kill that group.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't have their names, we don't have their visuals, we don't have anything. But when you see-
SPEAKER_0:  someone being like, you know, the.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a book about, I think, the Rwandan genocide.
SPEAKER_0:  and the title is, We regret to inform you that tomorrow we will be executed with all of our families like a telegram.
SPEAKER_0:  And like when you get a telegram like this, it's very different than reading some history book about the Assyrians killed the Phoenicians. It's like, I don't know who this is. I don't know who that is. Right?
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I think this is something that has changed very recently. It was this kind of-
SPEAKER_0:  Interesting moment just that speaks to the
SPEAKER_0:  the way technology has liberated people from violence.
SPEAKER_0:  Kristallnacht, which was a moment in the lead up to the Holocaust.
SPEAKER_0:  where basically, with Hitler's blessing, you had a nationwide burning of Jewish...
SPEAKER_0:  businesses.
SPEAKER_0:  Synagogues burnt down.
SPEAKER_0:  And Kaiser Wilhelm.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, you know, the Kaiser.
SPEAKER_0:  He said, for the first time in my life, I'm embarrassed to be a German.
SPEAKER_0:  But that was a moment where worldwide...
SPEAKER_0:  Even plenty of people who did not think very highly of Jewish people were like,
SPEAKER_0:  This is.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, rap. This is a complete nightmare.
SPEAKER_0:  200 years ago, 100 years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  maybe not literally a Kristallnacht, but.
SPEAKER_0:  There's an out group and we hate them and we're going to kill them and it's fine.
SPEAKER_1:  Anything is even.
SPEAKER_1:  More difficult now.
SPEAKER_1:  with the internet.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes. Do that kind of thing. Yeah, I'm not, now, more difficult doesn't mean it doesn't happen, or it can't happen. I'm not saying that at all.
SPEAKER_0:  But I'm saying...
SPEAKER_0:  We know a lot about what's going on in North Korea, you know, probably the most secretive country on earth. There's a lot of atrocities in Eritrea.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... which is kind of known so i think
SPEAKER_0:  It also, it's also.
SPEAKER_0:  Like if you think about it, if you're-
SPEAKER_0:  how many years ago, 300 years ago, you only know the people in your village and they're all probably gonna look like you so on and so forth
SPEAKER_0:  Whereas now, if I'm on social media and there's someone from any country...
SPEAKER_0:  and maybe their picture looks a little different they could use the same anime picture as somebody else
SPEAKER_0:  but they're putting forth their ideas.
SPEAKER_0:  you do see the humanity in them and you do see a sense of familiarity and a familial
SPEAKER_0:  bond with them.
SPEAKER_0:  And when you hear about these things, you know, when I, again, like I did, when I did Dear Reader,
SPEAKER_0:  No one.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was on Al Qaeda and I was on Alex Jones.
SPEAKER_0:  No one pushed back.
SPEAKER_0:  about like.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, the North Koreans. They were all like, this is horrible.
SPEAKER_0:  If I had a magic wand.
SPEAKER_0:  I'd give them food. I wouldn't have them live in fear.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... and this is something that i don't think was the case
SPEAKER_0:  a couple hundred years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  That said, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I'd love to get your thoughts about what's going on in Iran, the protests.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like the regime there is able to crack down on violence.
SPEAKER_0:  My thoughts about Iran, let me just, there's something else about Iran which I think is interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  this whole idea of care for what you wish for.
SPEAKER_0:  because people have this sight and something I kind of one of the reasons I have the white pill
SPEAKER_0:  is Americans really are very naive about the nature of evil.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? I really think that
SPEAKER_0:  A dictator has a weird mustache and he's banging the table and he's, you know, like a crazy person.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's often not the case, but they also think
SPEAKER_0:  if something is bad.
SPEAKER_0:  Therefore, the alternative's gonna be better.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, so you had the shah of Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  and he was.
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of authoritarian and no, he's not a good guy.
SPEAKER_0:  So in 1979, there were a lot of people like, this guy's a-
SPEAKER_0:  horrible.
SPEAKER_0:  He's oppressing the Iranian people. Let's get him the F out of there.
SPEAKER_0:  He's so bad.
SPEAKER_0:  that whatever comes after it has to be an improvement.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like...
SPEAKER_0:  No, that's, if you think, I mean, this drives me crazy.
SPEAKER_0:  when conservatives are like
SPEAKER_0:  You know, Joe Biden's the worst president we ever had. Like this is destroying America. I'm like.
SPEAKER_0:  You have no idea.
SPEAKER_0:  how bad things can get.
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that you are in a position to
SPEAKER_0:  complain.
SPEAKER_0:  means we got a ways to go.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, every time.
SPEAKER_1:  You say that Donald Trump or Joe Biden is the worst president ever.
SPEAKER_1:  That warms my heart.
SPEAKER_1:  because you're allowed to.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes. Isn't this a flock of chickens?
SPEAKER_1:  It's like, I just let it, it's like music.
SPEAKER_1:  has.
SPEAKER_1:  You're allowed to be pretty, in response to a president's tweet, you can write that.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  and it still lives there and it's.
SPEAKER_1:  and nobody arrests you.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  which is a rare thing in human history. Yes. It's the rare thing in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, what?
SPEAKER_1:  It does seem that...
SPEAKER_1:  Iran, the current regime, is able to crack down on communication channels.
SPEAKER_1:  It's still-
SPEAKER_1:  It's surprising to me.
SPEAKER_1:  how much power a government can have.
SPEAKER_1:  Like they could.
SPEAKER_1:  use violence to control the population.
SPEAKER_1:  Right.
SPEAKER_1:  and nobody's gonna do anything about it.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I just- The rest of the world.
SPEAKER_1:  just watches.
SPEAKER_0:  But here's the thing, right? Because if the rest of the world starts doing too much,
SPEAKER_0:  then they have a justification to crack down even more.
SPEAKER_0:  This regime, this.
SPEAKER_0:  protests are not legitimate.
SPEAKER_0:  These are, this happened constantly in the Soviet Union. These are foreign provocateurs.
SPEAKER_0:  This is meddling in our country.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, curfew, lockdown.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, mandatory searches, everyone's a spy. So that narrative is a very convenient one for people who are authoritarian.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, I...
SPEAKER_0:  know a lot of people who are Persian, as I'm sure you do as well.
SPEAKER_0:  very hard working.
SPEAKER_0:  very bright, great people.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and you know, all you could do is hope.
SPEAKER_0:  for a peaceful
SPEAKER_0:  liberalization of your- but here's the- people don't realize how-
SPEAKER_0:  liberal Iran used to be.
SPEAKER_0:  Andy Warhol
SPEAKER_0:  Andy Warhol used to be friends with the Shah.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you read his diaries, he talks about how he knew things weren't going well for the Shah because they had less caviar at the table.
SPEAKER_0:  But like, this is, he was really kind of-
SPEAKER_0:  There's.
SPEAKER_0:  There's I think a.
SPEAKER_0:  for understanding in America.
SPEAKER_0:  and I'm not sure why.
SPEAKER_0:  of what these liberal Muslim countries are like.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, I-
SPEAKER_0:  gave a talk in Bodrum in Turkey which is a resort town in Turkey.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I had thought previous to that.
SPEAKER_0:  or I suspected.
SPEAKER_0:  If push comes to shove and they have to choose people in Turkey between the West.
SPEAKER_0:  and like al-qaeda, not al-qaeda but like you know
SPEAKER_0:  hardcore Islam.
SPEAKER_0:  They're gonna choose Hardcore as love. You go there?
SPEAKER_0:  And you're like, oh, this is like Los Angeles. Like these people are so liberal, so-
SPEAKER_0:  and they're the first to be killed. They're the first targets.
SPEAKER_0:  So that, people like that in Iran are who.
SPEAKER_0:  my thoughts are and with that i gotta tell you like
SPEAKER_0:  Nothing makes me more of a feminist.
SPEAKER_0:  than seeing the women.
SPEAKER_0:  in countries like this fight for the right to education, the right to dress as they please.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe we don't need them driving, but.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, that's okay.
SPEAKER_0:  There he is!
SPEAKER_1:  with that characteristic brilliant humor.
SPEAKER_1:  that you're so loved for.
SPEAKER_1:  I should probably be banned for on Twitter. I'm doing my best. Every time you tweet, I just report, report, report. Is
SPEAKER_0:  this man. You don't have a script. Exactly.
SPEAKER_1:  Funny enough, I do.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  but I don't abuse my power.
SPEAKER_1:  I wear the ring like Frodo.
SPEAKER_1:  and I respect the power.
SPEAKER_1:  But you look like goll-
SPEAKER_1:  That's not what your mom said last night.
SPEAKER_0:  She said you're hung like Gollum.
SPEAKER_1:  Heh.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not going down that road with you. I'm not holding hands one another time. I learned my Fumi once.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  My close childhood friend is from Iran.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh wow, okay. And uh.
SPEAKER_1:  I talk to them a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  I wanted-
SPEAKER_1:  to go to Iran.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's so far away.
SPEAKER_1:  I can see it from my house, my friend.
SPEAKER_1:  Um,
SPEAKER_1:  I would love to take that trip, even now.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just culturally. So all the different little pockets of local cultures that make up Iran. I just heard so many amazing things.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, my friend Paul went there. He had an amazing time. He just absolutely loved it. He thought the people were awesome.
SPEAKER_0:  It was so interesting, very developed.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... just like to run is the history in toronto's insane
SPEAKER_1:  I would really love to...
SPEAKER_1:  to visit. Now we return back.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know how we ended up in Iran.
SPEAKER_1:  but let us let us stroll back to Stalin taking power.
SPEAKER_1:  What role did the suppression of speech?
SPEAKER_1:  the censorship, the suppression of the freedom of the press.
SPEAKER_1:  have.
SPEAKER_1:  in the
SPEAKER_1:  Stalin.
SPEAKER_1:  taking hold, taking power.
SPEAKER_1:  in Lenin.
SPEAKER_1:  Trotsky and Stalin having power.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it was a very useful mechanism to.
SPEAKER_0:  Direct
SPEAKER_0:  public.
SPEAKER_0:  and inform.
SPEAKER_0:  public perspectives and everything. So first of all, there was a lot of news about how
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  great things were, you have a bumper crop here, you know, grains never better. There's another anecdote.
SPEAKER_0:  where President Kalinian is talking about how
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm Karl Mark Street in Karkev.
SPEAKER_0:  There's all sorts of new skyscrapers being built and it's just absolutely amazing. And some of the audience gets up and goes, Comrade, I-
SPEAKER_0:  work on Karl Marx Street, I walk there every day, there's none of these skyscrapers. It goes, see, that's your problem. You're trusting your eyes instead of reading something and learning what's in the papers.
SPEAKER_0:  So there was this kind of disconnect between.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, uh, uh,
SPEAKER_0:  I forgot you probably know the joke like pravda ne pravda
SPEAKER_0:  Like, Pravda means truth, but there's no truth to be had in Pravda is the kind of Russian line.
SPEAKER_0:  The point is it.
SPEAKER_0:  very much.
SPEAKER_0:  and the other thing this is you know my mom wasn't politically motivated
SPEAKER_0:  But she talked about how.
SPEAKER_0:  You didn't have to be smart.
SPEAKER_0:  to realize how...
SPEAKER_0:  Dishonest it was?
SPEAKER_0:  Because one day...
SPEAKER_0:  someone is the great hero of the Soviet people.
SPEAKER_0:  And the next week...
SPEAKER_0:  he's been a traitor and a class enemy and the worst, and then sometimes they reverted.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like, okay, like they couldn't even keep their story straight.
SPEAKER_0:  And in fact, at a certain point when Gorbachev liberalized...
SPEAKER_0:  They had to cancel tests because the history books had to be rewritten so quickly.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  So, and the thing that also with these newspapers.
SPEAKER_0:  is there was a lot of, it was very monotonous.
SPEAKER_0:  because you know you had the same message over and over.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of these papers were about kind of speaking to the lowest common denominator. Stalin's great.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything's great, overseas bad.
SPEAKER_0:  So it,
SPEAKER_0:  very much was about not informing, but creating.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  a certain perspective in the public at large. And also, you were educated as a citizen.
SPEAKER_0:  on what you're supposed to think and say.
SPEAKER_0:  So you have, a lot of this was this kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  private truth, public lies situation.
SPEAKER_0:  So you could read the paper and at your factory, you could be like...
SPEAKER_0:  Oh my God, this guy Carl Raddick's great. He's like, oh my God, yeah, he's amazing. You knew what to talk about?
SPEAKER_0:  and you knew how to look at it as well.
SPEAKER_0:  And then when you get home, you could just kind of be more honest with.
SPEAKER_0:  family.
SPEAKER_1:  But the question is, to which degree does this propaganda and this ideology infiltrate your actual-
SPEAKER_1:  Thinking.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... you get you give examples of sex scientists infiltrated science
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yeah, so basically, you know, Lisenko is the
SPEAKER_0:  textbook example of synchroism in biology.
SPEAKER_0:  So because Marxism is materialist...
SPEAKER_0:  uh... they didn't like the idea that jeans pass on
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, from one generation to the next. So, Lysenkoism kind of was a rejection.
SPEAKER_0:  of Mendel and that kind of genetics.
SPEAKER_0:  And
SPEAKER_0:  If you reject genes, you're really going in a bad direction in terms of biology. The Soviet Union's biological program became an international laughing stock.
SPEAKER_0:  At one point, Lysenko claimed he crossed a tomato and a potato.
SPEAKER_0:  You had things where they said they
SPEAKER_0:  had nuclear, which is, wait, we have.
SPEAKER_0:  fishing, but they said they invented fusion or hard or heavy water or hard water.
SPEAKER_0:  point being.
SPEAKER_0:  in cultures like this.
SPEAKER_0:  Your-
SPEAKER_0:  way to achieve.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, status.
SPEAKER_0:  wasn't necessarily about your accomplishments, but about your loyalty to orthodoxy. So if you were saying things that got to a result that was congruent,
SPEAKER_0:  with the broader ideology as a whole.
SPEAKER_0:  That was much better as a means of furthering yourself in the arts or in the sciences.
SPEAKER_0:  than if you had something that was innovative, because if you're innovative, it's like, well, how do I fit this in with the broader ruling ideology? The problem with totalitarianism, one of the many problems is...
SPEAKER_0:  Everything.
SPEAKER_0:  Literally everything has to be perceived.
SPEAKER_0:  through the lens of ideology.
SPEAKER_0:  So, and that is, you know, there were...
SPEAKER_0:  scientists who were arrested or at least fired.
SPEAKER_0:  because of their theories about sunspot developments, because it was regarded as un-Marxist. There is just —
SPEAKER_0:  There was a...
SPEAKER_0:  An epidemic and all these horses got sick.
SPEAKER_0:  And because the vaccine didn't work on the horses.
SPEAKER_0:  the bacteriologists were arrested because they regard as wreckers. It's like, we gave you a job. You didn't do it. You're undermining the socialist state.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's kind of a backward series of incentives.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and it's designed to maintain at all costs.
SPEAKER_0:  the ruling ideological superstructure.
SPEAKER_1:  You draw a small distinction between the ideology and the ideological superstructure and the propaganda. Aren't those kind of intermixed together?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, the ideologicals like in the sciences and what's true in genetics or what's true in astronomy, that doesn't really percolate out to the masses, right? So the prob does not is maybe covering this scientist is great or these discoveries are great.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's not necessarily the same as day to day.
SPEAKER_0:  or glorifying political leaders.
SPEAKER_1:  But Pravda is a manifestation of the idea that truth can be.
SPEAKER_1:  conjured up. Yes, you can be constructed and it could be altered quickly and then.
SPEAKER_1:  I just, I wonder, sort of 1984 caricatures that.
SPEAKER_1:  I wonder to what degree.
SPEAKER_1:  it really could control the way you think.
SPEAKER_1:  that like how many people that are.
SPEAKER_0:  I can give you an example, a very easy one. So again, regarding North Korea.
SPEAKER_0:  The great leader Kim Il-sung, who was the founder of North Korea, had a tumor on the back of his neck.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It was too close to the skull, the spinal column, so they couldn't operate on it. And throughout his life, it got bigger and bigger.
SPEAKER_0:  And I got mixed messages in my research about whether North Koreans knew about it because they always photographed them from this angle.
SPEAKER_0:  and I met a refugee.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And I asked her, I'm like, did you know that he had this tumor? She goes, yeah, yeah. When people played him in the movies, they would make up there. And she goes, it was an old war injury.
SPEAKER_0:  And I go, why would a war injury get bigger throughout your life? And she just stood there.
SPEAKER_0:  And she was like, holy crap, but she never questioned it.
SPEAKER_0:  But it was the kind of thing where they put the idea in her head. And since there was no reason to question it, she just kind of went with it her entire life until I talked to her.
SPEAKER_0:  Audrey, his name.
SPEAKER_0:  Hi Audrey.
SPEAKER_1:  Hi Audrey.
SPEAKER_1:  I wonder what percent of the population is like that.
SPEAKER_0:  Here's the thing.
SPEAKER_0:  If there is a cost...
SPEAKER_0:  to me questioning Lisenko as a great scientist and there was no benefit.
SPEAKER_0:  Why wouldn't I just go with what's going to-
SPEAKER_0:  keep me and my family safe.
SPEAKER_1:  But I also mean just the psychological.
SPEAKER_1:  there might be a very.
SPEAKER_1:  local psychological costs are not a cost you go to jail but a cost like
SPEAKER_1:  You're gonna kind of ruin the conversation by bringing it up.
SPEAKER_1:  Kind of like.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't, I'm just.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like Debbie Downer, right? Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  But there's also the whole metaphor of like there's two fish in the river. One says, man, the water is really great today. And the other one goes, what's water? Yeah, like a friend of mine, Adriana, her mom.
SPEAKER_0:  came to the West.
SPEAKER_0:  And they went to the supermarket and the mom just in front of all the Fanta.
SPEAKER_0:  The sense of it just crying.
SPEAKER_0:  And she's like, what's going on? And she goes, they told us we had more food than you.
SPEAKER_0:  And when something is, you can, it's, you can under think this story.
SPEAKER_0:  This guy's an enemy of the people, he was the hero, he just offended someone, this is bullshit.
SPEAKER_0:  It's almost impossible psychologically.
SPEAKER_0:  to think.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm living in the Truman Show.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's it.
SPEAKER_0:  EVERYTHING in the media.
SPEAKER_0:  is not just wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  but a carefully constructed narrative and a lie.
SPEAKER_0:  Like what, they're never gonna tell the truth? How you, you know, like what?
SPEAKER_0:  Like, and even if you do understand that.
SPEAKER_0:  How would you even read between the lines to deduce what the truth is?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it must have been a strange experience. These are stories of soldiers.
SPEAKER_1:  the Red Army soldiers throughout World War II.
SPEAKER_1:  as they go to different countries, even Romania.
SPEAKER_1:  in Europe.
SPEAKER_1:  to understand that people live much better.
SPEAKER_1:  than the soldiers did back in the...
SPEAKER_0:  And that's why a lot of times when they went back, Stalin had them killed because they saw too much or sent to the camps.
SPEAKER_1:  So just to linger on this idea of free speech, so there's constant.
SPEAKER_1:  discussion about free speech and this modern debate about social media and all that kind of stuff what
SPEAKER_1:  What's your take on it?
SPEAKER_1:  grounding it.
SPEAKER_1:  not in some kind of
SPEAKER_1:  shallow discussion of free speech we have today, but more in the context of
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  Правда
SPEAKER_1:  and the suppression of speech in...
SPEAKER_1:  Stalinist Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  I hate the term free speech.
SPEAKER_0:  because it's used in many different contexts. Some I agree with entirely, some I disagree with at all.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think everyone.
SPEAKER_0:  has something to say or some conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I have my locals community, um, and it used to be, I think that the boilerplate language is, you know, come support.
SPEAKER_0:  free speech and free discourse and I changed that because I don't like that term.
SPEAKER_0:  because people will tell you.
SPEAKER_0:  with some reason that, oh, if you block me on Twitter, you're...
SPEAKER_0:  avoiding my free speech. Take me.
SPEAKER_0:  So I don't like that term as a whole.
SPEAKER_0:  But one of the points of the white pill, and something I see enormous parallels with today,
SPEAKER_0:  If you have.
SPEAKER_0:  One.
SPEAKER_0:  News outlet.
SPEAKER_0:  or three news outlets with identical ideology.
SPEAKER_0:  you're not going to be able to get.
SPEAKER_0:  to any kind of truth.
SPEAKER_0:  or any kind of useful information. It's all gonna be pre-filtered for you. It's like a baby bird, and you're eating the mother bird's vomit, right?
SPEAKER_0:  if you have what we have increasing now.
SPEAKER_0:  with technology.
SPEAKER_0:  if you have a world where everyone has a camera on their phone.
SPEAKER_0:  if you have a world where anyone can put their ideas out there.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe they're banned.
SPEAKER_0:  from certain outlets, but they're not literally.
SPEAKER_0:  vanished like they were in the USSR.
SPEAKER_0:  That is very healthy. That is something I'm enormously supportive of.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  Back in the day.
SPEAKER_0:  if you only had the TV crews with cameras.
SPEAKER_0:  You can only see what they're capturing and they could edit it.
SPEAKER_0:  Whereas now...
SPEAKER_0:  We saw this recently during COVID, right?
SPEAKER_0:  You had these reporters with masks on and they're talking.
SPEAKER_0:  but the cameraman.
SPEAKER_0:  wasn't wearing a mask. So you have the people in the street being like, look.
SPEAKER_0:  They don't believe it.
SPEAKER_0:  Or as soon as they would start filming, the guy took the mask off and they'd film them. destructive places and they go-
SPEAKER_0:  You are lying. You don't believe this. You're putting this on for some purpose. Whether you're leaving the thick of sea of mass or not, that person clearly does not. He's only putting on for show. So that's all crimes.
SPEAKER_0:  It's people, you know, are anti-police. They say, okay, the cop said this.
SPEAKER_0:  Did he draw the gun in the sky necessarily so and so forth?
SPEAKER_0:  It is so much.
SPEAKER_0:  better.
SPEAKER_0:  when everyone.
SPEAKER_0:  has access to as much of the information as possible.
SPEAKER_0:  and can make that informed decision themselves. Now, there certainly is-
SPEAKER_0:  space.
SPEAKER_0:  for informed people to be like, no, no, no, no, this isn't what it looks like. If you look here, if you look there.
SPEAKER_0:  It's cropped here so and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  but that's still much more useful.
SPEAKER_0:  than just having.
SPEAKER_0:  20 second clip.
SPEAKER_0:  that someone has decided to edit for you.
SPEAKER_1:  So like truth has a way of.
SPEAKER_1:  because everything is so interconnected, truth, no matter what has a way of finding its way to the
SPEAKER_0:  the populace. Also, there's an
SPEAKER_0:  There's a big asymmetry in terms of trust.
SPEAKER_0:  So if I tell you a hundred truths...
SPEAKER_0:  and one lie.
SPEAKER_0:  That lie is equal, I'm screwed. Because once you catch me in a, like a-
SPEAKER_0:  You don't have to kill someone every day to be a murderer, right? You only have to do it once.
SPEAKER_0:  So if you catch me in a brazen lie.
SPEAKER_0:  You're going to look at everything I say after that with an enormous grain of salt.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, so that is another big asymmetry in favor of truth. If someone trusts you, you have to be honest all the time and you're going to make mistakes, you can own those mistakes and be like, Hey, this is why I made the mistake. This is why I said such and such.
SPEAKER_1:  But the flip side of that, which.
SPEAKER_1:  has been disheartening to me.
SPEAKER_1:  is that people on the conspiracy side
SPEAKER_1:  conspiracy theory side of things.
SPEAKER_1:  I've noticed how-
SPEAKER_1:  Easy it is to just call something a lie.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  And then that becomes viral. For some reason there's a desire for people.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, for anyone who points out that the Emperor is not wearing a clothes, even when the Emperor is fully clothed.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know what that is, but that really seems to mess with this tooth mechanism.
SPEAKER_1:  So when...
SPEAKER_1:  when it becomes viral to call people a liar, whether they're a liar or not.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like you feel like on unstable ground.
SPEAKER_1:  Because it-
SPEAKER_1:  To me, that idea of revealing
SPEAKER_1:  a lie that somebody told is a really powerful mechanism to keep people honest.
SPEAKER_1:  but when you're like misusing a crying wolf too much.
SPEAKER_1:  But well, it seems.
SPEAKER_1:  seems to break the system. It makes me nervous because there's also like a
SPEAKER_0:  But just if someone is a liar that doesn't mean literally everything they say is a lie.
SPEAKER_0:  No but what is a lion with-
SPEAKER_1:  isn't.
SPEAKER_1:  I just noticed that there's money to be made.
SPEAKER_1:  in calling out something as a lie.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just...
SPEAKER_1:  The conspiracy theories.
SPEAKER_1:  straight up.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  the first thing, some traumatic event happened, give an explanation that's not the mainstream explanation. no matter what, whether it's true or lie.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot of virality and money to be made in that.
SPEAKER_1:  And that makes me nervous.
SPEAKER_1:  because it doesn't matter if it's true or not.
SPEAKER_1:  it becomes.
SPEAKER_1:  anti-establishment ideas are viral whether they are true or not.
SPEAKER_0:  Sure, but I think establishment ideas are powerful whether they're true or not.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think I'm.
SPEAKER_1:  the whole I think you're right and the whole it's good to test the power centers but it just makes me
SPEAKER_1:  Nervous.
SPEAKER_1:  in our attention economy.
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  the sexy thing seems to be the anti-establishment message.
SPEAKER_1:  and then it feels like that becomes a drug.
SPEAKER_1:  where you everything.
SPEAKER_1:  I
SPEAKER_1:  anything the establishment says, anything institutions say.
SPEAKER_1:  Anything the mainstream says must be wrong, because it comes from the mainstream.
SPEAKER_0:  I have that line that you're supposed to take one red pill, not the whole bottle.
SPEAKER_0:  I am certainly one of those people who is of the idea that they are dishonest far more open that they're honest.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  That said, there are people who are of the belief.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's use an extreme example.
SPEAKER_0:  that Trump is still the shadow president.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and, and, you know, there's going to be these QAnon mass arrests. I thought this was something that like the Daily Beast made up.
SPEAKER_0:  to make fun of MAGA.
SPEAKER_0:  But I was just on the phone with my buddy last night and he was like, no, no, if you go to truth central, they're like all over there. And if you disagree with them, they call you a controlled opposition or a grifter or so on and so forth. Is that unfortunate or where?
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, Truth Central, Trump's social media outlet. Oh, Truth Central.
SPEAKER_0:  No, truth. We have a, he, he, he forgot the name of it himself. So he's like, that's why I had to create jokes. You gotta explain the jokes. I gotta explain the jokes.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you like the way Twitter puts that context?
SPEAKER_1:  Better.
SPEAKER_1:  You gotta do the joke and then pause.
SPEAKER_1:  and I turned to the camera and.
SPEAKER_0:  And have a laugh track.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so people know what the jokes are. That's real humor.
SPEAKER_0:  So we and then we just clap and then everybody clap
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I think for the last two years.
SPEAKER_0:  especially vis-a-vis COVID.
SPEAKER_0:  The overwhelming message was...
SPEAKER_0:  the experts know what they're talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you are questioning this, you're a vax denier, and you basically should be read out of Polite Society.
SPEAKER_0:  And one obvious counter example to this was social distancing.
SPEAKER_0:  If social distancing was efficacious.
SPEAKER_0:  Why were there no attempts ever to bring it back?
SPEAKER_0:  right, when you had different waves?
SPEAKER_0:  And if it wasn't efficacious, why was it so insistent?
SPEAKER_0:  that we do it, all do it, at the very beginning. In fact, in many places you'll still see the signs on the floor where it's six feet apart.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's an incongruity there and I think we are forgetting.
SPEAKER_0:  as a people.
SPEAKER_0:  The intensity.
SPEAKER_0:  with and understandably to some extent, if you have this worldwide deadly plague, like yeah, like it's going to be go where the leakiest hole is. So you really got to kind of get everyone on board.
SPEAKER_0:  but to the vehemence.
SPEAKER_0:  with which we're told we know what we're doing.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the way to solve it. If you don't do it, you are causing mass death.
SPEAKER_0:  that I think fed in very heavily.
SPEAKER_0:  to people's enormous sense of skepticism toward establishment sources.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of the plague, you opened the book with a quote from Camus. It's a strong, strong quote.
SPEAKER_0:  KEMU brings me to tears and it's funny because I reread the myth of Sisyphus, which I've been recommending to people and like this book is not good.
SPEAKER_0:  but he's got his.
SPEAKER_0:  Ethos is my favorite of all the philosophers.
SPEAKER_1:  It sounds like the myth of Sisyphus was a myth.
SPEAKER_0:  He says, after I cute.
SPEAKER_0:  All I maintain is that on this earth there are plagues and there are victims.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's up to us so far as possible.
SPEAKER_0:  not to join forces with the plagues.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Why I have that as the introductory quotes the book.
SPEAKER_0:  is.
SPEAKER_0:  I think morality and ethics are very, very complicated subjects.
SPEAKER_0:  There's lots of gray areas where you don't know which way to choose.
SPEAKER_0:  but at a bass level.
SPEAKER_0:  He has another quote that's ascribed to him he never actually said.
SPEAKER_0:  But something about...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, is the duty of thinking people not to be on the side of the executioners.
SPEAKER_0:  if you are, we should do whatever we can.
SPEAKER_0:  not to have blood on our hands.
SPEAKER_0:  not to be.
SPEAKER_0:  murderers not to want.
SPEAKER_0:  Death.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  That in and of itself is a big pill for a lot of people to swallow. We're all brought up.
SPEAKER_0:  taught.
SPEAKER_0:  that war is a last resort.
SPEAKER_0:  And yet when it comes to international affairs, it's always often a first priority and people are champing at the bit.
SPEAKER_0:  start going in and killing people and what war means isn't
SPEAKER_0:  good guy soldiers versus bad guy soldiers.
SPEAKER_0:  My concern is always with the civilians.
SPEAKER_0:  with the kids who become orphans, with the wives who become widows and things like that. And then communities which are ruined forever.
SPEAKER_0:  I love that quote of his. I think he's.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, the book started, it was going to be...
SPEAKER_0:  A recontextualization of Kamus thought I was going to rip off.
SPEAKER_0:  my old buddy Ryan Holiday, what he did with the Stoics and do about Camus. And then when I started rereading Camus, I'm like, oh, there's, I've read more into him than is really there.
SPEAKER_0:  and then it went the whole other direction.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, so you wanted to do...
SPEAKER_1:  almost.
SPEAKER_1:  like an existentialist manifesto. So like, one must imagine Sisyphus happy.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, more like Camus for today and what his philosophy can teach us, like Ryan did with his
SPEAKER_0:  Many books about the Stokes.
SPEAKER_0:  and it was gonna be called The Point of Tears.
SPEAKER_0:  Live to the point of tears? Yes, but the title is going to be the point of tears.
SPEAKER_1:  I know but from that line.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a good line, right? I hear so many good lines.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe it's not about how- Just such an ingredients,...
SPEAKER_0:  in bed though right?
SPEAKER_0:  No, he was a big lethario. He was probably pretty good. He got around.
SPEAKER_1:  What percent of the audience?
SPEAKER_1:  of humans on earth you think not the word letharia.
SPEAKER_0:  How up percent of them have a computer? Look it up.
SPEAKER_0:  Lothario. It's not some weird term. Lothario. L-O-T-H-A-R-I-O, Lothario. Lothario.
SPEAKER_1:  A man who behaves selfishly in a response to being in sexual relationships with women
SPEAKER_1:  They're seduced by handsome, in quotes, they're seduced by handsome Motharia who gains control of their financial...
SPEAKER_0:  affairs. Oh, I didn't think, I always thought of as more as just someone who's like a stud.
SPEAKER_0:  Like a player, but not-
SPEAKER_1:  fire yet is uh... um... eleven mull attempt
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, I didn't realize that. Okay. Well then he's... Selfishly. Okay, that's not him.
SPEAKER_1:  irresponsibly.
SPEAKER_1:  And a man, too.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Although Ayn Rand would be proud, selfishly.
SPEAKER_0:  What's wrong with selfishness? She wouldn't like that kind of selfishness.
SPEAKER_0:  That's Explicit Haves.
SPEAKER_0:  A man who behaves su-
SPEAKER_1:  and irresponsibly in his sexual relationships with women.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  So he was just a player.
SPEAKER_0:  No, no, maybe a stud. I don't think he was promiscuous particularly.
SPEAKER_1:  Nature didn't get...
SPEAKER_1:  He got
SPEAKER_1:  He didn't never got laid, right?
SPEAKER_0:  He had syphilis, he died of syphilis. Oh, it was from prostitutes. Was it? Okay. Possibly, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  It's giving me like I knew the guy. I heard it's from.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  He never had a deep, loving, fulfilling relationship.
SPEAKER_1:  had a very skewed understanding on
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  the way he wrote about women. Although somebody wrote to me and said that's-
SPEAKER_1:  mischaracterization that he was actually very respectful with
SPEAKER_0:  But hear that line if you're going before women bring a whip?
SPEAKER_0:  Wasn't that him or was that Shrobenhauer? If I were to quote-
SPEAKER_1:  you from your Twitter.
SPEAKER_1:  I think I could.
SPEAKER_1:  make a very convincing argument that you're sexist, racist, and probably a Nazi.
SPEAKER_0:  Well I do own like-
SPEAKER_0:  some of Hitler's stuff. Exactly.
SPEAKER_0:  I- I got the- I rest.
SPEAKER_0:  My case.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like I'm in Nuremberg. I'm going to be hung by his own tie. This isn't a tie, it's a noose.
SPEAKER_0:  You should have thought about that.
SPEAKER_1:  We were saying all those things.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think of the leak of the-
SPEAKER_0:  Twitter files.
SPEAKER_0:  I
SPEAKER_0:  was
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  Happy.
SPEAKER_0:  that Elon gave.
SPEAKER_0:  the information to Matt Taibbi and Barry Weiss.
SPEAKER_0:  who are both by any metric lefties.
SPEAKER_0:  who are both.
SPEAKER_0:  professional journalists of longstanding
SPEAKER_0:  with great resumes.
SPEAKER_0:  And overnight now they're doing PR for the world's, which all the way of the party line was.
SPEAKER_0:  And the fact that you had all these corporate journalists now having to play catch up.
SPEAKER_0:  and not having control of the microphone to me.
SPEAKER_0:  was just absolutely.
SPEAKER_0:  Amazing
SPEAKER_0:  I think transparency is...
SPEAKER_0:  what brought down in many aspects of Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  at what will bring down what negative aspects of the regime we have here.
SPEAKER_0:  when you see.
SPEAKER_0:  the machinations behind the scenes.
SPEAKER_0:  and then when you see the rationalizations after the fact
SPEAKER_0:  you realize, oh, these people are not acting in good faith.
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that...
SPEAKER_0:  For example, the New York Post article about the
SPEAKER_0:  Hunter.
SPEAKER_0:  Biden laptop.
SPEAKER_0:  And how the New York Times covered it as well. They didn't mention any kind of dick pics.
SPEAKER_0:  Twitter made it.
SPEAKER_0:  So I couldn't even DM you.
SPEAKER_0:  the link to the New York Post article, which was a tool they had previously used only.
SPEAKER_0:  to prevent.
SPEAKER_0:  child pornography.
SPEAKER_0:  So that shows to what extent they were.
SPEAKER_0:  willing to put their thumb on the scale.
SPEAKER_0:  but it also shows that
SPEAKER_0:  for any layman when they're looking at this to realize.
SPEAKER_0:  what you are perceiving as news or information.
SPEAKER_0:  is very much sculpted, edited, and guided.
SPEAKER_0:  by powerful people who have a vested interest in maintaining their.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... power
SPEAKER_1:  I think to me the important lesson is this is not a left the right thing.
SPEAKER_0:  No, not at all. Power versus powerless.
SPEAKER_1:  but and also the important lesson there.
SPEAKER_1:  I think at least in the case of Twitter.
SPEAKER_1:  in our society. It's a-
SPEAKER_1:  It's a slippery slope, you don't get there overnight.
SPEAKER_1:  You start using those tools a little bit.
SPEAKER_1:  A little bit.
SPEAKER_1:  to slow down this information to just a little bit you start
SPEAKER_1:  uh, sending emails to each other a little bit and it becomes more and more.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  You, you, you start forming justifications. You still getting a little more and more comfortable kind of talking about the stuff!
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  There are several ways to fight that one is having hardcore integrity upfront.
SPEAKER_1:  So don't even open the door.
SPEAKER_1:  But I think realistically human nature is what it is. So I think the only way is through transparency.
SPEAKER_1:  is this is why the nice, I hate the fact they got politicized.
SPEAKER_1:  I really hate that the right has run with it. Like, look, the left is...
SPEAKER_1:  planning the rig elections and so on. To me, it shouldn't be left or right, it shouldn't be about politics.
SPEAKER_1:  that transparency is good.
SPEAKER_1:  Other companies should do the same.
SPEAKER_1:  Facebook should do the same. In effect—
SPEAKER_1:  That transparency will protect Facebook.
SPEAKER_1:  who protect.
SPEAKER_1:  Google.
SPEAKER_0:  I look.
SPEAKER_0:  Like this is our situa-
SPEAKER_1:  tell us what to do.
SPEAKER_0:  and we'll do our best. I remember when I was writing the new right.
SPEAKER_0:  Twitter's line was...
SPEAKER_0:  We're not going to tell you guys what the metrics are by which we ban or censor people.
SPEAKER_0:  because then bad actors are going to navigate around them.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  What are you doing?
SPEAKER_0:  tell people in any establishment.
SPEAKER_0:  what are the rules for which behavior is permissible.
SPEAKER_0:  If I go to a store...
SPEAKER_0:  If I return the sweater, is it cash back?
SPEAKER_0:  No refunds or if I get store credit, you know what I mean? So that they were having this place which was-
SPEAKER_0:  presented as a
SPEAKER_0:  huge international space republic discourse
SPEAKER_0:  and they're not telling you ahead of time, this is what we will tolerate, this is what we will warn you about, this is what will kick you out overnight, that to me was-
SPEAKER_0:  crazy and outrageous.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and I'm really pleased.
SPEAKER_0:  With to what extent Elon is looking.
SPEAKER_0:  is being open with their policies. And what I really want to commend him about...
SPEAKER_0:  is...
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  Now I'm triggered.
SPEAKER_0:  because one of the things that he.
SPEAKER_0:  took over, he's like, our first priority is getting with a child pornography and child exploitation. Yeah. Right.
SPEAKER_0:  racial slurs, homophobic slurs, anti-semitic slurs, yeah, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  That's cool.
SPEAKER_0:  Kids getting harmed is number one.
SPEAKER_0:  And, you know, he fired the old task force because they weren't doing their job.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, Eliza blue, who you know, you know, she had been on this for a long time, but people who were victims of child pornography, child exploitation were emailing Twitter being like, these are my images, get them off. They're like too bad, porn is allowed on Twitter.
SPEAKER_0:  he starts trying to crack down on it, this is a very hard problem.
SPEAKER_0:  because these
SPEAKER_0:  bad actors have mechanisms to evade
SPEAKER_0:  you know being bad they they want to get there
SPEAKER_0:  for lack of a better term product out there.
SPEAKER_0:  Forbes Magazine.
SPEAKER_0:  who is an agent of the devil.
SPEAKER_0:  had a tweet and they tweeted this nine times.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, now that Elon's here...
SPEAKER_0:  Twitter's child porn nightmare has gotten much worse.
SPEAKER_0:  They tweet this nine times.
SPEAKER_0:  I looked up, anyone listening to this can look up, look at Forbes and do a search.
SPEAKER_0:  They never mentioned this problem before.
SPEAKER_0:  So now that Elon is doing something about it, now it's a problem for you. No, it's a problem. Elon's the problem. It's not the child porn that you guys had a problem with. And that to me is like, yeah, I understand that you think that...
SPEAKER_0:  Elon is a bad guy because he's upset your apple cart.
SPEAKER_0:  This isn't a political issue.
SPEAKER_0:  This isn't a gotcha moment. This is a right.
SPEAKER_0:  Here are some tips.
SPEAKER_0:  We talked to 10 experts, digital experts.
SPEAKER_0:  And here are some techniques, Mr. Musk.
SPEAKER_0:  that you might want to.
SPEAKER_0:  Take from us free of charge.
SPEAKER_0:  that will help you solve this. That would be a great article.
SPEAKER_1:  And I just want to use this opportunity to say quite clearly and strongly.
SPEAKER_1:  that even though Twitter and other parts of the internet are interpreting some of my statements to mean I'm right.
SPEAKER_1:  In this case.
SPEAKER_1:  meaning leaning right, right wing.
SPEAKER_1:  And in other cases, leaning left, left-wing, I'm not, I'm apolitical, or at least I try to be in my thinking. Take one issue at a time.
SPEAKER_1:  I do take an opinion on each issue at a time, but I hate camps. I try to avoid.
SPEAKER_1:  political accounts in general.
SPEAKER_1:  It just, it sucks that.
SPEAKER_1:  promoting transparency in this case or celebrating transparency.
SPEAKER_1:  Um,
SPEAKER_1:  is somehow.
SPEAKER_1:  connected to being right wing.
SPEAKER_0:  being made into.
SPEAKER_0:  of supposed euphemism.
SPEAKER_0:  for being right wing.
SPEAKER_1:  It just, it sucks. It sucks even though I'm wearing a red suit and this is very red themed.
SPEAKER_1:  conversation..
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, the revolution was the color of blood.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's sit on that for a second.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, you mentioned New York Times bestseller list.
SPEAKER_1:  You chose to self-publish. Yes, we just.
SPEAKER_1:  linger on that decision.
SPEAKER_1:  What are the pros and cons of self-publishing?
SPEAKER_0:  The cons are...
SPEAKER_0:  It is acceptable.
SPEAKER_0:  in our current.
SPEAKER_0:  business climate or cultural climate.
SPEAKER_0:  for.
SPEAKER_0:  corporate media outlets to pretend the book doesn't exist.
SPEAKER_0:  So basically, and there's reason for it. Oh, I can
SPEAKER_0:  make the case them pretty easily.
SPEAKER_0:  If someone's doing it themselves...
SPEAKER_0:  Who is this guy? Some crackpot.
SPEAKER_0:  writing crazy stuff from his basement, right? It's a little different, I think, for me, because I'm an established author. C-SPAN gave me an hour on BookTV.
SPEAKER_1:  little crack bar be.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, established. For Dear Reader, I think I was the first one to get an hour on BookTV for a book that I did myself.
SPEAKER_0:  So there is.
SPEAKER_0:  Thanks for that.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, it didn't go through a
SPEAKER_0:  vetting process the way a book.
SPEAKER_0:  going through a corporate publisher did. So those are the minuses.
SPEAKER_0:  up.
SPEAKER_0:  Pros are...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I can drop it and publish it immediately.
SPEAKER_0:  If you go through a bit of-
SPEAKER_0:  Corporate publisher, you have to wait a year.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  you can do what you could have the book you want instead of getting past the editor.
SPEAKER_0:  And some editors are very, very good and there's a whole spectrum. Some of them not so good.
SPEAKER_0:  So we're good? Let's post on social media!
SPEAKER_0:  I know the best and the real killers.
SPEAKER_1:  All right, let's beat the good people on both sides.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't mean the white nationalists who I condemn totally.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  So, but the thing is in terms of money, you get six times as much.
SPEAKER_0:  profit when you self-publish than when you go through corporate publisher.
SPEAKER_0:  The buck stops here.
SPEAKER_0:  It's, you know, in one of my books that I co-authored, I won't even mention the name.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a typo.
SPEAKER_0:  and they didn't, they don't care. They didn't fix it.
SPEAKER_0:  for the paperback edition.
SPEAKER_0:  Here, since I'm going through Amazon, if there's a typo, I can fix it live and it updates. Oh yeah? Yep. You can just update it. F muddles out
SPEAKER_0:  So that's very useful.
SPEAKER_1:  You get like a fight club thing where...
SPEAKER_1:  You can insert like a deck pick in one of the pages.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, why are you so f-
SPEAKER_0:  Why do you keep texting me to send you dick pics? Talk about North Pole. Just suggesting, all right, all right. All right, I get it. I'm not the editor. I get it, North Pole, I get it. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  The other advantage...
SPEAKER_0:  just socially is I think people are
SPEAKER_0:  Like I found this with the Kickstarter I did for Deereader.
SPEAKER_0:  people are much more excited to
SPEAKER_0:  Buy it.
SPEAKER_0:  and promote it and talk about it when they know you're doing it yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  instead of you're getting a big check from.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, St. Martin's, HarperCollins, Penguin, whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  Are you also trying to use some kind of service to get it distributed to bookstores or you just want to do it?
SPEAKER_0:  Amazon. No, just Amazon.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's probably where most sales happen.
SPEAKER_0:  The vast majority, yeah. So it's not going to be in bookstores.
SPEAKER_1:  So how difficult is the process of getting it on Amazon?
SPEAKER_0:  So I'll tell you a funny story about how Amazon works and cause this was a, I always plan for because everyone.
SPEAKER_0:  A-
SPEAKER_0:  People's.
SPEAKER_0:  Here's another piece of advice I will give people. Your life will be a lot easier if you realize that the majority of people in every industry are bad at their jobs.
SPEAKER_0:  Like once you have that realization, everything else makes sense and your life will be a lot easier, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So when I did the Anarchist Handbook, which was a collection of essays from various anarchist throughout history,
SPEAKER_0:  when I submitted it to Amazon.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a lot of copyright issues.
SPEAKER_0:  Cause they're like, do you have the rights to this essay? Do you have the rights to this essay? Let's go back and forth with them a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  to make sure I had copyright where everything was public domain.
SPEAKER_0:  And the thing is you forward it, you update it, you get the information.
SPEAKER_0:  Three days, there's another problem, it's not three days.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's weeks.
SPEAKER_0:  The other thing with their CreateSpace program is...
SPEAKER_0:  The.
SPEAKER_0:  Paperback?
SPEAKER_0:  and the ebook, the Kindle.
SPEAKER_0:  art.
SPEAKER_0:  approved independently.
SPEAKER_0:  So just because it's approved for one side, it's not approved for the other.
SPEAKER_0:  After I-
SPEAKER_0:  published Amicus Handbook and it was a big success.
SPEAKER_0:  They unleashed, unrolled, excuse me, a hardcover edition program.
SPEAKER_0:  So I'm like, oh, great, I'll put in hardcover.
SPEAKER_0:  They're like, sorry, this is too similar to Murray Rothbard's An Amidst State, which is a pamphlet or short book that Murray Rothbard wrote. I go, wait, wait.
SPEAKER_0:  I have the entirety of anatomy state.
SPEAKER_0:  In here.
SPEAKER_0:  I have permission from the Mises Institute in writing, which I'm giving to you to reprint it, initiallyuttering, but they're going to start writing it in the future.
SPEAKER_0:  and you guys already.
SPEAKER_0:  haven't been published for a year as a paperback and ebook. Yep. And they're like too bad, blocked.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's not available as a hardcover on Amazon.
SPEAKER_0:  even though it's available, maybe now it's going to be pulled as paper, like an ebook.
SPEAKER_0:  So with this book.
SPEAKER_0:  I was anticipating, alright, this is gonna be some whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  The thing with...
SPEAKER_0:  How it works is you have to upload it and hit publish.
SPEAKER_0:  and then you gotta wait for the approval.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm like, okay, this is gonna be who knows. I just want to get as fast as possible.
SPEAKER_0:  4 a.m.
SPEAKER_0:  For less than 24 hours, I get a notification, Congratulations, your book's available for sale, and I have to run downstairs and pull it.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. From publication because otherwise it was out and I didn't finish editing it. Yeah. So that's the situation there.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, that's fascinating. But that's like powerful. That's like your, it's all in your hands. It's all on you.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think the program is great.
SPEAKER_0:  It charts just like any other book.
SPEAKER_0:  The quality of the books is great. I am very happy with.
SPEAKER_0:  I have no contact with them. My buddy Tucker Maxx, he had a company that did this and they-
SPEAKER_0:  basically help people self-polish their own book. They did Dave Goggins book. I think you've talked to him, haven't you? Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Or maybe they emailed me or something.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, yeah. And.
SPEAKER_0:  He said, I have done dozens, maybe hundreds of books with them. I have never been able to get someone on the phone.
SPEAKER_0:  So I don't know what's going on over there, but.
SPEAKER_0:  Guys, if you want to reach out to me, please call me.
SPEAKER_0:  It's Michael at LexFreedman.com.
SPEAKER_0:  Friedman is spelled wrong. Yeah, if you ever have a-
SPEAKER_1:  Any complaints.
SPEAKER_1:  please just at me at Twitter.
SPEAKER_1:  About Michael now
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh...
SPEAKER_1:  Why do you think so few established authors?
SPEAKER_1:  self-publish.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, what?
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like it makes perfect sense in this modern society to be able to, when you finish the book.
SPEAKER_1:  to publish it within.
SPEAKER_0:  A few days, a few weeks. I think I talked to Jordan Peterson about this at length.
SPEAKER_0:  and Michaela, his daughter, who I'm also good friends with.
SPEAKER_0:  She's actually named after Gorbachev, who's the big hero of this book. Also a friend.
SPEAKER_0:  Mikhail Gor- you know I was-
SPEAKER_0:  In talks.
SPEAKER_0:  to interview Gorbachev.
SPEAKER_0:  And then COVID hit. And that's one of the big regrets of my life. I think if I met him, I would be.
SPEAKER_0:  on my knees, literally kissing his feet, crying.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, cause of, you know, I mean, one of the big points of the white pill.
SPEAKER_0:  is there were so many moments.
SPEAKER_0:  when they were calling him up.
SPEAKER_0:  Send in the tanks, we want another Tiananmen Square.
SPEAKER_0:  And he's like, fuck you.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  when you have anyone who has the capacity.
SPEAKER_0:  to murder.
SPEAKER_0:  thousands of people.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  chooses to withhold that power. Like all I could do is applaud.
SPEAKER_1:  this that the cynicism.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes. Wait, so why the authors, why don't they publish the books? I think they're still in the...
SPEAKER_0:  You know how like there's this whole idea about if you're a movie actor, you don't go on TV because that kind of ruins your brand?
SPEAKER_0:  So, and that's kind of going away. There's a lot of shows where the lead is now like a former movie actor. And this is kind of like a big thing, like Matthew McConaughey, you know, he had a TV show on HBO, I believe.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think there's this kind of like, wait a minute. What's that?
SPEAKER_0:  And he said, I said, all right.
SPEAKER_1:  I
SPEAKER_1:  Is it alright?
SPEAKER_1:  Alright alright alright.
SPEAKER_1:  Matthew McConaughey, alright, alright. I don't- I don't-
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know what that is. Sorry.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  I'll explain it. Look at the context below. Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think for them it might be A.
SPEAKER_0:  a loss of credibility to some extent.
SPEAKER_0:  but B.
SPEAKER_0:  They, their agent.
SPEAKER_0:  whose job is to sell them and get a big advance.
SPEAKER_0:  wouldn't be encouraged to self-publish because they're age, you know, so I don't think it's percolated to powerful people yet.
SPEAKER_0:  how feasible this is.
SPEAKER_0:  and how profitable it is.
SPEAKER_0:  And how they'll still be able to reach their audience.
SPEAKER_0:  feel.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I don't.
SPEAKER_0:  If Anarchist Handbook wasn't such a gigantic success...
SPEAKER_0:  Um, I would be more, more nervous about the white pill.
SPEAKER_0:  But the fact that it was, and that I saw it from start to finish and I know the ins and outs now I'm like, what are you guys bringing to the table? Besides taking years of my time.
SPEAKER_0:  and introducing edits that I would not otherwise agree with.
SPEAKER_1:  I think for some people a book is a...
SPEAKER_1:  is a sort of beacon of reputation. So it's really important to not.
SPEAKER_1:  There's somehow not as much reputation associated with self published book unless it's successful. Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  And then, and then like the.
SPEAKER_1:  It's success.
SPEAKER_1:  outshines the actual, however it was published.
SPEAKER_1:  I think, I guess David Goggins self-published his book.
SPEAKER_0:  Because it used to be you self-publish when you can't get a book deal. So it's like an admission of failure.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so you would recommend it as something for authors.
SPEAKER_0:  No, I would recommend it as something for authors of a certain...
SPEAKER_0:  stature for lack of a better term because it is still in terms of.
SPEAKER_0:  your resume and your experience.
SPEAKER_0:  It's better to get a crappy advance.
SPEAKER_0:  and have a book with St. Martin's that goes nowhere.
SPEAKER_0:  then
SPEAKER_0:  a self-published book that goes nowhere.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  The other thing is you have to make sure you have enough an audience that you can move some copies.
SPEAKER_1:  What about OnlyFans? Would you recommend authors?
SPEAKER_1:  How much money do you think you and I could make if we did like bathtub scenes?
SPEAKER_1:  Only fans not just chilling just reading like reading like Animal Farm
SPEAKER_1:  Just like.
SPEAKER_1:  while sitting in a bathroom. They live in the bathroom, you
SPEAKER_0:  can't wait to catch the rest of the fun
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know. I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  Snowball sorry snowball. Okay snowball
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  Uhhhhhh
SPEAKER_0:  Alright. What was his name? Snowball. No, the horse.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, boxer. I hung like a bug.
SPEAKER_1:  I will work harder.
SPEAKER_1:  And that guy, I think about-
SPEAKER_0:  that guy a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  Boxer?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, his motto was, I will work harder. Anything that happens like the.
SPEAKER_1:  the pigs would take advantage and...
SPEAKER_1:  his response to everything.
SPEAKER_1:  He was inspiring to me because he never gave in to the sin of...
SPEAKER_0:  This is right.
SPEAKER_0:  and they killed him.
SPEAKER_0:  Spoiler, sorry.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a good way to die, never giving in.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, yeah, there's a lot of that in this book about the people who are like, I'm not, you're not going to break me.
SPEAKER_0:  Like I am.
SPEAKER_0:  bigger than this.
SPEAKER_1:  Did you ever believe in Santa?
SPEAKER_0:  I remember the day.
SPEAKER_0:  I woke up on New Years and there was a president under my pillow and it was like, holy shit.
SPEAKER_0:  Cause DEDMOROZ LEFT IT.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the whole thing, he leaves your present under your pillow.
SPEAKER_1:  Right. So you believed, but what I thought the story was going to be when you first realized he's not real.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't remember when I realized he wasn't real, but that story was, I did think it was real. I was like, oh my god.
SPEAKER_1:  And okay.
SPEAKER_1:  There's this.
SPEAKER_1:  Cause I did too and I don't remember.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't think I can put myself in the mindset of the kind of person that believed
SPEAKER_1:  He was real.
SPEAKER_1:  What did I think? What was my world view that allowed?
SPEAKER_1:  Like a giant person in a red suit to be real.
SPEAKER_1:  Although I do remember, I think-
SPEAKER_1:  The first time a Santa Claus showed up.
SPEAKER_1:  to our, like, lived in this very small apartment.
SPEAKER_1:  And when he first showed up to our apartment.
SPEAKER_1:  I just remember it because he was really drunk and smelled.
SPEAKER_1:  It was like a party. It was like a new year's party or whatever. So one of the people dressed up with Santa Claus, I just remembered this.
SPEAKER_1:  Wow, this has gotten like real fast.
SPEAKER_1:  Of course, like I remember like thinking of course.
SPEAKER_1:  Of course it would be like, what was I thinking? It's going to be some perfect.
SPEAKER_1:  like being a perfect being like better than.
SPEAKER_1:  Like the best of humanity, he was just a regular dude.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of fat.
SPEAKER_1:  But like not sexy fat, it was like.
SPEAKER_1:  Not really that jolly
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of exhausted.
SPEAKER_1:  not showering well, but also funny.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember, I love telling this story.
SPEAKER_0:  how old I was and I must have been five or six.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was just that age where you distinguish between what's real and what's not.
SPEAKER_0:  So like Vikings.
SPEAKER_0:  and Nights and Ninjas are Real.
SPEAKER_0:  and dragons.
SPEAKER_0:  and mermaids.
SPEAKER_0:  and elves are fake.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was on the corner of Shore Parkway right before the park.
SPEAKER_0:  Bensonhurst in Brooklyn.
SPEAKER_0:  and around the corner wearing a denim vest.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... was a little person at work
SPEAKER_0:  And I saw him.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was like, all right, back to the drawing board. Like, I don't know what's real or not anymore because I just saw a dwarf. So I don't know what's going on.
SPEAKER_1:  And since then...
SPEAKER_1:  given your relationship with Alex Jones, you've continued the journey of not knowing what's real or not. That's correct.
SPEAKER_1:  Alright, let's talk about the next steps after Stalin took power.
SPEAKER_1:  he started to actually implementing some of the economic
SPEAKER_1:  some of the policies in this idea of
SPEAKER_1:  collectivization. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the story of that in the...
SPEAKER_1:  in the 20s.
SPEAKER_1:  leading into the 30s. What was this idea?
SPEAKER_1:  or is the relationship between the regime?
SPEAKER_1:  the ideology and the farmers.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, there's always been and obviously very much this day an enormous amount of
SPEAKER_0:  Em... Emily.
SPEAKER_0:  for lack of a better term, hatred between Ukraine and Russia. I mean, this is...
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  centuries in the making, if not more.
SPEAKER_0:  and the Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  or Ukraine now, but at the time, I'm speaking of the region.
SPEAKER_0:  is and still is the breadbasket of Europe. It was very fertile lands. This is where the food comes from.
SPEAKER_0:  And this was an issue also for Lenin.
SPEAKER_0:  as I discuss in the book, because when you had famines there...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you have famines.
SPEAKER_0:  throughout.
SPEAKER_0:  what later became the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  And the problem is this happened in North Korea as well in the 90s when they don't have food.
SPEAKER_0:  If you let in foreigners and feed your people.
SPEAKER_0:  all of a sudden you as the government are either superfluous
SPEAKER_0:  or downright.
SPEAKER_0:  deleterious to their well-being and that's a threat to your power.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, so Lenin let in.
SPEAKER_0:  an American organization, the early 20s, which is actually headed by Herbert Hoover of all people.
SPEAKER_0:  And after a while, Hoover left because he found that the Bolsheviks were just taking the grain that the Americans were giving to feed the people and selling it for export.
SPEAKER_0:  while the people suffered. And one of the people who grew up in these
SPEAKER_0:  uh... starvation times was a young mikhail gorbachev where he had you know i think it's like a quarter or a third of his village starved to death
SPEAKER_0:  during one of these periodic famines.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, Stalin's idea, this was a good-
SPEAKER_0:  mechanism for him.
SPEAKER_0:  to break.
SPEAKER_0:  the idea of Ukraine being an independent.
SPEAKER_0:  nation within its own identity.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and you know, he had this kind of liquidation of the cool locks, you know, very famously, which thankfully is much more discussed now.
SPEAKER_0:  than it was maybe when you and I were kids.
SPEAKER_0:  And a kulak, the real meaning or the literal meaning is kind of this wealthy landowner.
SPEAKER_0:  But very quickly, it's kind of like it becomes outgroup.
SPEAKER_0:  So, you know, there was a...
SPEAKER_0:  a big incentive.
SPEAKER_0:  call someone you didn't like a cool lock and then good luck to you because now the eyes of the state are on you
SPEAKER_0:  and you have to prove that you know you didn't.
SPEAKER_0:  hire people, you didn't have four cows or how many acres or so and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  They took a huge
SPEAKER_0:  percentage of the population, the cool locks.
SPEAKER_0:  and they just deported them.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, these are lands that they had for generations and they just spread them throughout.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, uh, uh, broader Russia. Many of them never made it. And many of them were killed. This was by design.
SPEAKER_1:  And the dark thing about the cool locks, like you said.
SPEAKER_1:  when it becomes abused, when it becomes the outgroup.
SPEAKER_1:  is.
SPEAKER_1:  Kuok is supposed to be.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... wealthier
SPEAKER_1:  and sort of the general.
SPEAKER_1:  farmer-peasant.
SPEAKER_1:  And so basically it gives you a mechanism of resentment. And yes, that's better off.
SPEAKER_1:  must be better off because they're cool. Let's get rid of them.
SPEAKER_1:  And it has a-
SPEAKER_1:  uh... just from an economics perspective
SPEAKER_1:  even leaving ethics aside.
SPEAKER_1:  It basically completely de-incentivizes.
SPEAKER_1:  productivity.
SPEAKER_1:  It wants you to fail because if you succeed your cool lock you're going to be tortured you can be deported
SPEAKER_1:  Are you going to be dera-
SPEAKER_0:  I did all that. And also you're poor because he's rich.
SPEAKER_0:  Like that's a big part of it.
SPEAKER_0:  So while this was going on and food was becoming a problem because you had a
SPEAKER_0:  for weather conditions.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, there was a campaign about, oh, the reason you're hungry.
SPEAKER_0:  is because the cool locks are hoarding all their grain.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you're somewhere else in the Soviet Union, how are you supposed to know any better?
SPEAKER_0:  because you're being told every year the crops are.
SPEAKER_0:  Bumper crop, bumper crop, bumper crop, now there's no food, there's no bread.
SPEAKER_0:  And so, you see, we produced all this bread. It's not getting to you because the Kool-Ax are hoarding the grain.
SPEAKER_0:  So they came like in what became known as the Haldemore and Applebaum who's a great historian.
SPEAKER_0:  who unfortunately I disagree with a lot in contemporary politics, but who's done so much great work.
SPEAKER_0:  about.
SPEAKER_0:  the Soviet Union that I...
SPEAKER_0:  pretty much give her a blank check and whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  she wants to say nowadays.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, she wrote a great book about this called Red Famine.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  these activists descended on these villages like locusts.
SPEAKER_0:  and their job was to requisition as much food as possible.
SPEAKER_0:  and they would come back at all hours of the night to make sure you weren't hiding food.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is what was so...
SPEAKER_0:  pernicious about it.
SPEAKER_0:  your own body would betray you.
SPEAKER_0:  They could look at you.
SPEAKER_0:  and see that you're not losing weight.
SPEAKER_0:  Got those chubby cheeks?
SPEAKER_0:  That means you have food and that's the government's food.
SPEAKER_0:  That is the food of the people. And if you are keeping food for yourself, you are stealing from the people. You're an enemy of the people and you deserve whatever comes to you.
SPEAKER_0:  And it got to a point where they didn't have grain to-
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  plant for the next harvest.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and.
SPEAKER_0:  what was even sicker.
SPEAKER_0:  is one of the big criticisms of communists.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Tsar was his internal passport system that...
SPEAKER_0:  I can't go where I want within.
SPEAKER_0:  Russia, the Russian Empire, without permission.
SPEAKER_0:  Stalin reintroduced this.
SPEAKER_0:  So if your village was targeted, you can't leave.
SPEAKER_0:  Now some people got away, they tried to get to the cities and so on and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  but you get to the city.
SPEAKER_0:  and you're starving, you have no clothes.
SPEAKER_0:  You're a Coolock!
SPEAKER_0:  I'm hungry because of you and now you're too lazy to work. Get the F out of there.
SPEAKER_0:  And there were stories, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I have them in the white pill of this like starving teenage girl and she's
SPEAKER_0:  begging for food.
SPEAKER_0:  And the guy knocks the shopkeeper knocks the food out of her hand and she dies on the spot and everyone in that line knew not to, you know, give her.
SPEAKER_0:  any food or any sympathy because she's a Kulak sympathizer and very quickly if you're a Kulak sympathizer all that has to happen is someone has to call
SPEAKER_0:  I think it was the NKVD at the time, you know, the different names of the checker.
SPEAKER_0:  the secret police and they have to be like, oh.
SPEAKER_0:  You see, whatever her name was, Genia?
SPEAKER_0:  She was a Kulak sympathizer. We saw Kulak.
SPEAKER_0:  who was trying to shake us down for food too lazy to work and she
SPEAKER_0:  felt so bad for them. So you might want to check in on Zhenya. So yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  But in 32 and 33.
SPEAKER_1:  Call it a More.
SPEAKER_1:  It wasn't just...
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Small injustice here and there.
SPEAKER_1:  It was...
SPEAKER_1:  Mass starvation and suffering.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, millions starve to death.
SPEAKER_0:  in the Ukraine alone.
SPEAKER_0:  and by design.
SPEAKER_1:  So you mentioned an Apple bombs book, Red Famine, Star Wars 1 Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  but another excellent book on the topic. And by the way, thank you for recommending that to me. So, Was.
SPEAKER_1:  Her work's amazing.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's a really, really powerful.
SPEAKER_1:  a book about not just about Hanumer, but like the context of Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  Basically the history of Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  that's relevant for today. Ya.
SPEAKER_1:  to understand the relationship between Russia and Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  But another great book is Bloodlands Europe Between Hitler and Stalin by Timothy Snyder. I don't know, I think you also recommended that to me at some point, or maybe not.
SPEAKER_0:  I haven't but I'm familiar with that and read it. So he-
SPEAKER_1:  He does quite a bit of, it's brief, but extremely well researched writing about cannibalism there.
SPEAKER_1:  and that it was not uncommon during the Stalin imposed famine in the Soviet Ukraine for parents to cook and eat their children.
SPEAKER_1:  He writes, quote,
SPEAKER_1:  Survival was a moral as well as a physical struggle. A woman doctor wrote to a friend in June 1933 that she had not yet become.
SPEAKER_1:  a cannibal.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  was not sure that I shall not be won by the time my letter reaches you.
SPEAKER_1:  in quotes.
SPEAKER_1:  The good people died first. Those who refused to steal or to prostitute themselves died.
SPEAKER_1:  Those who gave food to others died.
SPEAKER_1:  Those who refused to eat corpses died.
SPEAKER_1:  Those who refused to kill their fellow man died.
SPEAKER_1:  Parents who resisted cannibalism died before their children did. There are stories in there about...
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, cooking. Cooking your children.
SPEAKER_1:  The other thing about
SPEAKER_1:  cannibalism about famine in general.
SPEAKER_1:  that stood out to me, unlike a lot of atrocities.
SPEAKER_1:  is the people that are starving.
SPEAKER_1:  are exhausted.
SPEAKER_1:  They're basically unable to think.
SPEAKER_1:  so they don't even have the energy to protest.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a strange kind of way.
SPEAKER_1:  to kill thinking in the populace.
SPEAKER_1:  That it kind of, I suppose it was obvious.
SPEAKER_1:  but there's something fundamental about starvation where...
SPEAKER_1:  It slowly removes your humanity.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there was a scene in the book where...
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of times people literally go crazy.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's a scene where mom at some nursing, a train station was nursing her kid.
SPEAKER_0:  She was going mad from hunger.
SPEAKER_0:  and she starts beating the crap out of her baby and kicking it and then she just reverts to normal like nothing had happened.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, madness. Like you lose, yeah, you lose your mind. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I don't know what the physiological cause of this. It's not just, I think it's, you know, if someone has dealt with like glycogen depletion, it affects their mood, things like that. So taking to an extreme, who knows what happens when.
SPEAKER_0:  parts of the brain start functioning and start imploding.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  But yeah, it's...
SPEAKER_0:  what i want what just happened this is something that's really cool regarding the holodomor
SPEAKER_0:  So there was one.
SPEAKER_0:  Western journalist, Gareth Jones.
SPEAKER_0:  who was like, all right, something's not adding up here.
SPEAKER_0:  So he was supposed to take a train.
SPEAKER_0:  through Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  and he got out early.
SPEAKER_0:  and decided to start walking through the countryside to go from village to village.
SPEAKER_0:  and I'll get to his story in a minute.
SPEAKER_0:  right before we started recording.
SPEAKER_0:  I got this book in the mail. I ordered it on November 28th.
SPEAKER_0:  from Great Britain. It was the only copy available on the whole internet.
SPEAKER_0:  It's called Experiences in Russian 1931. It is anonymous.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's
SPEAKER_0:  Uh
SPEAKER_0:  Gareth Jones wrote the introduction. It was published by the Alton Press in Pittsburgh. It was self-published.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  See, it just says forward, it just says by the author.
SPEAKER_0:  So it was the author who went alongside.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Gareth Jones was summoned by the name of...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Henry John Hines.
SPEAKER_0:  who was...
SPEAKER_0:  Heir to the Heinz fortune.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  You only know that if you start looking at the internet because his name is not anywhere his book.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I opened this book up right when I got it.
SPEAKER_0:  right before we're taping.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's signed by him.
SPEAKER_0:  And it took me a second. I'm like, wait a minute, who's this signed by? And it's H.J. Hines because his name was Jack Hines, but it was Henry John Hines.
SPEAKER_0:  So I'm very excited that I had this little miracle in the mail.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, but Christmas miracle. It's a Christmas miracle. Um, traveled, they traveled together. They traveled together. So this book's a diary of their travels.
SPEAKER_1:  Why do you think so few journalists?
SPEAKER_1:  they was able to do with you.
SPEAKER_0:  So there were several reasons. First of all, if you were a Western journalist in the Soviet Union,
SPEAKER_0:  you're under very strict
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  First of all, you could be deported anytime.
SPEAKER_0:  You had no, there was no pretense.
SPEAKER_0:  that you have a right to be a journalist in.
SPEAKER_0:  especially as a representative of a capitalist by which they met Western paper.
SPEAKER_0:  Second, it was a complete nightmare getting your articles filed.
SPEAKER_0:  because you had a censor that you had to go through and the censor's job, whose life depended on it, was to make sure that your story was advantageous to the Soviet Union, or at least neutral.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, and they had all sorts of techniques, you know, they could spy, they spied on you all the time. They followed you around because you know, you're a foreigner.
SPEAKER_0:  but also that sensor had to answer somebody.
SPEAKER_0:  So all the sensor has to do is be like, look, I'm having trouble with my supervisor.
SPEAKER_0:  And the reporter could be like, well, can I talk to supervisor? It's like, well, I'm sorry, that's not possible. And he's on deadline, but it's too bad. Bureaucracy doesn't recognize the needs of deadlines. So.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a big.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of pressure.
SPEAKER_0:  on Western journalists to.
SPEAKER_0:  have to get through this net and that's literally constant. You know, every story it's going to be a fight.
SPEAKER_0:  So at a certain point, you're just going to be like, all right, and you're going to pre-sensor yourself. You know, if you know...
SPEAKER_0:  Alright, if I include this, it's not going to get through. What are you supposed to do?
SPEAKER_0:  I think human beings are naturally, and also a lot of these journalists were.
SPEAKER_0:  pro-soviet.
SPEAKER_0:  They thought.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the society, the future.
SPEAKER_0:  At least everyone's trying.
SPEAKER_0:  to make it a better country for everyone, not like back home.
SPEAKER_0:  with a poor slip between the cracks.
SPEAKER_0:  We gotta do what we can to make this work.
SPEAKER_0:  And...
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  There was.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of, I don't want to say conspiracy, but within the industry.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a consensus.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  The Stalin was the good guy, and we were, if not the bad guys, certainly not as good.
SPEAKER_0:  in certain regards.
SPEAKER_0:  So when this news of the famine started percolating...
SPEAKER_0:  all the other Western journalists besides Gareth Jones and Malcolm Muggeridge
SPEAKER_0:  We're saying this isn't true.
SPEAKER_0:  It's nothing that they haven't seen before.
SPEAKER_0:  Paper that took the lead in this was New York Times with
SPEAKER_0:  their guy Walter Durante who had previously won a Pulitzer.
SPEAKER_0:  I had interviewed Stalin, which was an enormously rare honor for a Westerner.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and he, because he has so much experience covering Russia and the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  He basically took the lead and other people followed his lead. You know, he was kind of the Dean.
SPEAKER_0:  of the press corps in Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... and he made a point and the thing that they just so many quotes i have from him
SPEAKER_0:  where he's not only denying that this mass starvation is happening, he's also going after journalists who are questioning the narrative.
SPEAKER_0:  and he says things like, look.
SPEAKER_0:  This is nothing that the Russians haven't experienced before they're simply tightening their belts and it's like
SPEAKER_0:  You only have to tighten your belt.
SPEAKER_0:  When you don't have enough food, it's not like they started a new exercise regimen and now their body fat's dropping. That's why would someone tighten their belt?
SPEAKER_0:  So that was one.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  The New York Times had a 13 page.
SPEAKER_0:  article.
SPEAKER_0:  Big headline, Russians hungry, not starving.
SPEAKER_0:  And he went after Jones, he went after-
SPEAKER_0:  I believe
SPEAKER_0:  No, he did go after Margarit, but the point being that...
SPEAKER_0:  This is just propaganda from people who want the Soviet Union to fail.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, they don't understand what they're building here. Uh, you know, he had so many excuses like, Oh,
SPEAKER_0:  You know, the reason.
SPEAKER_0:  All these Russians are supposedly leaving their villages to go to the cities isn't because there's no food. It's because they're nomadic. It's tradition. They go from town to town looking for new experiences and it's just.
SPEAKER_0:  at a certain point, and I think it was 1941.
SPEAKER_0:  where he was eventually like, or 51 rather, I don't remember.
SPEAKER_0:  He was like, oh, well, uh.
SPEAKER_0:  I guess I was kind of wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like, he's like, any journalist worth his salt can admit when he's wrong. And it's like, well, were you worth your salt?
SPEAKER_0:  because you sure, he explicitly said.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no point.
SPEAKER_0:  in.
SPEAKER_0:  sending out journalists to look for themselves. I've been through the countryside and everyone's fine. And it's just that the loudest people are making noise, whereas everyone else is doing the work and trying to...
SPEAKER_0:  And this isn't about famine, but it's about Westerners skeptical about collectivization, which is just simply a new way of farming. And yeah, it was a new way of farming, and the results were by design.
SPEAKER_0:  and also accidentally, absolutely catastrophic.
SPEAKER_0:  Ha ha
SPEAKER_1:  How?
SPEAKER_1:  How hard was it?
SPEAKER_1:  to see the truth at that time, do you think?
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think that was a mistake that's understandable to make?
SPEAKER_1:  This is Journalist.
SPEAKER_0:  if my job.
SPEAKER_0:  as a journalist.
SPEAKER_0:  I have two bosses if I'm in Moscow.
SPEAKER_0:  I've got my reporter in New York or London or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  but I've got my sensor.
SPEAKER_0:  here.
SPEAKER_0:  and he is making sure I have.
SPEAKER_0:  house?
SPEAKER_0:  The department.
SPEAKER_0:  He makes sure I have food.
SPEAKER_0:  you make sure you have access to dignitaries.
SPEAKER_0:  He's my lifeline.
SPEAKER_0:  If I piss him off...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm on the next plane.
SPEAKER_0:  Out of town.
SPEAKER_0:  So that enough.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that enough to uh...
SPEAKER_1:  slowly
SPEAKER_1:  suffocate the integrity of a journalist.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think it was slow at all and it was clearly enough. And because what are they going to do?
SPEAKER_1:  I disagree with that. I think the failure of integrity...
SPEAKER_1:  has to come from the New York and the American side.
SPEAKER_1:  that it's just the flock of fish or whatever that all move in the same.
SPEAKER_1:  narrative
SPEAKER_1:  Right.
SPEAKER_1:  I think journalists
SPEAKER_1:  would like to be the kind of people that have integrity.
SPEAKER_1:  So if they are conscious of sacrificing their own integrity, they wouldn't do it. If they're conscious of an act.
SPEAKER_1:  that's doing it, they wouldn't do it.
SPEAKER_1:  So it has to happen like a lobster slowly boiling.
SPEAKER_0:  No, I think it happens when everyone else...
SPEAKER_0:  is it's a it's a Greek card.
SPEAKER_1:  Right, right, it's a chorus. That's right. So it's not about the act.
SPEAKER_1:  But they will, I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  I've talked to no journalists where I'm.
SPEAKER_1:  I get the sense.
SPEAKER_1:  that they will sell the.
SPEAKER_0:  sold for access.
SPEAKER_0:  because that's their job.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it though?
SPEAKER_1:  because what they do, what journalists do...
SPEAKER_1:  I've seen American journalists.
SPEAKER_1:  They.
SPEAKER_1:  Take a huge amount of pride for having gotten.
SPEAKER_1:  The interview, whatever that is, the Putin interview.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  First of all, they're glowing with pride.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like they're always showing off to the other journalists back in America.
SPEAKER_1:  So they're showing off like, look, I got the access you didn't.
SPEAKER_1:  And second thing they're doing when they show up to that interview is they ask all the questions that signal to the other journalists.
SPEAKER_1:  We're on the same side.
SPEAKER_1:  They asked the most generic.
SPEAKER_1:  Aggressive.
SPEAKER_1:  questions to which they know the answers.
SPEAKER_1:  to, they just, they want to.
SPEAKER_1:  I want to basically get the access and ask.
SPEAKER_1:  the quote unquote, hard hitting questions.
SPEAKER_1:  that they know will not be answered.
SPEAKER_1:  And this is the entire machinery of it. It's not, it's-
SPEAKER_1:  This modern journalism.
SPEAKER_1:  And I suppose at that time...
SPEAKER_1:  It was worse? It was worse?
SPEAKER_1:  They weren't even doing the hard hitting, the display of hard hitting.
SPEAKER_0:  questions.
SPEAKER_0:  Because think about what
SPEAKER_0:  high status that is.
SPEAKER_0:  If I'm an American journalist in Moscow, I'm-
SPEAKER_0:  allowed in this secretive country.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm in a- I'm the- I'm the guy!
SPEAKER_0:  who's very privileged to have access.
SPEAKER_0:  to live in Moscow and tell Americans, which were all fascinated about this new society, the future, what it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  and as soon as I...
SPEAKER_0:  Kinda.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... start questioning the narrative i'm gonna get kicked out of humiliated very publicly it will well i thought you're in moscow what am i supposed to say
SPEAKER_0:  So, you know, they...
SPEAKER_0:  Eugene Lyons.
SPEAKER_0:  was, you know, he's one of the heroes in the book. He was a young communist and I think he was United Press.
SPEAKER_0:  he was working for, they sent him there.
SPEAKER_0:  And when he went there, he's like, oh, this is not what I thought it was going to be like. This is horrible. And he's turned very heavily against it.
SPEAKER_0:  but he talks about how
SPEAKER_0:  they would write one thing.
SPEAKER_0:  and say another thing and then think another thing. And each of those steps was just more and more like kind of lying.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of maintaining your sanity and maintaining your narrative.
SPEAKER_1:  So you...
SPEAKER_1:  reference an Apple bomb.
SPEAKER_1:  and say that, quote, starvation was not simply a consequence, it was the goal and it was the law. Stalin intended to break the Ukrainians once and for all.
SPEAKER_1:  It thus became common for villagers to spy and inform on one another, turning in a neighbor
SPEAKER_1:  for having a sack of grain might be the...
SPEAKER_1:  easiest and safest way to procure food.
SPEAKER_1:  for one's family. Without using any of the
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  To what degree was this the intention?
SPEAKER_1:  To what degree does Stalin anticipate this kind of
SPEAKER_1:  suffering as a consequence of the collectivization.
SPEAKER_1:  policy.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know that he intended the suffering to be a consequence of the collectivization.
SPEAKER_0:  But he, it was.
SPEAKER_0:  Quite.
SPEAKER_0:  apparent and I think there's a pretty heavy consensus nowadays.
SPEAKER_0:  that his goal was very much
SPEAKER_0:  because Ukraine again.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, resent to the czar and had this kind of very contentious relationship.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, with Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  which obviously very clearly remains today. I mean, the hatred of Ukrainians for Russians proceeded.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin's war, I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  This is even when I was a kid, this, uh, you know, I obviously don't remember it, but my parents just told me like the hatred that they had and understandably, I mean, they're basically under foreign occupation. Uh, what they were going to support an occupation for.
SPEAKER_1:  So your parents talked about a hatred.
SPEAKER_1:  by Ukrainian stores Russian.
SPEAKER_0:  Yo yes
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yes.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  I certainly haven't visited there this year.
SPEAKER_1:  because of the most recent invasion in February.
SPEAKER_1:  that hatred.
SPEAKER_1:  is nationwide and very intense.
SPEAKER_1:  But I don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  I think the feeling, the emotions were much more complex before.
SPEAKER_0:  But at the same time, they were under occupation before, right? And they couldn't speak Ukrainian. They had to speak Russian.
SPEAKER_0:  So this was a thing.
SPEAKER_0:  but because of the force...
SPEAKER_1:  intermixing.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a more complex story.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, they weren't certainly fans.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, but there's...
SPEAKER_1:  people that came from Russia, they're living there, they're marrying, they're falling in love, they're working with each other. So like there is the bigger atrocity of the genocide of it.
SPEAKER_1:  but there's also the reality of...
SPEAKER_1:  intermixing of the people.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, sure. I mean, let's say.
SPEAKER_1:  atrocity of slavery.
SPEAKER_1:  in the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  but then there's also a reality that there's now an intermixing of a
SPEAKER_1:  of other peoples and they fall in love and they live after slavery is abolished.
SPEAKER_1:  That's just the reality.
SPEAKER_1:  after the genocide.,
SPEAKER_1:  proceeds.
SPEAKER_1:  a kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  generational integration.
SPEAKER_1:  that still remembers, like the suffering reverberates, but they're still...
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  It's a different culture that's created.
SPEAKER_1:  And now...
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I have complex story.
SPEAKER_1:  Most of my family is from Ukraine. So I have a
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  It's my understanding.
SPEAKER_1:  is grounded in...
SPEAKER_1:  Soviet Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  But there is something...
SPEAKER_1:  in the last 30 years.
SPEAKER_1:  that's different.
SPEAKER_1:  Where now, after the collapse of the Soviet Union, there's a true...
SPEAKER_1:  maybe a renewed fight for independence.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a different thing.
SPEAKER_0:  But there's also a difference, like, you know, if I go to North Korea as an American.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? They're very friendly.
SPEAKER_0:  Now.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? They don't perceive me.
SPEAKER_0:  as part of the
SPEAKER_0:  Yank devils.
SPEAKER_0:  They're like, okay, you're an American, but you, you know, you come from America, so...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there's going to be intermarriage, but that's the big difference between.
SPEAKER_0:  perception of
SPEAKER_0:  Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  as an entity.
SPEAKER_0:  as opposed to some individual Russians.
SPEAKER_1:  I just, that wasn't the...
SPEAKER_1:  the experience I've had talking to a lot of friends and family in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  until the war starts.
SPEAKER_0:  Really? So they really didn't have this kind of low-key animosity toward Russians? No.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a lot of.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... factional conflict
SPEAKER_1:  inside Ukraine. OK.
SPEAKER_1:  Now the whole country is united. I think I think there's a clarity now
SPEAKER_1:  The war gave a clarity.
SPEAKER_0:  that wasn't there before.
SPEAKER_0:  No, this is I was saying earlier how humans define themselves by opposition. So now that there's a war, it's like, okay, this all this little stuff doesn't matter. We are all united because we have a common enemy.
SPEAKER_1:  But there's also, as you know, there's...
SPEAKER_1:  regions and there's
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  There's just groups of different people that people, and then one of the big divides of course is the city versus rural.
SPEAKER_1:  And then in the case of Ukraine, it's...
SPEAKER_1:  Eastern Ukraine and Western Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  It's very difficult to know what the truth is.
SPEAKER_1:  because my personal experience is sampled. Right.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know how many Ukrainians I know, maybe like 30 or 40, before this trip, like 30 or 40.
SPEAKER_1:  and then I'm close with just a handful.
SPEAKER_1:  but then it's hard to know because you get a lot of western press perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  and you get the Russian perspective and you get other perspectives. It's very hard to know.
SPEAKER_1:  how much hate there is.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  outside of this.
SPEAKER_1:  conflict.
SPEAKER_1:  My primary question is, and this is what I ask a lot of people when I...
SPEAKER_1:  visited Ukraine as...
SPEAKER_1:  Will you ever be able to forgive the Russians?
SPEAKER_1:  And a lot of people said.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... never
SPEAKER_1:  Never.
SPEAKER_1:  So this isn't just about.
SPEAKER_1:  Assuming assuming we win
SPEAKER_1:  they would say.
SPEAKER_1:  Assuming we win, we still will not ever forgive.
SPEAKER_1:  Never forgive.
SPEAKER_1:  And they said it in a way where like...
SPEAKER_1:  not only us but our children.
SPEAKER_1:  never forgive.
SPEAKER_1:  And it wasn't just, you know what, it wasn't just about.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Russia or the Russian leadership.
SPEAKER_1:  is about the Russian people.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  But a lot of people also said that this is our feeling currently, we understand. Like you're lost in the rage of war. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Because you lose so much. I mean, if you asked Americans, would you ever be friends with Germany or Japan? It'd be like, are you kidding?
SPEAKER_0:  After Pearl Harbor?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, but of course most Americas didn't feel Pearl Harbor.
SPEAKER_1:  is different.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  It's a good point when it's your own land, but uh...
SPEAKER_1:  What when?
SPEAKER_1:  imagine was just pro-harbor but it was new york right
SPEAKER_1:  and Chicago.
SPEAKER_1:  and Dallas and all these cities being, being bombed. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  It's...
SPEAKER_1:  just to linger on this war in Ukraine currently.
SPEAKER_1:  Does it break your heart to see what's going on there now that it's in the same land?
SPEAKER_1:  as
SPEAKER_1:  The same series.
SPEAKER_1:  The same stories are now brought back to the surface.
SPEAKER_1:  to pit the generational pain.
SPEAKER_1:  as it was in the time that you're writing about.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think it's a fundamentally different?
SPEAKER_1:  country different war different situation or does it do you see here echoes of the same.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think it's the same because I think there is.
SPEAKER_0:  no one, I mean, there is no one.
SPEAKER_0:  Pooh.
SPEAKER_0:  is like, I'm glad this is happening to the Ukrainian people.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  So even.
SPEAKER_0:  people who are for.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin and for the invasion.
SPEAKER_0:  and whatever justification they might have for his war.
SPEAKER_0:  No one is like, yeah, let's get those darn Ukrainians.
SPEAKER_0:  I think there was that sense in America after 9-11.
SPEAKER_0:  when we invade Afghanistan.
SPEAKER_0:  and Iraq and there was like F those Iraqis F those Afghan people.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Whereas now...
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's completely the opposite. I also think a lot of-
SPEAKER_0:  Russians, I'm sure if I ask them.
SPEAKER_0:  They're not.
SPEAKER_0:  thinking like, let's wipe the Ukrainian people off the map. I think whatever reasons they have, it's not.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of going after this. Even if you have to kind of rile up people against the citizenry, it's not to that level.
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  The H of the Coolox.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... hatred of
SPEAKER_0:  of those villages.
SPEAKER_1:  There's still a belief though.
SPEAKER_1:  amongst the soldiers outside the big cities, their belief that the Ukrainian people
SPEAKER_1:  who the Russian soldiers believe are their brothers and sisters.
SPEAKER_1:  are occupied by an evil regime.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so you need to save them from the evil of...
SPEAKER_0:  regime. That's also very different from
SPEAKER_0:  Yes. So tomorrow morningק he said he wanted to another morning?
SPEAKER_0:  And also...
SPEAKER_0:  There is...
SPEAKER_0:  dispute in the press.
SPEAKER_0:  about.
SPEAKER_0:  causes.
SPEAKER_0:  consequences, the victims, the villains of...
SPEAKER_0:  Putin's war.
SPEAKER_0:  But when it came to this...
SPEAKER_0:  No one is denying.
SPEAKER_0:  that the war is happening.
SPEAKER_0:  The New York Times isn't saying.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything is fine.
SPEAKER_0:  And the only reason people are saying it's a problem is because they hate.
SPEAKER_0:  Putin or the H. Zulinski. That's not a thing.
SPEAKER_0:  and the fact that we have so much footage.
SPEAKER_0:  of what's happening in Ukraine. And you know, you have, it takes two seconds to go on Google and you have a map of, you know, Russian advancement.
SPEAKER_0:  parts of the occupying, what parts are not under the control.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, you know, I did a little live stream. I raised money for Ukrainian refugees.
SPEAKER_0:  to feed them because that's my concern, is just keeping people fed.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  There was none of that, you know, and, and, uh, the, the two people who kind of spoke the truth, Gareth Jones was shot, I think, the day.
SPEAKER_0:  before his 30th birthday while he was on...
SPEAKER_0:  uncovering news, I think it was in Mongolia.
SPEAKER_0:  Malcolm Margaridge.
SPEAKER_0:  had problem finding work when he exposed this.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and I think the, like we was talking about earlier, the ubiquity.
SPEAKER_0:  of things like cell phones and camera phones.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... would make something like this
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, I wouldn't say an impossibility, they could still do it.
SPEAKER_0:  but it would be really hard.
SPEAKER_0:  to cover it up.
SPEAKER_1:  Well...
SPEAKER_1:  Sir.
SPEAKER_1:  Push back on that if you just look at Iran.
SPEAKER_1:  I would draw a different side. I agree with you mostly, but I would also draw a different distinction when the atrocity is happening.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  your own people versus there's a war you crane is a sovereign independent nation there's now a war between two nations
SPEAKER_1:  It feels like it's easier for journalists to somehow reveal the truth in that.
SPEAKER_1:  when atrocities happen within the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_1:  for some reason that's easier to hide.
SPEAKER_1:  that's easier for journalists to deceive themselves and easier for the authoritarian leader to hide the information. I think I agree with you. And so that's...
SPEAKER_1:  That's the dark.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, that's why people maybe, maybe you can.
SPEAKER_1:  educate me on this, but this is why I think.
SPEAKER_1:  people don't talk about uh...
SPEAKER_1:  or more.
SPEAKER_1:  and other atrocities, the greatly forward.
SPEAKER_1:  Because it's inside the country. Yep.
SPEAKER_1:  versus the Holocaust that's part of a war.
SPEAKER_1:  What? Why is that?
SPEAKER_1:  that we...
SPEAKER_1:  The word too almost like
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  afraid to polite to what is it that we don't want to cover the atrocities because side the country gets their business
SPEAKER_1:  so we don't want to touch it. I don't get it.
SPEAKER_0:  What is it? I think it's that-
SPEAKER_0:  what we refer to as the news.
SPEAKER_0:  is in the business of selling narratives, right?
SPEAKER_0:  And the narrative of the Holocaust is a very powerful one, which is
SPEAKER_0:  If you let hatred
SPEAKER_0:  of a subgroup in a population.
SPEAKER_0:  Get out of control.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the ultimate.
SPEAKER_0:  consequence and this is something that we all have to be scared of.
SPEAKER_0:  and do everything in our power to avoid in the future for any.
SPEAKER_0:  group. Whereas what's the narrative of
SPEAKER_0:  The Hollidahmore.
SPEAKER_0:  Sometimes governments kill their own citizens. There's nothing you could do about it. There's nothing we, I mean, they wouldn't have let us send food. They wouldn't acknowledge, like the newspapers, even Russia weren't acknowledging it. Like, what's the, like, this is some of the issues I had.
SPEAKER_0:  with regard to trying to advocate for the North Korean people.
SPEAKER_0:  The reporters would be like, well, what can I do as an American? It's a very natural question. And I'm like, I don't know. I like, all I know is how to speak.
SPEAKER_0:  to what is happening.
SPEAKER_0:  But in terms of next steps, I don't have a good answer for you. So that is where.
SPEAKER_0:  the news kind of-
SPEAKER_0:  does break down.
SPEAKER_0:  If there isn't a story or a call to action.
SPEAKER_0:  the kind of you're kind of almost like.
SPEAKER_0:  having a movie with a cliffhanger and there's no sequel, it's like, what am I supposed to do here?
SPEAKER_0:  Like this is not scratching that itch, which for me, as a consumer of news, you know, a layman is like, okay, here's the story. There was a bad guy and the cop shot him or they took him to jail and now the bad guys caught.
SPEAKER_0:  Beginning middle end.
SPEAKER_0:  Here it's just like, Mal did this.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of people were executed and starved, isn't that awful?
SPEAKER_0:  well, and now still in power now Richard Nixon is raising a toast to him like that story is just like, how am I supposed to feel about this?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it feels like when there's tanks and there's war and this military conflict, then I'm-
SPEAKER_1:  It's more actionable. You can cover it. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  And it did seem like Nazi Germany.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if the Holocaust was the thing that made it most coverable. I think it was that this is a threat to the entire.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, yeah, we were at war with them, yeah. That's what makes a cover wall in-
SPEAKER_1:  if the Holocaust was happening just inside the country.
SPEAKER_1:  inside of Germany.
SPEAKER_1:  or even if it didn't expand beyond Poland.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it would be like a footnote. It wasn't in many ways a footnote. Like many of the early steps toward it was like they didn't cover it. It's just like, all right, they're being oppressive toward their own people, okay.
SPEAKER_1:  especially given some of the
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe if you negotiate certain
SPEAKER_1:  peace treaties with the Soviet Union and with Germany. Your two, uh, the basic-
SPEAKER_1:  to pacifist imperative.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh boy.
SPEAKER_0:  Sorry, Santa.
SPEAKER_1:  So we say every time you masturbate.
SPEAKER_1:  No.
SPEAKER_1:  after you're done.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I'm sorry.
SPEAKER_1:  Fuck that.
SPEAKER_1:  Alright.
SPEAKER_1:  Now see, I hate it when you don't yes and because it leaves me in a hole I dug for myself.
SPEAKER_1:  Um,
SPEAKER_1:  and I sit there in a hole.
SPEAKER_1:  in my sadness.
SPEAKER_1:  How long have you been writing this book? I mean, how long? Two years. Mentally, it was like two years since you spent time with it. But, um...
SPEAKER_0:  No, almost three.
SPEAKER_1:  half, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  And I suppose it stages you much longer, like you said, your family.
SPEAKER_1:  So in many ways, this is a book you've been writing your whole life.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's fair that all my work's been leading to this, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  It's certainly the most, in my opinion, the most important thing I've done.
SPEAKER_1:  What stands out to you?
SPEAKER_1:  about Hollermore.
SPEAKER_1:  What moments?
SPEAKER_1:  What aspects of human nature stand out to you?
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know. I think that story is, I don't want to say story, but I mean like that incident.
SPEAKER_0:  is...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I was familiar with it before.
SPEAKER_0:  You know what I mean? So I kind of knew about it, you know, in part, thanks to kind of the North Korean work.
SPEAKER_0:  And it.
SPEAKER_0:  coming from Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, the thing that was also.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of insane about it is that they were taking all this grain.
SPEAKER_0:  and not using it even to feed the Russian people. They were selling it for export for hard currency.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I think...
SPEAKER_0:  W-what?
SPEAKER_0:  The takeaway there.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think, again, this is something Westerners and especially Americans don't appreciate.
SPEAKER_0:  They think that evil often has...
SPEAKER_0:  Like a logic to it?
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like, why would, like, because it makes no sense to them, like, why would they kill their own people?
SPEAKER_0:  Therefore, it probably didn't happen. Right? There's that thing. They really think like, okay,
SPEAKER_0:  They can understand, you know, country A, country B.
SPEAKER_0:  You slaughter as a bunch of people country B as a means of conquest. Like that kind of makes sense to them. They know that thing.
SPEAKER_0:  But like.
SPEAKER_0:  Why you-
SPEAKER_0:  starving all these people, like what are you gaining out of it? That doesn't make sense?
SPEAKER_0:  to them and because it doesn't make sense, there's kind of like, well...
SPEAKER_0:  It's probably more of this story that I'm hearing and.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of times there's not, it's just like evil for the sake of power.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't really have that.
SPEAKER_0:  certainly anywhere near that scale.
SPEAKER_0:  and never have.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, certainly, you know, since, since, since America, uh, has been a thing, I mean, it's, it's.
SPEAKER_0:  It's—and the fact that this is, like, the 30s, you know what I mean? This isn't that long ago.
SPEAKER_0:  But I think also the narrative.
SPEAKER_0:  in some ways is
SPEAKER_0:  How?
SPEAKER_0:  You know, technology is also something that kind of people have mixed feelings about.
SPEAKER_0:  I think like I said this before and this is something I really believe very strongly.
SPEAKER_0:  the ability of information to be captured and spread easily.
SPEAKER_0:  is such an effective tool.
SPEAKER_0:  in exposing.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  humanity at its worst.
SPEAKER_0:  Because it's one thing if I sit here and tell you...
SPEAKER_0:  what I saw in these villages.
SPEAKER_0:  It's another thing where I sat you down and showed you a YouTube.
SPEAKER_0:  And you and I don't know what it's like to look in the eyes of someone who's...
SPEAKER_0:  thinking about kill eating their own kids.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, and you see that face.
SPEAKER_0:  and you know it's, you know, not something some...
SPEAKER_0:  CGI, it will haunt you forever.
SPEAKER_1:  Just looking at the different mechanisms that made all of this happen. So this is not just one guy, Stalin, having a policy.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a whole system.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, one of it is just a system of fear.
SPEAKER_1:  But how do you implement that system of fear?
SPEAKER_1:  Well, what- There's a giant-
SPEAKER_0:  bureaucracy of fear.
SPEAKER_0:  So what he implemented with the Great Terror.
SPEAKER_1:  is that's in the 30s in the late 30s.
SPEAKER_0:  It's throughout the 30s, but yeah, it starts in the...
SPEAKER_0:  mid to late 30s.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, you know, communism was based on the common good and the public good.
SPEAKER_0:  and anything private, which was bourgeois.
SPEAKER_0:  was a problem when they were started.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, when the revolution came, the October Revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  They wanted to recreate society entirely.
SPEAKER_0:  And that included like, okay, let's make it so.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... everyone eats in the cafeteria so that eating by themselves less design buildings everyone has to share bathrooms
SPEAKER_0:  Like their whole plan was to eliminate any kind of concept of privacy at all. They also had this bizarre kind of radical idea of like...
SPEAKER_0:  attacking shame.
SPEAKER_0:  So many of these, you know, before the 1917 people were also very involved, like free love.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, cause the idea of like having this private bond between husband and wife was also bourgeois and old fashioned. And you know, we're
SPEAKER_0:  the society of the future that-
SPEAKER_0:  changed relatively quickly, but they were talking about things like raising kids communally, uh, and, and so on and so forth. So for Stalin,
SPEAKER_0:  If you and I are friends...
SPEAKER_0:  We have a bond. That's a threat.
SPEAKER_0:  to him, the family's a threat.
SPEAKER_0:  the, any kind of organization is a threat because it's a power center that is, uh, not between a relationship between you and him. And now you have a relationship with somebody else.
SPEAKER_0:  So he systemically...
SPEAKER_0:  went through that whole society.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  you know, it became.
SPEAKER_0:  There are certain things that became a crime.
SPEAKER_0:  Then it became a crime to be a spouse.
SPEAKER_0:  of the enemy of the people.
SPEAKER_0:  Now right away.
SPEAKER_0:  I as a child become an orphan because my dad was an enemy of the people, my mom is married to many of the people.
SPEAKER_0:  Now I don't have parents, they get arrested or executed or whatever, but now—
SPEAKER_0:  I have nowhere to go, but I can't go to my friend's house.
SPEAKER_0:  because their family doesn't want to take in a child at the enemy of the people.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, you had this culture.
SPEAKER_0:  where everyone was very much encouraged to turn people in.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you turn, if you're arrested.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I'm tortured.
SPEAKER_0:  You're like, okay, who are your accomplices?
SPEAKER_0:  and now you just gotta name names people you knew.
SPEAKER_0:  And then it becomes this whole chain and it's like, how am I going to protest my innocence?
SPEAKER_0:  If Lex.
SPEAKER_0:  just said.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  I-
SPEAKER_0:  uh... worked with michael and we were working with trotsky it's
SPEAKER_0:  And we were plotting to overthrow Stalin. Lex testified to this. He signed a confession. What am I supposed to do now? Right. So it worked its way in a most viral fashion.
SPEAKER_0:  through the whole society. There was a
SPEAKER_0:  amazing moment where
SPEAKER_0:  Poor people, peasants, because obviously the powerless are often-
SPEAKER_0:  going to be caught in the web. They were going to jail for being Trotskyites.
SPEAKER_0:  I try and they have to ask themselves what's a tractorist.
SPEAKER_0:  Like they didn't even know who Trotsky was.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, and the thing, other thing is...
SPEAKER_0:  Ethnicity was a problem, right? If you were an ethnicity, you have more power with...
SPEAKER_0:  other members of that ethnicity than you have with this kind of broader Soviet culture.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  He would just deport entire populations.
SPEAKER_0:  from their ancestral lands to other parts.
SPEAKER_0:  A to spread the population around, but also to break that link between the people's.
SPEAKER_0:  and their lands, there was this 1937 NKVD order.
SPEAKER_0:  against Polish people where it's just like
SPEAKER_0:  if you had come from Poland or had a...
SPEAKER_0:  been just this whole list?
SPEAKER_0:  And basically people were being arrested because they had
SPEAKER_0:  Polish last names and I think it was a million people?
SPEAKER_0:  were killed at like some astronomical number.
SPEAKER_0:  So there was this anything that was a bond.
SPEAKER_0:  was a threat to him and it went systemically. So after he had all these kind of-
SPEAKER_0:  executions of people who were like Lenin's people, the old Bolsheviks.
SPEAKER_0:  Then he went after, he started arresting the secret police.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, he arrested all the cops.
SPEAKER_0:  he arrested all the judges and all these prisoners got to see the judges who yelled at them for being counter revolutionaries and spies. Now they were in the jails.
SPEAKER_0:  If you were a foreigner, if there was a huge push from the Soviet Union toward African-Americans, right? Cause they're like, look, you were living in a racist country. Here we have.
SPEAKER_0:  No, um...
SPEAKER_0:  racial inequality come come live here a bunch of them went
SPEAKER_0:  and they were all vanished.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, anyone who knew information about the outside world, if you're a foreigner, Andre Babel, I forget his first name.
SPEAKER_0:  He had a French writer he was friends with. He was arrested and shot cause he's a spy. Cause you're friends with Melrose. And if you, that means if you're a foreigner, you're a spy speaking Esperanto.
SPEAKER_0:  became a crime. Having a pen pal. Literally anything that was some kind of chain between yourself and someone else was a threat and was grounds for arrest. It was.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... the russians would joke
SPEAKER_0:  about how relieved they would be if someone knocked on your door in the middle of the night to tell you your house was on fire.
SPEAKER_0:  because it wasn't the NKVD coming to rescue.
SPEAKER_1:  And of course, most of the accusations probably.
SPEAKER_1:  or completely false.
SPEAKER_1:  So not only could you not do all of those things.
SPEAKER_1:  You
SPEAKER_1:  were also a victim of just.
SPEAKER_0:  Being late to work became a felony and also not doing your job became a felony because now you're taking
SPEAKER_0:  food or product away from the people and you're supposed to be there working for the people.
SPEAKER_0:  There's this one story, which, you know, I was doing the audio book and this is like I still trying to get through without crying.
SPEAKER_0:  This was 1920. They were a bunch of kids in Moscow who were pickpockets between ages 11 and 15. They rounded them up.
SPEAKER_0:  And they're like, all right, point out your accomplices. And they would take them in the trams and you have to point out people. Then they would take them back to the cellar, beat the crap out of these children.
SPEAKER_0:  And then they take them out again. And if they didn't point out to anybody, they beat them. They're like, all right. So they just start pointing at random.
SPEAKER_0:  And the thing that was really sick about this story, if that wasn't sick enough...
SPEAKER_0:  Is that the screams?
SPEAKER_0:  that the other criminals, the adult hardened criminals had to hear from these children as they realized they were being taken back to the cellar. It was just...
SPEAKER_0:  horrifying
SPEAKER_1:  and they so they
SPEAKER_1:  They tortured people, they tortured confessions out of people.
SPEAKER_1:  at scale.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  The dark aspect of this is it's all...
SPEAKER_1:  It's like this weird.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a bureaucracy of torture. Yes. So like, it's not like that there's.
SPEAKER_1:  What is it? The torturer is afraid of-
SPEAKER_1:  Like does it so that he doesn't become the prisoner.
SPEAKER_0:  Right. Because then it's like, oh, you couldn't get a confession out of him. Are you an enemy that people know as well?
SPEAKER_0:  and the thing that was even crazier.
SPEAKER_0:  is that a lot of these interrogators were frustrated.
SPEAKER_0:  Cause they're like, look.
SPEAKER_0:  We both know you're innocent.
SPEAKER_0:  just signed this confession to make my life easier. they knew it was crap.
SPEAKER_0:  Stalin joked about Stalin
SPEAKER_0:  joked about this. This is one of his little jokes.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a kid.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, who was arrested.
SPEAKER_0:  And he was said, oh, it was forced to say, you wrote Eugene O'Nagin, which is a play. It goes, that play was by Pushkin.
SPEAKER_0:  and they tortured him and they tortured him and tortured him.
SPEAKER_0:  and then his parents are walking down the street.
SPEAKER_0:  and they run into a secret police and they go, congratulations. And they go for what? Your son wrote Eugene and Egan.
SPEAKER_0:  like he admitted to it last night like it's just like they could get you to say anything and what else was really really sick
SPEAKER_0:  which they understood.
SPEAKER_0:  is they lower the death penalty for kids, I think, to either 14 or 12. I don't remember the top of my head.
SPEAKER_0:  and what Stalin's head of the secret police did.
SPEAKER_0:  is when you were interrogating someone, they would, you either had to have.
SPEAKER_0:  some of that family members.
SPEAKER_0:  uh um
SPEAKER_0:  Possessions on the desk?
SPEAKER_0:  or a copy of the decree.
SPEAKER_0:  that saying that they can go after your family.
SPEAKER_0:  And the amount of people who would confess to anything when they saw their family was in danger and they knew this wasn't a bluff.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... was astronomical then it becomes a chain
SPEAKER_0:  Because if you confess and I have your confession, how hard is it to get your neighbor?
SPEAKER_1:  What do you make of the...
SPEAKER_1:  for time.
SPEAKER_1:  for most of the time the NKVD was about the head of NKVD.
SPEAKER_1:  Lavrentiy Pavlovich Beria.
SPEAKER_0:  No, Barry, yeah, I have a death warrant signed by him hanging in my kitchen that I acquired.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... he was one of the most
SPEAKER_0:  evil people who ever lived.
SPEAKER_0:  The thing that Americans don't appreciate is how clever.
SPEAKER_0:  some of the sadism.
SPEAKER_0:  is.
SPEAKER_0:  So there was one actress, I think he took her back to his house.
SPEAKER_0:  And he asked her to, he tried to get her to sleep with him. Then he promised her that.
SPEAKER_0:  If she did her.
SPEAKER_0:  father and either her husband or her grandfather, I don't remember which one it was, is going to be released from jail. Well, they were already dead at that point. He had them executed.
SPEAKER_0:  They're still finding the bodies of the women he murdered in the grounds of his dacha. It's an embassy now.
SPEAKER_0:  And the thing is, Stalin knew because at one point, there's a picture of Stalin's daughter in his lap, you know, and she was at his house one day and Stalin calls up, he goes, get out of there immediately.
SPEAKER_0:  So he...
SPEAKER_0:  like a good bureaucrat.
SPEAKER_0:  He had a list, he kept a list of all of his sexual partners. It's still, uh, um.
SPEAKER_0:  Sealed.
SPEAKER_0:  but both him and his bodyguard had this list.
SPEAKER_0:  So just to clarify. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  He headed the operation that did this whole giant mechanism of forced confessions. Yes. He was part of expanding the Gulag. So he was in the head of the Gulag, but he was part of the Gulag.
SPEAKER_0:  And his famous quote was, show me the man and I'll show you the crime.
SPEAKER_1:  But on top of that, what you're describing is he was also.
SPEAKER_1:  related or not.
SPEAKER_1:  was also just a matter of
SPEAKER_0:  rapist.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, and there's some dispute about whether he went after-
SPEAKER_0:  with his rapes, but there's plenty of adult women.
SPEAKER_0:  that were targets for this. There was also another little joke about him, about how Stalin is looking for his pipe and he can't find it and he calls it a barrier.
SPEAKER_0:  And he's like, okay, I can't find this pipe. And then the afternoon he calls Barry again. He's like, oh, I found the pipe. He goes, but comrade Stalin, we've got four people to confess to still already.
SPEAKER_0:  So you have to laugh, but then you think about the nature of how it operates. Well, it also the fact that you have to laugh, but then you think about the nature of how it operates.
SPEAKER_1:  that this kind of person was allowed to run.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I suppose...
SPEAKER_1:  It's all different kinds of evil, and rape was just a part of the story.
SPEAKER_1:  his own personal.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  willingness to uh
SPEAKER_1:  oversee torture and commit torture himself.
SPEAKER_0:  and rape.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's also what happens when you're in a country where it has no rights of any kind.
SPEAKER_1:  And by the way, I should mention...
SPEAKER_1:  that people should get your book.
SPEAKER_1:  and audio, when's your audiobook coming out?
SPEAKER_0:  in a couple of weeks.
SPEAKER_1:  That'll be out shortly. Yeah. You gave me the great honor of voicing this man. That's for the promo.
SPEAKER_1:  for the promo. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I appreciate that.
SPEAKER_1:  for a moment, I actually.
SPEAKER_1:  It was really difficult.
SPEAKER_1:  Really?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it was just a sentence.
SPEAKER_1:  Understand, understand.
SPEAKER_1:  Ahh
SPEAKER_1:  because it takes you to that place.
SPEAKER_0:  place.
SPEAKER_0:  because he told her, scream if you want, doesn't matter.
SPEAKER_0:  And he was right.
SPEAKER_0:  Like that's the thing. He wasn't bluffing. She could scream or she had these women could scream their head off. No one's going to come help them.
SPEAKER_0:  He would drive around Moscow at night in his limo looking for victims.
SPEAKER_1:  But somehow me saying those words was tough.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm sure.
SPEAKER_1:  is uh... stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  Because this is where we came from. Do you know what I mean? This isn't just like some kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, Tolkien villain.
SPEAKER_1:  But it also was tough because I could see myself being somewhere in that machine somewhere. Like somehow that put me right there.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, I guess, any, like, they're.
SPEAKER_1:  Any cog in that machine is committing evil.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the dark thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  I think the higher you are to the top, the closer you are to the top.
SPEAKER_1:  the more.
SPEAKER_1:  ability you have to stop it.
SPEAKER_1:  but the less...
SPEAKER_1:  The more freedom you have to stop it, I suppose.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  to a point, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  but like the little things.
SPEAKER_1:  So Beria had the freedom to commit rape.
SPEAKER_1:  or not to.
SPEAKER_1:  And so he chooses to...
SPEAKER_1:  sort of increase the amount of evil he's putting out into the world.
SPEAKER_0:  But then you have to counterbalance that as dark as this calculus is after Stalin dies.
SPEAKER_0:  Like that week they start.
SPEAKER_0:  making the gulag shrink.
SPEAKER_0:  they start pulling back.
SPEAKER_0:  on the labor camps.
SPEAKER_0:  So I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  So that is a big plus in his.
SPEAKER_0:  Side.
SPEAKER_0:  Like you start liberating, having this mass amnesty and freeing.
SPEAKER_0:  people from work camps.
SPEAKER_0:  That's not minor things, so it's crazy. It's like...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not St. Peter, right? I don't know where-
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not saying he's a good person, but it's kind of insane.
SPEAKER_0:  that someone can do things that
SPEAKER_0:  everyone listening to this.
SPEAKER_0:  would regard as pure evil.
SPEAKER_0:  And at the same time this guy
SPEAKER_0:  Also...
SPEAKER_0:  when the time came.
SPEAKER_0:  Saved.
SPEAKER_0:  tens of thousands of lives.
SPEAKER_1:  So in some sense, Stalin is the kind of cancer that permeates all the Soviet minds.
SPEAKER_1:  And once it's gone...
SPEAKER_1:  You almost like wake up, wait a minute.
SPEAKER_1:  What the fuck was I ap-
SPEAKER_0:  And Khrushchev in, it was a 56 when he gave his secret speech.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... you know behind closed doors
SPEAKER_0:  And he's just like, all this criticism of Stalin was true.
SPEAKER_0:  This is completely not what Mark Sisson's, you know, he tried to salvage the system. This is not what Mark Sisson's about. We can't have a personality cult.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... you know stalin killed all these
SPEAKER_0:  Top Generals.
SPEAKER_0:  And when Hitler turned to betray the pact and invaded, Stalin didn't believe his buddy Hitler was going to do this. And as a result of this, we lost a lot of territory and lives. This is not a military genius. This was Stalin being...
SPEAKER_0:  An idiot.
SPEAKER_0:  or a moron, whatever term you want to be. So.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, yeah, but the thing is...
SPEAKER_0:  Khrushchev also was a butcher.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, he had a lot of blood in his hands. You don't become, you know, the thick, solid seat.
SPEAKER_0:  without having overlooked a lot of murder and chaos. So RM We accepted thatators are paying fine but you don't really want to be one
SPEAKER_0:  It's such a...
SPEAKER_0:  That's why it's called subtitled books, a tale of good and evil. There's so much sh-
SPEAKER_0:  malevolence to go around.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think was going through Stalin's mind?
SPEAKER_1:  in the 20s and the 30s.
SPEAKER_1:  Did he directly...
SPEAKER_1:  Allow himself to acknowledge the reality.
SPEAKER_1:  of the suffering he was causing? What does it take to be that human?
SPEAKER_1:  Hey, I'm almost interested.
SPEAKER_1:  to extract lessons from that for leaders of today.
SPEAKER_1:  How hard is it? Is it that Stalin is evil?
SPEAKER_1:  Or can you just dilute yourself gradually?
SPEAKER_1:  into where you don't have a sense.
SPEAKER_1:  of the effect of your policies in the pod.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you're not diluting yourself because you have around you.
SPEAKER_0:  an entire government.
SPEAKER_0:  of people telling you.
SPEAKER_0:  24-7.
SPEAKER_0:  how great you are.
SPEAKER_0:  how thankful they are for you, how awesome you are, you're the best.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  so that.
SPEAKER_0:  Certainly going to play into it. I've asked myself that question as well. Like, do these people believe they're on bullshit?
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  And I think the receipts are.
SPEAKER_0:  When Elena Ceaușescu, who's one of the four women on the cover...
SPEAKER_0:  when she's being taken away to be executed in 1989.
SPEAKER_0:  She's yelling at the soldiers, how could you, I raised you like a mother.
SPEAKER_0:  So she at least.
SPEAKER_0:  believed her own bullshit.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  With Stalin, he was obviously extremely intelligent.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's...
SPEAKER_0:  kind of easy for us to kind of psychologize and say he's a sociopath, he's a narcissist, he's this, he's that.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  but at a certain point, like if you're surrounded.
SPEAKER_0:  by a culture.
SPEAKER_0:  dedicated to glorifying you and everyone you meet.
SPEAKER_0:  It's so happy to see you.
SPEAKER_0:  and oh my god all your pronouncements are so good.
SPEAKER_0:  And you know what, if you make a decision that's wrong...
SPEAKER_0:  The people around you, it's their job to tell you why it's not your fault.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the fault of the Wreckers or it's the fault of, you know, Hitler or whoever it is, the Kulaks.
SPEAKER_0:  At a certain point the human mind wants to believe
SPEAKER_0:  how great it is.
SPEAKER_0:  especially someone in that vaunted position.
SPEAKER_0:  But he had his love, there was this one.
SPEAKER_0:  funny, I'm using the word loosely quote.
SPEAKER_0:  when Hitler invades Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  and he couldn't believe it and he's just missing in action for days because how could Hitler betray me? Deal, birds of a feather.
SPEAKER_0:  and he had this quote about like we've taken Lenin's legacy and shitted out our asses.
SPEAKER_0:  I think he was very aware.
SPEAKER_0:  That's no question that he was aware.
SPEAKER_0:  that in terms of being a philosopher or a thinker.
SPEAKER_0:  He wasn't on Lenin's level.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, so that was, I'm sure, played a lot into his psychology.
SPEAKER_1:  that he never quite lived up to the...
SPEAKER_1:  everything he tried. I mean there's some sense that the collectivization
SPEAKER_1:  that this idea was a failure.
SPEAKER_1:  the way he responds to the economic policy being a failure.
SPEAKER_1:  is to lean in.
SPEAKER_1:  and basically torture anyone who says it's a failure.
SPEAKER_1:  and double down on the policy.
SPEAKER_1:  That says something about-
SPEAKER_0:  But it wasn't a failure, it broke.
SPEAKER_0:  the Ukrainians.
SPEAKER_1:  You don't think he believed early on.
SPEAKER_1:  That's what it turned into, but you don't think in the very early days.
SPEAKER_1:  There was a thought that collectivization.
SPEAKER_1:  is the right mechanism by which
SPEAKER_1:  to enact communism.
SPEAKER_0:  But I think his goal...
SPEAKER_0:  was to break.
SPEAKER_0:  their spirit.
SPEAKER_0:  and getting them fed was secondary, right?
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  given the fact that they stopped complaining because they're dead.
SPEAKER_0:  He got what he wanted.
SPEAKER_0:  He got it compliant.
SPEAKER_0:  population.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, that's really interesting. I didn't.
SPEAKER_1:  I wonder how much disagreement there is about...
SPEAKER_1:  Because if that was the goal from the beginning, that's a different level of evil.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that was clearly the g- so his h- like I said earlier, he broke with Lenin because he wanted socialism in one country, right? That was his vision.
SPEAKER_0:  right? And he was also very aware.
SPEAKER_0:  What became the Soviet Union was extremely diverse. First of all, it's gigantic countries, the big country on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not always gigantic. You had-
SPEAKER_0:  all these peoples, these nationalities within it.
SPEAKER_0:  that have had historical enmity and they're not going to have loyalty to Moscow. He's a Georgian himself, this was always a big problem.
SPEAKER_0:  So that was.
SPEAKER_0:  What he wanted to do as well is to homogenize.
SPEAKER_0:  and have them be standardized.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't see how you do that.
SPEAKER_0:  without either massive re-education, which is only going to go so far.
SPEAKER_0:  or really just crushing people's spirits.
SPEAKER_1:  So, like a...
SPEAKER_1:  Forced.
SPEAKER_1:  Homogeneity. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  And the other big thing, a big element of Soviet culture.
SPEAKER_0:  and the Soviet mythology. I mean, he called his name, his anxious name is Stalin. I can't even pronounce his Georgian name, I'm sure it was really or something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  It means man of steel.
SPEAKER_0:  So a large part of the, and this still remains in Russian culture to this day. I see it in my family too. And like other Russians I know.
SPEAKER_0:  There is this pride in ruthlessness.
SPEAKER_0:  and this kind of like, I'm so tough, like, nothing's gonna affect me, like, yeah, we're gonna suffer, but it's for a greater good or for the long term and not to be kind of sentimental or squeamish about things.
SPEAKER_0:  Like that was a big part of it. Don't take.
SPEAKER_1:  Take that away from me too, Michael. You've taken everything.
SPEAKER_0:  Am I wrong?
SPEAKER_1:  I admire.
SPEAKER_1:  not stoicism, but that kind of hardness.
SPEAKER_1:  I look forward to myself. There's nothing to do with
SPEAKER_0:  But not to the extent that like if some like for example like if you
SPEAKER_0:  See?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Someone's suffering.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's being used as a mechanism to get you change your opinion. You're like, they're not going to get to me. Like that is very much part of that Russian psychology.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  At least at that time. Yes. They'll largely know.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not going to be manipulated by someone else's suffering or weakness. That kind of thing. I think that's really part of it to this day.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know how much of it is character, how much of it is reality. but sure
SPEAKER_0:  Sure.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember I knew someone who was...
SPEAKER_0:  him and his fiance were Russian.
SPEAKER_0:  and they had this big fight she took off the ring.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  And she's like, he's like, that's it.
SPEAKER_0:  And just like the way he told the story to me, she's like, what do you want me to say?
SPEAKER_0:  Oh don't leave me baby, I can't live without you. Like that nasty-
SPEAKER_0:  cruelty.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, man. I know you're... I don't know if there's a Russian thing. That's just...
SPEAKER_0:  It's just a people thing.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think that's an American thing.
SPEAKER_1:  I think there's all kinds of flavors and they're different.
SPEAKER_1:  by region.
SPEAKER_1:  of the way that people are cruel to each other. Sure, I'm not arguing that. America...
SPEAKER_1:  New Jersey is different than Texas is different than California.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't think Americans are a higher trust?
SPEAKER_0:  more kind society.
SPEAKER_0:  Then Russia?
SPEAKER_0:  Even today?
SPEAKER_0:  higher trust.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, listen, I'm not going to, so first of all,
SPEAKER_1:  I
SPEAKER_1:  I have a very complex
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  feelings about Russia today.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm talking about January before the war. I'm talking about nowadays.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's a co-
SPEAKER_1:  complex psychological dynamic of what trusting means. I think Russians are generally
SPEAKER_1:  Less friendly, but have more intimate.
SPEAKER_1:  friendships yes that's true
SPEAKER_1:  So it's just a different.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not different. It's just one is more trusting.
SPEAKER_0:  Who's wishes more trusting? Americans!
SPEAKER_1:  but then we define.
SPEAKER_1:  Trust thing different.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, I'll give you an example. If someone's having a party in America and people come over...
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, that's fine. Everyone's welcome. If it's in Russia, it's like, who's that? Who'd you bring?
SPEAKER_0:  And there's much more of a like, let me be sure that's okay. This person's here. I know, maybe. You don't have parties. I have never been in a party. And you don't come to mine.
SPEAKER_0:  www.globalonenessproject.org
SPEAKER_0:  Van Eskri was very sad.
SPEAKER_0:  I love that, I love that. Well you should have showed it by showing up. Tührt.
SPEAKER_1:  Man, I'm a high height from the world and I'm afraid of social interaction
SPEAKER_1:  and I just lay on the ground instead and feel sorry for myself.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not bad Santa, it's sad Santa.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I conserve my emotional energy towards this one day of the year.
SPEAKER_1:  intensely spread my joy.
SPEAKER_1:  Alright.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of which, you tell a Christmas story in the book.
SPEAKER_0:  Are you spoiling that chapter?
SPEAKER_0:  It's called Die Hard.
SPEAKER_1:  All right, well, I'm not gonna spoil it.
SPEAKER_0:  really good. I was very proud of that chapter.
SPEAKER_0:  Because the ending that's a Christmas story is just like, I know everyone reading it's going to go Google it, be like, this can't be real, but it was real. There was a我知道 que假.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, this has to do with the bigger picture. We don't have to, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  do the big reveal, but the bigger picture of there was an iron curtain and it was coming down.
SPEAKER_1:  in complex ways.
SPEAKER_1:  How would you define the Iron Curtain? There's a set of ideologies, a set of countries united by an ideology, and a set of countries united by a different ideology.
SPEAKER_1:  And…
SPEAKER_1:  There's a curtain that divided them.
SPEAKER_1:  and it eventually came down. So how would you describe how it came down?
SPEAKER_0:  It came, I hate that I can never remember, ever, ever remember if this was Hemingway.
SPEAKER_0:  No, what's Hemingway? It is Mark Twain.
SPEAKER_0:  No, it came down two ways, gradually then suddenly.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  The thing with the Iron Curtain and the Warsaw Pact, these were a bunch of nations run under communism.
SPEAKER_0:  but they were all.
SPEAKER_0:  Almost all.
SPEAKER_0:  under the sway of Moscow.
SPEAKER_0:  So if they were going to make big changes, Moscow had to prove it.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, it was in 19, in the, in the fifties when Hungary.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... decided to rebel
SPEAKER_0:  or not liberalized and they even were thinking of leaving the Warsaw Pact.
SPEAKER_0:  And the Russians send in the tanks.
SPEAKER_0:  and you have the development of what was called the Brezhnev Doctrine.
SPEAKER_0:  which was the idea that...
SPEAKER_0:  It is the duty of all the Warsaw Pact nations.
SPEAKER_0:  If another country tries to, and this was also in 68 in the Prague spring Czechoslovakia
SPEAKER_0:  If a nation wants to leave.
SPEAKER_0:  socialism is incumbent of the social stations to in to do whatever is necessary to make sure there is an account revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  So they were.
SPEAKER_0:  very much under Moscow's.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And one of the big ways it changed...
SPEAKER_0:  was one man.
SPEAKER_0:  And that was Mikhail Gorbachev.
SPEAKER_0:  and he was the first.
SPEAKER_0:  Russian leader.
SPEAKER_0:  to be born after the October Revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  He grew up and his grandfather was arrested for being a Trotskyite.
SPEAKER_0:  The other one, you know, was arrested for this or that.
SPEAKER_0:  He saw his village starve as a result of Stalin.
SPEAKER_0:  So even though he was a very committed...
SPEAKER_0:  communists.
SPEAKER_0:  He also was very
SPEAKER_0:  and increasingly skeptical of authoritarianism.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  You know, in Poland, for example, you had the Solidarity Movement.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  and this is a labor union movement.
SPEAKER_0:  And the government didn't know what to do. They were getting a lot of support from the peoples. They had strikes that, um, then the Gdansk shipyard was, was when, when they started.
SPEAKER_0:  And basically, mascots hold them.
SPEAKER_0:  Either you crack down or we're cracking down on you.
SPEAKER_0:  And they're like, all right. And they declared martial law and the rest of the leaders put them away.
SPEAKER_0:  But then when Gorbachev, you know, was in charge.
SPEAKER_0:  there wasn't a gun to their back.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was the communist leaders themselves who were like, you know what? There's this really funny moment where
SPEAKER_0:  Lekhvelesta is meeting with Margaret Thatcher.
SPEAKER_0:  And he's telling her what solidarity the movement wants.
SPEAKER_0:  and she had been meeting with the Polish government as well.
SPEAKER_0:  And she's like, look, like.
SPEAKER_0:  Tell them like what, cause they had, you tried.
SPEAKER_0:  They wanted, the government wanted her to tell them that we wanted to go shit and work things out. She goes, all right, tell the government what it is that you're asking for. And he just points to the ceiling. He goes, he's like, oh yeah, our meetings are bugged anyway.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  They then had the freedom.
SPEAKER_0:  because they knew.
SPEAKER_0:  Gorbachev wasn't forcing them.
SPEAKER_0:  to drive solid air underground.
SPEAKER_0:  So they had the idea of like, let's work together with these people. And as a result of this, Poland liberalized and...
SPEAKER_0:  Read itself.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, um...
SPEAKER_0:  fairly easily and with a minimum of bloodshed in 89.
SPEAKER_0:  And there was this whole argument for the Vietnam War with something called domino theory, which is if you lose Vietnam, then you're going to lose Laos, then you lose Cambodia. One by one, the countries are going to turn communist to the dominoes.
SPEAKER_0:  People didn't realize the reverse was true.
SPEAKER_0:  Because after Poland liberalized, then you have...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, Hungary, then you have, you know, Czechoslovakia, then, you know, you had East Germany and...
SPEAKER_0:  fall the Berlin Wall so.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a great thing because as this is happening...
SPEAKER_0:  the people are looking around.
SPEAKER_0:  And they're like, wait.
SPEAKER_0:  That's it? That was, like-
SPEAKER_0:  This has gotta be a trick.
SPEAKER_0:  And it wasn't a trick, so.
SPEAKER_0:  One of my favorite books, which was a big inspiration for this one.
SPEAKER_0:  was by my favorite historian. I apologize to Victor Petrusa, David Petrusa and Arthur Herman, my second and third.
SPEAKER_0:  they're tied. But Victor Sebastian wrote a book called Revolution 1989.
SPEAKER_0:  And he just talked about that year and how all these countries.
SPEAKER_0:  one after another liberalized and it's just such a
SPEAKER_0:  and none of them thought this was possible.
SPEAKER_0:  My f-
SPEAKER_0:  One of my favorite, favorite moments in this book.
SPEAKER_0:  is Helmut Kohl, who is the head of West Germany, is in Warsaw with Lech Walesa.
SPEAKER_0:  discussing the Berlin Wall.
SPEAKER_0:  And like, Willis is like, I don't think it's going to be around for like another few years. And, and whole Nicole laughs in his face.
SPEAKER_0:  And he goes...
SPEAKER_0:  Look, you're young.
SPEAKER_0:  This isn't how things work. Like, this is gonna take some doing.
SPEAKER_0:  It fell the next day and Helmut Kohl literally says, I'm at the wrong party. And he got on a plane and got out of Warsaw.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  there are why this book has a broader message.
SPEAKER_0:  than the actual stories of these incidents.
SPEAKER_0:  is that.
SPEAKER_0:  as these wonderful things are happening.
SPEAKER_0:  The universal consensus at the time is
SPEAKER_0:  It's never gonna happen.
SPEAKER_0:  Or if it does happen, it's going to happen only through an enormous amount.
SPEAKER_0:  of carnage and blood.
SPEAKER_0:  And when it doesn't, then everyone's like, Oh, it was inevitable.
SPEAKER_0:  You didn't say it was inevitable at the time. You only said it was inevitable after the fact. And the other thing that I-
SPEAKER_0:  was really.
SPEAKER_0:  brought me a lot of joy.
SPEAKER_0:  is there are so many moments.
SPEAKER_0:  of men with guns.
SPEAKER_0:  saying, we're not shooting anyone.
SPEAKER_0:  Cause they wanted.
SPEAKER_0:  several Tiananmen squares.
SPEAKER_0:  They wanted it in.
SPEAKER_0:  you know east berlin they wanted it in romania
SPEAKER_0:  as they wanted in Moscow.
SPEAKER_0:  And these strong, tough, trained men with guns were like...
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  We're not.
SPEAKER_0:  shooting the civilians.
SPEAKER_0:  And then.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything else was history.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, just as-
SPEAKER_1:  surprising as the mass violence committed by
SPEAKER_1:  Like police and the army on its own citizenry
SPEAKER_1:  Equally surprising is when they choose not to. Yeah. TURN TO 1 minute 2 seconds
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  And what is that? the two
SPEAKER_1:  How do you explain?
SPEAKER_1:  1989 how do you explain this?
SPEAKER_1:  Progress.
SPEAKER_1:  that happened so suddenly.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you explain?
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  in the beginning of the twentieth century.
SPEAKER_1:  So much revolution happened.
SPEAKER_1:  that created communism.
SPEAKER_1:  And how do you explain then the collapse of that?
SPEAKER_1:  across so many nations at the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  I think a large part of it had to do.
SPEAKER_0:  with the closer.
SPEAKER_0:  interconnections.
SPEAKER_0:  between people like Gorbachev and Thatcher and Gorbachev and Reagan.
SPEAKER_0:  because both of them visited Red Square.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, in the years before, these are...
SPEAKER_0:  enemies you know they want to invade they want to kill us the Americans thought this about the Russians the Russians thought this about the Americans obviously not so much the British
SPEAKER_0:  And...
SPEAKER_0:  they got on really well.
SPEAKER_0:  When Gorbachev came to checkers, which is the prime minister's
SPEAKER_0:  countryside estate.
SPEAKER_0:  Thatcher sat him down and she's lecturing him about human rights and she's lecturing about economics and she's lecturing about this and that.
SPEAKER_0:  and then she's lecturing him about why he's in eating while he's yelling at her.
SPEAKER_0:  And he goes...
SPEAKER_0:  Mrs. Thatcher?
SPEAKER_0:  I know you have a lot of strong opinions.
SPEAKER_0:  I do too.
SPEAKER_0:  I haven't been sent here to recruit you to the communist party." And she just started laughing.
SPEAKER_0:  But right away, there was such a sense in the air.
SPEAKER_0:  of we can do better.
SPEAKER_0:  We're spending all this money on missiles. We're spending all this money on the military. It's expensive.
SPEAKER_0:  And for what?
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, we don't have to be looking at each other as enemies. We can-
SPEAKER_0:  try to work together to kind of at the very least.
SPEAKER_0:  lower the volume and the heat.
SPEAKER_1:  How much credit do you give to Gorbachev the man?
SPEAKER_1:  meaning.
SPEAKER_1:  How much power does a single individual have?
SPEAKER_0:  I could not give him more credit.
SPEAKER_0:  I had a tweet last year where I said, who do you think is the greatest person alive right now? And my answer by far would be Gorbachev. Then he died, I don't know who it is right now.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's just funny because.
SPEAKER_1:  Because Gorbachev also had a tweet.
SPEAKER_0:  Ah, ha ha ha ha ha ha!
SPEAKER_0:  But it was, it was my thing. And he said...
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, sure.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  That would be a good, now I wish I interviewed Gorbachev and ask them the famous question of what do you like?
SPEAKER_1:  best about Michael Malus.
SPEAKER_0:  Look, the transition after the Soviet Union fell.
SPEAKER_0:  to Russia and Yeltsin was not a smooth one by any means.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, as I say at the end of the book, it's not like they lived happily ever after.
SPEAKER_0:  But my point, broader point is you take the wins when you can get them.
SPEAKER_0:  people now had access to passports.
SPEAKER_0:  They don't have to have.
SPEAKER_0:  They can leave the country. They have food.
SPEAKER_0:  They have access to information. It's somewhat censored, but it's really nothing like it was.
SPEAKER_0:  under the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  and they didn't have to live in this kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  constant fear and they had opportunities and it's such a step forward.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and there was this one great moment and I'm good.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a super, Boris Yeltsin became president of Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  He's also mayor of Moscow at one point, or the equivalent of mayor.
SPEAKER_0:  and he came here to visit NASA in the capacity of one or the other.
SPEAKER_0:  And while he was there, he went to visit a supermarket. It was a Randall's, then I think it's a food town now. It still exists. I'm going to go there. I'm going to start bawling.
SPEAKER_0:  and as he's looking around...
SPEAKER_0:  Like, he had never seen so much food.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is food that even wealthy people in Russia don't have access to.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's pictures of him just like this, like what the...
SPEAKER_0:  And the scene that
SPEAKER_0:  really
SPEAKER_0:  was poignant to me.
SPEAKER_0:  is on his flight back.
SPEAKER_0:  He's sitting there on the plane like this.
SPEAKER_0:  And he's like...
SPEAKER_0:  They had to lie to the people.
SPEAKER_0:  Because if they knew...
SPEAKER_0:  they wouldn't have been able to get away with it.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's the moment where it's just like, oh, this wasn't like.
SPEAKER_0:  skewed propaganda, you know, this was like-
SPEAKER_0:  they knew and it was a lie from A.
SPEAKER_0:  to Z.
SPEAKER_0:  and he was just like, holy crap, just like, and you can just imagine him on that plane, his brain reprogramming.
SPEAKER_0:  Because if you're taught since you're a kid, and he was an older man, he was no dummy, you think, okay, the Americans are starving and poor, and they're lynching people every day, and then you go to f***.
SPEAKER_0:  A SUPERMARKET!
SPEAKER_0:  the most banal place on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  And you see, like, I think when the article said, like, they couldn't believe how big the onions were or something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  And you're seeing this and you're seeing these like janitors, school teachers, these aren't dignitaries and they're regular people just-
SPEAKER_0:  pick whatever they want and you're just like.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, it's like the equivalent of having a stroke?
SPEAKER_1:  I do think that that's one of the most powerful things is the grocery store.
SPEAKER_1:  as they go in terms of drawing.
SPEAKER_1:  A distinction between the two systems. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Cause you know, you can have like technology, you can show off technology and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  But you can kind of sign right off technologies like, okay, that's the mechanism.
SPEAKER_1:  of the devil.
SPEAKER_1:  But when you look at just.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Fruit and veggies and like
SPEAKER_1:  very big fruit and veggies and like.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and fruit in particular.
SPEAKER_1:  like certain kinds of fruit that are just not available in Russia.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, yeah, that really shows.
SPEAKER_1:  Wait a minute.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  It's interesting, like when you're older and you...
SPEAKER_1:  have to face.
SPEAKER_1:  the reality that you believe to be true.
SPEAKER_1:  that your whole life has been based.
SPEAKER_0:  And a set of lies. And you're not mistakes, not like a little bit like blatant.
SPEAKER_0:  lies from top to bottom.
SPEAKER_0:  start to finish that I don't know what that's like.
SPEAKER_0:  How much uh...
SPEAKER_1:  You start the book, I think you start the book with Ayn Rand.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes. Yes. Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  as one does.
SPEAKER_1:  So before the revolution, she was born in Russia, she witnessed the revolution.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  and moved.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... to the united states in the twenty twenty six twenty six
SPEAKER_1:  I remember like it was yesterday.
SPEAKER_1:  Anyway, she you write that she spent a lot of her life trying to convince Americans in the world that.
SPEAKER_1:  the negative effects of totalitarian government.
SPEAKER_1:  Just.
SPEAKER_1:  you know maybe using her as an example but also
SPEAKER_1:  this question can we draw a distinction between
SPEAKER_1:  authoritarian regimes, and communism.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it possible to steal man the case that not all implementations of socialism and communism
SPEAKER_1:  would lead to the atrocities we've seen in the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_1:  and in China under Mao.
SPEAKER_1:  Like when you in studying all of this, how much blame do you put?
SPEAKER_1:  on the ideologies.
SPEAKER_1:  on Marxist ideologies.
SPEAKER_1:  versus the particular leaders and dictators.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you have to blame the leaders a lot because they had different leaders in different countries where
SPEAKER_0:  uh, different from each other. Oh hi from DukeCheck, who took
SPEAKER_0:  Czechoslovakia and he tried to introduce socialism with a human face.
SPEAKER_0:  in the Prague Spring of 1968, he was like, all right, we got to do away with this authoritarianism.
SPEAKER_0:  We gotta have more free speech. He was thinking of introducing elements of democracy. Now then the Russians sent in the tanks.
SPEAKER_0:  But the point is he certainly was someone who was like, all right, this, this has got to stop. This is just absolutely crazy.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Khrushchev and
SPEAKER_0:  Stalin were not the same animal at all.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think the problem with...
SPEAKER_0:  communism in the Marxist sense.
SPEAKER_0:  is that you're going to have an introducing element of authoritarianism simply because you can't have economic planning.
SPEAKER_0:  If I don't have a price mechanism, I don't know how price is what.
SPEAKER_0:  is me knowing as a consumer or a producer.
SPEAKER_0:  what should be produced or what there's a shortage of. As prices increase, that's a signal that we have a shortage here. As prices decrease, that means that there's a surplus here. But if I'm setting the price, I don't really have...
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  how much weed I need to produce if I'm compared to corn, compared to shoes as compared to Santa costumes.
SPEAKER_0:  So that is a big problem. The other issue is...
SPEAKER_0:  If you have one...
SPEAKER_0:  uh... agency the government
SPEAKER_0:  having a monopoly on, let's suppose, the news.
SPEAKER_0:  like you were talking about earlier with Twitter, it's gonna be really hard to have any kind of objective discourse.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone is going to be working for the same organization that is going to cause a problem in terms of having a feedback mechanism, even in the best scenario, in terms of...
SPEAKER_0:  This is a problem, this isn't a problem.
SPEAKER_0:  And when you have a monopoly, which is what a government is...
SPEAKER_0:  I think people are very familiar with what the problems happen with monopoly. There's a lack of accountability, bureaucracies are faceless and then no one's to blame, yet everyone kind of suffers as a consequence.
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't necessarily have to be.
SPEAKER_0:  as authoritarian as Stalinism.
SPEAKER_0:  You-
SPEAKER_0:  I can't have it.
SPEAKER_0:  a government which is authority by its nature.
SPEAKER_0:  be this pervasive.
SPEAKER_0:  without a strong amount of
SPEAKER_0:  of oppression. Same thing with even if you just have like let's say socialized healthcare.
SPEAKER_0:  You're going to have to make it illegal for doctors to practice privately. You're going to have to have rationing, so on and so forth. Now that might be a price that people are willing to pay because you can't have infinite spending on healthcare, right? So something's going to have to give somewhere. So there is an element of authoritarianism there and people are comfortable with that and I can wrap my head around it.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you're going to have...
SPEAKER_0:  one organization running literally everything in society.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't see how you do that and have any.
SPEAKER_0:  measure of liberalism.
SPEAKER_1:  Why do you think Ayn Rand had so much trouble?
SPEAKER_1:  time.
SPEAKER_1:  people the danger of
SPEAKER_1:  Soviet
SPEAKER_1:  Stalinism.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I think...
SPEAKER_0:  The pertinent question is why did Emma Goldman and Alexander Berkman have so much problems?
SPEAKER_0:  So they were hardcore. These are anarchists. Yeah, they're Emma Goldman's on the cover. They were deported.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  from the US, J. Edgar Hoover saw them off at Ellis Island. They were sent to...
SPEAKER_0:  Russia
SPEAKER_0:  They were.
SPEAKER_0:  Bloodthirsty revolutionaries. They had no shortage advocating violence when necessary.
SPEAKER_0:  And when they went there, they were just like, this is a complete nightmare. They both individually had meetings with Lenin complaining about.
SPEAKER_0:  political prisoners complaining about lack of free speech. He told them, you know, this is a revolutionary time. You could do that later.
SPEAKER_0:  And when they both left, she wrote a memoir, it was split into two books, My Disillusionment Russia and My Ferdinand Disillusionment Russia.
SPEAKER_0:  He wrote the Bolshevik Myth.
SPEAKER_0:  And she was in England and she gave a speech?
SPEAKER_0:  And she's just like, if you guys think this is for the workers, this is the biggest lie I've ever heard. Like they're oppressing the workers. Like no capitalist has ever imagined.
SPEAKER_0:  And you know, as she described it, like people just shifting their sheets, seats, they're interrupting her and she, when she opened her talk, she had a standing ovation and when she was done you could hear pin drop.
SPEAKER_0:  So they didn't want to hear it because this was.
SPEAKER_0:  This kind of, and Eugene Lyons talks about it later, this was like the guinea pig theory of the Russian people. Like, we're gonna experiment on them.
SPEAKER_0:  Over there.
SPEAKER_0:  If it works, great, we're right. If it's wrong, it's their problem. And sure, these animals squeal, but-
SPEAKER_0:  they're beneath us and of course they're gonna make some noise but
SPEAKER_0:  you know this is a noble experiment but they're experimenting on a country several countries
SPEAKER_0:  So I think...
SPEAKER_0:  an ideology like this which appeals.
SPEAKER_0:  to intellectuals because...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, if it works or if it's implemented, they're the ones who are gods.
SPEAKER_0:  in effect in a society, like their status cannot be higher, they really want this to work. They want a society where they are the near aristocracy of the most important people.
SPEAKER_0:  And their criticisms of America, if they had a binary worldview, if America is bad and this is the opposite of America, then by definition it's good. And the other binary that they bought into is the Nazis and the fascists hate the communists and the communists, true, up to a point, hated the fascists and the Nazis. Okay, well, Hitler is evil, so this guy's against Hitler, we're with him. So that's an argument that's still made.
SPEAKER_0:  in schools growing up when you talk about World War II, where they're like, we teamed up with Stalin, and they don't really talk about Stalin being a bad guy, but it's like, we worked with him to fight Hitler because Hitler was a unique evil. Now, that is certainly true that Hitler's a unique evil, but that doesn't mean or even imply that Hitler was a bad guy.
SPEAKER_0:  that Stalin is somehow an angel or a saint.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think some of the lessons of history are forgotten here in our?
SPEAKER_1:  in arm
SPEAKER_1:  Modern political discourse.
SPEAKER_1:  that are important to remember.
SPEAKER_0:  I was so triggered because I was in the supermarket and there was a company that's selling Russian ice cream because it meets these high-level Soviet standards.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm just like, you think this is some kind of joke?
SPEAKER_0:  You think this is some kind of kitschy punchline that you had decades of people.
SPEAKER_0:  who were taught in school to turn their parents into the police if they were hoarding grain, even if it cost them their own lives, where it was a crime to be married to someone who was an enemy of the state.
SPEAKER_0:  where you had torture being the norm, where people are institutionalized.
SPEAKER_0:  because they were politically disadvantageous and they were called insane. Like this isn't just like, oh, this hammer and sickle is this cool, wacky symbol. Like the amount of blood.
SPEAKER_0:  under this symbol was just enormous. And, and so, yeah, I think that lesson has very much been forgotten. How did the ice cream taste?
SPEAKER_0:  It was fine.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm a Baskin Robbins guy to be honest, but Van Lewin's does some great work.
SPEAKER_1:  Baskin-Ramos doesn't have any Soviet flavors.
SPEAKER_1:  No.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  Those are dark jokes, dark, dark jokes. I'm going to self-publish a book of jokes.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for watching!
SPEAKER_1:  Um, coming out.
SPEAKER_1:  Um,
SPEAKER_1:  in a grocery store near you. Okay guys.
SPEAKER_1:  What was the hardest part about writing this book?
SPEAKER_1:  Spent two years writing it.
SPEAKER_0:  So when I write books for celebrities and I was co-authoring them, I did it kind of like method acting.
SPEAKER_0:  I try to get into their head as much as possible to kind of speak in their voice.
SPEAKER_0:  And when you're dealing with...
SPEAKER_0:  children being.
SPEAKER_0:  tortured.
SPEAKER_0:  harmed.
SPEAKER_0:  Start.
SPEAKER_0:  and you're trying to empathize with.
SPEAKER_0:  The characters, it's-
SPEAKER_0:  It's hard to take.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, the other big part I had.
SPEAKER_0:  Like I was saying earlier, I was just very, very concerned.
SPEAKER_0:  that I told it.
SPEAKER_0:  this story and that it did it justice.
SPEAKER_0:  because I think this is something that is, I still don't understand and I'm kind of angry about it.
SPEAKER_0:  that it's fallen on me.
SPEAKER_0:  to tell this story. This is some-
SPEAKER_0:  Miner.
SPEAKER_0:  incident that happened in some random town and...
SPEAKER_0:  Pick a state.
SPEAKER_0:  This is half the world.
SPEAKER_0:  for, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  70, 80 years.
SPEAKER_0:  And the fact that it's, this is the eighties. This isn't, we were, I mean, you and I are old enough to remember the eighties. There's a show. I remember the eighties.
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that all these things have just kind of
SPEAKER_0:  We have this collective amnesia.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and if not even amnesia, I think a lot of this stuff, even I like, was not known even at the time or was kind of obscured.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh
SPEAKER_0:  This is, I remember I was at the Blaze, which is a network run by Glenn Beck, and they're conservatives and-
SPEAKER_0:  I have a lot of fun there.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm just sitting there and then.
SPEAKER_0:  Sometimes they veer off, they're like, oh, Biden's a communist. Okay, Biden's a communist.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm like, we talk so much about-
SPEAKER_0:  You know, slavery.
SPEAKER_0:  the civil war, the atrocities, we talk about World War II and the Holocaust. I'm like...
SPEAKER_0:  How is no one talking about this? And this was can very easily be portrayed as like conservatism's big victory because Reagan and Thatcher were so instrumental in guiding this to a safe landing.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I'm like, how is no one telling a story? And then one day my brain is like, you know, you.
SPEAKER_0:  Write books for a living. This is kind of your job.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm like, all right, but I still don't, I still, I got to tell you I'm.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of confused.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm the one who has to do this because this should be.
SPEAKER_0:  They should be.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  There should be 30 books like this. And this is a model to follow.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. And it's also, um,
SPEAKER_1:  That is such recent history. Yeah!
SPEAKER_1:  but it also kind of makes you realize that there might be...
SPEAKER_1:  other fights?
SPEAKER_1:  for progress.
SPEAKER_1:  going on right now.
SPEAKER_1:  The world that we don't know about, so you wrote about North Korea?
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know to what degree there could possibly be fights.
SPEAKER_1:  there.
SPEAKER_1:  for progress.
SPEAKER_1:  but...
SPEAKER_1:  They could be boiling up.
SPEAKER_1:  In China, that could be boiling up.
SPEAKER_1:  Battles for progress?
SPEAKER_1:  in other parts of the world.
SPEAKER_1:  Russia that could be.
SPEAKER_1:  And in America.
SPEAKER_1:  in America.
SPEAKER_1:  And these are all different kind of battles for progress.
SPEAKER_1:  And now.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Sometimes...
SPEAKER_1:  Sometimes I, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  We sometimes tend to criticize these battles for progress, like, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  If it's on the left, we'll call it like wokeism.
SPEAKER_1:  or whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  And we pick extreme.
SPEAKER_1:  elements of it.
SPEAKER_1:  and show how silly and ridiculous it is.
SPEAKER_1:  not realising it, not acknowledging that there's a...
SPEAKER_1:  a more civil battle going on underneath.
SPEAKER_1:  for actual for
SPEAKER_1:  for
SPEAKER_1:  respecting
SPEAKER_1:  human.
SPEAKER_1:  dignity from all.
SPEAKER_1:  for people for all walks of life.
SPEAKER_1:  And the same.
SPEAKER_1:  We tend to call anybody who questions mainstream narratives, conspiracy theorists, we dismiss them immediately. And they're ultimately fighting for progress.
SPEAKER_1:  to people who criticize Fauci and everybody else.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if they're...
SPEAKER_1:  I think they want.
SPEAKER_1:  institutions.
SPEAKER_1:  that serve the public.
SPEAKER_1:  They're fighting for progress too.
SPEAKER_1:  and we tend to dismiss them. Like each side tends to caricature the other.
SPEAKER_1:  But the battle for progress is happening. I guess that's what your-
SPEAKER_1:  That's the hopeful message with the white pill.
SPEAKER_1:  Right? That there- there's-
SPEAKER_1:  Progress being made.
SPEAKER_1:  Somehow we're all f-
SPEAKER_1:  Making progress here.
SPEAKER_0:  I think more the hopeful message is that...
SPEAKER_0:  It's not possible.
SPEAKER_0:  that we have to lose.
SPEAKER_0:  Like if someone tells you the straight face, you can't win.
SPEAKER_0:  the enemy is too impressive and strong, I'm like-
SPEAKER_0:  What are you talking about? I mean, look, this was-
SPEAKER_0:  The Soviet Union!
SPEAKER_0:  And it happened.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  relatively quickly and relatively peacefully. I mean, again, and it wasn't because.
SPEAKER_0:  the Hanuker in East Germany was like, oh, I'm just gonna vacate my seat. He was like sending the tanks and the military guy said no.
SPEAKER_0:  So they wanted blood. There were plenty of people who wanted blood and would have been happy to have it.
SPEAKER_1:  So to you.
SPEAKER_1:  What the f-
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe if not the fall of the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_1:  the fall of the Iron Curtain.
SPEAKER_1:  is great.
SPEAKER_1:  leap of progress in the 20th century.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't see how anyone can argue against that point.
SPEAKER_0:  with a straight face.
SPEAKER_1:  That gives you hope that we...
SPEAKER_1:  that we humanity were able to do that.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, and at the same time, we were told at the time...
SPEAKER_0:  Give it up!
SPEAKER_0:  Be realistic.
SPEAKER_0:  It's utopian.
SPEAKER_0:  to think this is going anywhere, maybe in 100 years. Look, there's a recent check off on Star Trek.
SPEAKER_0:  Because the idea is even for our future, you're going to have America and you're going to have the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  Like this is the reality. It was called Real Politics.
SPEAKER_0:  We're going to have detente because it's, you know, it's this permanent stalemate.
SPEAKER_0:  We had the Vietnam War, we got our asses kicked.
SPEAKER_0:  Russia's not going anywhere. America's not going anywhere. We got to learn to live with each other, blah, blah, blah. And Reagan said, you don't want to hear my strategy.
SPEAKER_0:  for the cold war some people might say it's simple or even simplistic here it is
SPEAKER_0:  We win, they lose.
SPEAKER_0:  and the people who won.
SPEAKER_0:  were the Russian people and the Ukrainian people and the Lithuanian people and the Polish people and the Romanian people especially and the Hungarian people.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's just...
SPEAKER_0:  There are so many moments of great joy.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... that you know it just tears coming down my face because
SPEAKER_0:  You're, you're
SPEAKER_0:  Go, you're like in Prague.
SPEAKER_0:  when Dubček, again, who tried to liberalize in 1968, and then when they sent in the tanks, they deported him to Slovakia somewhere to do some forestry job.
SPEAKER_0:  Like he appears in their big squares just waving from the balcony like this ghost.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... from twenty years prior
SPEAKER_0:  being like, look.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  The spirit of 68 is still alive here.
SPEAKER_0:  in Czechoslovakia and it was like a matter of weeks?
SPEAKER_0:  The entire government resigned and then they liberalized. It's just...
SPEAKER_0:  so many things about
SPEAKER_0:  just overnight.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... just change for the profound better
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and you know, people are so
SPEAKER_0:  Committed.
SPEAKER_0:  to making sure.
SPEAKER_0:  you don't have hope and if things get better, oh, it doesn't really matter because the broader picture never gets better.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's lots of data.
SPEAKER_0:  to the contrary where that's happened before. And this isn't some magical faraway place.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the opposite of magical faraway place. It's Eastern Europe.
SPEAKER_1:  To me, I think one such narrative that...
SPEAKER_1:  People assume will always be true
SPEAKER_1:  or just to a degree will always be true like in American politics.
SPEAKER_1:  is the extreme.
SPEAKER_1:  levels of division.
SPEAKER_1:  And it seems to me like that too we can overcome.
SPEAKER_1:  So the division in American politics that seems to be counterproductive, I think that can be overcome.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think the
SPEAKER_1:  the division in geopolitics currently.
SPEAKER_1:  with Russia, China and the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  particularly
SPEAKER_1:  China and the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  it be overcome.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think that requires great leadership.
SPEAKER_1:  that galvanizes the populace.
SPEAKER_1:  to the better angels of their nature.
SPEAKER_1:  I can't have hope for that.
SPEAKER_1:  People have become really cynical on social media and elsewhere in the way they talk.
SPEAKER_1:  The liberals are destroying this country.
SPEAKER_1:  the conservatives are destroying this country.
SPEAKER_1:  this kind of language is becoming more and more popular.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that's, I hope that that's temporary.
SPEAKER_1:  At least that's my weight pill.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if you have that kind of hope for, like what does hope look like for you?
SPEAKER_1:  in.
SPEAKER_1:  American politics.
SPEAKER_1:  Forget American politics, American the nation.
SPEAKER_1:  country.
SPEAKER_1:  people.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  My hope.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  which I don't think is an unrealistic one.
SPEAKER_0:  is that.
SPEAKER_0:  the next generation.
SPEAKER_0:  has a better life.
SPEAKER_0:  than you and I have had in this country.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think anyone who thinks...
SPEAKER_0:  that America is over.
SPEAKER_0:  Or is one president away?
SPEAKER_0:  from being destroyed.
SPEAKER_0:  cannot in good conscience call themselves a patriot.
SPEAKER_0:  because if you think America is so weak.
SPEAKER_0:  that it takes a Biden.
SPEAKER_0:  or a Trump.
SPEAKER_0:  to irrevocate or Obama to irrevocably destroy it.
SPEAKER_0:  then it's already a wrap.
SPEAKER_0:  And I-
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's just absolutely ridiculous. If you look what this country has survived.
SPEAKER_0:  Great Depression.
SPEAKER_0:  World War II.
SPEAKER_0:  The Civil War.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, my god, so we've been through worse before.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  It wasn't always easy, certainly not.
SPEAKER_0:  but I am-
SPEAKER_0:  I-I-
SPEAKER_0:  It's so hard for me as someone who's a helpful person, not by my nature, I'm not-
SPEAKER_0:  You know, Michael kindness, who does work for random house, or at least he did last time I talked to him.
SPEAKER_0:  I look at even like-
SPEAKER_0:  The thing is when you speak positively, it sounds corny. That's how screwed up our cynical culture is. Have you seen my Twitter?
SPEAKER_0:  I'm trying to.
SPEAKER_0:  You're verified now.
SPEAKER_0:  That's good.
SPEAKER_0:  But even like something like Etsy.
SPEAKER_0:  Like you can go and Etsy. Homer Nathan
SPEAKER_1:  for that verification.
SPEAKER_0:  Hahahaha
SPEAKER_0:  I earned it.
SPEAKER_0:  It's an opportunity for independent artists to create something special and cool. And I've bought a lot of stuff from them. That in and of itself is something that's pretty awesome. There's so much, I'm into shaving soaps.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  It's a f-
SPEAKER_0:  The point is, there's like dozens of artisans.
SPEAKER_0:  Every day when you have a shave it brings you...
SPEAKER_0:  uh... some joy
SPEAKER_0:  So there's just so many.
SPEAKER_0:  things that are wonderful and I know there's people listening to this.
SPEAKER_0:  Rollin' their eyes.
SPEAKER_0:  How can you talk about shaving soaps when my daughter...
SPEAKER_0:  or when my wife or when blah blah blah and I'm not
SPEAKER_0:  disparaging or dismissing what you're regarding as a problem.
SPEAKER_0:  My point is hope means the belief.
SPEAKER_0:  that it's not at all a certainty.
SPEAKER_0:  that this problem will be insurmountable. That's all it means.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you look forward to in 2023?
SPEAKER_1:  since this is a holiday special.
SPEAKER_0:  Honestly?
SPEAKER_0:  Like if I look forward.
SPEAKER_0:  to a lot of young people.
SPEAKER_0:  realizing.
SPEAKER_0:  that they still have lots of opportunity in this country.
SPEAKER_0:  and taking control.
SPEAKER_0:  of their own selves and realizing they can be a better person tomorrow than they are today.
SPEAKER_0:  which may they may not identify or government which they might not identify with or like or think is deplorable and realize you know what
SPEAKER_0:  I have it in me to improve and find joy and happiness and also the fact that that is
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  compelling and contagious. That is what I would want in 2023. And also for New York to get nuked.
SPEAKER_0:  So those two things could be accomplished. Can I go back and switch the order? Because I think New York won.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, the jokes.
SPEAKER_1:  the jokes and one day friends, if you, uh, if you work hard enough in believing yourself, you too can nuke New York. No, you too.
SPEAKER_1:  can, uh, spend.
SPEAKER_1:  Your-
SPEAKER_1:  days.
SPEAKER_1:  dressing up.
SPEAKER_1:  Grown men.
SPEAKER_0:  dressing up in a Santa outfit.
SPEAKER_1:  and putting on lipstick and having.
SPEAKER_1:  hours upon hours of conversation with each other and loving every second.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for writing this really, really important book.
SPEAKER_1:  Please
SPEAKER_1:  by the white pill.
SPEAKER_1:  I love you, brother. I love you too.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with Michael Malus.
SPEAKER_1:  To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me leave you with some words from Michelle.
SPEAKER_1:  Silverstein.
SPEAKER_1:  Listen to the mussins, child, listen to the don'ts.
SPEAKER_1:  Listen to the shouldn'ts, the impossibles, the won'ts.
SPEAKER_1:  Listen to the never-haves, then listen close to me.
SPEAKER_1:  Anything can happen, child.
SPEAKER_1:  anything.
SPEAKER_1:  can be.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for listening.
SPEAKER_1:  I hope to see you.
SPEAKER_1:  next time.