SPEAKER_0:  My friend is telling me that the volcano seems to be.
SPEAKER_0:  starting to erupt.
SPEAKER_0:  If that volcano goes up, we have nowhere to go.
SPEAKER_0:  That got my attention.
SPEAKER_0:  So if you say scared, I would say that.
SPEAKER_0:  I got the realization that...
SPEAKER_0:  That meant I went cold for like a fraction of a second.
SPEAKER_0:  but that meant that just my adrenaline started to kick in.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was a very, very strange experience because now you have tunnel vision, it's about survival.
SPEAKER_1:  The following is a conversation with Natalie Cabral.
SPEAKER_1:  and astrobiologist and scientist at the SETI Institute.
SPEAKER_1:  directing the Carl Sagan Center.
SPEAKER_1:  for the study of life in the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  She explores some of the harshest places on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  including.
SPEAKER_1:  free diving in volcanic lakes.
SPEAKER_1:  all in the pursuit of understanding living organisms beyond Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  For this,
SPEAKER_1:  She holds the Women's World Record.
SPEAKER_1:  for diving at altitude, both scuba and freediving.
SPEAKER_1:  She's amazing.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the Lex Friedman podcast. To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now, dear friends.
SPEAKER_1:  Here's Natalie.
SPEAKER_1:  about.
SPEAKER_1:  You are the director of the Carl Sagan Center for Research at the SETI Institute. SETI of course stands for Search for Extraterrestrial Intelligence.
SPEAKER_1:  One of the things you do is part of...
SPEAKER_1:  that is travel to some of Earth's most extreme and dangerous environments in search of organisms that live in conditions analogous to those on Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  First let me ask.
SPEAKER_1:  what the job posting for the work you do looks like. Is it like Shackleton's ad in 1900 that said people wanted for hazardous journey to the softball?
SPEAKER_1:  Small wages, bitter cold, long months of...
SPEAKER_1:  Complete darkness, constant danger.
SPEAKER_1:  And also, where do I apply?
SPEAKER_0:  That's funny because there was not really a job application. In fact, when you're a scientist, you have...
SPEAKER_0:  questions in your mind and.
SPEAKER_0:  You have hypotheses and you start to list the kind of thing you need to answer.
SPEAKER_0:  And then when you see the kind of thing you have to answer, then you...
SPEAKER_0:  kind of know the places where you need to go to do that.
SPEAKER_0:  As far as science is concerned...
SPEAKER_0:  started with analyzing data from Mars missions.
SPEAKER_0:  And I had written a PhD about water on Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  first looking at channels and the history evolution of.
SPEAKER_0:  of water.
SPEAKER_0:  But then...
SPEAKER_0:  during my postdoc.
SPEAKER_0:  I started to look.
SPEAKER_0:  where that water was ponding.
SPEAKER_0:  Interestingly enough, everybody was about channels and water and whether catastrophic or what not or seepage.
SPEAKER_0:  But when you are talking about...
SPEAKER_0:  like
SPEAKER_0:  Lakes?
SPEAKER_0:  or ocean, people started waving their arms a little bit. So it was a little bit of a uphill battle, interestingly enough, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  but that got us on track with my husband.
SPEAKER_0:  We were working together and we started developing the idea, the concept of lakes in impact craters.
SPEAKER_0:  So why an impact crater is just because...
SPEAKER_0:  the Viking mission at the time.
SPEAKER_0:  which is what we were working with.
SPEAKER_0:  The resolution and the topography were so poor that there was really no way of telling where you had a real low in the topography. The only thing you knew was a hole in the ground was an impact crater. So when you saw valleys.
SPEAKER_0:  What was the Viking mission?
SPEAKER_0:  The Viking mission landed on Mars in 1976 and there were two landers and two orbiters. So they were really...
SPEAKER_0:  our first feet on the ground on Mars, but they were under they were not moving. They were not going
SPEAKER_1:  And that was the data you were looking at.
SPEAKER_0:  It was already in the 90s, but we didn't have yet.
SPEAKER_0:  Mars Global Surveyor and whatnot. We still work for 20 years. We worked on that. I did my master in my PhD thesis on Viking.
SPEAKER_1:  You mentioned that the places you go to are defined by the questions you want to ask.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's just step back. What questions have always tugged at your heart?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, that's the thing. That's why I was looking at those images and saw some legs.
SPEAKER_0:  And then came time.
SPEAKER_0:  where we started talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  sending landers and rovers on Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  and looking maybe at the possibility that Mars was habitable.
SPEAKER_0:  And lakes are particularly good places.
SPEAKER_0:  look for those questions. So this is how it all ties up.
SPEAKER_1:  you were always curious about life.
SPEAKER_0:  out there.
SPEAKER_0:  25 years more in that business.
SPEAKER_0:  It's more about understanding the origin and nature of life.
SPEAKER_0:  rather than whether there is life or not on Mars. I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  This was really for me a stepping stone to bigger questions, but they were definitely important because they helped me.
SPEAKER_0:  frame.
SPEAKER_0:  my way of thinking about this question. And so.
SPEAKER_0:  Looking at Mars, at lakes, understanding what the conditions were.
SPEAKER_0:  3.5 billion years ago or close to 4 billion years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  Then I knew.
SPEAKER_0:  The type of environment.
SPEAKER_0:  I needed to explore here on Earth as analogous.
SPEAKER_0:  to be able to understand what type of life.
SPEAKER_0:  still survives in those environments, and what kind of instrument and what kind of resolution do I need?
SPEAKER_0:  to actually detect it.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is how the whole thing started. And it started with a small grant, literally 40K. It was a discretionary fund.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is how I got started in my career.
SPEAKER_1:  And so many of these questions you can answer by looking at life and extreme conditions here on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the-
SPEAKER_1:  back a little bit and look at Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  and Lakes on Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  Going back to your PhD and before, and maybe today.
SPEAKER_1:  What do we understand about life?
SPEAKER_1:  on Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  What do we understand about lakes?
SPEAKER_1:  Is there water on Mars? What do we understand about the conditions from 4 billion years ago on Mars?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, we've gone a long way. Remember from the Viking where we had no resolution. Well, we'll have a little bit more resolution with them.
SPEAKER_1:  What did you think at that time? Sorry to interrupt. It was......ா?
SPEAKER_0:  It was really the exploration, like your first look.
SPEAKER_0:  at a planet.
SPEAKER_0:  you have to remember that the first mission that successfully
SPEAKER_0:  snapped some pictures of Martha with Mariner.
SPEAKER_0:  for.
SPEAKER_0:  And then.
SPEAKER_0:  Everybody at that time was still under the spell of...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, etched wells and the idea that Mars looked.
SPEAKER_0:  with telescope.
SPEAKER_0:  so similar to the earth.
SPEAKER_0:  quarter caps.
SPEAKER_0:  We could see them with a telescope.
SPEAKER_0:  And we knew it had season.
SPEAKER_0:  the actual tilt is pretty much the same as the one for Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  When Mariner 4 left, everybody...
SPEAKER_0:  Not everybody, but a lot of people thought that we were cities, crystal cities and domes and stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  that another civilization might have evolved in parallel to us in the source system.
SPEAKER_0:  And of course, when the first images came back and Mars looked with that kind of resolution, it had a big pause.
SPEAKER_0:  Like the moon.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a huge disappointment.
SPEAKER_0:  Then Mariner 9.
SPEAKER_0:  came.
SPEAKER_0:  and that changed everything.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a little bit of drama.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  Morris.
SPEAKER_0:  started one of the biggest dust storms.
SPEAKER_0:  it ever experienced.
SPEAKER_0:  So for three months we had an orbiter circling around Mars and not seeing anything.
SPEAKER_0:  But then...
SPEAKER_0:  when the dust cleared.
SPEAKER_0:  All of a sudden, we started discovering.
SPEAKER_0:  Volcanoes.
SPEAKER_0:  Valleys, ancient channels.
SPEAKER_0:  dune fields, polar caps.
SPEAKER_0:  and see what I'm talking to you. I don't need to invent any words.
SPEAKER_0:  to describe Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  And although the myth
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  extraterrestrial civilization.
SPEAKER_0:  on Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  was gone.
SPEAKER_0:  All of a sudden...
SPEAKER_0:  The imagination of the scientists started to pick up because right away we were seeing something that was familiar.
SPEAKER_0:  that we could describe. So look.
SPEAKER_0:  right away.
SPEAKER_0:  Viking with-
SPEAKER_0:  put on the fast track and the idea was so Mars looks so much like
SPEAKER_0:  Earth could have been, although it's arid and there is little atmosphere, etc.
SPEAKER_0:  Could there be life?
SPEAKER_0:  And of course, behind this.
SPEAKER_0:  At the time, they were people like...
SPEAKER_0:  Klein and Sagan call Sagan.
SPEAKER_0:  Just you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  thinking about.
SPEAKER_0:  How can we test the idea of?
SPEAKER_0:  biology of life on Mars. So this is what Viking did.
SPEAKER_0:  But of course, at the time when the two landers arrived on Mars…
SPEAKER_0:  We didn't have...
SPEAKER_0:  the context of the geology of the environment. We didn't have much data at all.
SPEAKER_0:  So the data that Viking.
SPEAKER_0:  Send back.
SPEAKER_0:  was very confusing.
SPEAKER_0:  Some people still think today that we discovered life on Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  at the time because some of the experiment turned out.
SPEAKER_0:  to show a strange signal.
SPEAKER_0:  But most of the community think that it can be explained by chemical reaction that we see today.
SPEAKER_0:  So it was so confusing that NASA decided to say, okay, if we want...
SPEAKER_0:  to be serious about looking for life on Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  we have to understand the environment.
SPEAKER_0:  because life and environment co-evolve.
SPEAKER_0:  So as cause or effect.
SPEAKER_0:  A planet is going to give you the physical chemical environment.
SPEAKER_0:  life.
SPEAKER_0:  happen. These are the boundaries.
SPEAKER_0:  But once life is here...
SPEAKER_0:  is going to change everything. One of
SPEAKER_0:  The biggest impact of life was to inject oxygen.
SPEAKER_0:  into the atmosphere of the Earth 2 billion years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  And that changed everything, including our signature in space.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  There is this co-evolution. So if you want to understand one, you have to remove the other from the equation. It's kind of a two-and-none.
SPEAKER_1:  So even though oxygen changes our signature today.
SPEAKER_1:  What if all life on earth died?
SPEAKER_1:  And now we fast forward a billion years.
SPEAKER_1:  What would be the traces left? So...
SPEAKER_1:  The question I'm trying to ask is.
SPEAKER_1:  if life had existed on Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  What would be the signs?
SPEAKER_0:  would look for? That's a very good question. The thing is that if you draw the parallel with Earth,
SPEAKER_0:  It took 82% of Earth's history.
SPEAKER_0:  geological history.
SPEAKER_0:  to go from very simple life, microbial life.
SPEAKER_0:  Complexity. And when I'm saying complexity, I'm not even talking about us. I'm talking about animals.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Mars is smaller, lost its magnetic field.
SPEAKER_0:  very fast and lost its atmosphere very fast.
SPEAKER_0:  Live also.
SPEAKER_0:  appeared on Earth very fast. So the condition being quite similar at that time between the Earth and Mars, let's assume for a moment that life appeared on Mars. It would have been simple life.
SPEAKER_0:  when conditions started to degrade.
SPEAKER_0:  which was.
SPEAKER_0:  less than a billion years after the planet had formed.
SPEAKER_0:  So everything at the surface.
SPEAKER_0:  would have disappeared.
SPEAKER_0:  except maybe for...
SPEAKER_0:  morphological traces of the interaction between life and its environment. So on Earth, the best examples are what we call stromatolites.
SPEAKER_0:  These are.
SPEAKER_0:  rock formation.
SPEAKER_0:  that are built by microbes.
SPEAKER_0:  So we know that, we know how to recognize them.
SPEAKER_0:  You could have chemical traces.
SPEAKER_0:  as well.
SPEAKER_0:  There is some interesting question marks right now, but carbon isotopes at Gale Crater.
SPEAKER_0:  because we found an abundance of C12.
SPEAKER_0:  which normally is used by life on Earth, but it can be produced by other things. So it's not that it's a real biosignature in itself.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's intriguing, we have now the C12 and we have math in.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  Going back
SPEAKER_0:  It's a time on Mars 3.5 billion years ago where you have lots of destructions, where you have lots of impact cratering etc.
SPEAKER_0:  But we still have very old rocks.
SPEAKER_0:  that survived from that time.
SPEAKER_0:  So these are good.
SPEAKER_0:  good places, that's why we're sending the rovers in those places, ancient lakes and impact craters and places where you have very old rocks.
SPEAKER_1:  So when you say ancient lakes and impact craters.
SPEAKER_1:  The simple question.
SPEAKER_1:  So Impact Creator.
SPEAKER_1:  Is a crater created by a giant rock hitting the planet?
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, a big rock that can be metal or rock.
SPEAKER_0:  or it can be a comet as well, mostly ice.
SPEAKER_1:  So is that good for life or bad for life?
SPEAKER_1:  for creating life and destroying.
SPEAKER_0:  Both. It's actually both.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Interestingly enough...
SPEAKER_0:  the building blocks of life.
SPEAKER_0:  The bricks, the stuff we are made of.
SPEAKER_0:  carbon, hydrogen, oxygen, nitrogen, and phosphorus.
SPEAKER_0:  They were included.
SPEAKER_0:  on our planet.
SPEAKER_0:  They were built in.
SPEAKER_0:  just because our planet is made of these kind of rocks, asteroids and comets coming together by what we call accretion.
SPEAKER_0:  So they were built in.
SPEAKER_0:  when an asteroid comes.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a lot of destruction going on.
SPEAKER_0:  but at the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  Those rocks they bring with them.
SPEAKER_0:  Those bricks of life?
SPEAKER_0:  and they create lots of energy.
SPEAKER_0:  and if the environment around
SPEAKER_0:  is favorable.
SPEAKER_0:  You might-
SPEAKER_0:  possibly have some seeding going on. That's one of the aspects of what we call panspermia.
SPEAKER_0:  which is the fact that comets and asteroids have the building blocks of life.
SPEAKER_0:  and better than them.
SPEAKER_0:  and that given favorable conditions, they might be able to see planets. This is a theory.
SPEAKER_1:  What percent of you?
SPEAKER_1:  When you're looking up at the stars and wondering about this stuff, think step pass. Romeo has community.
SPEAKER_1:  is what happened on Mars or on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  which is the building blocks of life came from elsewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, but you know, that's the thing, panspermia is a vector, potential vector, which means that…
SPEAKER_0:  it actually distributes.
SPEAKER_0:  The stuff of life.
SPEAKER_0:  Left and right.
SPEAKER_0:  it doesn't explain the origin of life. It's not the environment.
SPEAKER_0:  itself.
SPEAKER_0:  It just promotes maybe, and we still have to prove this.
SPEAKER_0:  But what we know is that the stuff we are made of
SPEAKER_0:  is very abundant all over the place, including in interstellar medium.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's all over. It's all over.
SPEAKER_0:  The idea is that maybe it just waits.
SPEAKER_0:  to have the proper environment.
SPEAKER_0:  And we know what it needs here on Earth. It needs water. It needs energy, shelter.
SPEAKER_0:  a nutrient.
SPEAKER_1:  So you're fundamentally interested in the origin of life.
SPEAKER_1:  and the big leaps.
SPEAKER_1:  in evolutionary history.
SPEAKER_1:  that could be like an origin of something origin of your couriers origin of.
SPEAKER_1:  for a synthesis origin of.
SPEAKER_1:  Whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  I just think if we're a civilization here on earth and we survive another few hundred
SPEAKER_1:  Years.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it would be a good idea to take a big gun.
SPEAKER_1:  and just shoot life out there.
SPEAKER_1:  Like a life gun.
SPEAKER_1:  Basically try to create pan-spermia. That's a good backup solution.
SPEAKER_1:  So one way is to actually.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  copy our brains and actual humans some.
SPEAKER_1:  complex information and send it out there.
SPEAKER_1:  Another way to preserve life is just to like...
SPEAKER_1:  Send the basic building blocks. Send them with your bacteria.
SPEAKER_1:  bunch of
SPEAKER_1:  Whatever the rugged organisms are in earth, just send a bunch of
SPEAKER_0:  These are not the building blocks, they are actual organisms.
SPEAKER_1:  So what is not a nice shortcut? Or do we want to because you said building blocks are.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, the bricks have lived a c-
SPEAKER_0:  carbon, nitrogen, etc., they were produced.
SPEAKER_0:  by the death of previous stars. So this is how they were produced.
SPEAKER_0:  And, uh.
SPEAKER_0:  Stars like our sun.
SPEAKER_0:  started to form 10 billion years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  That doesn't mean that the...
SPEAKER_0:  The sun is the only kind of star that...
SPEAKER_0:  produce life or enable life.
SPEAKER_0:  but actually was produced 10 billion years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  Now what you're talking about is a little different.
SPEAKER_0:  Right now there are many...
SPEAKER_0:  Many efforts.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  Do the type of thing you are talking about, which is to...
SPEAKER_0:  put our DNA on whatever kind of substrate and preserve it in vaults, either in different places on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  or on the moon.
SPEAKER_0:  Some people are already thinking about putting DNA on the moon.
SPEAKER_0:  As far as brains concern and
SPEAKER_0:  It's drawing towards transhumanism.
SPEAKER_0:  which is the enhancement of who we are through AI and machine learning.
SPEAKER_0:  Of course, having backups is a good thing.
SPEAKER_0:  For me.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say that taking care of our planets and going back to a place where we are.
SPEAKER_0:  in equilibrium with our environment would be also maybe the best backup possible.
SPEAKER_0:  and let evolution do its things.
SPEAKER_0:  Right now we are like teenagers.
SPEAKER_0:  with enough brain to create.
SPEAKER_0:  cool tools.
SPEAKER_0:  but we don't have enough brain to understand yet the consequences of what we are doing.
SPEAKER_0:  And right now we're paying for this.
SPEAKER_0:  So the question is whether we are going to be able to move.
SPEAKER_0:  forward.
SPEAKER_0:  and learn.
SPEAKER_0:  from.
SPEAKER_0:  the mistakes we are making.
SPEAKER_0:  to become a mature civilization.
SPEAKER_0:  You probably heard of the Drake equation. That would be the L at the very end.
SPEAKER_0:  The duration.
SPEAKER_1:  Which iteration of intelligence it was?
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly. And, and, or at least.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  The length of time.
SPEAKER_0:  a civilization remains detectable.
SPEAKER_0:  It can disappear from the radar screen literally for a number of reasons. The first one is...
SPEAKER_0:  destroy itself or being destroyed by external...
SPEAKER_0:  events.
SPEAKER_0:  or it can become so in tune.
SPEAKER_0:  and with the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  and so advanced that it disappears because it melts really in the background and it's not visible anymore.
SPEAKER_0:  There are some wild theories out there saying that.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Civilization might be so advanced that you cannot distinguish them.
SPEAKER_0:  from.
SPEAKER_0:  physical processes.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh
SPEAKER_0:  That was an example. It doesn't say that this is the case, but some people say, imagine that. In fact, all the dark matter that we see or we theorize about is in fact some sort of a biological.
SPEAKER_0:  process.
SPEAKER_0:  So you can think about a number of things.
SPEAKER_0:  Personally.
SPEAKER_0:  I believe that.
SPEAKER_0:  What you
SPEAKER_0:  talk about preserving our information.
SPEAKER_0:  It's kind of what life does. We need to look at ourselves.
SPEAKER_0:  as not different.
SPEAKER_0:  of what the little sale that started off.
SPEAKER_0:  was.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is what tells you not about the origin of life, but in fact, the nature of life, which is a lot more interesting to me because the nature of life.
SPEAKER_0:  is really what is going to give you some universal.
SPEAKER_0:  signature to look for it all over the place and not only around ponds of water.
SPEAKER_0:  for life as we know it.
SPEAKER_0:  But the nature of life is telling you that…
SPEAKER_0:  life wants.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  get the most information possible around its surroundings.
SPEAKER_0:  And complexity is in fact the ability to...
SPEAKER_0:  Gather.
SPEAKER_0:  and exchange.
SPEAKER_0:  and preserve the most information possible.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  What you're saying is kind of preserving the kind of information we have.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  in the things that we're doing.
SPEAKER_0:  as life.
SPEAKER_0:  happened.
SPEAKER_0:  And I say happen because we don't know what life is.
SPEAKER_0:  We have 123 definitions of life and some people are saying we don't have any definition, we only have descriptions.
SPEAKER_0:  life.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's true.
SPEAKER_0:  Think about it for two minutes. We are looking for something we don't know it is. But we have a few clues about the nature of life.
SPEAKER_0:  There are some really good theories. The first one was Schrodinger, right? In the 40s.
SPEAKER_0:  Right now there is a guy named Jeremy England. It's another biophysical theory of life. It says life is the inevitable result.
SPEAKER_0:  of thermophysics.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the best way to beat entropy, to fight entropy.
SPEAKER_0:  But when you look at what we are doing, if you want to know what the nature of life is,
SPEAKER_0:  look at our languages and they can be very different languages but they all have the same purpose right?
SPEAKER_0:  exchange information.
SPEAKER_0:  understand, you know, store information and also whether it is with somebody at the outside.
SPEAKER_0:  or thoughts in yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the same thing the cell was doing.
SPEAKER_0:  But now when you're looking at life.
SPEAKER_0:  and add.
SPEAKER_0:  the structure of our languages.
SPEAKER_0:  Life started with an anthem.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's another.
SPEAKER_0:  they got together to create inorganic molecules.
SPEAKER_0:  then you have complex inorganic molecules.
SPEAKER_0:  Then you get to organic molecules, complex organic molecules.
SPEAKER_0:  And then you have RNA, DNA, et cetera.
SPEAKER_0:  Look at the structure of our language.
SPEAKER_0:  We created alphabets.
SPEAKER_0:  letters.
SPEAKER_0:  That's your anthem.
SPEAKER_0:  then we put them together to create syllables.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  The syllables get together to create words.
SPEAKER_0:  Words tell you something.
SPEAKER_0:  but they are nothing without a verb.
SPEAKER_0:  that gives the direction.
SPEAKER_0:  That's RNA and DNA.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  and then you can put all the complements you want.
SPEAKER_0:  our languages are built exactly.
SPEAKER_0:  as life is built. We are repeating patterns.
SPEAKER_0:  I call this the Mandelbrot universe and the fractal universe because this is exactly what it is.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say that as much as I do believe to sending probes…
SPEAKER_0:  to explore the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  I say we should also look inward.
SPEAKER_0:  to find.
SPEAKER_0:  the answer to some of the profound questions of who we are, what's life, what's the nature of life, because we are expressing.
SPEAKER_1:  So searching not for life.
SPEAKER_1:  but for the nature of
SPEAKER_0:  The nature of life, absolutely. I am more interested in that because the day we understand...
SPEAKER_0:  The nature of life.
SPEAKER_0:  Then we have a universal
SPEAKER_0:  by your signature.
SPEAKER_0:  And it doesn't matter whether this life
SPEAKER_0:  respond to the same kind of biochemical processes as we do, although it makes sense. I told you about the generational aspect.
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  The bricks of life, the stuff we are made of.
SPEAKER_0:  The sun is part of the youngest generation of stars.
SPEAKER_0:  And the first two generations of stars didn't produce the kind of elements we are made of.
SPEAKER_0:  they were stars that were either
SPEAKER_0:  without.
SPEAKER_0:  Metal?
SPEAKER_0:  just made of helium and hydrogen?
SPEAKER_0:  or poor in metals.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  The stars died off.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Stars like the sun were born from...
SPEAKER_0:  those.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is why.
SPEAKER_0:  we have elements like carbon, hydrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  oxygen that is running now.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's the life we're built on. So-
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's not.
SPEAKER_0:  Stupid to be looking for something that looks like us, because right now in the universe this is the stuff that's the most abundant?
SPEAKER_0:  And we see with the exoplanet.
SPEAKER_0:  with Kepler, with Tess, and now with JamSwap.
SPEAKER_0:  we see that there are many, many different types of planets that may be habitable in the habitable zone of their stars.
SPEAKER_0:  There are countless stars like the sun.
SPEAKER_0:  But more interestingly enough, there are other types of stars.
SPEAKER_0:  where you do have habitable zone as well, and where the duration of the stars
SPEAKER_0:  sometimes a thousand times more than our sun.
SPEAKER_0:  So you can imagine all sorts of things.
SPEAKER_0:  and you can imagine what type of life would be.
SPEAKER_0:  on around those stars.
SPEAKER_0:  The biochemistry might be quite similar, in fact, and especially for the simple life.
SPEAKER_0:  because simple life starts really quickly.
SPEAKER_0:  on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  So my take on this is that the universe is full of cyanobacteria.
SPEAKER_0:  but as far as intelligence.
SPEAKER_0:  Life.
SPEAKER_0:  It takes more time.
SPEAKER_0:  So that can take...
SPEAKER_0:  different, you know, aspect.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think it's possible that...
SPEAKER_1:  The universe.
SPEAKER_1:  It's full of bacteria and even those stars that last a thousand times longer than the sun.
SPEAKER_1:  Even even under.
SPEAKER_1:  planets.
SPEAKER_1:  that orbit those.
SPEAKER_1:  stars.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe it's bacteria.
SPEAKER_1:  for billions and billions and billions of years.
SPEAKER_0:  We actually don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  triggered.
SPEAKER_0:  evolution to complexity on Earth? That's still a big question mark.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that the most impressive invention on earth to you?
SPEAKER_0:  That's it.
SPEAKER_0:  Cambrian Revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  is really what took us towards what we are.
SPEAKER_0:  And in the meantime, there were the dinosaurs, et cetera. The dinosaurs were wiped out. So the evolution could have taken the...
SPEAKER_0:  completely different turn.
SPEAKER_0:  It's always, I would say, mass extinction that are going to drive.
SPEAKER_0:  What's the end game?
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, you take two planets and you change.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, those asteroid impacts, all those big...
SPEAKER_0:  geological events.
SPEAKER_0:  that wipe out.
SPEAKER_0:  like 90% of life.
SPEAKER_0:  at any time.
SPEAKER_0:  The thing that seemed to be...
SPEAKER_0:  Interesting. There are two things.
SPEAKER_0:  The first one is where you are located on
SPEAKER_0:  Galaxy.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  matters a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  We actually are in the habitable zone.
SPEAKER_0:  of our galaxy.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you are.
SPEAKER_0:  close to the center then it's a lot denser.
SPEAKER_0:  And remember, we have the Oort cloud around our solar system. And if you are in the region of the galaxy that's too populated,
SPEAKER_0:  then you're going to run interaction.
SPEAKER_0:  gravitational interaction with all these stars.
SPEAKER_0:  And since it's more dense, you will have more of the comets that are leaving.
SPEAKER_0:  in the old cloud being ejected from the old cloud and.
SPEAKER_0:  coming towards the inner solar system.
SPEAKER_0:  and collide with planets. So you will have more of these impacts if you are too close to the center of the galaxy, not to mention the radiation. There is-
SPEAKER_0:  a place in our galaxy where it's a really bad neighborhood. You don't want to be there. You wouldn't be able to have life.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  What really matters is...
SPEAKER_0:  Extinctions?
SPEAKER_0:  but also...
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Climate History.
SPEAKER_0:  of a planet has a role to play.
SPEAKER_0:  And
SPEAKER_0:  It seems...
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a theory, it still has to be backed up by more observation, but there is a good correlation.
SPEAKER_0:  between only the passage of the solar system towards the center of the galaxy. There is one place where we get hit by asteroids.
SPEAKER_0:  because of the interaction I was telling you about.
SPEAKER_0:  But the other one.
SPEAKER_0:  is the climate.
SPEAKER_0:  with the Milankovitch cycles.
SPEAKER_0:  Big jumps.
SPEAKER_0:  in life's evolution seem to be associated.
SPEAKER_0:  with
SPEAKER_0:  Snowball Earth episodes.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  Why yet?
SPEAKER_0:  Snowball episode.
SPEAKER_0:  intuitively you would think that they are connected.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  decrease in life because the whole Earth is covered in ice.
SPEAKER_0:  but for some reason.
SPEAKER_0:  there were big jumps in evolution right after.
SPEAKER_0:  each of those episodes.
SPEAKER_0:  And today there are other things like...
SPEAKER_0:  Why all of a sudden you have mutation that seems to be responsible for a big jump in evolution?
SPEAKER_0:  We are not clear yet. So all of those sayings when you're thinking about life elsewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  are going to come into play.
SPEAKER_0:  And I cannot tell you.
SPEAKER_0:  that a planet that remains habitable for much longer than the Earth
SPEAKER_0:  will have.
SPEAKER_0:  an evolutionary path that's the same or different.
SPEAKER_0:  depends on extension, depends on climate, depends on...
SPEAKER_0:  but not.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a little bit surreal that we're two descendants of apes.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's some
SPEAKER_0:  some people. girl.
SPEAKER_1:  what the heck is going on. And I mean we're very biased even as a so you.
SPEAKER_1:  We're biased as humans.
SPEAKER_1:  You're less biased as a scientist.
SPEAKER_1:  But we still love earth. We still don't know anything but this earth
SPEAKER_1:  And so even though you try to get escape.
SPEAKER_1:  from thinking of what life is.
SPEAKER_1:  in the search for the nature of life we still kind of connected to.
SPEAKER_1:  the way we understand the nature of life here on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  I think that it's a little different than that.
SPEAKER_0:  We are biased when it comes to the origin.
SPEAKER_0:  of life.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes. Becauseă
SPEAKER_0:  Well, we are the only model we know.
SPEAKER_0:  And as I said, it makes sense.
SPEAKER_0:  because
SPEAKER_0:  It seems that
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, stars like the sun.
SPEAKER_0:  appeared 10 billion years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  and there are lots of words that really resemble the Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  and lots of water out there and lots of conditions that could be a repeat of what we know.
SPEAKER_0:  and we know that this biochemistry works.
SPEAKER_0:  So, again, as I mentioned, what is going to change is really the evolution of a planet, extinction, geology, etc.
SPEAKER_0:  But our model...
SPEAKER_0:  is probably very abundant. I'm not saying that the endgame
SPEAKER_0:  is going to resemble us because of all these extinctions, etc.
SPEAKER_0:  But this is...
SPEAKER_0:  A good bias, it's one that has the number for it.
SPEAKER_0:  You know the principle of mediocrity. I think that in that case
SPEAKER_0:  It really applies.
SPEAKER_0:  where the Earth
SPEAKER_0:  is representative.
SPEAKER_0:  of an abundance.
SPEAKER_0:  of other words.
SPEAKER_0:  Now, of course, there can be other biochemistry. We have
SPEAKER_0:  Some examples in our own source system Titan might be
SPEAKER_0:  representative of that.
SPEAKER_0:  We are not very clear the kind of biochemistry that can come out.
SPEAKER_0:  of a world where you have hydrocarbon lakes and rains and things like that.
SPEAKER_0:  But we're going there.
SPEAKER_0:  So we will learn something about this.
SPEAKER_0:  So the bias is right there.
SPEAKER_0:  The nature of life is different.
SPEAKER_0:  If really.
SPEAKER_0:  Life.
SPEAKER_0:  is
SPEAKER_0:  the best way the universe has to fight entropy.
SPEAKER_0:  There is no bias there.
SPEAKER_0:  Because physics is the same all across the universe, at least the universe we know, there might be other universes.
SPEAKER_0:  but the one we know works with the same physics.
SPEAKER_1:  So if life is the-
SPEAKER_1:  the best way to fight entropy.
SPEAKER_1:  You can imagine that life permeates.
SPEAKER_1:  the entire universe.
SPEAKER_1:  and then the question might change to.
SPEAKER_1:  like flavors of ice cream, what are the flavors of complexity?
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  this
SPEAKER_1:  process this nature of life leads to.
SPEAKER_1:  and there we might have bias.
SPEAKER_1:  about what complexity.
SPEAKER_1:  Looks like.
SPEAKER_1:  what beautiful complexity looks like. We'll look at humans that operate a certain.
SPEAKER_1:  physical scale and uh...
SPEAKER_1:  time scale.
SPEAKER_1:  And we think this is intelligence.
SPEAKER_0:  We have another problem.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't know what life is, we don't know what intelligence is, and we don't know what consciousness is, but we are trying to tackle the big question.
SPEAKER_1:  But do we know what complexity is also?
SPEAKER_0:  You know, no, I think that we have to be honest and as a scientist.
SPEAKER_0:  and I'm going to step back and talk about intelligence.
SPEAKER_0:  For me, bacteria...
SPEAKER_0:  that has survived like cyanobacteria.
SPEAKER_0:  that has survived just like us.
SPEAKER_0:  four billion years in one incarnation or another, and actually they are very similar to the one that they were 3.5 billion years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  It has some intelligence about its environment.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  For complexity.
SPEAKER_0:  It might be...
SPEAKER_0:  that we need to take the world literally, which is an assemblage.
SPEAKER_0:  or additional capacity to
SPEAKER_0:  gather, collect, store information. Maybe this is something like that, or actually use that information to do something with it.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  I do completely agree with you when you talk about flavor of ice cream.
SPEAKER_0:  I think this is exactly it.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I have a basic...
SPEAKER_0:  Education about
SPEAKER_0:  What physics is doing right now?
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm-
SPEAKER_0:  Look at quantum physics.
SPEAKER_0:  and what it says about the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  and about the connection.
SPEAKER_0:  about.
SPEAKER_0:  And Adam here.
SPEAKER_0:  And another hair.
SPEAKER_0:  the bottom here and the bottom there.
SPEAKER_0:  I am starting to put maybe...
SPEAKER_0:  wrongfully, two and two together.
SPEAKER_0:  But in my mind...
SPEAKER_0:  And of course it's nothing until I can prove it.
SPEAKER_0:  but in my mind.
SPEAKER_0:  The universe is connected everywhere.
SPEAKER_0:  in all different places. So this is life.
SPEAKER_0:  connection is.
SPEAKER_0:  Something that.
SPEAKER_0:  As you said, permit.
SPEAKER_0:  the universe and
SPEAKER_0:  The way to find life.
SPEAKER_0:  might be very different than to look for the origins of life. I think it's a good thing to go out there and look for the origins of life somewhere else.
SPEAKER_0:  because it's the manifestation.
SPEAKER_0:  of the nature of life that all of a sudden becomes.
SPEAKER_0:  Apparent, evident to our eye.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  What I think.
SPEAKER_0:  would be our greatest achievement is that if we can find
SPEAKER_0:  that process.
SPEAKER_0:  of life.
SPEAKER_0:  Because at that point, in my mind, the universe all of a sudden is going to…
SPEAKER_0:  illuminate itself.
SPEAKER_0:  with actually.
SPEAKER_0:  It's living force, what I can only call a living force.
SPEAKER_0:  To me, this is what we are looking at, a universe that...
SPEAKER_0:  becomes more and more complex with time.
SPEAKER_0:  more and more able to gather information.
SPEAKER_0:  And interestingly enough, why?
SPEAKER_0:  to understand.
SPEAKER_0:  itself.
SPEAKER_0:  So Sagan was right.
SPEAKER_0:  when he was telling, we are the universe trying to understand itself.
SPEAKER_0:  And the more we go, the more...
SPEAKER_0:  the universe become.
SPEAKER_0:  Alive?
SPEAKER_0:  maybe intelligent and maybe also conscious.
SPEAKER_0:  conscious, self-aware.
SPEAKER_1:  Exactly. Through us.
SPEAKER_1:  It does make me a little bit sad as a human.
SPEAKER_1:  just watching all the breakthroughs on artificial intelligence side when applied to natural sciences.
SPEAKER_1:  Now more and more to physics.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  the creatures that will solve.
SPEAKER_1:  the question of the origin of the nature of life or just the process.
SPEAKER_1:  The nature of life.
SPEAKER_1:  will be AI systems.
SPEAKER_1:  Makes me a bit sad.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think so.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think so. You think humans will. At this point in time, remember who's behind AI.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not buying in the singularity thing yet.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  AI is not aware.
SPEAKER_0:  AI is being built by humans?
SPEAKER_0:  So, um.
SPEAKER_0:  AI is a tool.
SPEAKER_0:  an extremely smart tool.
SPEAKER_0:  as long as we build it.
SPEAKER_0:  And as long as we use it as a tool, it remains a tool.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think there is a lot of brouhaha and of course, science fiction and movies.
SPEAKER_0:  They don't help.
SPEAKER_1:  See, I gotta push back a little bit. Yes, I agree with you for the most part, which was a boo-ha-ha.
SPEAKER_1:  and sci-fi.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  There is, like in the work of DeepMind.
SPEAKER_1:  We can look at chest, or we can look at protein folding.
SPEAKER_1:  So chess is a simple one.
SPEAKER_1:  to first look at.
SPEAKER_1:  What?
SPEAKER_1:  Alpha zero.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, which is their game playing engine.
SPEAKER_1:  was able to discover an outstock fish about chess.
SPEAKER_1:  HUMBLES
SPEAKER_1:  the best human players.
SPEAKER_1:  not just is better than them.
SPEAKER_1:  It comes up with ideas that the humans don't understand.
SPEAKER_1:  And so the AI now is telling you.
SPEAKER_1:  Even though it's programmed by humans, the AI is saying like
SPEAKER_1:  Sacrificing a pawn here is a good idea. Sacrificing a queen or a bishop here is a good idea.
SPEAKER_1:  and then you start to kind of intuit as a human why.
SPEAKER_1:  but you don't deeply understand.
SPEAKER_1:  And you can say that AI is not conscious. It doesn't deeply understand the way humans do, but there's still a wisdom and a depth of knowledge in that.
SPEAKER_1:  chess playing program that humans.
SPEAKER_1:  don't have and the same with the alpha fold with protein folding.
SPEAKER_1:  There's another applying it to physics to simulating nuclear reactions and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  It feels like there might be a way to understand the nature of life.
SPEAKER_1:  that we can kind of intuit poetically as humans.
SPEAKER_1:  the true understanding will come from a system that's much more complex.
SPEAKER_1:  computation is sophisticated.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, I would push back on my turn because I still think that humans give themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  Ability.
SPEAKER_0:  to do that by building that tool.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  The idea that we are getting into the Kardashev scale and the dark forest and all these things.
SPEAKER_0:  We can see the world this way. Uh, at this point in time for me.
SPEAKER_0:  I still see.
SPEAKER_0:  A great tool.
SPEAKER_0:  Now.
SPEAKER_0:  whether the sci-fi scenario is going to, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  I still think that we are far away from this.
SPEAKER_0:  But if that tool is capable of giving me a new perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just that
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  we are starting to jump into a deeper.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  cognition of what the universe is.
SPEAKER_0:  whether it's
SPEAKER_0:  through our brain or through a different way of gathering information, remember, this is what we do.
SPEAKER_1:  able to actually build tools.
SPEAKER_1:  and then integrate them.
SPEAKER_1:  enter their way of thinking. Maybe another generation has to be born.
SPEAKER_1:  that is raised with those tools, but we seem to like...
SPEAKER_1:  take for granted all the cool technologies you integrate into your.
SPEAKER_1:  way of thinking.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of people are growing up now.
SPEAKER_1:  Their mind is integrated with the internet.
SPEAKER_1:  You basically.
SPEAKER_1:  reconfigure the way you memorize things. You no longer have to memorize a lot of facts because you can look them up really quickly. And so like
SPEAKER_1:  So you reallocate a lot of resources for.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... thinking versus memory of
SPEAKER_1:  just strict facts.
SPEAKER_1:  That kind of stuff, and we integrate all of that.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and you know.
SPEAKER_0:  There I would completely agree with you. In fact, I wrote about this again.
SPEAKER_0:  in this new book that's coming out.
SPEAKER_0:  When is the book coming out? In January. It's it will be in French actually, uh, to start with. You wrote it in French? Actually, I wrote it first in English. Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  and I translated it into French, so the English version is already pretty much ready to go if we find a publisher.
SPEAKER_0:  in the US.
SPEAKER_0:  But anyways, the point being here that I looked at this as
SPEAKER_0:  our relationship with technology.
SPEAKER_0:  as a complete
SPEAKER_0:  change, to me this is the singularity, more than anything else.
SPEAKER_0:  which is the coevolution.
SPEAKER_0:  of human with technology, not anymore with their environment.
SPEAKER_0:  while we are messing up the environment right now.
SPEAKER_0:  why we don't respond to pandemic the way we should.
SPEAKER_0:  because we are disconnected.
SPEAKER_0:  the environment we are taking our information from and we were adapting from.
SPEAKER_0:  right now exactly as you said.
SPEAKER_0:  we take the information from the web.
SPEAKER_0:  from the phones, etc. You have no filter.
SPEAKER_0:  over that information.
SPEAKER_0:  Before you were out in the environment, the information you get is the one the planet is sending you.
SPEAKER_0:  Now this information is coming from different ways. You have no way of knowing if information is correct or not. You gotta push back on that. No, you look at this as an ecosystem and it explains a lot of our behavior.
SPEAKER_1:  See, I like that you said teenagers.
SPEAKER_1:  So we, the technology, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  when we move past the teenager stage.
SPEAKER_1:  enriches our ability to sense the earth.
SPEAKER_1:  to understand what's going on with the environment.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just that we're very, so it's not that technology disconnects us from the environment.
SPEAKER_1:  It gives us more tools with which to understand what's going on with the environment.
SPEAKER_0:  true for the people who are building the tools and know how to use it. Take those tools now, put them in the general public with no filter, which is happening with social media, which is happening with a lot of things.
SPEAKER_0:  And you see the disaster this is creating. And it's not the disaster.
SPEAKER_1:  There's challenges. You sound like a parent talking about a teenager. Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  Did you know? It's the growing pains of a civilization that is becoming deeply connected.
SPEAKER_1:  without we can communicate all across the world.
SPEAKER_1:  Even through the pandemic.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the good thing about technology. This is also something I wrote. It's not the tools we create that are bad. It's the way we use them.
SPEAKER_0:  But we are learning.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, and hopefully we'll do all the learning before it's too late because our response.
SPEAKER_0:  to what's going on in the environment.
SPEAKER_0:  Our response to pandemics is deeply connected to this disconnect we have with nature.
SPEAKER_0:  Anyways, we all agree that...
SPEAKER_0:  We are.
SPEAKER_0:  in growing pains?
SPEAKER_0:  and hopefully...
SPEAKER_0:  we can move forward because there is a fantastic universe.
SPEAKER_0:  something absolutely magical.
SPEAKER_0:  around us. And I'm talking as a scientist. I mean, there is magic.
SPEAKER_0:  not in the sense of trickery.
SPEAKER_0:  but in sense of wonder.
SPEAKER_0:  around us.
SPEAKER_0:  and there are so many signs.
SPEAKER_0:  We are getting...
SPEAKER_0:  So close.
SPEAKER_0:  too.
SPEAKER_0:  Revolutions.
SPEAKER_0:  in cosmology, in astrobiology, in astronomy.
SPEAKER_0:  Which
SPEAKER_0:  I think to me.
SPEAKER_0:  This is where the hope lies and also an awakening of understanding that we need to.
SPEAKER_0:  be in equilibrium with the planet if we want to move forward because
SPEAKER_0:  Even though we have these big dreams of going on Mars and the Moon and listen, I am a
SPEAKER_0:  planetary geology.
SPEAKER_0:  I am all for exploration.
SPEAKER_0:  Right now.
SPEAKER_0:  The moon or Mars is not going to save your butt, because for the logistics, we'll still depend very much on the Earth and for a long time.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  This
SPEAKER_0:  time we are living in.
SPEAKER_0:  will be remembered.
SPEAKER_0:  as
SPEAKER_0:  A.
SPEAKER_0:  pivot.
SPEAKER_0:  in our history for a number of reasons.
SPEAKER_0:  a time where there is a growing consciousness.
SPEAKER_0:  where we are creating tools that are going a little bit ahead of us, that we have some.
SPEAKER_0:  some difficult time to catch up on with, where we have to deal with a population that's way!
SPEAKER_0:  too big.
SPEAKER_0:  for the planet we have.
SPEAKER_0:  we need to really learn a sense of balance.
SPEAKER_0:  and maturity as a civilization.
SPEAKER_0:  So how is this going to unfold?
SPEAKER_0:  Right now I have no clue.
SPEAKER_1:  I draw a lot of optimism from the...
SPEAKER_1:  similar things that happened.
SPEAKER_1:  many decades ago.
SPEAKER_1:  when nuclear weapons were developed.
SPEAKER_1:  Boy, it was that at the time even more terrifying.
SPEAKER_1:  You just now created weapons that could destroy the entirety of life on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  or not entirety, but.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of it.
SPEAKER_1:  and we somehow found a balance.
SPEAKER_1:  and that the threat constantly is out there.
SPEAKER_1:  and that threat has been made more visceral in recent times.
SPEAKER_1:  um
SPEAKER_1:  because of the war in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  we find a balance somehow.
SPEAKER_1:  So I have a thread of optimism.
SPEAKER_1:  for human civilization, that we figure it out. We're clever teenagers.
SPEAKER_0:  I think. We are clever teenagers. There is definitely a thread of optimism.
SPEAKER_0:  But I think it's thin.
SPEAKER_0:  It's thin because...
SPEAKER_0:  Something that has changed as well.
SPEAKER_0:  is the mentality.
SPEAKER_0:  of humans.
SPEAKER_0:  Although the threat...
SPEAKER_0:  was terrifying.
SPEAKER_0:  when nuclear weapons were created.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a sense...
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  limits you were willing to push in the threads.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a sense of.
SPEAKER_0:  Distancy.
SPEAKER_0:  of moral values.
SPEAKER_0:  It was not perfect.
SPEAKER_0:  but it was at least a time.
SPEAKER_0:  where people could come together.
SPEAKER_0:  from very different perspectives and agree.
SPEAKER_0:  that something was more important.
SPEAKER_0:  than destroying everything.
SPEAKER_1:  But that's so hilarious you say that. Yes, you're talking about a small slither of humans.
SPEAKER_1:  which is the scientist in the Manhattan Project, perhaps. No, absolutely not. It's also the time.
SPEAKER_1:  when over a hundred million people were tortured or murdered.
SPEAKER_0:  No, no, I agree with that. Absolutely, absolutely. I'm not talking about scientists here.
SPEAKER_0:  Actually, I'm talking about politicians.
SPEAKER_0:  We've gone.
SPEAKER_0:  beyond that point now.
SPEAKER_0:  This is what I'm worried about.
SPEAKER_0:  torture, et cetera. Unfortunately, well, we are apes.
SPEAKER_0:  exactly what you said. So I think that there is a lot to be, not to blame grandpa for that, but because we can always get better.
SPEAKER_0:  Grandpa was a wild man.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Hehehehe
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  We have to improve a lot on that side before we can claim that we are a material civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  When you um just because you mentioned the magic when you look out there
SPEAKER_1:  Perhaps it's not a scientific question, but...
SPEAKER_0:  You don't have to be scientific all the time. Yeah. Well, this.
SPEAKER_1:  You said magic. So there's a magic to magic that is in part scientific and in part.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, whatever fills us with awe as humans when we look up at the stars.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think?
SPEAKER_1:  the universe is full of life or not.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, when you're sitting drinking some wine, looking up at the stars and-
SPEAKER_1:  and wandering as a human.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think we're alone?
SPEAKER_1:  Or do you think?
SPEAKER_1:  It's life is.
SPEAKER_0:  everywhere. I am going to make such an unmagical response to that.
SPEAKER_0:  My response is...
SPEAKER_0:  That's the scientific response.
SPEAKER_0:  that if we are alone...
SPEAKER_0:  then the universe is a statistical absurdity.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  And I have no doubt.
SPEAKER_0:  in my mind and that is an unscientific.
SPEAKER_0:  response as well.
SPEAKER_0:  but I have no doubt in my mind.
SPEAKER_0:  that the universe is teeming with life.
SPEAKER_0:  What if...
SPEAKER_1:  keeps dying.
SPEAKER_0:  This is what life does.
SPEAKER_0:  Unfortunately.
SPEAKER_1:  So that extinction.
SPEAKER_1:  is as a process, as a part of the process of life.
SPEAKER_1:  Extinction seems to be a fundamental...
SPEAKER_1:  both negative and positive.
SPEAKER_1:  component.
SPEAKER_1:  So what if all the...
SPEAKER_1:  Complex life out there just keeps dying.
SPEAKER_1:  and not making way for.
SPEAKER_1:  Like we're actually a statistical anomaly.
SPEAKER_1:  in us being able to survive that L.
SPEAKER_1:  in the Drake equation, being able to survive long enough to form complex organisms.
SPEAKER_1:  of the kind that mammals are.
SPEAKER_1:  Things with brains.
SPEAKER_0:  things that are able to cause us harm. L is not about that, L is about how long a civilization is capable of.
SPEAKER_0:  being detectable, which means that rich technologies and being detectable.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so there's a more nuanced things to L because you can have intelligent civilizations that are not very detectable
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, we had civilization.
SPEAKER_0:  for thousands of years.
SPEAKER_0:  We started to be detectable 150 years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's about technology, technology that we can actually.
SPEAKER_0:  capture from space, you become visible to your neighbors.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is all about the Fermi paradox, right?
SPEAKER_0:  It takes time.
SPEAKER_0:  Obviously, if we're taking again.
SPEAKER_0:  ourselves as a model, but this is the only one we have.
SPEAKER_0:  to get to the point where we become detectable.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  Look at the edge of the universe, even if…
SPEAKER_0:  Life as we understand it, not...
SPEAKER_0:  Not saying even as we know it, but as we can understand it.
SPEAKER_0:  started 10 billion years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  and it takes.
SPEAKER_0:  4 billion years.
SPEAKER_0:  to get to the point where it becomes detectable.
SPEAKER_0:  That means that the first planet where those civilizations started off
SPEAKER_0:  starting to be detectable when we were still cyanobacteria in ponds. So they were, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  throwing messages and
SPEAKER_0:  that were passing above our heads at that point.
SPEAKER_0:  And those civilizations, when you look at them now, close to 10 billion years.
SPEAKER_0:  after the start.
SPEAKER_0:  So their son would be dead.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  In the best-case scenario, they move somewhere else.
SPEAKER_0:  And what that means is that civilizations are going.
SPEAKER_0:  to rise.
SPEAKER_0:  die or move?
SPEAKER_0:  and transform themselves, we can see ourselves changing. We know that humans are still changing as a species.
SPEAKER_0:  The human being in a thousand or even 500 years from now might not be looking a lot like we are doing right now. Who knows where we will be? We might be migrating into our planetary system. We might be migrating somewhere else.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, you said migrating, but...
SPEAKER_1:  It seems when you look at life, it doesn't necessarily migrate. It expands.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's not.
SPEAKER_1:  or
SPEAKER_1:  Place A or Place B is Place A and Place B.
SPEAKER_0:  It seems to expand. It could be. We are talking about the human civilization here.
SPEAKER_0:  So they are different.
SPEAKER_0:  factor, if you are a cyanobacteria or any type of even a mammal.
SPEAKER_0:  that doesn't have the technology to escape.
SPEAKER_0:  the planet we were born on.
SPEAKER_0:  then it's plan A, it's right there. You know, whatever happens to your planet, you are tied to it. You cannot escape it.
SPEAKER_0:  For humans, it's a little different. It's A and B, or whatever we can.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  We have to expect that a number of the civilizations
SPEAKER_0:  extraterrestrial civilization that might be technologically advanced, a number of them will have disappeared just because they run the course of their.
SPEAKER_0:  evolution or because their son…
SPEAKER_0:  run out of fuel and they didn't have a way to escape.
SPEAKER_0:  or they were wiped out.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  any kind of event and then there will be those that survive.
SPEAKER_1:  everything I've seen from life, it seems.
SPEAKER_1:  obvious that there's life everywhere out there.
SPEAKER_1:  In fact,
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe I don't understand the jump from bacteria enough.
SPEAKER_1:  but it seems obvious that there's intelligent civilizations out there.
SPEAKER_1:  Now I don't know how to define intelligence, but there's.
SPEAKER_1:  beautiful complexity. Like when you look at a
SPEAKER_1:  I've looked at enough cellular automata, which is a very
SPEAKER_1:  primitive mathematical
SPEAKER_1:  construction that when you run.
SPEAKER_1:  complexity emerges.
SPEAKER_1:  I've looked at that enough to know that it just seems like there's complexity everywhere out there so F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F- F-
SPEAKER_1:  That's why I'm deeply puzzled by the Fermi paradox. It makes no sense to me.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  that have trivial answers to it. Why haven't aliens at scale not shown up?
SPEAKER_1:  I think the two possible options for me.
SPEAKER_1:  is
SPEAKER_1:  Either we're too dumb to see it, they're already here, they've been talking to us.
SPEAKER_1:  through processes we just don't understand.
SPEAKER_1:  Mike.
SPEAKER_1:  What we experience as life here on earth is actually there everywhere. Aliens could be consciousness.
SPEAKER_1:  that when we feel love for one another, that could be aliens. When we, I don't know, or feel fear or whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  That could be aliens.
SPEAKER_0:  I have to agree with you.
SPEAKER_0:  None of this is scientifically provable. Right now we talked a little bit already about that.
SPEAKER_0:  But I would say that I...
SPEAKER_0:  Do not.
SPEAKER_0:  there too the Fermi paradox.
SPEAKER_0:  because it's very anthropomorphic. It's an interesting exercise. Let's put it that way.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  It's a typical example of seeing the universe through our own.
SPEAKER_0:  ice.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  This is where the limitation is.
SPEAKER_0:  Understanding?
SPEAKER_0:  what's going on with complexity, as you said, and looking at the biophysical.
SPEAKER_0:  model.
SPEAKER_0:  and theories.
SPEAKER_0:  for the nature of life.
SPEAKER_0:  I would agree that
SPEAKER_0:  Probably.
SPEAKER_0:  This extraterrestrial message is all around us.
SPEAKER_0:  we're not yet capable of picking it up.
SPEAKER_1:  But I think unfortunately, even though that makes me sad, the way to pick it up is by studying life here on Earth, doing some of the science you're doing.
SPEAKER_1:  better understand the nature of life until you realize.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... holy crap
SPEAKER_1:  The thing I was looking for all along has been here all along.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you know, a good example of that and it doesn't need to be.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  and extraterrestrial civilization.
SPEAKER_0:  look at something that I really...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, whether or not it's...
SPEAKER_0:  Real?
SPEAKER_0:  I don't care because in terms of intellectual exercise, I think it's fantastic. Look at the Shadow Biosphere.
SPEAKER_0:  The idea.
SPEAKER_0:  ZERD
SPEAKER_0:  Life
SPEAKER_0:  didn't appear.
SPEAKER_0:  Only once.
SPEAKER_0:  on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  but there were many different pathways.
SPEAKER_0:  of it.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Today, we know when we study.
SPEAKER_0:  The Tree of Life.
SPEAKER_0:  That's it.
SPEAKER_0:  to us.
SPEAKER_0:  from Luca to us.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  The shadow biosphere is telling us that there is...
SPEAKER_0:  Or there are.
SPEAKER_0:  other pathways.
SPEAKER_0:  that came.
SPEAKER_0:  at the time where life originated.
SPEAKER_0:  But they are so different.
SPEAKER_0:  that we cannot recognize them.
SPEAKER_0:  as being the living.
SPEAKER_0:  and we cannot pick them up in our tests because our tests are being
SPEAKER_0:  built.
SPEAKER_0:  to recognize life as we know it.
SPEAKER_0:  And for me...
SPEAKER_0:  Again, I don't know if this theory...
SPEAKER_0:  will be verified.
SPEAKER_0:  or
SPEAKER_0:  it would be...
SPEAKER_0:  discredited but...
SPEAKER_0:  What I like about it is that it forces me to think on
SPEAKER_0:  How do I look for life?
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  that starts here on our planet.
SPEAKER_0:  not even with little green men.
SPEAKER_0:  It starts with very simple light that be...
SPEAKER_0:  can be so different.
SPEAKER_0:  that it might be just right in front of our nose, and we don't see it.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's probably starts with the scientific humility of.
SPEAKER_1:  Always.
SPEAKER_1:  realizing that.
SPEAKER_1:  We might be too biased in understanding of what is the phenomena we're trying to study.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I don't like the term bias because it involves some moral connotation. But I understand the bias in terms of scientific pathway, intellectual framework.
SPEAKER_0:  Definitely.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think about the...
SPEAKER_1:  UFO sightings.
SPEAKER_1:  the widespread
SPEAKER_1:  experiences that people have and seeing.
SPEAKER_1:  different phenomena.
SPEAKER_1:  that they...
SPEAKER_1:  sort of that are mysterious that people project.
SPEAKER_1:  ideas about whether it's aliens or not, but they can't explain it and there's pictures and data and the government is involved and
SPEAKER_1:  Releasing
SPEAKER_1:  footage and all that kind of stuff and that it seems to captivate the public.
SPEAKER_0:  It always does. There are a number of things that...
SPEAKER_0:  captivate people.
SPEAKER_0:  especially children, actually, dinosaurs and aliens. Still a child. Yeah, we are all such a child at heart.
SPEAKER_0:  So, about UFOs.
SPEAKER_0:  I am a scientist and I'm a citizen.
SPEAKER_0:  So I'm going to tell you a couple of things. Thirst, I don't mind talking about that at all, because I think as a scientist, this is extremely interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  cuz the thing I don't know
SPEAKER_0:  I want to learn about it. This is more knowledge.
SPEAKER_0:  So we all know the statistics about UFOs.
SPEAKER_0:  95% of them are just natural phenomenon or things that are being misinterpreted. We know that.
SPEAKER_0:  Then you have the 2% that might be secret programs by whatever government.
SPEAKER_0:  It's out there.
SPEAKER_0:  Another person say is about natural phenomenon.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  we don't know about yet and we cannot explain. And then there is this tiny percentage.
SPEAKER_0:  that don't fall into all these categories of things. I think that the report about the UAPs falls into the same kind of scheme except that now they have at least
SPEAKER_0:  some patterns of speed of...
SPEAKER_0:  other things that were in the report.
SPEAKER_0:  Today we don't know if these sightings are...
SPEAKER_0:  part of military program or actual.
SPEAKER_0:  UFOs.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I always run into that question because of course as the director of the Carsteg and Center at the study institute, I received a number of emails about the subject. People actually...
SPEAKER_0:  Confused about what the study institute is? We are not studying UFOs.
SPEAKER_0:  We are studying, we are actually looking for messages. The way I put it, you know, usually is that we are studying.
SPEAKER_0:  extraterrestrial in their natural habitat. The UFO people are trying to understand whether they invaded our aerial space. Which is two very different things.
SPEAKER_0:  And unfortunately, over the years...
SPEAKER_0:  I actually respect very much people who are trying.
SPEAKER_0:  to go to the bottom of what UFOs are.
SPEAKER_0:  following some very
SPEAKER_0:  scientific ways of doing this. They are very-
SPEAKER_0:  very credible agencies doing this.
SPEAKER_0:  Unfortunately, there is a folklore.
SPEAKER_0:  around UFOs.
SPEAKER_0:  And this has been a huge disservice.
SPEAKER_0:  to the scientific community.
SPEAKER_0:  This is why you have been having that much pushback for a long time by the scientific community because
SPEAKER_0:  No congressman in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  wants to tell their taxpayer that they are supporting something that's looking for flying saucers and you know
SPEAKER_0:  When you see what's happening, it's terrifying. And I am actually-
SPEAKER_0:  concern, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  about that relationship that people do between.
SPEAKER_0:  folklore.
SPEAKER_0:  and real search for extraterrestrial intelligence.
SPEAKER_0:  In fact,
SPEAKER_0:  It's been so bad that...
SPEAKER_0:  Until today.
SPEAKER_0:  There is no government agency that is actually...
SPEAKER_0:  funding.
SPEAKER_0:  the city search.
SPEAKER_0:  It is a private funded.
SPEAKER_0:  Endeavor.
SPEAKER_0:  What NASA finds right now, which is a progress, is a search for techno-signature, which means that when you are looking, you can see the
SPEAKER_0:  the atmosphere of the planet.
SPEAKER_0:  You look for some disequilibrium that could tell you that something is there.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's not going to fund.
SPEAKER_0:  a institute.
SPEAKER_0:  or whatnot that is looking for messages or other things like that.
SPEAKER_1:  Does that just have to do with the taboo associated with the folklore?
SPEAKER_0:  Yes!
SPEAKER_0:  And I think there was a pushback.
SPEAKER_0:  from the political.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, arena.
SPEAKER_0:  decades ago.
SPEAKER_0:  about that at the time where all the flying saucers were coming out.
SPEAKER_0:  and then the study institute.
SPEAKER_0:  God, it's.
SPEAKER_0:  started.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  But now...
SPEAKER_0:  there is more of a willingness to look at the UAP.
SPEAKER_0:  Ah.
SPEAKER_0:  you whistle.
SPEAKER_0:  a phenomenon.
SPEAKER_0:  from a scientific standpoint. So much so.
SPEAKER_0:  that the government is actually seeking.
SPEAKER_0:  Some.
SPEAKER_0:  help from.
SPEAKER_0:  scientific.
SPEAKER_0:  institution.
SPEAKER_0:  and their programs.
SPEAKER_0:  to start.
SPEAKER_0:  looking into those phenomena.
SPEAKER_0:  And as a scientist...
SPEAKER_0:  I am interested.
SPEAKER_0:  what I'm not interested in.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, Carl Sagan comes back here.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't want to believe.
SPEAKER_0:  I want to know.
SPEAKER_0:  And so to know you have to have.
SPEAKER_0:  a real experiment, you have to have observation and you have.
SPEAKER_0:  things that are done the right way.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't want to have somebody that starts with, what if…
SPEAKER_0:  as a question and then turns this what if into the only argument and the only conclusion there is. You understand what I'm saying? Cool.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's valuable to.
SPEAKER_1:  appreciate the mystery.
SPEAKER_1:  and not deny the mystery. So
SPEAKER_0:  Now the mystery is there, but what I don't want is people taking advantage of the public and making money out of folklore.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, let me flip that. I understand.
SPEAKER_1:  But so there's a folklore in like the stuff I do AI and robotics, for example.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a clear fear, Terminator, and movies, and all those kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  You could say that I'm very concerned about this.
SPEAKER_1:  miscalibrated understanding of the public of what robots.
SPEAKER_1:  role are in society.
SPEAKER_1:  Or you could see it as a-
SPEAKER_1:  Let's use a metaphor of a wave. You can say this giant wave.
SPEAKER_1:  the local folklore is a really bad idea. We need to avoid it. We need to hide. We need to build dams.
SPEAKER_1:  or you can be a surfer and ride the wave as a scientist.
SPEAKER_1:  To me, the fact that people are wondering about the mystery of UFOs.
SPEAKER_1:  It means they're wondering.
SPEAKER_0:  No, they are. The thing, I will stop.
SPEAKER_0:  surfing that wave.
SPEAKER_0:  when it comes back to bite and then tire.
SPEAKER_0:  Scientific discipline. Science sure.
SPEAKER_0:  for now the past 60 years.
SPEAKER_0:  We were not able to raise money from the government, no grants.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a discipline that has no postdoc, very little postdoc.
SPEAKER_0:  Just because.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a fear.
SPEAKER_0:  of that folklore.
SPEAKER_0:  on the political arena.
SPEAKER_0:  People don't want to be associated with that because they confuse the two.
SPEAKER_0:  So I stopped.
SPEAKER_0:  There.
SPEAKER_0:  And as the director of the Carl Sagan Center, I am just very happy to see now that there is a course correction.
SPEAKER_0:  in the government seeking
SPEAKER_0:  scientific.
SPEAKER_0:  investigators for these kinds of issues and hopefully that we're right.
SPEAKER_0:  The ship.
SPEAKER_0:  there.
SPEAKER_1:  I love it, I'd love to see it, but.
SPEAKER_1:  I want, and I love our little disagreements. I'm doing so obviously respectfully and with love and it's, it makes it for a fun conversation. But I think.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, just like with surfing a wave there, there, there's some level of.
SPEAKER_1:  the more you resist it.
SPEAKER_1:  the worse it is.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I- We didn't resist it.
SPEAKER_0:  It didn't come from us and we pay the price.
SPEAKER_0:  I just think.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  The role of us.
SPEAKER_1:  scientists.
SPEAKER_1:  in part.
SPEAKER_1:  in the 21st century when we talk about social media.
SPEAKER_1:  is to direct this sense of wonder that people have.
SPEAKER_1:  into a direction of the rigors of science.
SPEAKER_0:  I think we do that pretty well.
SPEAKER_1:  I would disagree.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't think so. Society does much better, but there's other places in science.
SPEAKER_0:  The search for life is a fairly easy place to draw the wonder of people. Yes. Because it's a profound question that pretty much everybody has.
SPEAKER_1:  But I think I just want to highlight the fact that.
SPEAKER_1:  I think a lot of scientists, my colleagues, friends.
SPEAKER_1:  think that all you need to do is science.
SPEAKER_1:  All you need to do is the scientific process, the peer review process, the data and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  But I think communication is actually a fundamental part.
SPEAKER_1:  of the process.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, cause it has to do with funding, but also has to do with like work.
SPEAKER_1:  We're a bunch of humans.
SPEAKER_1:  trying to ask big questions, trying to figure this whole puzzle out.
SPEAKER_0:  I totally agree. We do have more.
SPEAKER_0:  public presentation at the Institute than peer-reviewed articles. And believe me, we have lots.
SPEAKER_0:  of peer-reviewed articles. So our scientists are out there and they are sharing the wonder of discoveries.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's so easy these days. I mean, there is not one day. I'm telling you about writing a book right now about the search for life in the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's almost every single day I had to correct something.
SPEAKER_0:  in the chapters I was writing.
SPEAKER_1:  So said he.
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of both signatures and signals is a pretty active.
SPEAKER_1:  feel.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's getting better right now. It's getting better.
SPEAKER_0:  But remember that the SETI Institute is not only about the search for extraterrestrial intelligence. It's about the historical root of the Institute.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's about 10% of what we do. In fact, we are searching for life in the universe from the origins of life to extraterrestrial intelligence.
SPEAKER_0:  So 90% of everything else is exoplanet. For instance, we have a-
SPEAKER_0:  good chunk of the caper theme that
SPEAKER_0:  is actually with the study institute and they are working with tests right now. Some already have some time on the jam's web.
SPEAKER_0:  We have astrobiologists, we have astronomers.
SPEAKER_1:  and those are looking.
SPEAKER_1:  for data, for signals.
SPEAKER_1:  for Planets Out.
SPEAKER_0:  Go to analog places to try and understand the type of life that survive in...
SPEAKER_0:  planetary type environments.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, people are always surprised when I tell them, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Whatever flies.
SPEAKER_0:  in the source system.
SPEAKER_0:  As long as we'll be flying.
SPEAKER_0:  We're involved.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is not something that pops in everybody's mind when they are thinking about the Sutt Institute because we started off.
SPEAKER_0:  as the search for extraterrestrial intelligence.
SPEAKER_0:  But the Institute has really bloomed into the search for life along the Drake equation, all the terms of the Drake equation.
SPEAKER_1:  Just to clarify because by the way you're saying a bunch of terms sometimes it's good to return to the basics when you're saying
SPEAKER_1:  Whatever's flown.
SPEAKER_1:  SETI.
SPEAKER_1:  is a part.
SPEAKER_1:  of the things that have flown.
SPEAKER_1:  So we, because we're using we elucid sometimes, we say we humans and sometimes we saidy. So the saidy is really broadly involved. A lot of.
SPEAKER_1:  the fingertips reaching out.
SPEAKER_0:  towards the stars.
SPEAKER_0:  Eh.
SPEAKER_0:  Cassini, New Horizon.
SPEAKER_0:  also missions that will be coming.
SPEAKER_0:  It's.
SPEAKER_0:  The search for life, we do this all across the Drake equation. So, a city is part of it.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's a root and it's
SPEAKER_0:  expanding a little bit right now. We hope it will continue to expand. So this is a good time for the Institute.
SPEAKER_0:  And you also...
SPEAKER_0:  In my mind, it was the very first astrobiology institute because we have this multidisciplinary approach.
SPEAKER_0:  where I can bring
SPEAKER_0:  many of the scientists from different
SPEAKER_0:  domains and disciplines to think about a question and as you know
SPEAKER_0:  Discoveries happen at the Nexus.
SPEAKER_0:  of disciplines and it's really a privilege when you are in an institute like that.
SPEAKER_1:  You've dived.
SPEAKER_1:  in volcanic lakes at high altitudes to study the creatures within. Can you tell me the technical?
SPEAKER_1:  the fun, the human story of that effort.
SPEAKER_0:  The image that is associated with the scientist is the person with the white coat in the lab.
SPEAKER_0:  In fact,
SPEAKER_0:  A number of us at the Institute are athletes doing extreme sports.
SPEAKER_0:  what would be considered extreme stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  and not
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's fun.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a little dangerous too, but it's to get data and more knowledge.
SPEAKER_0:  So there are so many stories. I don't even know.
SPEAKER_1:  When was the first time you did a dangerous thing with a volcano?
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, so the first...
SPEAKER_0:  one associated.
SPEAKER_0:  to the search for life.
SPEAKER_0:  understanding was in
SPEAKER_0:  2002, where I started climbing those high volcanoes in the Andes that are 20,000 footers.
SPEAKER_0:  The view out there is just beautiful.
SPEAKER_1:  You got...
SPEAKER_1:  You're so hilarious at spending almost no time on some epic things. I love this. You're so hilarious at spending almost no time on some epic things.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, how tall are these volcanoes? What are you doing with a volcano? What's required to prepare for that? What does a mission like that look like? I mean, that is true.
SPEAKER_1:  that this is.
SPEAKER_1:  science embodied, it's like athletics and science and you're studying the extreme conditions of life on earth, extreme beauty.
SPEAKER_1:  of life on earth in those conditions. So what, what, what was, what was, what are we talking about with this volcano?
SPEAKER_0:  So remember when we were talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  How do I understand how I should throw life on Mars? This is how it started for me. And then I looked at the environment, in my head started going through the environment on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  that would be good analysis.
SPEAKER_0:  and then you only have a few. And the end is in that case are
SPEAKER_0:  some of the best in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  just because of the aridity of the place.
SPEAKER_0:  in.
SPEAKER_0:  the higher you go.
SPEAKER_0:  The least atmosphere you have, the more UV radiation you have.
SPEAKER_0:  And the Andes are volcanic, hydrothermal, plus you have the climate change that's coming, you have evaporation.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a picture of Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  3.5 billion years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  Now you are.
SPEAKER_0:  actually entering a time machine.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  Remember, I'm a diver.
SPEAKER_0:  And the first time I got in 2002 to the places we wanted to explore.
SPEAKER_0:  All sudden I was standing.
SPEAKER_0:  at 14,000 feet, looking at 20,000 feet.
SPEAKER_0:  and saying.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I need to get up there.
SPEAKER_0:  Are you scared? No!
SPEAKER_0:  No, because we are prepared.
SPEAKER_0:  And the only thing I didn't know is if I was going to be able to make it to the top, because now you're dealing with high altitude, you can deal with high altitude sickness, you can deal with a number of things, and for God's sake, these are volcanoes and they are dormant, they are not extinct.
SPEAKER_0:  That can buy.
SPEAKER_0:  to buy toast a couple of times.
SPEAKER_1:  your preparation.
SPEAKER_1:  for that kind of, I mean this.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a lot of hiking and trekking at altitude around here, but not so high because we don't have anything closer to those elevations around here in the US.
SPEAKER_0:  But in volcanic environment, climbing volcanoes here, we have plenty of those.
SPEAKER_0:  Diving as well. I am a free diver. So this is where it's going to be hilarious.
SPEAKER_0:  because...
SPEAKER_0:  I started with a completely rational fear of pressurized vessels.
SPEAKER_0:  comes from an incident in my childhood.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I became a free diver to avoid having to carry oxygen.
SPEAKER_0:  tags on my back.
SPEAKER_1:  freediving is diving with
SPEAKER_0:  without anything, just your lungs, right?
SPEAKER_1:  That was that started from childhood.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, no, it was to the point where when I saw it, I was like, oh, I'm going to do it.
SPEAKER_0:  I saw a pressure vessel like him.
SPEAKER_0:  metten tanks or anything, I would be...
SPEAKER_0:  going around and
SPEAKER_0:  puts a lot of distance between me and that tank. So I was not going to carry any oxygen tank.
SPEAKER_0:  And the first time I actually...
SPEAKER_0:  Dive at the summit of that lake was free diving.
SPEAKER_0:  People look at me like I'm nuts. Well, maybe I am a little bit.
SPEAKER_1:  people that work with you as well. I mean, that kind of seems kind of nuts.
SPEAKER_0:  No, uh, we knew with- It's a risk.
SPEAKER_0:  Actually, it's a lot of.
SPEAKER_0:  less of a risk.
SPEAKER_0:  than getting with conventional air. And I can explain that.
SPEAKER_0:  But ultimately what decided me to certify Scuba.
SPEAKER_0:  and go over.
SPEAKER_0:  my fear.
SPEAKER_0:  was that as a scientist I needed more time at the bottom.
SPEAKER_0:  of the lake to sample.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, rationally.
SPEAKER_0:  Take my time to think.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I can stay.
SPEAKER_0:  quite long enough.
SPEAKER_0:  as a freediver underwater.
SPEAKER_0:  But the last thing you want to do at 20,000 feet is to come up at the surface with empty lungs.
SPEAKER_0:  because there is not much you can breathe out there to replenish your oxygen.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Definitely your time and the water is cut short.
SPEAKER_0:  just for safety and I realized that it was not a good trade off for me at some point. So I certified Scuba and after...
SPEAKER_0:  three years of exploring that lake freediving.
SPEAKER_0:  we finally came up with a full scuba diving expedition.
SPEAKER_0:  but we were diving with rebreather, which means that we dived with...
SPEAKER_0:  pure oxygen.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Rebrievers, give you a bag.
SPEAKER_0:  with.
SPEAKER_0:  Stuff that looks like...
SPEAKER_0:  cat liters in it, which is basically to absorb the CO2.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, that you are expelling when you're breathing.
SPEAKER_0:  and they're resaking oxygen this way.
SPEAKER_0:  So basically you are re-breathing.
SPEAKER_0:  your own.
SPEAKER_0:  respiration.
SPEAKER_1:  How long can you do that? So what's interesting about that technology?
SPEAKER_0:  So it is very interesting because then that...
SPEAKER_0:  completely avoids.
SPEAKER_0:  The potential.
SPEAKER_0:  issues you may have with
SPEAKER_0:  the binds.
SPEAKER_0:  when you are diving, the risk of bubbles.
SPEAKER_0:  trapped in your lungs.
SPEAKER_0:  because of different pressures and different gases.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's a complexity to the flow of oxygen.
SPEAKER_0:  underwater. When you are breathing regular air, when you are scuba diving here.
SPEAKER_0:  You know that you have to do some different, when you're coming back, when you're diving deep.
SPEAKER_0:  and you have conventional air, then you need to stop.
SPEAKER_0:  so that you can equalize.
SPEAKER_0:  the gases in your lungs. If you come back
SPEAKER_0:  too fast.
SPEAKER_0:  then you can have air bubbles.
SPEAKER_0:  Stuck.
SPEAKER_0:  And then you can risk the vines, which you can risk to be paralyzed. You can risk a number of nasty issues.
SPEAKER_0:  And we wanted absolutely to avoid that. So
SPEAKER_0:  diving with pure oxygen.
SPEAKER_0:  Avoid this completely.
SPEAKER_0:  and it has another.
SPEAKER_0:  benefit.
SPEAKER_0:  at high altitude is that
SPEAKER_0:  Well.
SPEAKER_0:  The greater risk when you're at high altitude.
SPEAKER_0:  is altitude sickness. What is altitude sickness is just you not having enough oxygen in your blood.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  This was a good benefit, it was a good trade-off.
SPEAKER_0:  We were lucky enough to be also trained by the military.
SPEAKER_0:  So we came up with.
SPEAKER_0:  not the civilian rebreather, which is the big thing on the back.
SPEAKER_0:  that you carry on your back, we actually...
SPEAKER_0:  we're given.
SPEAKER_0:  Navy SEALs, commando, rebreather.
SPEAKER_1:  Navy SEALs.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the director of military operations. Yes, we were trained like astronauts.
SPEAKER_0:  three months.
SPEAKER_0:  I spent more time, I had a joke that if somebody wanted to reach me, they better put a phone line at the bottom of the swimming pool because this is where I was.
SPEAKER_0:  So we train and we train and our manual about the safety.
SPEAKER_0:  was about that thick.
SPEAKER_0:  So it was a real operation.
SPEAKER_0:  That was three years into it because when you are freediving in the years prior.
SPEAKER_0:  There is no risk. You don't have any other gas in your lung than what you are breathing. The only risk is come short.
SPEAKER_0:  of air and then you're in trouble, which happened to me one time, seriously.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  that time I gotta ask you about freediving before we return to the rebreat
SPEAKER_0:  Well, all these legs, I had altitude, they are cold. They are at the minimum temperature that you can have on bodies of water, clear bodies of water, which is for degree C.
SPEAKER_0:  it's very very cold.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you can now. Nice bath.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so you cannot...
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  just dive with a wetsuit.
SPEAKER_0:  So the idea was to take a dry suit.
SPEAKER_0:  and I learned.
SPEAKER_0:  how to freedive with it.
SPEAKER_0:  dry suit, which is really the worst thing you can do.
SPEAKER_1:  to what it was.
SPEAKER_0:  a dry suit. So a dry suit, a wet suit is usually what you use in the ocean when it's not too cold. You can use also a dry suit, but the wet suit basically is going to keep you warm.
SPEAKER_0:  because water is getting into the suit.
SPEAKER_0:  and at the contact of your skin.
SPEAKER_0:  is getting to body temperature.
SPEAKER_0:  And so for a while you can...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, dive like that.
SPEAKER_0:  and in the ocean here.
SPEAKER_0:  That's fine.
SPEAKER_0:  The drysuit is the opposite. It's completely closed, which means that
SPEAKER_0:  You don't have any contact with the water outside.
SPEAKER_0:  and you keep your warmth.
SPEAKER_0:  through.
SPEAKER_0:  your body temperature and even clothing that you can put into it. So these dry suits, they are used by dither, go really deep.
SPEAKER_0:  in very cold water and need to stay a long time underwater. So what's the bad part?
SPEAKER_0:  The bad part is that
SPEAKER_0:  when you have those dry suit
SPEAKER_0:  You.
SPEAKER_0:  have a lot of air that can be trapped.
SPEAKER_0:  in it.
SPEAKER_0:  Usually we do what we call burping the suit. It's not a very pleasant expression, but...
SPEAKER_0:  You get in the water and as soon as you get in the water, you can see the air pockets all over the place. Right? So you burp the suit, you open the valve and the air comes out.
SPEAKER_0:  Once you have done that, then you look with your lead belt.
SPEAKER_0:  and you know when you're ready to go down.
SPEAKER_0:  And so what happened that day?
SPEAKER_0:  is that I actually did burp the suit.
SPEAKER_0:  but didn't realize I burped it.
SPEAKER_0:  completely.
SPEAKER_0:  And so...
SPEAKER_0:  I went.
SPEAKER_0:  down.
SPEAKER_0:  And immediately I felt an air pocket going to my legs.
SPEAKER_0:  So basically, air was trapped in the suit and went.
SPEAKER_0:  on my legs.
SPEAKER_0:  as I was diving like that.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I didn't pay too much attention to that. Because you're diving down.
SPEAKER_0:  I was diving down.
SPEAKER_0:  and so didn't pay too much attention.
SPEAKER_0:  But that, as I was busy, just an awkward position.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Then I wanted to...
SPEAKER_0:  turn in the go up.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, no can do.
SPEAKER_0:  I was just like a buoy.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was like that.
SPEAKER_0:  The first time I say, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  I tried a second time and a third time. By the fourth time, I kind of realized I was in trouble.
SPEAKER_0:  And the fifth time I say, OK, now you better give it your best try, otherwise it's going to be big trouble.
SPEAKER_0:  Um,
SPEAKER_1:  This is free diving. I was free diving. And then you can't.
SPEAKER_1:  And I cannot turn around. What were you feeling? Yummy is there a pan-
SPEAKER_0:  No
SPEAKER_0:  There is no panic because you can't, you cannot afford.
SPEAKER_0:  be panicking. In fact, you are always thinking because there is training and this is the best part about training.
SPEAKER_0:  Your training allows you that space.
SPEAKER_0:  to keep you cool.
SPEAKER_0:  and compose which you need to be in that kind of situation.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  Finally, after the fifth time.
SPEAKER_0:  I was able to rectify the position and get myself up.
SPEAKER_0:  But when I get up...
SPEAKER_0:  My lungs were empty. I had been in the water for quite some time.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I have co-
SPEAKER_0:  I knew what was going to happen, so I decided to just be the plank, not move and don't do anything, just open my mouth and try to suck oxygen.
SPEAKER_0:  But obviously oxygen.
SPEAKER_0:  at 6,000 meters, 20,000 feet.
SPEAKER_0:  There is not that much.
SPEAKER_0:  It's about a little, it's a...
SPEAKER_0:  48% of what you breathe at sea level.
SPEAKER_0:  So, although it was...
SPEAKER_0:  Noon.
SPEAKER_0:  at that time.
SPEAKER_0:  The sky is that pretty dark and starry.
SPEAKER_0:  Such stars everywhere. Oh my god, yes.
SPEAKER_0: ttationalty
SPEAKER_0:  The funny thing was...
SPEAKER_1:  And that's the first time you experienced that kind of uh
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, can you possibly train for that? Like-
SPEAKER_1:  Can you also pass out?
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, you could. I mean, the fact that I was already seeing dark was a real sign that my brain was starved of oxygen.
SPEAKER_0:  And I had one of my friends or colleagues on the shore.
SPEAKER_0:  just telling me because I'd been under for a real while and say...
SPEAKER_0:  Is everything okay? I remember trying to say something.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was just like...
SPEAKER_0:  That's I think the best lie I ever ever.
SPEAKER_1:  You're lying to the friend and maybe to yourself
SPEAKER_0:  No, because I knew I was going to be okay, but it took me to be still for a few minutes.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, can you talk about free diving? I mean, what's the technical skill involved here? It just seems...
SPEAKER_1:  It seems exceptionally difficult. Like for most people that swim, you go under water.
SPEAKER_1:  It's hard. So what's the skill there?
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I think...
SPEAKER_0:  You probably can get good or better at freediving.
SPEAKER_0:  by training. So you have different techniques. You can train in swimming pool and you can say, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Frankly, for me, I go at the bottom of the swimming pool and I sit.
SPEAKER_0:  there.
SPEAKER_0:  and then you have relaxation.
SPEAKER_0:  techniques.
SPEAKER_0:  Some people meditate, I can't. I am not a good person that can meditate, or if I do, I don't know about it.
SPEAKER_0:  But, um...
SPEAKER_0:  My way of doing things and taking my mind off the situation I'm in.
SPEAKER_0:  is by singing my head.
SPEAKER_0:  I love music or hearing music. And in fact, knowing the kind of song I'm singing, I know about the length of time.
SPEAKER_0:  that I'm staying on the water as well. So this is my own way. People have different ways. What kind of music are we talking about?
SPEAKER_0:  All sorts of music can be classical, can be pop music, you know, just songs.
SPEAKER_0:  when you really know.
SPEAKER_0:  that you are a
SPEAKER_0:  Relax.
SPEAKER_0:  and something I experienced actually at
SPEAKER_0:  20,000 feet, which was the
SPEAKER_0:  greatest experience of my life in those terms.
SPEAKER_0:  is when you forget.
SPEAKER_0:  that you have water around you.
SPEAKER_0:  At that point...
SPEAKER_0:  You cannot tell whether you are the water or whether it is you. There is actually no separation anymore.
SPEAKER_0:  And I felt that.
SPEAKER_0:  when I was training.
SPEAKER_0:  In a swimming pool, I never...
SPEAKER_0:  could have imagined that I would.
SPEAKER_0:  feel.
SPEAKER_0:  that way once on top of that volcano, and it happened.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was absolutely amazing. It was.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, we were talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  How life consciousness.
SPEAKER_0:  permits the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  at that point in time, on that volcano, that day.
SPEAKER_0:  It took me by surprise. I was not expecting it.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything around me, the lake was...
SPEAKER_0:  Arctic blue?
SPEAKER_0:  with all the ray of the suns you can...
SPEAKER_0:  You could tell them apart, every single one of them. I was surrounded by golden darts.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was the most incredible experience and I don't know if it's that kind.
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  environment that led me to just...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, going to...
SPEAKER_0:  whatever state of meditation or whatnot.
SPEAKER_0:  But all of a sudden...
SPEAKER_0:  There was no separation anymore between me, the water, the volcano.
SPEAKER_0:  And if I came with questions...
SPEAKER_0:  They didn't matter anymore because for that fraction of a second, it seemed that I had all the answers of the—
SPEAKER_0:  in the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  the connectedness with everything.
SPEAKER_0:  You can call it that way. I still don't know what it means, you know, literally.
SPEAKER_0:  But it is.
SPEAKER_0:  that moment where you feel that
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't matter.
SPEAKER_0:  It really doesn't matter anymore.
SPEAKER_0:  It was a-
SPEAKER_0:  Absolutely, absolute peace, absolute understanding.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was incredible. It was an absolute awareness.
SPEAKER_0:  Could you describe it as beautiful?
SPEAKER_0:  That wouldn't go beyond that. I think that there is clearly in my mind...
SPEAKER_0:  Mine today.
SPEAKER_0:  No words that can express how perfect.
SPEAKER_0:  This was.
SPEAKER_1:  Does that start to speak to why you love diving?
SPEAKER_1:  Or is there something special about that place?
SPEAKER_1:  diving at such elevations.
SPEAKER_0:  volcanoes. You know, I started diving pretty much, this is the first thing I did when I was near water. In fact, there is a very fun little...
SPEAKER_0:  incident with my parents, me being a
SPEAKER_0:  on the shore of the lake on vacation I was.
SPEAKER_0:  three years old, maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  and I had these little lifesavers.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, on my arms and my parents were not
SPEAKER_0:  watching and in my little brain I still can remember today.
SPEAKER_0:  saying.
SPEAKER_0:  Well...
SPEAKER_0:  Nothing bad can happen to me. I cannot drown if I go underwater.
SPEAKER_0:  See, that's the logic of a three year old. Yes. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  It kind of works. I mean, that's.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, well, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  So I removed.
SPEAKER_0:  the lifesavers that I had.
SPEAKER_0:  And I just went in the water. And my mom said before, she could do anything.
SPEAKER_0:  I was under.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was like a natural thing. And for me, I felt immediately at home.
SPEAKER_0:  and you know, as little as I was.
SPEAKER_0:  completely and it goes beyond that.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, this sense of connectiveness or oneness or whatever.
SPEAKER_0:  I always felt.
SPEAKER_0:  good underwater. So it doesn't matter really if it's 20,000 feet. The thing that matters at that point is that you need to get there.
SPEAKER_0:  So you need to get with all the gears with your...
SPEAKER_0:  hiking trekking equipment.
SPEAKER_0:  high mountaineering gears.
SPEAKER_0:  And when you get on top of that, you have to remove all that and...
SPEAKER_0:  Don't shoot.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there something you can speak to the challenging aspects of that process? Or is it just like this rigorous process that's well designed that you have to go through and you don't think...
SPEAKER_0:  We are humans.
SPEAKER_0:  This is where most of the risk.
SPEAKER_0:  is.
SPEAKER_0:  because.
SPEAKER_0:  You can be well prepared.
SPEAKER_0:  but for one reason or another.
SPEAKER_0:  you get sick, you know, and you can get sick not only because of high altitude sickness, it can be a number of things.
SPEAKER_0:  or you can be tired or you can...
SPEAKER_0:  catch a cold.
SPEAKER_0:  And then of course you have the mountain itself.
SPEAKER_0:  We had a magnitude 7.8 earthquake.
SPEAKER_0:  hitting one day when we are 50 meters away from the summit. So you can't obviously plan for that. No you can't and that's the acts of gods you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Working with NASA, although I am the director of the SETI Institute, my grants are coming from NASA, so I'm a NASA contractor. Every time we go to those environments, we have to go through the rigorous process of training with NASA and checking all the boxes for safety. So they are training and training and training us, and I have to thank them.
SPEAKER_0:  because a lot of those...
SPEAKER_0:  Trainings are the things that are in your brain when these kinds of things happen.
SPEAKER_0:  You know how to react, and you are not freaking out.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  in all of the things they are training us for.
SPEAKER_0:  you have the green risk, the yellow risk, and the red risk.
SPEAKER_0:  So the green risks are basically the don't be stupid and don't do the kind of thing you wouldn't be doing at home like it.
SPEAKER_0:  jumping, you know, on rocks that are not stable. you can.
SPEAKER_0:  tweak your ankle, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  And then you have other risks like high altitude sickness, how you prepare for that, how you recognize that.
SPEAKER_0:  These are the yellow risks and then the red risks.
SPEAKER_0:  The red bricks are what they call the acts of gods, the kind of thing that
SPEAKER_0:  They can happen.
SPEAKER_0:  You know there is nothing you can do about it and you accept that when you do that.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Those are...
SPEAKER_0:  volcanic eruptions when you're in this kind of environment.
SPEAKER_0:  Earthquakes?
SPEAKER_0:  and everything that an avalanche is for.
SPEAKER_1:  So you're in this giant mountain.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's shaking.
SPEAKER_0:  No, it's not shaking. That's the interesting f-
SPEAKER_0:  part of it.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  There was a whole background of things that happened that day when we started off.
SPEAKER_0:  We got
SPEAKER_0:  to 50 meters from the summit. And I have part of my logistics team that is at the foot of the mountain.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  being so close to the summit we have to go under an overhang of lava.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's just like we are just under this big vault of lava.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's actually beautiful.
SPEAKER_0:  If you want something beautiful, it's the Altiplano seen from 20,000 feet.
SPEAKER_0:  just absolutely stunning. What's the colors? What are we looking at? The colors are that of...
SPEAKER_0:  early Earth, which means primordial Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  It's...
SPEAKER_0:  Aukers, yellows, oranges, browns.
SPEAKER_0:  with a dark
SPEAKER_0:  Blue.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you're just, you know, it's a time machine.
SPEAKER_0:  You're just out there and you're climbing 42 degree slopes.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  All of a sudden, I'm right next behind the guide, and the guide has been with us, it's family, we've been together for 10 years.
SPEAKER_0:  and he's starting to do that.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't discuss. When my career do that, I listen.
SPEAKER_0:  I asked the team to do the same thing where maybe half a dozen.
SPEAKER_0:  And then I went to talk to him and say, what's going on? He's on the radio.
SPEAKER_0:  And then he gives me the radio, I'm talking to my logistic chief officer who was at the bottom and he say we're having a...
SPEAKER_0:  tremendous earthquake.
SPEAKER_0:  It was saying that the...
SPEAKER_0:  Actually, the ground was waving. It was so bad.
SPEAKER_0:  and it was freaking out.
SPEAKER_0:  because he said, everything is avalanching and I'm very puzzled because we are in a very dangerous part of the volcano, nothing's happening.
SPEAKER_0:  I turn around.
SPEAKER_0:  And then this is when I realized there is dust absolutely everywhere.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything that I saw two minutes before it's
SPEAKER_0:  gone, just disappear into a wall of dust.
SPEAKER_0:  But nothing's happening where we are.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Our friends were freaking out because they were seeing everything avalanche, especially the other side of the mountain we were on.
SPEAKER_0:  was avalanche. So they have no visuals? They have no visual. They thought that we are caught in the avalanche.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  I said no, but...
SPEAKER_0:  Some, uh, uh, so at that point, They thought you were screwed. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  And I said, okay, so if this is.
SPEAKER_0:  What's happening?
SPEAKER_0:  then I'm taking everybody.
SPEAKER_0:  to the summit.
SPEAKER_0:  because we have a very large crater that will take care of avalanches, will be safe.
SPEAKER_0:  and I'm waiting for the aftershock because this is what you do.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, when you have earthquakes.
SPEAKER_0:  So here we go.
SPEAKER_0:  taking everybody in the crater, and now you have half a dozen scientists.
SPEAKER_0:  in
SPEAKER_0:  The crater with the crater lake.
SPEAKER_0:  Eh.
SPEAKER_0:  and this is why we came for.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  We just had a 7.8 earthquake and what do you think they do?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, of course they do the science they came to.
SPEAKER_0:  to do.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  The only thing is that I couldn't because my radio...
SPEAKER_0:  was only working when I was on the rim of the crater.
SPEAKER_0:  But I had a little assistant with me, a young...
SPEAKER_0:  a Bolivian teenager had been shadowing me for.
SPEAKER_0:  three weeks so he knew exactly what to do and he said now you don't
SPEAKER_0:  No problem, give me your bag, I'll do the sampling for you.
SPEAKER_0:  So I was monitoring.
SPEAKER_0:  the situation.
SPEAKER_0:  And, uh......
SPEAKER_0:  I wasn't at that point.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  There was another moment.
SPEAKER_0:  my friend downstairs, I could, you know- At the foot. At the foot, yeah. We've known each other. As I say, we're family. This team is family. We've known each other. I am the godmother's kid, so we are close.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I could feel for the first time.
SPEAKER_0:  in my life that.
SPEAKER_0:  He actually was scared.
SPEAKER_0:  And he was calling me every 30 seconds, telling me stuff. I say, you have to stop this now.
SPEAKER_0:  Just...
SPEAKER_0:  me to give me information that is useful for me to make decisions.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I say, okay, what's going on?
SPEAKER_0:  It tells me.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, there is still avalanche, etc.
SPEAKER_0:  And then a few minutes later, he calls me and says, I think that last car is erupting. So now I have to tell you, we are on a volcano.
SPEAKER_0:  The next volcano, we share a slope with it, is a little lower, but that's the most temperamental.
SPEAKER_0:  volcano.
SPEAKER_0:  of the entire chain.
SPEAKER_0:  And this one as an.
SPEAKER_0:  History of Eruption.
SPEAKER_0:  And then my friend is telling me that the volcano seems to be.
SPEAKER_0:  starting to erupt.
SPEAKER_0:  If that volcano goes up, we have nowhere to go.
SPEAKER_0:  That got my attention.
SPEAKER_0:  So if you say scared, I would say that.
SPEAKER_0:  I got the realization that
SPEAKER_0:  That meant I went cold for like a fraction of a second.
SPEAKER_0:  But that meant that just my adrenaline started to kick in.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was a very, very strange experience because now you have tunnel vision, it's about survival.
SPEAKER_0:  And I say, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Now you are going to tell me what I need to know, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  Tell me.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you see?
SPEAKER_0:  I see smoke.
SPEAKER_0:  What kind of smoke? University of Oklahoma 854- myself
SPEAKER_0:  It's white, I say.
SPEAKER_0:  No big deal, that's water vapor.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Where it's going?
SPEAKER_0:  is going to Argentina. That was the opposite direction of where we are. I said, okay, I'm staying where I am.
SPEAKER_0:  because right now there is no, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  No danger.
SPEAKER_0:  and there is still the issue of the aftershock.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't want to have the team.
SPEAKER_0:  caught in the central gully of the volcano with a nevalanche coming at us.
SPEAKER_0:  So is that there.
SPEAKER_0:  And he called me after that and said, well, you know, it's still going to Argentina. Fine. Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And then a little later, he calls me and says,
SPEAKER_0:  Natalie, things are changing here. Say, okay, what's going on? Say, well...
SPEAKER_0:  The cloud is a little yellow.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was thinking...
SPEAKER_0:  myself.
SPEAKER_1:  What does it mean when it's yellow?
SPEAKER_0:  All for it.
SPEAKER_0:  And then when you have software...
SPEAKER_0:  Mixed.
SPEAKER_0:  with
SPEAKER_0:  the water vapor or the water in your lungs, this turns into sulfuric acid.
SPEAKER_0:  Then you're really screwed.
SPEAKER_0:  NSA, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you for the information. Where is the club going?
SPEAKER_0:  The wing is shifting, it's coming your direction.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that was a day like that, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  I am talking to him on the radio and I'm turning around and as I turn around I see the clouds starting to pop.
SPEAKER_0:  on the opposite side of the rim.
SPEAKER_0:  So at that time, we had no choice anymore, because now you have to figure out what's going to kill you first.
SPEAKER_0:  And so there was the risk.
SPEAKER_0:  or the potential.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Netherlands.
SPEAKER_0:  But at least you can see the rocks.
SPEAKER_0:  The gas is going to kill you before you can see it.
SPEAKER_0:  So I called everybody back.
SPEAKER_0:  We gather our stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't give too much detail, but I say it's time to go.
SPEAKER_0:  downhill.
SPEAKER_0:  and fast.
SPEAKER_0:  So, which we did.
SPEAKER_0:  We stopped only when we were at mid camp.
SPEAKER_0:  And then
SPEAKER_0:  At that point, we saw the cloud.
SPEAKER_0:  is completely covering the summit where we were.
SPEAKER_0:  So we did well to bail out.
SPEAKER_0:  But that was 500 meters.
SPEAKER_0:  500 meters higher than we were, so we are safe. I was just making sure that it would not go down the slope.
SPEAKER_0:  where we were, we were safe, so we stayed.
SPEAKER_0:  and just rested for a little while.
SPEAKER_0:  And after that, we descended.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was all on adrenaline, I can tell you what, I had two of my crew with headaches. One of them was because of the altitude, we climbed really fast.
SPEAKER_0:  The other one was because of the cloud. She was the closest to the cloud when it happened.
SPEAKER_0:  So we descended fast. Wow, that was close.
SPEAKER_0:  That was close and it's interesting how the human...
SPEAKER_0:  body and mind works because I know that from the moment my friend told me that.
SPEAKER_0:  The volcano seemed to be erupting.
SPEAKER_0:  I was
SPEAKER_0:  going on adrenaline.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  when we got...
SPEAKER_0:  close to them and I saw him, we were getting close to the cars, I saw him coming towards me.
SPEAKER_0:  and the slope also and all the adrenaline.
SPEAKER_0:  When away.
SPEAKER_0:  I was a mess.
SPEAKER_0:  I had to find the first rock and sit down.
SPEAKER_0:  It was gone.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean. Fascinating.
SPEAKER_1:  So you just basically physically and mentally collapsed one.
SPEAKER_0:  Absolutely! There was nothing left!
SPEAKER_0:  of me.
SPEAKER_0:  I got in the car.
SPEAKER_0:  And I felt in the cars we were heading back towards camp, I could have passed out.
SPEAKER_0:  I really fought back and I'm not the kind of passing out really easy.
SPEAKER_0:  but-
SPEAKER_0:  There was nothing like-
SPEAKER_0:  I had no energy, no nothing.
SPEAKER_0:  It's.
SPEAKER_0:  Fabulous how you react.
SPEAKER_0:  and how this is embedded in your own.
SPEAKER_0:  brain.
SPEAKER_0:  from.
SPEAKER_0:  And...
SPEAKER_0:  of evolution, of reaction to.
SPEAKER_0:  dangerous situation.
SPEAKER_0:  basically.
SPEAKER_0:  that drive to survive.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, something like that.
SPEAKER_1:  You just told us one heck of a story. And as you said, such story comes along with many.
SPEAKER_1:  of the diving expeditions that you do.
SPEAKER_1:  on the science side.
SPEAKER_1:  What is that world that simulates, that travels back in time into the Martian landscape?
SPEAKER_1:  What does the science reveal?
SPEAKER_0:  So the science reveals that...
SPEAKER_0:  I feel resilient.
SPEAKER_0:  When I started that...
SPEAKER_0:  I told my husband I say this is going to be very fast. We are going in such nasty environment
SPEAKER_0:  that we're not going to find anything.
SPEAKER_0:  and you know, world back home.
SPEAKER_0:  Ah.
SPEAKER_0:  See you soon.
SPEAKER_0:  So 20 years later, we are still studying those environments.
SPEAKER_1:  That was your gut feeling like nothing.
SPEAKER_1:  Not much can possibly survive.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, the UV environment is so nasty.
SPEAKER_0:  But there you find...
SPEAKER_0:  the same microorganism.
SPEAKER_0:  that made the very first fossils on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  3.5 billion years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  and they keep surviving, they developed an adaptation.
SPEAKER_0:  Swiss or Minna if you prefer.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you learn about that, you learn about...
SPEAKER_0:  what they are.
SPEAKER_0:  How they adapt.
SPEAKER_0:  through times and through environmental changes, which is really important.
SPEAKER_0:  What are their signatures? We learn to recognize them, we learn what kind of instrument we need, what kind of signature, whether it's chemical or morphological or whatnot.
SPEAKER_0:  So basically we learn how to explore.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  I would say that to me, and this is a realization interestingly enough that came three years into the project.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I really woke up literally one morning saying...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, we've been coming here for three years now.
SPEAKER_0:  Try and understand.
SPEAKER_0:  how to search for life on Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  But what this place is showing us is what's happening right here, right now on our own planet.
SPEAKER_0:  And by exploring those extreme environments, we are also reaching to places not too many people go.
SPEAKER_0:  And so we're learning more about our own biospheres.
SPEAKER_0:  and...
SPEAKER_0:  the diversity of our own life here on earth.
SPEAKER_0:  So these are the two main things that I would say.
SPEAKER_1:  What kind of life?
SPEAKER_1:  survives up there.
SPEAKER_0:  top of those volcanoes it's about bacteria mostly.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there something?
SPEAKER_1:  specific about that bacteria that's able to be so rugged.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, they have adapted to very high UV radiation, and it's not only because they are at high altitude, it's because early Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  didn't have an ozone layer.
SPEAKER_0:  So when those...
SPEAKER_0:  the ancestors of those bacteria.
SPEAKER_0:  originated.
SPEAKER_0:  They have to survive a world where you had lots of short UV coming down at the surface.
SPEAKER_0:  and also lots of hydrothermal environment, volcanoes and hot water, lots of salt.
SPEAKER_0:  And you see all this toolbox.
SPEAKER_0:  Steele.
SPEAKER_0:  embedded in those microorganisms today, four billion years later. It's just amazing.
SPEAKER_0:  And depending on the environment, they are going to switch.
SPEAKER_0:  some of these defenses adaptation on or off.
SPEAKER_0:  there.
SPEAKER_0:  UV
SPEAKER_0:  situation there is so nasty.
SPEAKER_0:  that
SPEAKER_0:  here.
SPEAKER_0:  You have bacterias like that, I know bacteria, you find them everywhere. It's really something you find all over the place.
SPEAKER_0:  If you found them here in California…
SPEAKER_0:  they will turn their protection.
SPEAKER_0:  against UV during the day in summer?
SPEAKER_0:  and they will switch it off.
SPEAKER_0:  at the end of the day.
SPEAKER_0:  There in the Andes, it's so nasty that that thing stays on all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you take samples and bring them back here...
SPEAKER_0:  and start to...
SPEAKER_0:  culture then.
SPEAKER_0:  like we did on top of a building, leaving them, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  you will see the second generation of this organism.
SPEAKER_0:  they are starting to switch on and off again.
SPEAKER_0:  So they're extremely adaptable.
SPEAKER_0:  extremely rugged.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's why they are still here.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably that's why we're here, because life finds ways.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there some degree to which...
SPEAKER_1:  The harshness of the conditions.
SPEAKER_1:  enables
SPEAKER_1:  the flourishing of life versus shut down.
SPEAKER_0:  down.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it will shut down.
SPEAKER_0:  those that cannot survive. Obviously, this is a statement that's kept an obvious right there, but it's also...
SPEAKER_0:  the survival of the fittest.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is what evolution is, all right?
SPEAKER_0:  Um, so.
SPEAKER_0:  They are here because they were the most adaptable.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  Evolution is going.
SPEAKER_0:  to show.
SPEAKER_0:  have.
SPEAKER_0:  of the fittest.
SPEAKER_0:  The one that cannot resist, they might have a good time for a little while but then...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, we've seen this at much…
SPEAKER_0:  different scale.
SPEAKER_0:  and with complex knife.
SPEAKER_0:  Not so long ago, a hundred thousand years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  Neanderthal.
SPEAKER_0:  was side by side by homo sapiens.
SPEAKER_0:  But Nandethor was completely adapted to a cold earth, to a glacial earth.
SPEAKER_0:  of the end of the play-stocene.
SPEAKER_0:  and when conditions change.
SPEAKER_0:  He couldn't lie.
SPEAKER_1:  You think, I mean, there's still some mysteries around that, right? Like exactly what were the harshness of the conditions.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  I still...
SPEAKER_1:  Really suspicious, what did Homo say?
SPEAKER_0:  No, no, no, no. I really want to know. No, no, I'm shady stuff that happened
SPEAKER_0:  shitty stuff happen, they met.
SPEAKER_0:  They bred together, they fought against each other.
SPEAKER_0:  What humans do. You had to expect that.
SPEAKER_0:  But the thing is that...
SPEAKER_0:  Nendirthal was completely adapted for a very long time.
SPEAKER_0:  to live at the edge of those glaciers.
SPEAKER_0:  They are where.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably.
SPEAKER_0:  in a weakened situation when homo sapiens came.
SPEAKER_0:  and started to spread.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically...
SPEAKER_0:  This is what life does. It adapts, and if you cannot adapt anymore, then you disappear and something else takes over.
SPEAKER_1:  You hold the Women's World Record for diving at altitudes.
SPEAKER_1:  both scuba and freediving.
SPEAKER_1:  So I have to ask what...
SPEAKER_1:  Can you describe the details of those records?
SPEAKER_0:  I never looked.
SPEAKER_0:  For those, I'm not after records at all. In fact, I didn't know I had broken those records when that happened.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  We did that as part of our expedition, as part of our scientific expedition.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's basically sport in the name of science versus.
SPEAKER_0:  No, it's science in the name of science and it's just a very physical thing that you have to do. So we train ourselves like athletes.
SPEAKER_0:  But to get the job done. To get the job done.
SPEAKER_1:  you're holding your breath underwater for a very long time, like with free diving, what are we talking about? do you think in terms of time?
SPEAKER_1:  Is there like...
SPEAKER_1:  layers where you know.
SPEAKER_1:  through training, you're in a good place. I'm sure you take time off and get rusty.
SPEAKER_0:  And I have not been diving in a while, so probably I need to go back to the drawing board at the bottom of the swimming pool.
SPEAKER_0:  Having training from the past, I think, you know, we will pick up much more faster than.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, I would never, at those altitudes, I would never go over three minutes.
SPEAKER_0:  that would be suicidal.
SPEAKER_1:  So the altitude is much tougher than the pool
SPEAKER_0:  back at ground level.
SPEAKER_0:  It is.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's not- When you come up and you have to get up. That's not the going in the water. When I'm underwater I'm fine.
SPEAKER_0:  And if I wanted, I could stay longer.
SPEAKER_0:  But he wouldn't be very wise.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  You've written about the history of life on Mars. Like you said, you've kind of exploring that by looking at the lakes.
SPEAKER_1:  here.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think there's been life?
SPEAKER_1:  On Mars, do you think there is life on Mars?
SPEAKER_0:  Right, so when you're looking at the environment of Mars early on...
SPEAKER_0:  is fairly similar.
SPEAKER_0:  to that of early Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  never was exactly the same because Mars was always farther from the Sun than the Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  So it was always a little cooler.
SPEAKER_0:  But you have to imagine.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe the Arctic during the summer?
SPEAKER_0:  That would be early March with a lot going on for it in terms of environment, very favorable to even life as we know it.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  How First Life
SPEAKER_0:  happen on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  they are signs right now showing that it might have actually originated only 200 million years after the cross cooldown.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh wow.
SPEAKER_0:  This still has to be verified, but that's the closest. And these are indirect evidence, like…
SPEAKER_0:  carbon left by the activity of life, not life itself.
SPEAKER_0:  And there is a twist in the story.
SPEAKER_0:  for Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  is that it seems that Mars came together as a planet faster.
SPEAKER_0:  than the Earth and had water.
SPEAKER_0:  earlier.
SPEAKER_0:  than the Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  So, it may be that Mars was habitable.
SPEAKER_0:  and my have seen.
SPEAKER_0:  The beginning of life.
SPEAKER_0:  earlier.
SPEAKER_0:  than the Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So all of this is speculation. Obviously, we haven't found any evidence.
SPEAKER_0:  or solid evidence yet.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say unambiguous evidence, but unambiguous.
SPEAKER_0:  evidence of life.
SPEAKER_0:  is going to be something interesting to prove because we don't know what life is, remember.
SPEAKER_0:  So I always joke that the only way we would know that there is life on Mars is if there was a rabbit jumping in front of the rover.
SPEAKER_0:  but we might be.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, gathering, we have what we call a ladder of life detection.
SPEAKER_0:  which is that you have a series of
SPEAKER_0:  ranks that you need to go through.
SPEAKER_0:  that actually
SPEAKER_0:  are not proving you that you've discovered life.
SPEAKER_0:  BUD-
SPEAKER_0:  are making.
SPEAKER_0:  the possibility that what you discovered
SPEAKER_0:  was made only by the environment more and more improbable.
SPEAKER_0:  So we are trying to prove the contrary, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So this is what we have right now.
SPEAKER_0:  And as far as I'm concerned.
SPEAKER_0:  Considering all the unknowns we have, I think there was as much chance.
SPEAKER_0:  that life.
SPEAKER_0:  originated on Mars, that it did on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  and...
SPEAKER_0:  if it was at the surface.
SPEAKER_0:  then it got in trouble.
SPEAKER_0:  after 500 million years because of the
SPEAKER_0:  disappearance of the magnetosphere, the loss of the magnetosphere and the atmosphere.
SPEAKER_0:  But as we know...
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  Life doesn't.
SPEAKER_0:  only.
SPEAKER_0:  Stay in one place.
SPEAKER_0:  As soon as it's out there, it's going to adapt, it's going to give itself more chance.
SPEAKER_0:  to survive.
SPEAKER_0:  And that to me means that...
SPEAKER_0:  If life appeared...
SPEAKER_0:  I would say.
SPEAKER_0:  It's still there, and probably on the ground where it...
SPEAKER_0:  can be in an environment that's more stable. I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  how stability is good or not. It might not be so good, but...
SPEAKER_0:  they might be in a different type of metabolism.
SPEAKER_0:  through dormancy, waiting for different climate cycles.
SPEAKER_0:  And there is the fact that Mars changes.
SPEAKER_0:  Ballots.
SPEAKER_0:  faster.
SPEAKER_0:  than the Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  and climate changes are a lot stronger in magnitude.
SPEAKER_0:  So there might be a place on Mars. We know that there is a place on Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  deeper in the subsurface where temperature and pressure are good for liquid water to stay there. So these would be good places for a stable habitat over time, no matter what happens at the surface.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  If
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, life is also.
SPEAKER_0:  hot.
SPEAKER_0:  between that dip.
SPEAKER_0:  zone.
SPEAKER_0:  and the surface.
SPEAKER_0:  there is an active layer, there is a lot of ice in the subsurface of Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  And when the climate changes...
SPEAKER_0:  when the obliquity goes beyond 30 degrees.
SPEAKER_0:  Then at that point.
SPEAKER_0:  You will have some.
SPEAKER_0:  activation of that zone.
SPEAKER_0:  You have thawing of the ice.
SPEAKER_0:  So all this region is reactivated and maybe that's a way.
SPEAKER_0:  where you have.
SPEAKER_0:  pathways for life to move from.
SPEAKER_0:  the deep zone.
SPEAKER_0:  closer to the surface.
SPEAKER_0:  This is why I'm one of those scientists who thinks that...
SPEAKER_0:  Life might not be so far from the surface than we think.
SPEAKER_1:  so we don't have to dig very far to find it.
SPEAKER_0:  We probably won't. And the reason I'm... That would be so amazing. I am thinking of that just because of this experience as well of extreme environments.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to sit and look.
SPEAKER_0:  and listen basically.
SPEAKER_0:  The story of my life. If I want to understand where microbes are located on Mars, I have to become the microbe, right?
SPEAKER_0:  This is the thought experiment. And if I want to understand where ET is, then I have to become ET. So it's a big stretch.
SPEAKER_0:  But in extreme environment.
SPEAKER_0:  You said.
SPEAKER_0:  in the desert for a while.
SPEAKER_0:  and you just...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, try to understand.
SPEAKER_0:  where the wind's coming from.
SPEAKER_0:  where the humidity, when it's showing up, and then you start to understand the patterns of those things.
SPEAKER_1:  What are the useful signals that you need for survival?
SPEAKER_0:  You need to know where water is, where the source of energy is going to be drawn from. You need to find shelters, and shelters don't mean that, for instance, you can have a water column.
SPEAKER_0:  of the lake or river or whatnot.
SPEAKER_0:  or the ocean. It can be also...
SPEAKER_0:  Very thin.
SPEAKER_0:  Layer of dust.
SPEAKER_0:  or it can be a translucent rock.
SPEAKER_0:  And you see what we call andeliths. These are the same cyanobacteria, but a different version of them.
SPEAKER_0:  They live inside the rocks, inside those crystals.
SPEAKER_0:  because they have the best of life.
SPEAKER_0:  They are-
SPEAKER_0:  into translucent.
SPEAKER_0:  crystals.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  that they receive the light from the sun.
SPEAKER_0:  They can do the photosynthesis.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  There is enough of that crystal so that the nasty UV is being stopped.
SPEAKER_0:  and they are in their little...
SPEAKER_0:  house.
SPEAKER_0:  a
SPEAKER_0:  when you are looking at temperature within those rocks.
SPEAKER_0:  They tend to make it toaster.
SPEAKER_0:  than the outside temperature. So there is a lot of things going on.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  What I'm saying for Mars is that, yeah, right now you don't have an atmosphere very much 160 times thinner than the Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  6 mB is really not much, but it's there.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  But you still have a lot of UV, the short UV, like the nasty one, UVA, UVB, UVC, that can really mess up your DNA.
SPEAKER_0:  and destroy it beyond repair.
SPEAKER_0:  But as soon as you have a little alcove...
SPEAKER_0:  into a rock.
SPEAKER_0:  or a cliff.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  I'd be looking at those places, but you have to understand Mars, or any other planet for that matter.
SPEAKER_0:  at the level that matters for the microbe.
SPEAKER_0:  and it is.
SPEAKER_0:  So then you.
SPEAKER_1:  one with the micro.
SPEAKER_0:  be one with the microbes, which means that we have lots of orbital data.
SPEAKER_0:  which is good to understand habitability at the planet level or at the regional level.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  We have very little data right now that is very useful to understand habitability.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  at the scale that matters for the microbes.
SPEAKER_0:  at this point in time. So we need to do a better job with that. My idea is to have arrays.
SPEAKER_0:  of environmental station that could have a lot of benefits.
SPEAKER_0:  one would be to give us that vision.
SPEAKER_0:  for the microbes.
SPEAKER_0:  That would be good for astrobiology.
SPEAKER_1:  And second, a collection of stations on Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  Marcia.
SPEAKER_1:  that collect, that give us a good map.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, high resolution.
SPEAKER_0:  We can do that regionally and on top of that. It's good for us through biology for the search for life on Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  That's good about how to learn where microbes could be that can be a problem for contamination both ways.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's good for planetary protection.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  since those stations would have communication.
SPEAKER_0:  capabilities on them.
SPEAKER_0:  that excellent for human exploration because now normally you have
SPEAKER_0:  weather stations all over the place that can tell your astronauts.
SPEAKER_0:  Learn the pattern when it's a good time to go out or not go out.
SPEAKER_0:  and also helps them communicate.
SPEAKER_0:  when they go and do sorties. So there are a number of things you can do that can tell you lots of information.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's rewind the clock a little bit. You grew up in Paris.
SPEAKER_1:  I was just there.
SPEAKER_1:  Helen McDonald in her New York Times amazing profile piece of you.
SPEAKER_1:  writes that your teenage years were troubled.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  how did the challenging early years.
SPEAKER_1:  Make the human being the scientist that you are today.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that...
SPEAKER_0:  This is what's taking me on top of those big mountains.
SPEAKER_0:  And the irony is for me to be looking for the origin and nature of life.
SPEAKER_0:  because I was so close to losing it.
SPEAKER_0:  But to me that was...
SPEAKER_0:  a great lesson learned.
SPEAKER_0:  and that helped me see.
SPEAKER_0:  through the beauty of life?
SPEAKER_0:  Going on the other side of that
SPEAKER_0:  it became really what made me.
SPEAKER_0:  helped me go through absolutely.
SPEAKER_0:  everything and anything in life.
SPEAKER_0:  high mountains and tell me.
SPEAKER_0:  there is something I want to know and you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I am going to give it my best.
SPEAKER_0:  and I won't give up.
SPEAKER_0:  And I won't give in.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is a message that I carried all my life and I'm so very grateful.
SPEAKER_0:  that I did because...
SPEAKER_0:  all the things that I would have missed if I hadn't done that.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, this is...
SPEAKER_0:  something that I wrote in my first book and
SPEAKER_0:  Part of it is the reason why I wrote it.
SPEAKER_0:  just because I felt that there were messages.
SPEAKER_0:  in my path.
SPEAKER_0:  Oftentimes teenagers are troubled. It can be one way or another. Or if it's not a troubled teenage, you have times in your life where you doubt, where you know, you're just waving your arm and say...
SPEAKER_0:  What's the purpose? What's the reason? Why carry on?
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  when I see all the things that I'm doing.
SPEAKER_0:  the dream that I was able to fulfill.
SPEAKER_0:  What a waste it would have been.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_1:  So there was a point in your life where you...
SPEAKER_1:  thought about suicide. It's like a
SPEAKER_0:  And I did more than thinking about it.
SPEAKER_0:  But I was a lyrical one.
SPEAKER_0:  For some reason I'm still here, I still don't know why.
SPEAKER_0:  but I'm still here. And the lesson for me was that never, ever again.
SPEAKER_0:  because
SPEAKER_0:  You have to give tomorrow a chance. You never can think.
SPEAKER_0:  about tomorrow.
SPEAKER_0:  in the terms of the present.
SPEAKER_0:  You never know what can happen. You know what is going to happen if you go.
SPEAKER_0:  through.
SPEAKER_0:  what you want to do.
SPEAKER_0:  Tomorrow's never happening.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, and I had, I had a, the other lessons came a few years later.
SPEAKER_0:  We're actually.
SPEAKER_0:  Somebody was drowning in a wind.
SPEAKER_0:  after that person. I almost died that day too, not that I wanted to, but it's just because the conditions were very, very difficult.
SPEAKER_0:  that person.
SPEAKER_0:  died from there, although we took him out of the water.
SPEAKER_0:  But I had a lot of difficulty coming out. I came out, but then I thought a lot about that guy. He was in his 30s.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It was like a sort of an echo from a few years.
SPEAKER_0:  before.
SPEAKER_0:  telling me that person would never have a tomorrow.
SPEAKER_0:  that person would never be able to fulfill his dream or even have dreams of any kind.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was here and I was going to give myself the best chance.
SPEAKER_0:  fulfill all the dreams I wanted to and go after all the questions I wanted to.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is what gets me going now, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  The advice there is even if you don't see a Y.
SPEAKER_1:  an answer to the why question, why live.
SPEAKER_1:  today.
SPEAKER_0:  Give tomorrow a chance.
SPEAKER_0:  always.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think about your...
SPEAKER_1:  death today? Do you think about your mortality?
SPEAKER_0:  Thanks for watching!
SPEAKER_0:  Not really.
SPEAKER_1:  You've been so close with it. Yeahings
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, we know that.
SPEAKER_0:  part of life and you know what?
SPEAKER_0:  If something happens to me while I'm doing the stuff I love...
SPEAKER_0:  What a way of going!
SPEAKER_0:  This will happen.
SPEAKER_0:  wherever it is.
SPEAKER_0:  catches me.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, I don't care, it will be what it will be. And I had the best.
SPEAKER_0:  We were masters for that.
SPEAKER_0:  I had my husband.
SPEAKER_0:  My husband and I were 44 years apart.
SPEAKER_0:  in age.
SPEAKER_0:  and it was just a pure love story.
SPEAKER_0:  and it never
SPEAKER_0:  Look at his age.
SPEAKER_0:  never thought about himself.
SPEAKER_0:  or define himself.
SPEAKER_0:  by his age. In fact, he reinvented the life for himself.
SPEAKER_0:  At an age where everybody retires, we met when he was 66.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  That was a blessing!
SPEAKER_0:  And a curse, but a blessing most of it, because we took every single day as if it was the last.
SPEAKER_0:  So we enjoyed life.
SPEAKER_0:  And right now.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not so much, you know, I have to really think of him. It just passed away.
SPEAKER_0:  this August, last August.
SPEAKER_0:  And for me...
SPEAKER_0:  It's more like...
SPEAKER_0:  I have to draw.
SPEAKER_0:  from
SPEAKER_0:  is example.
SPEAKER_0:  on him always telling me.
SPEAKER_0:  Look forward.
SPEAKER_0:  Trust Life.
SPEAKER_0:  Be happy.
SPEAKER_0:  Live.
SPEAKER_0:  You know what?
SPEAKER_0:  Today, every single day.
SPEAKER_0:  I have to remind several times a day.
SPEAKER_0:  of this, it's not easy.
SPEAKER_0:  But he had the recipe.
SPEAKER_0:  He never thought about death.
SPEAKER_0:  Because when you start thinking too much about death, that prevents you from living.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you miss him?
SPEAKER_0:  Gosh, we were so close, I think we were.
SPEAKER_0:  It's more like...
SPEAKER_0:  One spirit in two bodies. We were that close. So missing him doesn't even cut it.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the toughest mountain I ever climbed.
SPEAKER_0:  What's the role of love in the human condition?
SPEAKER_0:  I think, I hope.
SPEAKER_0:  that this is the force that drives the universe, although, you know, we might be experiencing the other side of it.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe just to learn.
SPEAKER_0:  how important love is.
SPEAKER_0:  That might be it.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  For me?
SPEAKER_0:  my experience with my husband where I never had to.
SPEAKER_0:  Wake up every...
SPEAKER_0:  single morning.
SPEAKER_0:  Ever wondering if I was in love?
SPEAKER_0:  I had to look.
SPEAKER_0:  In his eyes.
SPEAKER_0:  and Lim looking back at me.
SPEAKER_0:  know it.
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  So when you get to that point where you don't question it anymore, I would hope for humanity to reach that point.
SPEAKER_0:  where you can feel the same love for the person.
SPEAKER_0:  that is unknown in the street.
SPEAKER_0:  that you feel for the people you love. I think that at that point, we are going to be reaching.
SPEAKER_0:  the maturity of that civilization we are hoping for and seeing.
SPEAKER_0:  the universe through love.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  That doesn't run spacecrafts.
SPEAKER_0:  course.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  putting love into our intent of going into.
SPEAKER_0:  and settling into another planet instead of, oh my God, we need to escape because we are.
SPEAKER_0:  Freaking messing up with our own planet.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that this is the answer to so many things.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there a part of you?
SPEAKER_1:  that maybe just a little bit.
SPEAKER_1:  wants to step foot on Mars?
SPEAKER_0:  Like you personally.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yeah, of course, I'm curious. I'm a scientist and I've been working on Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  I was actually privileged to be working on Gusev Crater and deciding for the landing site of the Spirit Rover, which means that I worked on that landing site for 15 years and I got to see it from the ground.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the closest.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, to being there and exploring. Of course, that's not phys-
SPEAKER_0:  be present there.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  If you were giving me the opportunity, of course I would go, but I know...
SPEAKER_0:  one thing.
SPEAKER_0:  I would want to come back.
SPEAKER_1:  So given the option.
SPEAKER_1:  of dying on Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  or dying on earth.
SPEAKER_1:  You'd visit Mars, but you would like to spend your last days here. Yep.
SPEAKER_0:  because of a number of things.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that
SPEAKER_0:  First we are not ready to set on Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  regardless of what being said.
SPEAKER_0:  It will happen.
SPEAKER_0:  It will happen and because we are explorers, humans, you know, they're explorers. So this will happen.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's a good thing. Depending on how we go about this, it can be a very good thing.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, with time, as much as I've been exploring, continue to explore the big questions of...
SPEAKER_0:  the original nature of life or exploring of a planet.
SPEAKER_0:  The love, you are talking about love.
SPEAKER_0:  The love for my own planet.
SPEAKER_0:  has grown deeper.
SPEAKER_0:  and my concern about it has grown deeper.
SPEAKER_0:  So the data that I'm collecting.
SPEAKER_0:  to learn about.
SPEAKER_0:  other planets. I'm also using it to understand better our home planet.
SPEAKER_0:  and trying to make it a little better for the next generation.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  If you were talking about love, this is love that would...
SPEAKER_0:  drive me back here.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, this planet.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just...
SPEAKER_1:  Sometimes I just pause.
SPEAKER_1:  and M&R at the incredible thing we have here.
SPEAKER_1:  and just.
SPEAKER_1:  And I have deep gratitude for...
SPEAKER_1:  all the life forms here.
SPEAKER_1:  The beautiful complexity, of course there's darkness behind it.
SPEAKER_1:  All the death.
SPEAKER_1:  or the extinction that led.
SPEAKER_1:  up to
SPEAKER_1:  us two descendants of Ape sitting here today. I feel that's a responsibility.
SPEAKER_1:  We're the fittest that survived.
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly right!
SPEAKER_0:  as the
SPEAKER_0:  dominant species at least, you know, technologically, etc.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe not.
SPEAKER_0:  the wisest one, but the dominant species, we have a responsibility towards the entire biosphere.
SPEAKER_0:  because the
SPEAKER_0:  Decisions we are making now.
SPEAKER_0:  None of you affect us.
SPEAKER_0:  They're affecting.
SPEAKER_0:  the entire biosphere.
SPEAKER_0:  And right now the choices we are making...
SPEAKER_0:  are leading to the disappearance of 150 species every single day.
SPEAKER_0:  all the big mammals.
SPEAKER_0:  on this earth.
SPEAKER_0:  today are on the brink of extinction.
SPEAKER_0:  We are.
SPEAKER_0:  within the 6.
SPEAKER_0:  greatest max extinction. It's unfolding before our eyes.
SPEAKER_0:  And, um...
SPEAKER_0:  I would.
SPEAKER_0:  strongly suggest that we use our smart.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  help.
SPEAKER_0:  a little bit this situation.
SPEAKER_0:  And we can do this. I think we can do this. We just need to...
SPEAKER_0:  redirect.
SPEAKER_0:  our energy.
SPEAKER_1:  in the name of love.
SPEAKER_1:  This was an incredible conversation. I'm really honored you sit with me. I've been a fan of your work for a long time now, so this is really awesome.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you so much for talking to me.
SPEAKER_0:  You're very welcome. Thanks.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with Natalie Cabral.
SPEAKER_1:  to support this podcast.
SPEAKER_1:  Please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now...
SPEAKER_1:  Let me leave you with some words from Stanislav Lem and Solaris.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you expect to communicate with the ocean?
SPEAKER_1:  when we can't even understand one another.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for listening and hope to see you next time.