SPEAKER_0:  You can study chemistry, you can study physics, you can study geology anywhere in the universe, but this is the only place you can study biology. This is the only place to be a biologist.
SPEAKER_0:  That's it.
SPEAKER_0:  So definitely something very fundamental happened here and you cannot take biology out of the equation if you want to understand how that vast chemistry space
SPEAKER_0:  of that general.
SPEAKER_0:  sequence space.
SPEAKER_0:  got narrowed down to what is available.
SPEAKER_0:  or what is used by life.
SPEAKER_0:  you need to understand the rules of selection. And that's when evolution and biology comes into play.
SPEAKER_1:  The following is a conversation with Batoo Kachar.
SPEAKER_1:  an astrobiologist at University of Wisconsin.
SPEAKER_1:  studying.
SPEAKER_1:  the essential biological attributes of life.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the Lex Friedman podcast, support it. Please check out our sponsors in the description. 0
SPEAKER_1:  Dear friends,
SPEAKER_1:  Here's the tool.
SPEAKER_1:  Kachar.
SPEAKER_1:  What is the phylogenetic tree or the evolutionary tree of life? What can we learn by running it back and studying ancient gene sequences as you have?
SPEAKER_0:  I think...
SPEAKER_0:  Phyrogenetic trees.
SPEAKER_0:  could be one of the most.
SPEAKER_0:  romantic and beautiful notions that can come out of biology.
SPEAKER_0:  It shows us a way to depict the connectedness of life and all living beings with one another.
SPEAKER_0:  itself is an ever evolving notion.
SPEAKER_0:  biologists like.
SPEAKER_0:  visualizations. They like these.
SPEAKER_0:  graphics, these diagrams and tree of life is one of them.
SPEAKER_1:  So the tree starts at a common ancestor.
SPEAKER_0:  It's actually the other way around. It starts from the-
SPEAKER_0:  the branches, it starts from the tip of the branch.
SPEAKER_0:  actually, and then further, depending on what you collected.
SPEAKER_0:  to build the tree. So depending on the branches, depending on what's on the tip of the branch, I will explain what I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  the root will be determined by what is really sitting on the tip of the branch of the tree.
SPEAKER_1:  So we could study the leaves of the tree by looking at what we have today and then start to reverse engineer, start to...
SPEAKER_1:  move back in time to try to understand what the rest of the tree, what the roots.
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly. So the tree itself, by just taking a few steps back and looking at the entire tree itself.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  give you an idea about the connectedness.
SPEAKER_0:  the relatedness of the organisms or whatever, again, you use to create your tree.
SPEAKER_0:  different ways.
SPEAKER_0:  but in this case, I'm imagining.
SPEAKER_0:  entire
SPEAKER_0:  diversity of.
SPEAKER_0:  life today is sitting on the tips of the branches of this tree.
SPEAKER_0:  and we look at.
SPEAKER_0:  biologists look at the tree itself.
SPEAKER_0:  We like to think of it as the topology of the tree to understand when certain...
SPEAKER_0:  organisms or their ancestry may have.
SPEAKER_0:  merged.
SPEAKER_0:  over time.
SPEAKER_0:  depending on the tools you use.
SPEAKER_0:  You might.
SPEAKER_0:  Use this.
SPEAKER_0:  to then reconstruct the ancestors as well.
SPEAKER_1:  And so what are the different ways to do the reconstruction? So you can do that at the gene level.
SPEAKER_1:  or you could do it.
SPEAKER_1:  at the higher complex biology level.
SPEAKER_1:  Right, so what...
SPEAKER_1:  In which way have you approached this?
SPEAKER_1:  this fascinating problem.
SPEAKER_0:  We approached it in every way we can. So it's the gene.
SPEAKER_0:  could be protein, the product of the gene.
SPEAKER_0:  or species.
SPEAKER_0:  or could be even groups of species.
SPEAKER_0:  It will depend, totally depends on what you want to do with your tree. If you want to understand certain...
SPEAKER_0:  past events whether an organism exchanged a certain DNA with another one along the course of evolution?
SPEAKER_0:  You can build your tree accordingly.
SPEAKER_0:  if you rather use the tree to reconstruct or resurrect ancient DNA which is what we do
SPEAKER_0:  then you
SPEAKER_0:  In our case, for instance, we do both gene protein and species because we want to compare.
SPEAKER_0:  the tree.
SPEAKER_0:  that we create using these different.
SPEAKER_0:  information.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, well, let me ask you the ridiculous question then. Answer in the next video...
SPEAKER_1:  How realistic is Jurassic Park?
SPEAKER_1:  Can we study the genes of ancient organisms and can we bring the...
SPEAKER_1:  those ancient organisms back. So the reason I ask that kind of ridiculous sounding question is because I guess the sounds come from the
SPEAKER_1:  maybe gives us context of what we can and can't do.
SPEAKER_1:  by looking back in time.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, sold.
SPEAKER_0:  dinosaurs or all these mammals in, at least for us is.
SPEAKER_0:  The exciting thing already happened by the time we hit to larger organisms or to eukaryotes.
SPEAKER_1:  See you, the fun stuff is before we got to the mail.
SPEAKER_0:  The fun stuff is what people think is boring, I think. The phase that's, well, at least two different times in the geologic history. One is the...
SPEAKER_0:  First life.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  past origin of life, how did first life look like?
SPEAKER_0:  And the second is why do we think that
SPEAKER_0:  over certain periods of geologic time.
SPEAKER_0:  no significant innovation happened to the degree of leaving no record behind.
SPEAKER_1:  So what do we not have a record of?
SPEAKER_1:  Which part? Is it the fun stuff to you?
SPEAKER_1:  is after the origin of life, which we'll talk about, after the origin of life, there's single cell organisms.
SPEAKER_1:  the whole thing with the photosynthesis, the whole thing with the eukaryotes and multicell organisms.
SPEAKER_1:  What else is the fun stuff? The whole oxygen thing?
SPEAKER_1:  which mixes in with the origin of life.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a bunch of different inventions all that have to do with this primitive kind of looking organisms
SPEAKER_1:  that we don't have a good record of.
SPEAKER_0:  So I will tell you the more interesting things for us.
SPEAKER_0:  One is the origin of life or what happened.
SPEAKER_0:  Following.
SPEAKER_0:  the emergence of life. How did the first cells look like?
SPEAKER_0:  and then pretty much anything.
SPEAKER_0:  that we think shaped
SPEAKER_0:  the environment and was shaped by the environment in a way that impacted the entire planet.
SPEAKER_0:  that enabled you and I to have this conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  We have very little understanding of the biological innovations that took place in the past of this planet.
SPEAKER_0:  We work with a very limited set of
SPEAKER_0:  I don't want to even say data because they are fossil records.
SPEAKER_0:  So let's say in prints.
SPEAKER_0:  either that comes from the rock.
SPEAKER_0:  in the rock record itself.
SPEAKER_0:  or
SPEAKER_0:  what I just described.
SPEAKER_0:  these trees that we create and whatever we can infer about the past. So we have two distinct ways.
SPEAKER_0:  that comes from geology and biology, and they each have their limitations.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so right. So there's an interplay. The geology gives you that little bit of data.
SPEAKER_1:  and then the biology.
SPEAKER_1:  Gezu.
SPEAKER_1:  that little bit of kind of constraints in the materials you get to work with to infer.
SPEAKER_1:  how does this result in the kind of data that we're seeing? And now we can have this through the fog.
SPEAKER_1:  we can see, we can look back hundreds of millions of years.
SPEAKER_1:  couple of billion years and try to infer.
SPEAKER_0:  Even further, and I like that you said fog. It is pretty foggy. What we're doing, and it gets foggier and foggier the more you, the further you try to see into the past.
SPEAKER_0:  biology is.
SPEAKER_0:  You basically study with
SPEAKER_0:  study the survivors.
SPEAKER_0:  broadly speaking, and you're trying to...
SPEAKER_0:  pitch, sort of put together their history based on whatever you can recover today.
SPEAKER_0:  What makes biology fascinating?
SPEAKER_0:  Also...
SPEAKER_0:  Let it rip.
SPEAKER_0:  B- B-
SPEAKER_0:  it erased its own history in a way, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So you work with this four billion year product, that's genome, that's the DNA.
SPEAKER_0:  It's great. It's a very dynamic, ever evolving.
SPEAKER_0:  chemical thing.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you will get some information, but...
SPEAKER_0:  You're not gonna get.
SPEAKER_0:  much unless you know where to look.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  because it is responding to the environment.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so what we have, that's fascinating.
SPEAKER_1:  What we have is the survivors.
SPEAKER_1:  the successful.
SPEAKER_1:  successful organisms, even the primitive ones, even the bacteria we have today.
SPEAKER_0:  So bacteria is not primitive and we... Sorry
SPEAKER_1:  Sorry to offend the bacteria.
SPEAKER_0:  We should be very grateful to Bakteria.
SPEAKER_0:  great great ancestors.
SPEAKER_0:  I like this quote by Douglas Adams, humans don't.
SPEAKER_0:  like their ancestors, they rarely invite them over for dinner.
SPEAKER_0:  But bacteria is in your dinner. Bacteria is in your gut. Bacteria is helping you along the way. So we do invite them for dinner. Well, they'd get themselves invited in a way.
SPEAKER_0:  And...
SPEAKER_0:  So we and they're definitely older.
SPEAKER_0:  And definitely very sophisticated, very resilient.
SPEAKER_0:  than anything else. As someone working at the, as a bacteriologist, I feel like I need to do.
SPEAKER_0:  Defend them in this case because they don't get much shout out.
SPEAKER_0:  Let me think about life.
SPEAKER_1:  So you do study bacteria, so which organism gives you hints that are alive today that give you
SPEAKER_1:  hints about what ancient organisms were like, and what they ate.
SPEAKER_1:  or just a renal lab.
SPEAKER_0:  We study a variety of different bacteria depending on the questions that we ask. We engineer bacteria.
SPEAKER_0:  So ideally we want to work with bacteria that we can engineer.
SPEAKER_0:  seldom we developed the tools to engineer them.
SPEAKER_0:  And it depends on the question that we are interested in. If we are interested in connecting the biology and geology.
SPEAKER_0:  to understand the early life and
SPEAKER_0:  fundamental innovations across billions of years.
SPEAKER_0:  there are really good candidates like cyanobacteria.
SPEAKER_0:  So we use cyanobacteria very frequently.
SPEAKER_0:  In the lab, we can engineer its genome. We can perturb its function by poking.
SPEAKER_0:  its own DNA with the.
SPEAKER_0:  foreignDNA.V
SPEAKER_0:  engineer in the lab.
SPEAKER_0:  We work with Ecoli. It's the most simple in terms of model systems go.
SPEAKER_0:  goes.
SPEAKER_0:  organism that one can study well established.
SPEAKER_0:  Ehh
SPEAKER_0:  sort of a pet, lab pet.
SPEAKER_0:  that we use it a lot for cloning and for understanding.
SPEAKER_0:  basic functions of the cell given that it's really well studied.
SPEAKER_1:  So, and then what you do with that E. coli.
SPEAKER_1:  You said that you injected with point DNA?
SPEAKER_0:  We inject pretty much all the bacteria that we work with, with foreign DNA. We also work with diazotrophs. These are azotobacteria.
SPEAKER_0:  They're one of the prime nitrogen fixers, nitrogen fixing.
SPEAKER_0:  Bacteria.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you explain what that is? Nitrogen fixing? Is that the source of its energy?
SPEAKER_0:  So nitrogen is a triple bond.
SPEAKER_0:  gas that's pretty abundant in the atmosphere.
SPEAKER_0:  Nitrogen itself cannot be directly utilized by cells given it has triple bond.
SPEAKER_0:  It needs to be converted to ammonia that is then used.
SPEAKER_0:  for
SPEAKER_0:  dude.
SPEAKER_0:  downstream.
SPEAKER_0:  cellular functions.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's what counts as.
SPEAKER_1:  nitrogen fixing.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, so...
SPEAKER_0:  to be fixed before our cells can make use of it.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  And it's... No offense to nitrogen either. Well, it's actually a very important element. It's one of the most abundant elements on our planet that is used by biology. It's in...
SPEAKER_0:  ATP, it's in chlorophyll.
SPEAKER_0:  users
SPEAKER_0:  that relies on nitrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's a very important enzyme for a lot of
SPEAKER_0:  cell functions.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's just one mechanism that evolution invented to convert.
SPEAKER_0:  It is.
SPEAKER_0:  So far we know there's only one nitrogen fixation pathway, as opposed to say carbon. You can find up to seven or eight different carbon ways.
SPEAKER_0:  microbes invented to fix carbon.
SPEAKER_0:  That's not the case for nitrogen. It's a singularity.
SPEAKER_0:  across geologic time. We think it evolved around 2.7 maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, roughly three.
SPEAKER_0:  probably less than three billion years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's the only way that nature invented to fix the nitrogen in the atmosphere for the subsequent use.
SPEAKER_1:  Would we still have life as we know it today if we didn't invent?
SPEAKER_1:  that nitrogen fixing step.
SPEAKER_0:  I cannot think of it, no.
SPEAKER_0:  It's essential to.
SPEAKER_0:  Life as we know, you and I are having this conversation because...
SPEAKER_0:  life.
SPEAKER_0:  found a way to fix nitrogen.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that one of the tougher ones? If you put it sort of-
SPEAKER_1:  uh, oxygen.
SPEAKER_1:  Nitrogen.
SPEAKER_1:  carbon.
SPEAKER_1:  What are-
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of being able to work with these.
SPEAKER_1:  elements.
SPEAKER_1:  What is the hardest?
SPEAKER_1:  What is the most essential for life?
SPEAKER_0:  Just to give context. Well, we think of this as the cocktail. You may hear schnapps. What's in the cocktail? It's the schnapps, right? Carbon hydrogen oxygen.
SPEAKER_0:  nitrogen, sulfur.
SPEAKER_0:  So there are five elements.
SPEAKER_0:  that life relies on.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't quite know whether that's...
SPEAKER_0:  the only out of many options that life necessarily needs to operate on. But that's just how it.
SPEAKER_0:  how it happened on our own planet.
SPEAKER_0:  and there are many abiotic ways to fix nitrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  and like lightning, right? Lightning can accumulate ammonia.
SPEAKER_0:  Humans found a way about a hundred years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  around World War I.
SPEAKER_0:  the Haber-Bosch process that we can abiotically convert nitrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  in Turmonia.
SPEAKER_0:  Actually, 50% of the nitrogen in our bodies comes from the human
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  conversion of nitrogen to ammonia.
SPEAKER_0:  It's helped, it's the fertilizer that we use, urea, comes from that process.
SPEAKER_0:  It's in our food. So we helped, we found a way to
SPEAKER_0:  fix our own nitrogen for ourselves.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, but that...
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  That's way after the original.
SPEAKER_1:  Invention of how to
SPEAKER_0:  Absolutely.
SPEAKER_1:  And without that we wouldn't have.
SPEAKER_1:  we wouldn't have all the steps of evolution along with it.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, absolutely. We tried to replicate.
SPEAKER_0:  in the most simplest way what nature has.
SPEAKER_0:  Come up, bitch.
SPEAKER_0:  We do this by taking nitrogen using a lot of pressure and then generating ammonia.
SPEAKER_0:  Life does this in a more sophisticated way, relying on one single enzyme called nitrogenase.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the nitrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  that is used together with 8 electron donor.
SPEAKER_0:  and ATP.
SPEAKER_0:  together with a lot of hydrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  life.
SPEAKER_0:  pushes this metabolism down to create.
SPEAKER_0:  fixed nitrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  It's quite remarkable.
SPEAKER_1:  So the lab pet, E. coli inject them with DNA. Those are the E. coli does nitrogen fixing.
SPEAKER_1:  in part or is that a different one?
SPEAKER_0:  So some biological engineers.
SPEAKER_0:  engineered E. coli to
SPEAKER_0:  fixed nitrogen, I believe, not us.
SPEAKER_0:  We use the.
SPEAKER_0:  Nature's nitrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  nitrogen fixing bug.
SPEAKER_0:  and engineer it with the nitrogen fixing.
SPEAKER_0:  metabolism that we resurrected using our computational and phylogenetic methods.
SPEAKER_1:  tools.
SPEAKER_1:  How complicated are these little organisms? What are we talking about?
SPEAKER_0:  depends on how you define complication.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so I could tell.
SPEAKER_1:  that you appreciate and respect the full complexity of even the most seemingly.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  primitive organisms because none of them are primitive. okay
SPEAKER_1:  That said, what kind of, what are we talking about? How, how, um...
SPEAKER_1:  What kind of machineries do they have?
SPEAKER_1:  that you're working with when you're injecting them with DNA.
SPEAKER_0:  So I will...
SPEAKER_0:  start with one of the most fascinating machineries that we target, which is the translation machinery.
SPEAKER_0:  It is a very unique.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  subsystem.
SPEAKER_0:  of cellular life.
SPEAKER_0:  in comparison to, I would say, metabolism.
SPEAKER_0:  And we used to...
SPEAKER_0:  When we are thinking about cellular life, we think of cell as the basic unit.
SPEAKER_0:  Ehh or dude
SPEAKER_0:  building block.
SPEAKER_0:  But from a key perspective...
SPEAKER_0:  That's...
SPEAKER_0:  Not the case. There's just gonna be a curse on the day, I know the curse already exists...
SPEAKER_0:  One may argue that everything that happens inside the cell
SPEAKER_0:  serves the translation.
SPEAKER_0:  and the translation machinery.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, there's a nice paper that called this that entire cell.
SPEAKER_0:  is hopelessly addicted.
SPEAKER_0:  to this main informatic.
SPEAKER_0:  computing, biological.
SPEAKER_0:  Chemical.
SPEAKER_0:  system that it's.
SPEAKER_0:  is operating at the heart of the cell.
SPEAKER_1:  which is the translation.
SPEAKER_1:  It is the translation. It is the translation form.
SPEAKER_1:  to what?
SPEAKER_1:  So RNA.
SPEAKER_0:  enzymes converts.
SPEAKER_0:  Linear Sequence.
SPEAKER_0:  of mRNA into a folded.
SPEAKER_0:  later folded protein.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the core processing center for information for life.
SPEAKER_0:  It has multiple steps. It initiates, it elongates.
SPEAKER_0:  It's...
SPEAKER_0:  terminates and it recycles.
SPEAKER_0:  operates.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Eww.
SPEAKER_0:  discrete.
SPEAKER_0:  bits of information itself is like a chemical decoding.
SPEAKER_0:  device and that is incredibly.
SPEAKER_0:  unique for translation that I don't think you will find.
SPEAKER_0:  anywhere else in the cell.
SPEAKER_0:  that does this.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  Even though it's called translation, it's really like a factory that reads.
SPEAKER_1:  The schematic.
SPEAKER_1:  and builds a three-dimensional object. It's a printer.
SPEAKER_0:  I would divide it into actually even four more.
SPEAKER_0:  additional steps or disciplines, then what would it take to study it by the way you described it?
SPEAKER_0:  It's a chemical system.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the compounds that make it up, or chemicals.
SPEAKER_0:  It's physical.
SPEAKER_0:  It tracks the energy.
SPEAKER_0:  to make.
SPEAKER_0:  its job to do its job.
SPEAKER_0:  It's on Informatic.
SPEAKER_0:  What is processed are the bits.
SPEAKER_0:  It's computational.
SPEAKER_0:  the discrete states that
SPEAKER_0:  the system is placed when the information is being processed, that itself is computational.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's biological. It's a, there's variability and inheritance that come.
SPEAKER_0:  from imperfect replication even.
SPEAKER_0:  and in perfect computation.
SPEAKER_1:  So your hand that's so good. So
SPEAKER_1:  From the biology comes the...
SPEAKER_1:  Like when you mess up.
SPEAKER_1:  The bugs are the features, that's the biology.
SPEAKER_1:  Informatics is obvious in the RNA that says several information there.
SPEAKER_1:  The different steps along the way is actually kind of what the computer does with with bits. It's done computation
SPEAKER_1:  physical there's a
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I guess, almost like a mechanical process to the whole thing that requires energy and actually, you know, it's manipulating actual physical objects.
SPEAKER_1:  and chemicals because you're
SPEAKER_1:  have to ultimately it's all chemistry. Not all chemistry is not going to be easy.
SPEAKER_0:  And it tracks this information. So it is almost a mini computer device inside ourselves. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  EW
SPEAKER_0:  computational device of life.
SPEAKER_0:  It's, it's, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Likely.
SPEAKER_0:  The key.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  operation system that had to evolve for life.
SPEAKER_1:  emerge.
SPEAKER_1:  It's more interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  or
SPEAKER_1:  It's more complicated in interesting ways than the computers we have today.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, everything you said, which is really, really nice.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I guess our computers have the informatic.
SPEAKER_1:  and then have the computational.
SPEAKER_1:  but they don't have the chemical, the physical.
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly. And the computers don't have, don't link information to function.
SPEAKER_0:  They are not tightly coupled, nowhere close to what transition.
SPEAKER_0:  and all the way translation does it.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's the number one, I think, difference between the two.
SPEAKER_0:  and yes, it's informatic and we can...
SPEAKER_0:  Disgust is...
SPEAKER_0:  further too.
SPEAKER_1:  100%. Let's please discuss this further.
SPEAKER_1:  which part are we discussing for each one of those fascinating worlds each each of the five
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so well, we can start with the more, I guess, the...
SPEAKER_0:  the ones that are more established, which is the chemical aspect.
SPEAKER_0:  of the translation machinery.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the specific compounds make up the assembly of RNA chemists.
SPEAKER_0:  show to this in many different ways.
SPEAKER_0:  We can rip apart the entire machinery. We know that it's the core of it.
SPEAKER_0:  there's an RNA that's...
SPEAKER_0:  Eww.
SPEAKER_0:  that operates.
SPEAKER_0:  not only as an information system itself or information itself, but also as an enzyme.
SPEAKER_0:  And origin of life chemists make these molecules easily. Now we know we can manipulate RNA, we can make even with single-part chemistries.
SPEAKER_0:  we can create compounds.
SPEAKER_1:  chemistry.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say when you add all the recipes that you know that will lead you to the final product.
SPEAKER_1:  original left cameras do is they they
SPEAKER_1:  come up with this part, they throw a bunch of chemicals in.
SPEAKER_1:  And they tried to.
SPEAKER_1:  They're basically chefs of a certain kind.
SPEAKER_0:  sure if that's what they call it, but that's how I think of it. Because it is all combined in a test tube and you know the outcome. And it's very mathematical once you know the right environment and the right chemistry that needs to get into this.
SPEAKER_0:  container with this pod.
SPEAKER_0:  You know what the outcomes, there's no luck there anymore. It's a pretty rigid, established.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  input-output system and it's all chemistry.
SPEAKER_1:  So you actually wear a lot of hats as one of them.
SPEAKER_1:  Origin of Life chemist
SPEAKER_0:  My PhD is in chemistry, but I don't do original life chemistry.
SPEAKER_1:  But you're interested in origin.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, absolutely.
SPEAKER_1:  Some of your best friends are original life chemists.
SPEAKER_0:  Just make sure that you have good chemist friends if you're interested in Origin of Life.
SPEAKER_0:  That's
SPEAKER_0:  100% requirement, should be mandatory.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so chemistry, so what else about this machinery that we need to know?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Chemically, I think that's it. You have enzymes, you have proteins. Enzymes are doing their thing. They know how to chew energy using ATP or GTP. They know what to do in their own way. They do their enzymatic thing.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's not just the ribosome that is at the heart of the transition, but there are a lot of different proteins.
SPEAKER_0:  You're looking at about 100 different components that compose this machinery.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, let me ask kind of maybe it's a ridiculous question, but did the chemistry.
SPEAKER_1:  Make this machine.
SPEAKER_1:  Or did the machine?
SPEAKER_1:  Use chemistry to achieve a purpose.
SPEAKER_1:  So like...
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  I guess there's a lot of different chemical possibilities on earth.
SPEAKER_1:  Is this translation machinery just like...
SPEAKER_1:  uh choosing picking and choosing different
SPEAKER_1:  chemical reactions that you can use to achieve a purpose.
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh
SPEAKER_1:  Or did the chemistry basically...
SPEAKER_1:  like there's like a momentum, like a constraint to the thing that can only build a certain kind of machinery.
SPEAKER_1:  that's basically is chemistry fundamental.
SPEAKER_1:  Or is it just emergent?
SPEAKER_1:  Like how important is chemistry to this whole process?
SPEAKER_0:  Yes. You cannot have life without chemistry. You cannot have any.
SPEAKER_0:  cellular process without.
SPEAKER_0:  What makes life interesting is that even if the chemistry is imperfect...
SPEAKER_0:  even if there are accidents along the way.
SPEAKER_0:  if something binds to another.
SPEAKER_0:  Chemical.
SPEAKER_0:  in a way it shouldn't.
SPEAKER_0:  there is resilience within the system that it can.
SPEAKER_0:  maybe not necessarily repair itself, but it moves on.
SPEAKER_0:  how every imperfect mistakes can be handled. That's where the biology comes in. But in terms of chemistry, you absolutely cannot have a transition missionary without chemistry.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  So as I said, there are four main steps. These are the core steps that are conserved.
SPEAKER_0:  in all translation machinery and I should say all life has this machine.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  every cell.
SPEAKER_0:  On Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  when you think of this machine.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think very specifically about the kind of machinery that we're talking about, or do you think more philosophically?
SPEAKER_1:  a machine that converts information into function.
SPEAKER_0:  It's I cannot separate the two. I think what makes this-
SPEAKER_0:  machinery fascinating is that those five components that I listed, they coexist.
SPEAKER_0:  So for instance, if we...
SPEAKER_0:  Let's just.
SPEAKER_0:  talking about the.
SPEAKER_0:  chemistry part.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  We know the certain...
SPEAKER_0:  rate constant, all these proteins that operate in this machinery needs to
SPEAKER_0:  Harbor.
SPEAKER_0:  in order to
SPEAKER_0:  Get the-
SPEAKER_0:  mechanism going.
SPEAKER_0:  right, if you are bringing the information to the translation machinery and you are the initiator
SPEAKER_0:  of this.
SPEAKER_0:  computation system.
SPEAKER_0:  you need to have.
SPEAKER_0:  You can only afford a certain range of mistakes. If you're too fast...
SPEAKER_0:  then the next message cannot be delivered fast. If you're too slow,
SPEAKER_0:  that you may stall the process.
SPEAKER_0:  So there is definitely chemistry constant going on within the machinery.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, it's not perfect.
SPEAKER_0:  Fire from it.
SPEAKER_0:  But they all...
SPEAKER_0:  have their own margin of error that they can tolerate versus they cannot, otherwise they collapse, the system collapses.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's like a jazz ensemble, the notes of the chemistry, but you can be-
SPEAKER_0:  I love that you said jazz, it's definitely true. It's a party and it's like everybody's invited and they need to.
SPEAKER_0:  operate together.
SPEAKER_0:  right? And they, what's really cool about it, I think, there are many things.
SPEAKER_0:  that are very interesting about this thing. But if you remove it from the cell...
SPEAKER_0:  and put it in a cell-free environment.
SPEAKER_0:  works just fine, right? So you can get...
SPEAKER_0:  cell-free translation systems.
SPEAKER_0:  put this transition in a...
SPEAKER_0:  this test tube and it is.
SPEAKER_0:  doing its thing. It doesn't need the rest of the cell.
SPEAKER_0:  to translate information. Of course you need to feed the information.
SPEAKER_0:  at least so far.
SPEAKER_0:  But because we.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, far from.
SPEAKER_0:  evolving a translation. Maybe not so far.
SPEAKER_0:  evolving a translation in the lab.
SPEAKER_0:  or the machinery that can
SPEAKER_0:  process information as it generates it. We have not done that yet.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a pretty complicated machinery, so it's hard for a digit.
SPEAKER_1:  for those, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  or original life chemists to find a pot that generates.
SPEAKER_0:  Because it's far more than chemistry. You need biology, obviously. You need biochemistry. You need to think as a...
SPEAKER_0:  Network Systems folk.
SPEAKER_0:  You need to think about computation. You need to think about information.
SPEAKER_0:  And that is not happening yet, except we are trying.
SPEAKER_0:  to bring this perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  But the more you understand how the information systems work, you cannot, once you see it, you cannot unsee it. That's one of those things.
SPEAKER_1:  So, but you can still rip it out and the chemistry happens.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  And chemistry can happen even if you strip some of the...
SPEAKER_0:  parts out.
SPEAKER_0:  It can, you can get very minimal.
SPEAKER_0:  level of information processing.
SPEAKER_0:  that does not look anything like the translation that cells relies on.
SPEAKER_0:  but chemists showed from linear, you can generate information that arrives.
SPEAKER_0:  to a processing center in the form of a linear.
SPEAKER_0:  Polymer
SPEAKER_0:  But the-
SPEAKER_0:  Informatic part of this system that I think sets the part.
SPEAKER_0:  from
SPEAKER_0:  computation and from metabolism.
SPEAKER_0:  comes in if you think about the information itself.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, so.
SPEAKER_0:  We have.
SPEAKER_0:  four nucleotide letters that compose DNA.
SPEAKER_0:  and they are processed in the translation in triplets.
SPEAKER_0:  So you have in triplet code on.
SPEAKER_0:  fragments.
SPEAKER_0:  So you have four times four times four. So you have 64 possible states that can be.
SPEAKER_0:  encoded.
SPEAKER_0:  by four letters in three positions.
SPEAKER_0:  Alright, so...
SPEAKER_1:  It's so amazing.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. It's so amazing. There's only one.
SPEAKER_0:  code that says start.
SPEAKER_0:  that there's only one.
SPEAKER_0:  And then there's...
SPEAKER_0:  to
SPEAKER_0:  if not three, that says stop.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what you work with. But you can have 64 possible states, but life only uses.
SPEAKER_0:  Sweeney.
SPEAKER_0:  Amino acids.
SPEAKER_0:  So we used, 6Live uses 64 possible states minus 4.
SPEAKER_0:  of the starts and stops.
SPEAKER_0:  to code for 20 amino acids in different combinations.
SPEAKER_0:  That is-
SPEAKER_0:  really amazing if you think about.
SPEAKER_0:  There are 500 different amino acids life can choose, right?
SPEAKER_0:  narrowed it down to 20. We don't know why.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of people think about this genetic code is quite fascinating.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it didn't do it for four billion years. I don't know, we may wait for another four billion years, but.
SPEAKER_1:  But you didn't have those amino acids in the very beginning, right?
SPEAKER_0:  know. So we would be fooling ourselves if we said we know exactly how many amino acids existed.
SPEAKER_0:  But there's no reason to think that it wasn't the same.
SPEAKER_0:  or similar.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't have a good reason.
SPEAKER_0:  but because, roughly...
SPEAKER_0:  2 any out of 60 states are used you're using one third.
SPEAKER_0:  of your.
SPEAKER_0:  possible states in your information system.
SPEAKER_0:  So this may seem.
SPEAKER_0:  like a waste.
SPEAKER_0:  but informatically.
SPEAKER_0:  It's important because it's abundant and it is.
SPEAKER_0:  redundant.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? right?
SPEAKER_0:  degeneracy, you see this in
SPEAKER_0:  that's implemented by this translation machinery inside the cell.
SPEAKER_0:  So it means we can make errors, right? We can make errors.
SPEAKER_0:  but the message will still get through.
SPEAKER_0:  You can speak.
SPEAKER_0:  missing some letters to the information can miss some parts, but the message will.
SPEAKER_0:  still get through. So that's two thirds of the not used states gives you that robustness and resilience within the system.
SPEAKER_1:  So at the informatic level there's room for error. There's probably room for error probably in all five
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  categories we're talking about there's probably room for error in the computation that's probably room
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there's, yes, exactly. Everywhere there's room for error. Because the informatic capacity is made possible together with the other.
SPEAKER_0:  And not only that, but also the product yields.
SPEAKER_0:  function.
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_1:  Ehh
SPEAKER_1:  Baby.
SPEAKER_0:  In this case, enzyme or protein.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? So, so...
SPEAKER_0:  That's really amazing to me.
SPEAKER_1:  It is, I mean, in my head, just, you know, because I'm a computer science AI person.
SPEAKER_1:  the parallels between even like language models.
SPEAKER_1:  that encode language.
SPEAKER_1:  or now they're able to encode basically any kind of thing, including
SPEAKER_1:  images and actions.
SPEAKER_1:  all in this kind of way.
SPEAKER_1:  the parallel in terms of informatic and.
SPEAKER_1:  computation.
SPEAKER_1:  is just incredible.
SPEAKER_0:  Actually, I have a...
SPEAKER_0:  image, maybe I can send you. Can we pull it up now? If you just do genetic codon charts.
SPEAKER_0:  We can pull that off. Yeah, it's a very standard table.
SPEAKER_0:  So I can explain why this is so amazing.
SPEAKER_0:  So you're looking at, this is life's alphabet, right? And so I also want to make a very quick link now to your first question, the tree of life.
SPEAKER_0:  When we try to understand ancient.
SPEAKER_0:  languages, right? Or...
SPEAKER_0:  the cultures that use these extinct languages.
SPEAKER_0:  We start with the modern languages, right? So we look at.
SPEAKER_0:  Indo-European.
SPEAKER_0:  languages and try to understand certain words.
SPEAKER_0:  and make trees.
SPEAKER_0:  To understand, you know, this is what Slavic word is for snow.
SPEAKER_0:  something like snig.
SPEAKER_1:  Now we jump to languages that humans spoke.
SPEAKER_0:  Look, exactly. So we make trees.
SPEAKER_0:  to understand what is the original ancestor, what did they use?
SPEAKER_0:  to say snow.
SPEAKER_0:  You have a lot of cultures who use the word snow. You can imagine that.
SPEAKER_0:  It was snowy.
SPEAKER_0:  That's why they needed that word.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the same thing for
SPEAKER_0:  Biology, right? If they have some...
SPEAKER_0:  If we understand some function about that enzyme.
SPEAKER_0:  We can.
SPEAKER_0:  understand the environment that they lived in. It's the similar.
SPEAKER_0:  It's similar in that sense. So now you're looking at the alphabet.
SPEAKER_0:  In this case, it's not 20 or 25 letters.
SPEAKER_0:  You have.
SPEAKER_0:  Four letters.
SPEAKER_0:  So what is really interesting that stands out.
SPEAKER_0:  me when I look at this. On the outer shell, you're looking at the too many amino acids. That's compost life, right?
SPEAKER_0:  The one, the methionine.
SPEAKER_0:  that you see, that's the start. So the start is always the same.
SPEAKER_0:  To me, that is fascinating that all life starts with the same starts. There's no other start code.
SPEAKER_0:  So you sent the...
SPEAKER_0:  uh... a g you know a u g to the south that when that information arrives
SPEAKER_0:  Translation knows, all right, I gotta start.
SPEAKER_0:  Function is coming.
SPEAKER_0:  Following this is a chain of information.
SPEAKER_0:  until the stop.
SPEAKER_0:  code arrives which are.
SPEAKER_0:  highlights in black squares.
SPEAKER_1:  So for people just listening, we're looking at a standard RNA.
SPEAKER_1:  colored table organizing a wheel.
SPEAKER_1:  There's an outer shell and there's an inner shell all using the four letters that we're talking about with that.
SPEAKER_1:  compose.
SPEAKER_1:  all of the amino acids and there's a start.
SPEAKER_1:  And let's just stop.
SPEAKER_1:  and presumably you put together.
SPEAKER_1:  the with these letters you walk around the wheel to put together
SPEAKER_1:  Words.
SPEAKER_0:  sentences that make- Yeah, the words and sentences and-
SPEAKER_0:  Again, you get one start, you get three, there are three different ways to stop this. One way to start it.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  For each.
SPEAKER_0:  letter
SPEAKER_0:  You have multiple options. So you say you have a code A.
SPEAKER_0:  The second code can be another A.
SPEAKER_0:  And even if you mess that up...
SPEAKER_0:  You still can't rescue yourself. So you can get, for instance, I'm looking at the lysine K.
SPEAKER_0:  You get an A and you get an A and then you get an A that gives you the lysine.
SPEAKER_0:  Right. But if you get an A, and if you get an A and then get a G, you still get the license. So there are different combinations. So even if there's an error, we don't know if these are selected because they were error-ness and somehow they got locked down.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't know if there is air.
SPEAKER_0:  mechanism behind this to orbit.
SPEAKER_0:  We certainly don't know this definitively.
SPEAKER_0:  This is Informatic.
SPEAKER_0:  And notice that the colors.
SPEAKER_0:  And in some tables too, the colors will be...
SPEAKER_0:  coded in a way that the type of the nucleotides can be similar chemically.
SPEAKER_0:  But the point is that you will still end up with the same.
SPEAKER_0:  amino acids or something similar to it, even if you mess up the code.
SPEAKER_1:  Do we understand the mechanism how natural selection interplays with this?
SPEAKER_1:  Resilience to error.
SPEAKER_1:  So which errors.
SPEAKER_1:  Result in the same.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  output like
SPEAKER_1:  the same function and which don't.
SPEAKER_1:  which actually results in a dysfunction which
SPEAKER_0:  We understand to some degree the
SPEAKER_0:  how translation and the rest of the cell work together.
SPEAKER_0:  have an error at the translation level. This is the really core level can impact.
SPEAKER_0:  entire self.
SPEAKER_0:  but we understand very little about the evolutionary mechanisms behind the selection.
SPEAKER_0:  of the system.
SPEAKER_0:  It's.
SPEAKER_0:  thought to be one of the hardest problems in biology, and it is still the dark side of biology, even though it is so...
SPEAKER_0:  essential.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is, yeah, you're looking at the.
SPEAKER_0:  language of life, so to speak, and how it can.
SPEAKER_0:  found ways rather to...
SPEAKER_0:  tolerates its own.
SPEAKER_0:  Mistakes.
SPEAKER_1:  Diaphylogenetic tree.
SPEAKER_1:  can be deconstructed with this wheel of language.
SPEAKER_0:  Because all the final letters, that's the 20 amino acids, that's our alphabet.
SPEAKER_0:  brought.
SPEAKER_0:  together with these bits of information, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So when you look at the genes, you're looking at those four letters. When you look at the proteins, you're looking at the 20 amino acids.
SPEAKER_0:  which may be a little easier way to track the information when we create.
SPEAKER_0:  the tree
SPEAKER_1:  So using this language.
SPEAKER_1:  can describe all life that's lived on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  I wish.
SPEAKER_0:  perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  We are not that good at it yet, right?
SPEAKER_1:  point theory.
SPEAKER_1:  This is one way to look at life on earth.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're a biologist and you want to understand
SPEAKER_0:  how life evolved from a molecular perspective, this would be the way.
SPEAKER_0:  to do it.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is what nature narrowed its code down to. So maybe think of nitrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  when we think of carbon, when we think of sulfur.
SPEAKER_0:  It's all in this.
SPEAKER_0:  nucleotides are built based on those elements.
SPEAKER_1:  And this is fundamentally the informatic perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly. That's the informatics.
SPEAKER_0:  perspective and it's important to emphasize that this is not engineered by
SPEAKER_0:  Humans.
SPEAKER_0:  this evolved by itself.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, right, humans didn't invent this just because we were just describing, we're trying to find-
SPEAKER_1:  trying to describe the language of life.
SPEAKER_0:  It appears to be...
SPEAKER_0:  highly optimized.
SPEAKER_0:  chemical and information code.
SPEAKER_0:  It may indicate that a great deal of...
SPEAKER_0:  chemical evolution and...
SPEAKER_0:  and this may
SPEAKER_0:  indicate that a lot of selection pressure and Darwinian evolution happened prior to the rise of last universal common ancestor.
SPEAKER_0:  because this is almost a bridge that connects the earliest cells to the last universal common ancestor.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, can you describe what the heck you just said? So this?
SPEAKER_1:  mechanism evolved before.
SPEAKER_1:  The what?
SPEAKER_1:  common ancestor, the last.
SPEAKER_0:  universal common sense. When we talk about the tree, when we think about the root, if you...
SPEAKER_0:  Ideally
SPEAKER_0:  Ehh
SPEAKER_0:  included all the living information, all the available information that comes from living organisms.
SPEAKER_0:  on your tree.
SPEAKER_0:  then at the root of your tree lies the last universal common ancestor, Luka.
SPEAKER_1:  Why last?
SPEAKER_1:  Last universal.
SPEAKER_1:  because the earlier universe, it also had trees, but they all died off.
SPEAKER_0:  We call it the last because it is
SPEAKER_0:  sort of the first one that we can track.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  because we cannot.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't know what we cannot track.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? One.
SPEAKER_1:  There's one organism.
SPEAKER_1:  that started the whole thing.
SPEAKER_0:  It's-
SPEAKER_0:  more like a I would think of it as more like a population a group of organisms
SPEAKER_1:  I tweeted this so I want to know the accuracy of my tweet. Alright.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_1:  Sometimes early in the morning I tweet very pothead like things.
SPEAKER_1:  I said that.
SPEAKER_1:  We all evolved.
SPEAKER_1:  from.
SPEAKER_1:  one.
SPEAKER_1:  common ancestor that was a single cell organism.
SPEAKER_1:  3.5 billion years ago.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... something like this
SPEAKER_1:  How?
SPEAKER_1:  How true is that tweet? Do I need to delete it? No, there's-
SPEAKER_1:  actually correct. I mean, I think of course there's a lot to say which is like we don't know exactly.
SPEAKER_1:  But to what degrees the single organism aspect is that true?
SPEAKER_1:  versus multiple organisms. Do you want me to be?
SPEAKER_1:  Brutally honest, yes please.
SPEAKER_1:  this.
SPEAKER_1:  Ha!
SPEAKER_1:  There's still time.
SPEAKER_1:  This is how we get like caveats.
SPEAKER_0:  and tweets. All right. So first of all, it's not. It's not.
SPEAKER_0:  3.5 is still a very conservative estimate. That's the first one. First direction.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say it's 3.8 is probably...
SPEAKER_0:  safer to say at this point. The point just people said...
SPEAKER_0:  probably wait before that. If you put an approximate, I'll take that.
SPEAKER_1:  I didn't. I just love the idea.
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  I was once.
SPEAKER_1:  First of all...
SPEAKER_1:  as a single organism.
SPEAKER_1:  I was once a cell.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you're still less.
SPEAKER_0:  you're a group of cells.
SPEAKER_1:  No, but I started from a single self.
SPEAKER_0:  Me, Lex. You mean like you-
SPEAKER_0:  versus Luca. Are you relating to Luca right now?
SPEAKER_1:  to my
SPEAKER_0:  Your own development.
SPEAKER_1:  my own development I started from a single cell.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like, it like built up and stuff, okay. That-
SPEAKER_1:  And then so that's a for single.
SPEAKER_1:  biological organs and then from an evolutionary perspective, the Luca.
SPEAKER_1:  I start like my ancestors a single cell.
SPEAKER_1:  And then here I am sitting half asleep.
SPEAKER_1:  tweeting.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I started from a single cell evolved a ton of murder along the way.
SPEAKER_1:  Delete this...
SPEAKER_1:  Brutal.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, search
SPEAKER_1:  for...
SPEAKER_1:  adaptation.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's the 3.5.
SPEAKER_1:  point eight billion.
SPEAKER_0:  So you defy the code of Douglas Adams. You are proud of your ancestors and you invite them over to dinner and you invite them over to your Twitter.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and it's amazing that this intelligence.
SPEAKER_1:  to the degree you can call it intelligence emerged to be able to tweet whatever the heck
SPEAKER_0:  I want. Yes, it's almost intelligence at the chemical level. And this is also.
SPEAKER_0:  probably one of the first.
SPEAKER_0:  chemically intelligent.
SPEAKER_0:  system that evolved by itself.
SPEAKER_0:  in nature.
SPEAKER_1:  So you see that translation is in a fundamental way.
SPEAKER_1:  intelligent mechanism.
SPEAKER_0:  in its own way and again, the
SPEAKER_0:  if we manage to figure out how to drive.
SPEAKER_0:  of life's evolution.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... in in it's ken
SPEAKER_0:  if it can evolve.
SPEAKER_0:  a sophisticated sort of informatic.
SPEAKER_0:  um
SPEAKER_0:  processing system like this.
SPEAKER_0:  you may ask yourself what might chemical systems...
SPEAKER_0:  be capable of.
SPEAKER_0:  independently doing.
SPEAKER_0:  100.
SPEAKER_0:  different circumstances.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so like locally, they're intelligent locally. They don't need the rest of the shebang. Like they don't need the big.
SPEAKER_0:  They need so that that's.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a great.
SPEAKER_0:  segue into what makes this biological.
SPEAKER_0:  The heart of the cellular activities are translation. You kill translation, you kill the cell.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes. The transition itself, you kill.
SPEAKER_0:  Ehh...
SPEAKER_0:  component that initiates it, you kill the cell. You kill, you remove the component that elongates it, you kill the cell.
SPEAKER_0:  So there are many different ways to disrupt this machinery. All the parts are important.
SPEAKER_0:  Now, it can vary across different organisms. We see variation between bacteria versus eukaryotes versus archaea, right? So it is not the same exact steps, but...
SPEAKER_0:  it can get more crowded.
SPEAKER_0:  as we get closer to eukaryotes, for instance.
SPEAKER_0:  but you are still computing about 20 amino acids per second. This is what you're generating every second.
SPEAKER_1:  that single machinery is doing 20 a second.
SPEAKER_0:  21 for bacteria, I believe 8 for eukaryotes or 9.
SPEAKER_1:  21 a second.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, that's super inefficient or super efficient depending on how you think about it.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's great.
SPEAKER_1:  I bet it's way slower than a computer.
SPEAKER_1:  could generate.
SPEAKER_0:  Is there simulation? I think-
SPEAKER_0:  If you can show me a computer that does this, we are done here.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, this is the big, this includes the five things.
SPEAKER_1:  Not just, but I could show you a computer that's doing the informatic.
SPEAKER_1:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  I guess you can show me that, but you cannot show me the one that has all.
SPEAKER_0:  For now.
SPEAKER_1:  For now. I will ask you about probably what, alfa-fold right?
SPEAKER_0:  I think the more we learn about, and this is why early life and origin is also very fascinating and applicable to many different disciplines. There is no way you see this the way we just described it, unless you think about early life and origin.
SPEAKER_0:  Early Geochemistry.
SPEAKER_0:  and earliest emergent systems.
SPEAKER_0:  but going.
SPEAKER_0:  going back to.
SPEAKER_0:  the biological component.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  All of these.
SPEAKER_0:  attributes that we think about.
SPEAKER_0:  Life.
SPEAKER_0:  or that we associate with biology, stems.
SPEAKER_0:  from translation and as well as metabolism.
SPEAKER_0:  I see metabolism as a way to keep translation going and translation keeps metabolism going.
SPEAKER_0:  Translation is arguably a bit more sophisticated process for the reasons that
SPEAKER_0:  I just described.
SPEAKER_1:  So metabolism is a source of energy for this translation process.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a way to process materials and it is inherently dynamic.
SPEAKER_0:  And it is flexible, but it is not focused on repetition as translation does. So that's the main difference. Translation is the kind of in a way just it's repeats, right? So.
SPEAKER_0:  You have the metabolism that can synthesize materials.
SPEAKER_0:  it creates or benefits from available energy.
SPEAKER_0:  And again, it's a dynamic system.
SPEAKER_0:  And then you have competition that it's.
SPEAKER_0:  that is inherently repetitive, right, needs to carry out repetitive processes.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... it and it
SPEAKER_0:  does the tasks and it implements an algorithm, but it is not dynamic.
SPEAKER_0:  So you see both of those attributes in translation combined. It is repetitive.
SPEAKER_0:  And it is dynamic.
SPEAKER_0:  and it also processes this information. So they are fundamentally different.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if you can get...
SPEAKER_0:  life if you don't find a way to process the information around you.
SPEAKER_1:  in a repetitive dynamic way.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and somehow that's what's got.
SPEAKER_0:  um, selected, maybe not selected. I don't know if it was.
SPEAKER_0:  accidental, but that's what it seems to be.
SPEAKER_0:  conserved for four billion years, that that's what life.
SPEAKER_0:  established.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the connection between translation and the self replication which seems to be a
SPEAKER_1:  another weird thing that life just started doing.
SPEAKER_1:  wanting to just replicate.
SPEAKER_0:  I think when we truly understand the answer to that question, we may have just made ourselves life, right? Something we know quite.
SPEAKER_0:  How?
SPEAKER_0:  Translation machinery as a whole.
SPEAKER_0:  fits into equation.
SPEAKER_0:  So we try to understand.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Ribosomes.
SPEAKER_0:  RNA, how the linear information is processed.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  Or the genetic code, why this codon's not others, why 20 not more, not less.
SPEAKER_0:  And we are sort of moving towards transition. That's what we're working on anyway.
SPEAKER_0:  to finally look at the patterns in which the system.
SPEAKER_0:  operates itself.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you understand that, you're really unlocking a very emergent behavior.
SPEAKER_1:  I, one of the things you didn't mention is.
SPEAKER_1:  physical.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there something to mention about that component that's interesting?
SPEAKER_0:  There's actually a paper.
SPEAKER_0:  published in 2013, I want to say the first author is Zirnoff.
SPEAKER_0:  So they
SPEAKER_0:  Surveys.
SPEAKER_0:  a computational.
SPEAKER_0:  engineered, systems level.
SPEAKER_0:  computation, energy consumption.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, and they-
SPEAKER_0:  Try to understand whether the universe
SPEAKER_0:  is using its own or life is using its full capacity of energy consumption.
SPEAKER_0:  and whether if different planets in the universe had life, would the capacity would increase or decrease? Does life operate at its energy maximum?
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  And they think that it does, that it actually.
SPEAKER_0:  operates at an efficiency that is far more
SPEAKER_0:  above and beyond any computational.
SPEAKER_1:  How is that possible to determine at all?
SPEAKER_0:  That you tell me. That's why I dropped the citation. I found the citation. It's quite an interesting paper.
SPEAKER_0:  Hey
SPEAKER_0:  And it's a.
SPEAKER_0:  Obviously, you can only calculate an infer these things.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... but uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Good question to ask.
SPEAKER_1:  is dull life.
SPEAKER_1:  that we see here on earth and life elsewhere in the universe? Is it using
SPEAKER_1:  the energy.
SPEAKER_1:  Most efficiently. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it seems to be very efficient again if we compare to computers. It seems to be incredibly
SPEAKER_1:  Efficient
SPEAKER_0:  I think they look at the theoretical optimum for electronic devices and then try to understand where life falls on this and life is...
SPEAKER_0:  certainly more efficient.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's ultimately the physical side. How well are you using for this entire mechanism?
SPEAKER_1:  the energy available to you.
SPEAKER_1:  And so given.
SPEAKER_1:  given all the resilience to errors and all that kind of stuff, it seems that it's close to its maximum.
SPEAKER_1:  And this paper aside, it does seem.
SPEAKER_1:  the life obviously that's the constraint
SPEAKER_1:  we have on earth, right, is the amount of energy.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's one way to define life.
SPEAKER_1:  The input is energy.
SPEAKER_1:  And the output is what? I don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  self-replicating.
SPEAKER_1:  Wait, okay, let's go there. How do you personally define life? Do you have a-
SPEAKER_1:  Do you have a favorite definition?
SPEAKER_1:  You try to sneak up on?
SPEAKER_1:  Um,
SPEAKER_1:  Is it possible?
SPEAKER_1:  I define life.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know. It depends on what you are defining it for. If you're defining it for...
SPEAKER_0:  finding different life forms, then it probably needs to have some quantification.
SPEAKER_0:  in it so that you can.
SPEAKER_0:  use it in whatever the mission that you're operating.
SPEAKER_1:  You mean like it's not binary, it's uh...
SPEAKER_1:  This is like a seven out of ten.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, uh, uh, no.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know. I don't think that-
SPEAKER_0:  defining is that essential? I think it's a good exercise.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not sure if we need to.
SPEAKER_0:  Agree.
SPEAKER_0:  a universally defined way of understanding life.
SPEAKER_0:  Because the definition itself seems to be ever evolving anyway, right? We have the NASA's definition. It's, it's, it's.
SPEAKER_0:  It has its
SPEAKER_0:  minuses and pluses, but it seems to be doing its job.
SPEAKER_1:  But what are the different if there is a line?
SPEAKER_1:  and it's.
SPEAKER_1:  impossible or unproductive to define that line.
SPEAKER_1:  Nevertheless, we know it when we see it.
SPEAKER_1:  is one definition.
SPEAKER_1:  that the Supreme Court likes.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's it.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of an important thing to...
SPEAKER_1:  to think about when we look at life on other planets.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  How do we?
SPEAKER_1:  to identify if a thing is living when we go to Mars when we go to
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  the different moons.
SPEAKER_1:  in our solar system, we would go outside our solar system to look for life.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. On other planets. It's unlikely to be a-
SPEAKER_0:  sort of smoking gun event, right? It's not going to be, hey, I found this. You don't think so? I don't think so, unless you find an elephant on.
SPEAKER_0:  some exoplanet, then I can say, yeah, there's life here.
SPEAKER_1:  No, but is there a dynamic?
SPEAKER_1:  Nature did the thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  It moves.
SPEAKER_1:  It has...
SPEAKER_1:  A membrane that
SPEAKER_1:  looks like there's stuff inside.
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't make no move, right? I mean, like look at plants.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, they grow, but there are plants that are.
SPEAKER_0:  can be also pretty dormant.
SPEAKER_0:  Arguably there.
SPEAKER_0:  They do everything that is one of my...
SPEAKER_0:  favorite professors once said that the plant does everything that a giraffe does without moving.
SPEAKER_0:  So movement is not necessarily.
SPEAKER_1:  But on a certain time scale, the plant does move. It just moves slower.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes. It moves pretty quickly. I would say that. It's hard to quantify this or even measure it, but it is a.
SPEAKER_0:  Life is definitely...
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  chemistry finding solutions, right? So it is chemistry exploring itself.
SPEAKER_0:  and maintaining this exploration for billions of years.
SPEAKER_1:  So, okay, so a planet.
SPEAKER_1:  is a bunch of chemistry.
SPEAKER_1:  And then you run it and say, all right.
SPEAKER_1:  figure out what...
SPEAKER_1:  what cool stuff you can come up with. that's essentially what life is.
SPEAKER_1:  Given a chemistry, what is the cool stuff I can come up?
SPEAKER_0:  If that chemistry or the solutions that it's...
SPEAKER_0:  embarks upon.
SPEAKER_0:  are maintained in a form of memory.
SPEAKER_0:  Right. So you don't just need to have the...
SPEAKER_0:  exploring chemical space, but you need to also maintain a memory of some of those.
SPEAKER_0:  solutions for over.
SPEAKER_0:  long periods of time.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's.
SPEAKER_0:  the memory components.
SPEAKER_0:  makes it more living to me.
SPEAKER_0:  Because chemistry can always sample, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Chemistry is chemistry.
SPEAKER_0:  but are you just constantly sampling or are you building on?
SPEAKER_0:  your former solutions and then maintaining a memory of those solutions over billions of years or at least that's what happened here.
SPEAKER_1:  how much you can't build life if it's always living in the moment
SPEAKER_1:  the physicist will be very upset with you.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  So memory could be.
SPEAKER_1:  fundamental.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, life is obviously chemistry and physics.
SPEAKER_0:  leading to...
SPEAKER_0:  So this is not a disciplinary.
SPEAKER_0:  problem of one discipline.
SPEAKER_0:  trying playing other disciplines. But what you need to have is definitely, chemistry is everywhere, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Tent a thing you can be a c-
SPEAKER_0:  chemists, you can study chemistry, you can study physics, you can study geology anywhere in the universe, but this is the only place you can study biology.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the only place to be a biologist. This poor guy.
SPEAKER_0:  That's it.
SPEAKER_0:  So definitely something very fundamental happened here and you cannot take biology out of the equation if you want to understand how that vast chemistry space.
SPEAKER_0:  of that general.
SPEAKER_0:  sequence space.
SPEAKER_0:  got narrowed down to what is available.
SPEAKER_0:  or what is used by life.
SPEAKER_0:  you need to understand the rules of selection. And that's when evolution and biology come.
SPEAKER_1:  So the rules of natural selection operate to you on the level of biology?
SPEAKER_0:  Rules, I don't know if there are any rules like that. It would be fascinating to find in terms of the biology's rules. They're onlyinaudible.
SPEAKER_0:  very interesting and
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  It's a very fascinating area of study now, and probably we will hear more about that.
SPEAKER_0:  decades to come. A
SPEAKER_0:  if you wanna go from the broad to specific.
SPEAKER_0:  you need to understand the rules of selection. And that is going to come from understanding biology, yes.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, actually, let me ask you about...
SPEAKER_1:  selection you have a paper on evolutionary stalling.
SPEAKER_1:  where you describe that evolution is not good at multitasking.
SPEAKER_1:  or like in populations that have.
SPEAKER_1:  evolve quickly.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a very specific thing, but there could be a generalizable fundamental thing to this.
SPEAKER_1:  that evolution is not able to improve multiple modules simultaneously.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess the question is...
SPEAKER_1:  What part of the organism does evolution...
SPEAKER_1:  quote unquote focus on to improve.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that was the driving question.
SPEAKER_0:  We meddled with...
SPEAKER_0:  the part where you shouldn't be messing up with translation.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the... Should or should not.
SPEAKER_0:  You shouldn't. As I said, there are many ways to break it and all life needs it. And there are some, oh, there's just so many ways
SPEAKER_1:  One of your favorite things to do is to break life, see what happens.
SPEAKER_0:  It's yeah, because that's how kids learn. Right. So you have to break something and see how it's.
SPEAKER_0:  Then you do it over and over again to see if it will...
SPEAKER_0:  fix itself in the same ways.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's our, I don't know, it's the most fundamental properties of our.
SPEAKER_0:  ourselves as human beings.
SPEAKER_0:  So if we shouldn't break translation, then we should try to break it to see how it will repair. So let's try to break it to see how it will repair.
SPEAKER_1:  break.
SPEAKER_0:  I broke elongation.
SPEAKER_1:  So what's the role of elongation in this process?
SPEAKER_0:  So we have four steps of the transitions, initiate, elongate. So elongate the chain of the information chain that you're now creating, the peptide chain.
SPEAKER_0:  or let's say broadly polymer chain.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's the termination step and there's the recycling. So all of these steps are.
SPEAKER_0:  carried out by proteins that are also named after these steps.
SPEAKER_0:  initiation.
SPEAKER_0:  is the initiation factor protein, elongation is the elongator protein.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, we, um,
SPEAKER_0:  broke.
SPEAKER_0:  elongation.
SPEAKER_0:  So the cell, the starting codon could still arrive to where it's supposed to be.
SPEAKER_0:  Go.
SPEAKER_0:  But the-
SPEAKER_0:  following.
SPEAKER_0:  information.
SPEAKER_0:  couldn't get carried out because we
SPEAKER_0:  replaced elongation.
SPEAKER_0:  with its own ancestral version. So we inserted.
SPEAKER_0:  roughly.
SPEAKER_0:  700 million year old.
SPEAKER_0:  elongation factor protein.
SPEAKER_0:  of turk.
SPEAKER_0:  removing.
SPEAKER_0:  Dude.
SPEAKER_0:  modern gene. So we made this ancient modern.
SPEAKER_0:  hybrid.
SPEAKER_0:  organism.
SPEAKER_1:  And that essentially creates in some way the ancient version of that organism.
SPEAKER_0:  I wouldn't say so. It's a hybrid organism. It's not necessary because the rest of the cell, the rest of the...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  genome is still.
SPEAKER_0:  Modern.
SPEAKER_0:  And that goes back to the difference between Jurassic Park.
SPEAKER_0:  There are many differences, obviously, given that this is not fiction, we're doing it.
SPEAKER_0:  but also we are not necessarily, I think in Jurassic Park they are taking
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  ancient or they find an ancient organism and then put in modern gene inside the ancient organism. In our case we are still working with what we got.
SPEAKER_0:  putting an ancestral DNA inside the modern organism.
SPEAKER_1:  So you're like taking a new car and putting an old engine into it.
SPEAKER_0:  In a way, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes. In the magician's shop.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, but in our case, it's more like a transformer than just a regular car.
SPEAKER_0:  doing things.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so it's a more complicated organism than just a car. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I got it. So what does that teach you?
SPEAKER_0:  We wanted to understand multiple things. One is how does the cell respond to perturbation?
SPEAKER_0:  And we didn't just put the ancient DNA, we inserted, we sampled DNA from currently existing organisms, so the cousins of this microbe.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  collected DNA sequences from the cousins as well.
SPEAKER_0:  So both ancestor and the...
SPEAKER_0:  current cousin.
SPEAKER_0:  DNA, so to speak.
SPEAKER_0:  and engineered all of these things to the modern bacteria and generated a collection.
SPEAKER_0:  of microbes.
SPEAKER_0:  that either have the ancient
SPEAKER_0:  component or the variant.
SPEAKER_0:  elongator component that
SPEAKER_0:  STILL
SPEAKER_0:  alive today, but...
SPEAKER_0:  coming from a different part of the tree.
SPEAKER_1:  So you broke elongation.
SPEAKER_1:  Was that something you did as part of the paper on evolutionary stalling to try to figure out?
SPEAKER_1:  how evolution figures out what to try to improve.
SPEAKER_1:  Did that help?
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, because we were not supposed to.
SPEAKER_0:  Messed with the translation. That's exactly what we did.
SPEAKER_0:  and we.
SPEAKER_0:  altered.
SPEAKER_0:  Elongation. My mind's at your service.
SPEAKER_0:  changing it with
SPEAKER_0:  different versions of elongation that are either coming from...
SPEAKER_0:  species.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  still are around today.
SPEAKER_0:  You can imagine them as sitting on the tips of the tree.
SPEAKER_0:  near.
SPEAKER_0:  branch for our branch.
SPEAKER_0:  compared to the organism that we're working with.
SPEAKER_0:  Cousins, distant cousins.
SPEAKER_0:  as well as the ancestors of the bacteria that we are now modifying.
SPEAKER_1:  How much different variation is there in that elongation step? Like what are the different flavors of elongation?
SPEAKER_0:  That's a very good question. So-
SPEAKER_0:  mechanistically or mechanically, it's the same. It's very conserved. So all life elongates the same way. You are, it's nothing but a shuttle. You just carry.
SPEAKER_0:  and...
SPEAKER_0:  Chemical with you.
SPEAKER_0:  the bits.
SPEAKER_0:  too.
SPEAKER_0:  the heart of the machine.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it essentially doing like a copy paste operation?
SPEAKER_0:  It has its tail.
SPEAKER_0:  that's attached to...
SPEAKER_0:  thing.
SPEAKER_0:  code.
SPEAKER_0:  which is then carried biochemically to the...
SPEAKER_0:  linear chain to the core of ribosome.
SPEAKER_0:  and it sits on there.
SPEAKER_0:  It's released in the peptides.
SPEAKER_0:  Click.
SPEAKER_0:  the codes rather click.
SPEAKER_0:  once that.
SPEAKER_0:  chemistry that is at the tail end, occurs the protein.
SPEAKER_0:  LEAVES DAY.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  So you can imagine it's like it hops in there and hops out. And when it hops in up south, it leaves the information behind.
SPEAKER_0:  That's all it does is bring the information, get out of there.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's all triggered by biophysics, biochemistry.
SPEAKER_0:  Because of the way the enzyme choose energy in this case gtp how the fast for leaves the center that kicks that gives the.
SPEAKER_0:  additional kick.
SPEAKER_0:  to the enzyme to leave.
SPEAKER_0:  the center.
SPEAKER_1:  to which parts are different then? where's the flavors of different flavors?
SPEAKER_0:  Go to K, not reeve Pepp excessive Especially in drips Eh Have got cash Erm eh That brings out my
SPEAKER_0:  usually the parts that matter don't change over time.
SPEAKER_0:  Nature conserves the sites of these proteins that are important for its job.
SPEAKER_0:  if there's a difference than V
SPEAKER_0:  we wanna know, especially if there's a difference between.
SPEAKER_0:  cousins.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  We look at the sites that interact with the most important.
SPEAKER_0:  parts of this machinery.
SPEAKER_0:  If we see any difference, we tend to mutate or we revert, we engineer that part, we alter that part because it gives us the clue that...
SPEAKER_0:  there must be something interesting going on here or not.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so that's not the fundamental part of the machinery, but it's some.
SPEAKER_1:  flavorful characteristic that you can play with.
SPEAKER_0:  So now you stripped the machinery down to its parts and now you're looking at the parts of the parts.
SPEAKER_0:  And it depends where you're looking and how you're looking and what you're looking at.
SPEAKER_0:  but usually we see.
SPEAKER_0:  up to 70% level.
SPEAKER_0:  conserved identity across all.
SPEAKER_0:  Modern.
SPEAKER_0:  versions.
SPEAKER_0:  when you travel back in time, identity decreases.
SPEAKER_0:  elongation likely existed. We have good reason to think that it existed at the dawn of life. So you're looking at a 3.8 billion year old.
SPEAKER_0:  mechanism.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And when we look at the ancestors that we resurrect, we see about 40% identity. So the identity definitely decreases.
SPEAKER_0:  as you go back in time, but still 60%.
SPEAKER_0:  Shared information over 4 billion years.
SPEAKER_0:  It's pretty good.
SPEAKER_1:  is that just for elongation for the entire translation.
SPEAKER_0:  depends on what you do.
SPEAKER_0:  So for initiation, we've also recently published this. It's a different story.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, but.
SPEAKER_0:  Overall, you see high level of identity.
SPEAKER_0:  that is kept intact, especially if the component is essential for life. Okay, so...
SPEAKER_1:  40% and 60, 70% he said, but like from generation to generation, how does evolution?
SPEAKER_1:  and presumably that's what that paper is looking at is the parts of the parts the
SPEAKER_1:  Haru-zu
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh...
SPEAKER_1:  able to say like mess with the parts and try to come up with a cooler improved.
SPEAKER_0:  version of the organism. Yeah, so let me describe to you what we did in that experiment. We took.
SPEAKER_0:  different, we took bacteria, we...
SPEAKER_0:  the elongation in all of these with different variants. So we had an initial set of
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  group.
SPEAKER_0:  bacteria that we had.
SPEAKER_0:  We then subjected these bacteria to evolution in the lab.
SPEAKER_0:  All right, so we.
SPEAKER_0:  First of all, we knew we broke it because upon engineering we measured.
SPEAKER_0:  What's going on with the cell? It's not growing as well. They're not healthy. We can see it with our eyes. We can measure it.
SPEAKER_0:  that if they were generating an offspring every 20 minutes, now it is 40 minutes. So we really messed them up. They don't wanna-
SPEAKER_0:  work.
SPEAKER_0:  with this thing day.
SPEAKER_0:  don't want each other, but they need each other. So we created that situation for them.
SPEAKER_0:  which is.
SPEAKER_0:  good because we want...
SPEAKER_0:  to see how we wanted to see how they will.
SPEAKER_0:  cooperate with each other.
SPEAKER_0:  to fix this problem.
SPEAKER_0:  because we know that that's not the condition that they want to live in.
SPEAKER_0:  especially when they know what they can do.
SPEAKER_0:  So with that, we subjected this.
SPEAKER_0:  organisms to evolution in the lab.
SPEAKER_0:  That's...
SPEAKER_0:  We refer to this as experimental evolution. We subject bacteria.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  different selection pressure.
SPEAKER_0:  project them through bottlenecks.
SPEAKER_0:  Everyday we...
SPEAKER_0:  randomly collect.
SPEAKER_0:  a handful of bacteria from the flask.
SPEAKER_0:  give them, put them in a new fresh environment with fresh food.
SPEAKER_0:  keep them in this environment for 24 hours until they reach a more dormant state.
SPEAKER_0:  subject introduced them to an even environment. A
SPEAKER_0:  repeated this for about it.
SPEAKER_0:  I will say 150 days.
SPEAKER_0:  of every day.
SPEAKER_0:  Not non-stop. We repeated this experiment.
SPEAKER_1:  Some kind of
SPEAKER_1:  how much
SPEAKER_1:  how many different kinds of environments are there.
SPEAKER_0:  We kept the environments to the same because we had different initial conditions. We kept the environment constant.
SPEAKER_0:  Same temperature, same food, same source of...
SPEAKER_0:  carbon.
SPEAKER_0:  but we created replicates for each.
SPEAKER_0:  So in some ways we created our own fossil record.
SPEAKER_0:  in the lab by evolving and generating these flasks and every.
SPEAKER_0:  in every step of the way we all saw.
SPEAKER_0:  froze these cells and took stacks of them in the cryopresence.
SPEAKER_1:  How long does it take to go from one generation to the next of bacteria?
SPEAKER_0:  If you, for E. coli, it's usually 20 minutes.
SPEAKER_0:  Great, so.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the experiment. That's the experiment. And in your
SPEAKER_1:  You're always messing it.
SPEAKER_1:  with it in the same way.
SPEAKER_1:  the initial.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the same way. So we introduce variation at the elongation level because...
SPEAKER_0:  So because we perdubbed it with different elongations, we found that if we introduce
SPEAKER_0:  different protein that is very different.
SPEAKER_0:  The cells.
SPEAKER_0:  don't like that, right? So if the distance is larger, the
SPEAKER_0:  consequences.
SPEAKER_0:  also large.
SPEAKER_0:  meaning that you hit them harder if you introduce a variant that is really foreign to them, that's really distant.
SPEAKER_0:  in our case, was the ancestor. They really did not like the ancestor.
SPEAKER_0:  but they were okay with their nearest cousin.
SPEAKER_1:  Right, okay, great. So you did vary in the distance.
SPEAKER_0:  We varied it to this evolutionary distance and then we kept the experimental conditions the same.
SPEAKER_0:  and we propagated these populations every day.
SPEAKER_0:  for 150 days.
SPEAKER_0:  and we collected bacteria every step of the way.
SPEAKER_0:  and looked at.
SPEAKER_0:  the sequence, we wanted to understand what sort of changes may have happened in the genome.
SPEAKER_0:  to respond to.
SPEAKER_0:  the variation that we've introduced.
SPEAKER_1:  So what kind of changes would you be seeing depending on the evolutionary distance of the thing you shoved into it?
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly. So we knew where we punched, right? We punched right at the heart.
SPEAKER_0:  We punched the translation.
SPEAKER_0:  We expect it. Is it going to be a translation?
SPEAKER_0:  Are we gonna see?
SPEAKER_0:  change the real translation respond to this by fixing itself right away.
SPEAKER_0:  or will it be?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  another outside of translation, something completely different, a different module, because translation itself is a module.
SPEAKER_0:  or would be within elongation at really sub protein level.
SPEAKER_0:  So we all.
SPEAKER_0:  had a strategy to identify.
SPEAKER_0:  the mutational pathways by categorizing.
SPEAKER_0:  what we expected to find or where.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so why?
SPEAKER_1:  does it not do multitasking?
SPEAKER_1:  Why is it not improving multiple things?
SPEAKER_0:  Why? Simultaneously.
SPEAKER_0:  Turned out that...
SPEAKER_0:  What we observed in general is that first of all the harder we...
SPEAKER_0:  hit the cells, the more likely they were to respond by changes right at where we
SPEAKER_1:  When you say hit it, you mean like change the something about it?
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't think of it as hitting because we are, I like to think of it as breaking the cell, right? I mean not breaking enough to kill it, but we still, because they're still alive, they're not doing their job well.
SPEAKER_1:  So the bigger the evolutionary distance.
SPEAKER_1:  of the thing you
SPEAKER_1:  put in there the heart of the hit is how you think about it. The bigger the hammer. The bigger the hammer.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what it turned out to be because that's what the data told us.
SPEAKER_0:  If the variation is higher, then the consequences will also be.
SPEAKER_0:  higher, in the sense that the cells will not grow as healthy compared to
SPEAKER_0:  a variant that is coming from a near evolutionary.
SPEAKER_1:  we can expect to be of interest. So will either be successful or not. But first let me point out the basic functionality for both the needs of the user text and the
SPEAKER_1:  Is it wrong to think of this kind of hitting as a...
SPEAKER_1:  akin to a mutation.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh no.
SPEAKER_1:  What are we supposed to learn from this hitting? How
SPEAKER_1:  how the thing evolves after it's being hit in this way. What does that teach us?
SPEAKER_0:  Because we see translation machinery as almost...
SPEAKER_0:  It is so conserved and so essential, it is not even clear whether we can remove some of the parts or whether the entire translation will need all of the same parts in the same efficiency.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't understand the rules of this machinery.
SPEAKER_0:  So the first thing we understand is that what is the resilience? What are we really talking about here when we talk about you cannot mess with this translation?
SPEAKER_0:  Is this true?
SPEAKER_0:  because it is so conserved and so similar and functions in the most conserved ways.
SPEAKER_0:  That was the first thing that we wanted to understand.
SPEAKER_1:  Did you learn anything interesting about the resilience at the chemical physical informatics
SPEAKER_0:  No, I wouldn't say that I think the biological level yes
SPEAKER_0:  because we found that the...
SPEAKER_0:  different modules started responding to the changes that we've introduced.
SPEAKER_0:  and that we could never recover.
SPEAKER_0:  translation as effectively as it used to be so that it never reached to
SPEAKER_0:  It is.
SPEAKER_0:  optimality, that it was always suboptimal. It needed, say, one more mutation perhaps to get there. It accumulated four mutations.
SPEAKER_0:  that was.
SPEAKER_0:  We did a lot of experiments to understand this, of course.
SPEAKER_0:  it was accumulating mutations, it was getting better at its task,
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe it needed
SPEAKER_0:  couple other mutations to get really good at it, but somehow those mutations never happened.
SPEAKER_0:  Before those mutations happened, we saw another module.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  emerging through mutations and getting better at its own different tasks. That is not translation.
SPEAKER_0:  You can think of cell as a web of networks, right? When we think of this as multiple almost.
SPEAKER_0:  Airports that are proteins that are more central hubs.
SPEAKER_0:  versus their proteins that maybe are not as important. If you.
SPEAKER_0:  In theory it's a problem in the most-
SPEAKER_0:  populated hubs.
SPEAKER_0:  you're going to mess up the traffic system more drastically. And that's what we were messing with in the biological terms.
SPEAKER_0:  as well.
SPEAKER_1:  So when we say module, like translation would be one of them.
SPEAKER_0:  Translation will be one. So you're-
SPEAKER_1:  Basically saying when you mess with translation
SPEAKER_1:  the organism.
SPEAKER_1:  would choose.
SPEAKER_1:  to either try to fix that module or another module.
SPEAKER_1:  depending exactly, but it wouldn't do multiple.
SPEAKER_0:  It wouldn't do multiple modules, it focused on one module at a time.
SPEAKER_0:  and right before that module maybe reached to its own maximum.
SPEAKER_0:  it's stalled, it's optimality at a certain degree. So you never get to a degree that is more optimal than you can achieve, even though perhaps another mutation could get you there.
SPEAKER_1:  Since you messed with the translation.
SPEAKER_1:  from a sort of optimal perspective with them.
SPEAKER_1:  Makes sense for the cell to try to start fixing the translation.
SPEAKER_0:  Not that's exactly what we thought. And it didn't, it was not the case for all the broken transition missionaries, for instance, if the.
SPEAKER_0:  variant was coming from a near ancestor that didn't happen.
SPEAKER_0:  It was almost cruising around trying different modules and sort of living its best life still.
SPEAKER_0:  because there is no real urgency in the system to fix the...
SPEAKER_1:  most important problem. And there's also not a direction.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, maybe to you it's obvious that's the problem with the cell
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe you're the problem. I'm living, like you said, my best life. Like, we don't, I mean, I guess that's the thing about evolution is we don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  What the right?
SPEAKER_1:  direction.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's almost like you can imagine that you have this messy closet and you know,
SPEAKER_1:  Go on.
SPEAKER_1:  happens to be an accurate representation of my life.
SPEAKER_0:  So you take a look at it and you see all the sweaters or jeans all over the place and then you look at a drawer that has socks.
SPEAKER_0:  coming out of it and you'd think that's the most important one I'm just gonna fix that one.
SPEAKER_0:  And then you fix that one and then you think you will get to the other one, but you don't because you just.
SPEAKER_0:  Fix the most important one, that is whatever that was getting into your way.
SPEAKER_0:  That's really what evolution is. It's quite lazy. It fixes the problem that seems to be the most immediate, and it doesn't go beyond what it really needs to. It seems like at least for our experimental setup, that was the case.
SPEAKER_1:  especially for rapidly evolving systems.
SPEAKER_1:  So like, is the environment they're operating pretty constrained?
SPEAKER_1:  Like, is there a-
SPEAKER_0:  I would say that we definitely constrain the environment.
SPEAKER_0:  removed from.
SPEAKER_0:  They are natural setup. We are not evolving them into guts.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a very homogeneous system, very controlled temperature, controlled food.
SPEAKER_0:  controlled carbon.
SPEAKER_1:  So just looking at that, let me ask the romantic question. How did evolution create so much beautiful, complex variety on Earth?
SPEAKER_1:  Like from that.
SPEAKER_1:  You're saying that we're talking about improving different modules, but if we step back and look at the entirety of the tree of the different organisms that created all throughout.
SPEAKER_1:  history.
SPEAKER_1:  the stuff that's fun to you with the first few billion and the stuff that's fun to me when I watch on YouTube, which is like the.
SPEAKER_1:  the lion versus gorilla fights and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  But the whole thing is fun, so all that beautiful variety from the predator and the prey.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh.
SPEAKER_1:  from the self-replicating bacteria and all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  How did it do it?
SPEAKER_0:  how is a very difficult question.
SPEAKER_0:  especially when we don't understand the past.
SPEAKER_0:  with clarity at all.
SPEAKER_0:  I-
SPEAKER_0:  can tell you that there seems to be very critical innovations that happened throughout the history of life.
SPEAKER_0:  that are each themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  this.
SPEAKER_0:  very sophisticated singularities that emerged once and then they said
SPEAKER_0:  the tone.
SPEAKER_0:  one of which is.
SPEAKER_0:  emergence of translation.
SPEAKER_0:  It's.
SPEAKER_0:  Seems like it happened once, it had to happen once.
SPEAKER_0:  Seems like that's all it took.
SPEAKER_0:  3.8 billion years, maybe older.
SPEAKER_0:  Clearly.
SPEAKER_0:  subjected to let off.
SPEAKER_0:  chemical evolution even prior to last universal common ancestor.
SPEAKER_0:  And then you...
SPEAKER_0:  Jump.
SPEAKER_0:  and you see.
SPEAKER_0:  emergence of
SPEAKER_0:  cyanobacteria.
SPEAKER_0:  that's undeniably changed the course.
SPEAKER_0:  of those planets.
SPEAKER_0:  in the subsequent.
SPEAKER_0:  Arabic
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  photosynthesis that life learned.
SPEAKER_0:  I have to...
SPEAKER_0:  utilize what's available in this environment in the most profound way.
SPEAKER_0:  and then you move forward, you see the emergence.
SPEAKER_0:  of eukaryotes to endosymbiosis.
SPEAKER_0:  Also another singular event.
SPEAKER_0:  and then you move forward and then comes the plants.
SPEAKER_0:  Desart.
SPEAKER_0:  I counted, I think, six different things.
SPEAKER_0:  that seems to have happened just once.
SPEAKER_1:  and singularity events in the history of evolution of life on earth.
SPEAKER_0:  What's really fascinating here is that there seems to be two different
SPEAKER_0:  courses, the time course.
SPEAKER_0:  evolution is operating at the molecular level. Right, we are talking about-
SPEAKER_0:  seconds. We're talking about mutations that happen every second. We're talking about selection that's also happening.
SPEAKER_0:  under a minute.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, so.
SPEAKER_0:  That is a very fast process. The fact that I can evolve bacteria in a lab.
SPEAKER_0:  And I.
SPEAKER_0:  say almost complaining me, oh my goodness, it took me 150 days.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean that's pretty rapid.
SPEAKER_0:  to for for a change to be seen.
SPEAKER_0:  But then the big changes and the ones that I'm talking, the really...
SPEAKER_0:  big innovations that caused an increase of...
SPEAKER_0:  oxygen on this planet or even its own mere presence.
SPEAKER_0:  are due to these molecular innovations.
SPEAKER_0:  seems to only happen a handful of times.
SPEAKER_0:  over billions of years of time scale.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask you this question.
SPEAKER_1:  having to deal with my half asleep tweet.
SPEAKER_1:  The saying that we all originated from one common ancestor.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  That's just one of them.
SPEAKER_1:  Miraculous things.
SPEAKER_1:  about life on earth. Of course you could say there's multiple common assessions in the beginning, multiple organisms and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  But the other stuff that you're talking about is these singular events.
SPEAKER_1:  these leaps of invention.
SPEAKER_1:  throughout evolutionary history.
SPEAKER_1:  Now there's a bunch of people who are commenting.
SPEAKER_1:  A bit surprising to me.
SPEAKER_1:  for watching.
SPEAKER_1:  basically skeptical of this idea.
SPEAKER_1:  Die, D.O.F.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I would say evolution, honestly.
SPEAKER_1:  process of evolution, but when you just actually focus in.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm like, holy crap.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  eukaryotes were invented holy crap photosynthesis was invented
SPEAKER_1:  Those are incredible inventions. And also-
SPEAKER_1:  We can even go to Homo sapiens, intelligence.
SPEAKER_1:  Like where did that come from? What are these mysteries?
SPEAKER_1:  I think with that.
SPEAKER_1:  skeptical comments are coming from.
SPEAKER_1:  or also just a general skepticism.
SPEAKER_1:  of science.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  from the pandemic, people, maybe a failure of institutions and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  I think the,
SPEAKER_1:  And there's been a growing distrust of science.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's not so much that it's anti-evolution.
SPEAKER_1:  It's more of a stepping back and saying.
SPEAKER_1:  Wait a minute.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe scientists don't have it all figured out.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  to Steel Man.
SPEAKER_1:  that case.
SPEAKER_1:  is.
SPEAKER_1:  Almost a step back and to realize there's so much mystery to each of these leaps
SPEAKER_1:  So it makes you wonder, is there something that in 100, 200 years we'll figure out?
SPEAKER_1:  that we totally don't understand yet.
SPEAKER_1:  like some, you know, there's.
SPEAKER_1:  I talked to a bunch of people, but...
SPEAKER_1:  another mystery which is consciousness.
SPEAKER_1:  All right, and there's.
SPEAKER_1:  People called panpsychists who believe
SPEAKER_1:  consciousness.
SPEAKER_1:  is one of the fundamental laws of the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  There could be a.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, like we have laws of physics that could be something.
SPEAKER_1:  That's.
SPEAKER_1:  like a consciousness field or something.
SPEAKER_1:  that permeates all matter.
SPEAKER_1:  And so like there might be.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  It's kind of like Newtonian physics versus general relativity.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, we have a good understanding.
SPEAKER_1:  of how things happen.
SPEAKER_1:  but we need another layer of understanding.
SPEAKER_1:  to fill in the gaps of the mysteries of it all.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  that sort of is a sobering reality that maybe there is something we really deeply don't understand. Do you have a sense of?
SPEAKER_1:  where the biggest mysteries here are.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it at the origin of life itself?
SPEAKER_1:  Is it the leaps?
SPEAKER_1:  that we're talking about. So you, you see the beauty.
SPEAKER_1:  You're fascinated by the translation mechanism.
SPEAKER_1:  What are the-
SPEAKER_1:  Deep mysteries there too.
SPEAKER_0:  We are nothing but chemical systems capable of.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  formulating or answering questions about our own existence.
SPEAKER_1:  We humans or all of life, you think?
SPEAKER_0:  Humans are, I mean, the fact that we can even have this conversation about...
SPEAKER_0:  Brbru
SPEAKER_0:  place in the universe is.
SPEAKER_0:  that this to our knowledge is quite specific to.
SPEAKER_0:  Ah, wrong chemical.
SPEAKER_0:  species.
SPEAKER_1:  It's kinda wild.
SPEAKER_1:  Good.
SPEAKER_1:  we're introspecting on our evolutionary history.
SPEAKER_1:  and we're just a couple of organisms.
SPEAKER_1:  would like another organism listening to this.
SPEAKER_1:  and like...
SPEAKER_1:  They're mind blown.
SPEAKER_1:  There's like three organisms.
SPEAKER_1:  Two of them talking and the third one's like, holy shit.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that understanding the...
SPEAKER_0:  What I really find interesting about understanding origin of life.
SPEAKER_0:  or even contemplating about our own place in the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  if at the end of this would come down to...
SPEAKER_0:  appreciating.
SPEAKER_0:  or even before appreciating, really truly comprehending.
SPEAKER_0:  what it is that we got here.
SPEAKER_0:  That to me is a huge gain.
SPEAKER_0:  Because there's...
SPEAKER_0:  No single...
SPEAKER_0:  question in biology, I think that will give that.
SPEAKER_0:  that will deliver that magnitude of that message and understanding.
SPEAKER_0:  But.
SPEAKER_0:  understanding how life here started at first place, if we truly comprehend that.
SPEAKER_0:  This is not a concept that is well thought.
SPEAKER_0:  in schools.
SPEAKER_0:  ask students to memorize these concepts if they are lucky they learned RNA World.
SPEAKER_0:  chicken and egg problem, et cetera. That's the extent to which maybe their biology teacher was personally interested in the subject matter.
SPEAKER_0:  if they're lucky.
SPEAKER_0:  You know the saying that...
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  Brains are...
SPEAKER_0:  evenly distributed.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  across any metric you can imagine, but...
SPEAKER_0:  Opportunities are not.
SPEAKER_0:  So if people aren't understanding...
SPEAKER_0:  The importance of this is because that's a lack of opportunity right there. That's.
SPEAKER_0:  It was skipped through.
SPEAKER_0:  proper education and training.
SPEAKER_0:  in the delivery of my
SPEAKER_0:  science matters or how science actually works.
SPEAKER_1:  But how do you even begin to...
SPEAKER_1:  Seriously?
SPEAKER_1:  Think about the origin of life.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  Every
SPEAKER_1:  problem.
SPEAKER_1:  of existence, of life.
SPEAKER_1:  has its time.
SPEAKER_1:  So I don't know if it's time to understand consciousness yet.
SPEAKER_1:  Who might be?
SPEAKER_1:  a hundred years away from that.
SPEAKER_1:  The Origin of Life
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if it's time for us to understand that yet. Maybe we need to solve so many more problems along the way.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not a competition of problems.
SPEAKER_0:  So there are
SPEAKER_0:  all kinds of problems and it takes a lot of people to make the world. So you will always have some
SPEAKER_0:  Interesting brain.
SPEAKER_0:  Going off the rim.
SPEAKER_0:  interesting problem to their own.
SPEAKER_0:  The issue here is that we need to first of all understand that
SPEAKER_0:  V.
SPEAKER_0:  What we have going on on this planet is pretty good.
SPEAKER_0:  Good planets are hard to find.
SPEAKER_0:  If we are alone in the universe, that's huge.
SPEAKER_0:  we need to take care of what we got here.
SPEAKER_0:  and we are incredibly vulnerable.
SPEAKER_0:  to the changes that our own species also helped create.
SPEAKER_0:  on at the biosphere at the ecosystem level.
SPEAKER_0:  We take it for granted. We take what we created for granted.
SPEAKER_0:  because of the fact that we think we are some sort of
SPEAKER_0:  ultimate endpoint.
SPEAKER_0:  the most sophisticated, amazing thing that nature could generate.
SPEAKER_0:  I think understanding
SPEAKER_0:  Not even understanding but-
SPEAKER_0:  asking these questions of
SPEAKER_0:  Where did this even come from?
SPEAKER_0:  How did this even begin?
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Attempting to understand that using chemistry and physics and biology
SPEAKER_0:  and because we can.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the ultimate gift we can give back to the entire species on this planet.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean it's humbling.
SPEAKER_1:  It's humbling to realize the complexity of this whole mechanism. It certainly puts humans in their proper perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  that were not.
SPEAKER_1:  just because we have brains and brains are intelligent.
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't mean
SPEAKER_1:  we're the most intelligent thing because ultimately the whole mechanism of nature seems to be orders and magnitude more intelligent. All of it, like we're a bunch of, we're like a hierarchy of organisms.
SPEAKER_1:  that have a history of several billion years.
SPEAKER_1:  and then all somehow came together to make a human.
SPEAKER_1:  and there'll be life after us.
SPEAKER_1:  just as was life before us, and something that comes after a bee.
SPEAKER_1:  Perhaps even more fascinating.
SPEAKER_0:  I think when you understand the magnitude of what happened here
SPEAKER_0:  There is no room for arrogance. It should overwhelm you and humiliate. It's pretty humiliating. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it's quite amazing what...
SPEAKER_0:  what happened here.
SPEAKER_0:  There is no other discipline that will.
SPEAKER_0:  deliver that, but exploring.
SPEAKER_0:  our own origins and looking at life as a more planetary system phenomena rather than.
SPEAKER_0:  one single species at a time, a collective look.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, you mentioned this question in your Ted talk is.
SPEAKER_1:  the two possibilities.
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  the Universe being full of life.
SPEAKER_1:  and the universe being empty and we're the only life in the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you feel about both options?
SPEAKER_1:  Just actually you as a single.
SPEAKER_1:  chemical organism introspecting about its existence in this.
SPEAKER_1:  world.
SPEAKER_0:  It's.
SPEAKER_0:  Having a planet full of life is interesting because there are...
SPEAKER_0:  We talked about...
SPEAKER_0:  life being all about chemistry exploring solutions.
SPEAKER_0:  and having solutions in front of you is great, it's beneficial.
SPEAKER_1:  solutions being different organisms like other humans you see them as a solution to a chemistry problem
SPEAKER_0:  different again
SPEAKER_1:  That's an interesting solution. That's not next time we were in Austin So there's a bunch of weirdos every time I see a weirdo. I feel like oh, that's an interesting solution to this chemistry problem
SPEAKER_1:  I'm going to...
SPEAKER_0:  Now you think like an origin of life science.
SPEAKER_1:  Funny that that one worked out.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's see where else it goes. But having-
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  emptiness and unpredictability.
SPEAKER_0:  off
SPEAKER_0:  uncovering a novel solution can also have its own benefits. And we should-
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  be open to.
SPEAKER_0:  what other solutions might be out there in exploring those solutions?
SPEAKER_1:  to different chemistry problems. So that's where you see the other planets out there as different chemistry problems.
SPEAKER_0:  to their own local environment, yes. So.
SPEAKER_1:  How many chemistry problems?
SPEAKER_1:  have solutions.
SPEAKER_1:  that are lifelike to you.
SPEAKER_1:  out there in the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a wide open palette if you think about it.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't quite know. It's the, we know the chemistry is chemistry.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think the chemistry will be different elsewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  But again, what is selected by chemistry will be determined.
SPEAKER_0:  by the environment most likely.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  There is life.
SPEAKER_1:  Everywhere.
SPEAKER_1:  there.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's a guy named Nick Lane.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  Gut.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's interesting to me.
SPEAKER_1:  I wonder what you think about it is.
SPEAKER_1:  His gut is, there's life everywhere out there.
SPEAKER_1:  but it stops at the bacteria stage. So he says the eukaryotes.
SPEAKER_1:  is like the biggest invention and the hardest one.
SPEAKER_0:  I wonder if he thinks that's an accidental outcome.
SPEAKER_0:  If he thinks that's inevitable, I wonder what that means.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's a likely possibility that the...
SPEAKER_0:  bacterial or microbial life is definitely more attainable.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, So that-
SPEAKER_1:  That's a weird...
SPEAKER_1:  world where our entire galaxy just says bacteria.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, everywhere. So, you know, if you don't like microbes, you aren't on the wrong planet.
SPEAKER_1:  Niner.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  And viruses. I don't know which one there's more of.
SPEAKER_1:  but they're both, and most of them are like.
SPEAKER_0:  They're fascinating. They do everything for us.
SPEAKER_1:  If you don't like my cups you're on the wrong planet.
SPEAKER_1:  You're full of good lines. Okay, right, right. I just can't
SPEAKER_1:  there's like an imperative to the whole thing.
SPEAKER_1:  To me.
SPEAKER_1:  The Origin.
SPEAKER_1:  is the hard question.
SPEAKER_1:  But once it gets going, I just don't see.
SPEAKER_1:  Wait, go ahead. It seems like it's constantly creating more intelligent things.
SPEAKER_1:  More.
SPEAKER_1:  fascinating complex things they're able to do.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a very interesting, I definitely...
SPEAKER_0:  agree that the initial steps may be the ultimate determinants, that once it's, you cannot stop it once it starts. It's possible.
SPEAKER_0:  rights and arm.
SPEAKER_1:  I just have never on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe it's, but maybe.
SPEAKER_1:  I just, whenever I see life...
SPEAKER_1:  It seems to flourish.
SPEAKER_1:  Everywhere.
SPEAKER_1:  The thing is, I don't...
SPEAKER_1:  The only thing I haven't seen is the start of it.
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly. But that's...
SPEAKER_0:  And how are we going to understand that if we don't the origin of life science? I mean, that's the end. The question here isn't exactly...
SPEAKER_0:  our ability to recapitulate everything that happened in the exact way that it happened.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  This is about
SPEAKER_0:  What can happen, or maybe how?
SPEAKER_1:  You think it's possible to study the origin of language?
SPEAKER_1:  using English.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  Like there's a very particular chemistry here. There's a particular.
SPEAKER_1:  set of assumptions, understanding about what life is, what...
SPEAKER_1:  Everything is our perception of reality is very specific.
SPEAKER_1:  Lee constructed through the evolutionary process.
SPEAKER_1:  I wonder if it's possible to-
SPEAKER_1:  get to some first principles, deep understanding of.
SPEAKER_1:  how life originates in such a way that you can actually
SPEAKER_1:  Constructed on other planets
SPEAKER_1:  I ultimately, it feels like if you're doing it in the lab on earth.
SPEAKER_1:  You're always going to be using...
SPEAKER_1:  some aspect of the life that's already here.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Ehh
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  What I-
SPEAKER_0:  sort of talked about in my talk as well.
SPEAKER_0:  and have a great day.
SPEAKER_1:  I should go.
SPEAKER_1:  Watch the TED Talks very good.
SPEAKER_1:  The annoying thing to me about Ted Talks, I guess it's by design, is they're too short.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like, come on.
SPEAKER_0:  And did you know that there's no prompter involved?
SPEAKER_1:  There's no, wait, there is or there isn't? Subscribe!!
SPEAKER_1:  You have to memorize stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  And thanks to my amazing editor who probably is watching this too, David Bielo, that it was very, very helpful.
SPEAKER_0:  But I would say that-
SPEAKER_1:  I like this podcast. It's a very professional organization.
SPEAKER_1:  I respect that medium.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, yeah, anyway, in the, in the tight talk about, yeah, life.
SPEAKER_1:  Life Creating Life.
SPEAKER_0:  is a likely scenario.
SPEAKER_0:  that once we understand.
SPEAKER_0:  How?
SPEAKER_0:  Life.
SPEAKER_0:  is a chemical system.
SPEAKER_0:  is.
SPEAKER_0:  capable of formulating.
SPEAKER_0:  its own expression.
SPEAKER_0:  and generating a memory.
SPEAKER_0:  and manages its existence on a.
SPEAKER_0:  planetary body for billions of years.
SPEAKER_0:  once we understand.
SPEAKER_0:  What's?
SPEAKER_0:  conditions gave rise to that.
SPEAKER_0:  We may.
SPEAKER_0:  be very likely to.
SPEAKER_0:  Understand.
SPEAKER_0:  whether a different planet also be likely to instigate its own.
SPEAKER_0:  chemical revolution if it were.
SPEAKER_0:  It was provided by
SPEAKER_0:  through some missing ingredients.
SPEAKER_0:  you can think of it as a sending fertilizer to a different planet.
SPEAKER_0:  that is missing its own.
SPEAKER_0:  chemical composition or lacking or.
SPEAKER_0:  that it needs more of what it has.
SPEAKER_0:  the difference between.
SPEAKER_0:  making
SPEAKER_0:  that planet Earth-like, which was, this is not what that's about. We're not talking about terraforming, or if you're not talking about turning that planet into Earth-like system.
SPEAKER_0:  We are talking about first understanding that planet.
SPEAKER_0:  studying its chemistry, studying its...
SPEAKER_0:  its properties well enough to understand.
SPEAKER_0:  whether it is close to its own chemical revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  and maybe giving it that extra nudge.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is obviously a pretty...
SPEAKER_0:  Big.
SPEAKER_0:  speculation and suggestion and
SPEAKER_0:  It's a very interesting proposition because...
SPEAKER_0:  This is a yes or no.
SPEAKER_0:  question, right? This is the ultimate would you rather.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the, and I think it says a lot about.
SPEAKER_0:  the perception of the person who's answering this question.
SPEAKER_0:  that if the answer is
SPEAKER_0:  No, no, no, absolutely not. That's not something we want to do.
SPEAKER_0:  I wanna know why that is the case.
SPEAKER_1:  So just to be clear, what we're talking about is looking at the chemical cocktail of a particular planet.
SPEAKER_1:  And.
SPEAKER_1:  having like tasting it.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's see.
SPEAKER_1:  Seeing what's missing so having a very systematic rigorous scientific process for understanding what is missing
SPEAKER_1:  not what is missing in terms of to make it Earth-like, but what is missing in order to.
SPEAKER_1:  be sufficiently.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... have the spark or the capacity of the spark to launch the
SPEAKER_1:  Evolution Revolution.
SPEAKER_1:  the evolutionary process. Exactly. And then the question is, do we want to then...
SPEAKER_1:  Complete the cocktail.
SPEAKER_0:  BOO
SPEAKER_0:  Proposition is to also.
SPEAKER_0:  make us think that we will likely have this capacity at some point.
SPEAKER_0:  especially when we understand.
SPEAKER_0:  Origin of Life.
SPEAKER_0:  better and better.
SPEAKER_0:  So we will be asking ourselves this question.
SPEAKER_0:  I guess I wanted to bring this to daylight a little bit because...
SPEAKER_0:  maybe in 10, 20 years, maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  more.
SPEAKER_1:  So you wanted to ask the ethical question, should we?
SPEAKER_1:  of.
SPEAKER_1:  basically
SPEAKER_1:  Start Life.
SPEAKER_1:  elsewhere on an-
SPEAKER_0:  or enabled.
SPEAKER_0:  the chemical.
SPEAKER_0:  the chemical capacity of that planet that it may one day itself.
SPEAKER_0:  Get there.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so for me the answer is yes.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  If you were to try to argue against my yes, what would you say? Why not?
SPEAKER_1:  What's the worst that could happen?
SPEAKER_1:  if we seed another planet with life.
SPEAKER_1:  What are the things we should...
SPEAKER_1:  think about is your main concern.
SPEAKER_1:  A chemical biological one or is it an ethical one?
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think about the worst thing that can happen is that it wouldn't work.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? So that's not a...
SPEAKER_0:  So, likely.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not likely that.
SPEAKER_0:  any attempt like this would work.
SPEAKER_0:  That's probably.
SPEAKER_0:  Because how do you?
SPEAKER_0:  You gotta be very, you know, you have to have an understanding that I don't think we have just yet.
SPEAKER_1:  I see, because if it doesn't work, then we could try again.
SPEAKER_1:  Right?
SPEAKER_1:  to me.
SPEAKER_1:  The worst case, the thing I would be worried about.
SPEAKER_1:  is we
SPEAKER_1:  Create life.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean the same stuff I worry about.
SPEAKER_1:  Like with plants or...
SPEAKER_1:  is things that might have a conscious experience.
SPEAKER_1:  And then.
SPEAKER_1:  the dark aspect of life.
SPEAKER_1:  is.
SPEAKER_1:  Life is increasingly complex life.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe I'm anthropomorphizing, but...
SPEAKER_1:  It seems to have the capacity to suffer.
SPEAKER_1:  And so we're creating something.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like when you have children.
SPEAKER_1:  You put.
SPEAKER_1:  creatures into this world.
SPEAKER_1:  that...
SPEAKER_1:  will suffer.
SPEAKER_1:  can suffer.
SPEAKER_1:  and may suffer.
SPEAKER_1:  Depending on how you view life.
SPEAKER_1:  may likely suffer.
SPEAKER_1:  And so now you carry this responsibility for.
SPEAKER_1:  doing your best to alleviate any suffering that might go through.
SPEAKER_1:  And that...
SPEAKER_1:  Perhaps it's a romanticizing this notion of life
SPEAKER_1:  Perhaps bacteria are not capable of suffering.
SPEAKER_1:  but perhaps it'll create more complex life forms that...
SPEAKER_1:  would be able to suffer.
SPEAKER_1:  And that feels like a responsibility as well.
SPEAKER_1:  Of course, other people would be concerned.
SPEAKER_1:  The more obvious.
SPEAKER_1:  concern is like
SPEAKER_1:  Well you just created a life form, how do you know it's not going to be a super deadly virus?
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  somehow is able to hurt humans.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, my concern is more. I feel like that's a solvable problem.
SPEAKER_1:  The problem of
SPEAKER_1:  creating conscious beings that are able to suffer. That's it.
SPEAKER_1:  tricky one.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I can see why, because-
SPEAKER_0:  It goes back to again, would we...
SPEAKER_0:  First of all,
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Do we have a responsibility?
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  propagate more.
SPEAKER_0:  of this chemistry that we have on this planet elsewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  given that we know ultimately.
SPEAKER_0:  We will.
SPEAKER_0:  be vanished.
SPEAKER_0:  By V, I mean the entire planet.
SPEAKER_0:  And if this is in fact a very rare.
SPEAKER_0:  chemical events.
SPEAKER_0:  that happens because all the.
SPEAKER_0:  right circumstances came together and we were lucky.
SPEAKER_0:  One.
SPEAKER_0:  do we have?
SPEAKER_0:  a responsibility to sponsor it.
SPEAKER_0:  This is it.
SPEAKER_0:  If we were to back up.
SPEAKER_1:  Sponsor, I like it.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's go ahead and put it.
SPEAKER_0:  If you try to...
SPEAKER_0:  backup.
SPEAKER_0:  remnants of our civilization, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Viva la...
SPEAKER_0:  potentially.
SPEAKER_0:  creates.
SPEAKER_0:  conditions on different planets so that humans can survive given that we know that we want to just just for the sake of
SPEAKER_0:  growing.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, propagating.
SPEAKER_1:  becoming multipletaries.
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly, but...
SPEAKER_0:  really is at stake here, I think is actually, or what is really more interesting is.
SPEAKER_0:  what we don't see.
SPEAKER_0:  Which is the-
SPEAKER_0:  again, that chemical behavior that enabled everything at first place.
SPEAKER_0:  That's different then.
SPEAKER_0:  sending potato crops.
SPEAKER_0:  or engineering bacteria to live on different planet. That's very different.
SPEAKER_0:  You're really good.
SPEAKER_0:  stripping it down to...
SPEAKER_0:  What is?
SPEAKER_0:  what is possible at the chemical level. So even if you are instigating chemistry on different planets,
SPEAKER_0:  you are letting that very planet to do its thing.
SPEAKER_0:  you're not necessarily contaminating this planet with different chemistry because
SPEAKER_0:  The idea behind this.
SPEAKER_0:  At least the way I would-
SPEAKER_0:  I thought about.
SPEAKER_0:  is that you understand that planet, you understand the conditions, you understand the chemistry of the planet really well.
SPEAKER_0:  Before...
SPEAKER_0:  choosing.
SPEAKER_0:  the planet is a candidate at first place.
SPEAKER_0:  And then...
SPEAKER_0:  It's not about sending a missing ingredient per se, but again, just sending more of what it already has.
SPEAKER_0:  that would be respecting.
SPEAKER_0:  that planet's condition to. So I'm not suggesting any occupation. I'm not suggesting any colonization. I'm not suggesting any.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, let's just strip everything and make everything Earth-like.
SPEAKER_0:  That's not what I'm saying.
SPEAKER_0:  It's more about empowering that place.
SPEAKER_0:  What's
SPEAKER_0:  you are saying is likely to be.
SPEAKER_0:  The motivator behind all this, that's not because I see suffering, I see pain.
SPEAKER_0:  It's very interesting. I think this is a question that really reveals about.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot about the person who's answering it.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, OK, so the pushback on my.
SPEAKER_1:  Push back.
SPEAKER_1:  If I so am deeply troubled by suffering.
SPEAKER_1:  then I should be probably paralyzed about the history of life on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  And, um...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there's...
SPEAKER_0:  Can you elaborate? What do you mean?
SPEAKER_1:  most of life who's ever lived.
SPEAKER_1:  suffered in ways that are almost unimaginable to me.
SPEAKER_1:  You mean, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  like our own species.
SPEAKER_1:  our own species than before.
SPEAKER_1:  and animals living today.
SPEAKER_1:  And we're not even talking about factory farms.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... would just
SPEAKER_1:  of animals living in extreme poverty in the jungle.
SPEAKER_1:  You don't, people think like in a natural environment, animals live in a happy place.
SPEAKER_1:  No, it's a brutal place.
SPEAKER_1:  of desperately trying to survive, of desperately trying to look for food.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's just like all of that life, that's just mammals. And we understand mammals, but like.
SPEAKER_1:  throughout.
SPEAKER_1:  like trillions of organisms.
SPEAKER_1:  that led up to those mammals.
SPEAKER_1:  and the organisms living everywhere, like even bacteria.
SPEAKER_1:  There's death everywhere.
SPEAKER_1:  So maybe this idea of death, this idea of suffering.
SPEAKER_1:  is actually this thing that we see as a bug.
SPEAKER_1:  is actually a feature.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think suffering is a linear property like that with life.
SPEAKER_0:  And I may be with Nick Lane on this one, that the likeliness of anything similar to what we got here, evolving in another planetary body, I think is quite low.
SPEAKER_1:  Where would you say is the look?
SPEAKER_1:  the biggest unlikely thing. Do you mean humans or do you mean even multicellular organisms?
SPEAKER_0:  probably mal Disney Lear
SPEAKER_0:  It's a, but.
SPEAKER_0:  I understand the-
SPEAKER_0:  both sides of the
SPEAKER_0:  equation, right? In one level, I can see that we may not have any other choice.
SPEAKER_0:  But too.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, back up this chemistry somewhere else.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. So you would be saving it's the ultimate safe saving or the record our own record. It's not about.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, yes, let's also save.
SPEAKER_0:  Beatles and all the amazing songs. But.
SPEAKER_0:  This would be the ultimate.
SPEAKER_0:  repository of life.
SPEAKER_0:  but I can also see your point of view.
SPEAKER_0:  For sure.
SPEAKER_1:  It's really interesting, so like.
SPEAKER_1:  Don't see to plan with the missing ingredient.
SPEAKER_1:  try to understand what the ingredients it has.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it possible to construct life?
SPEAKER_1:  For me, from a computer person.
SPEAKER_1:  It just feels like something that could be solved computationally.
SPEAKER_0:  we can learn from the mistakes that we've done.
SPEAKER_0:  here.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  aspire not to repeat them.
SPEAKER_0:  It is.
SPEAKER_0:  possible.
SPEAKER_0:  We do amazing things as humans. There's a lot of suffering, but there's also a lot of beauty.
SPEAKER_0:  we could choose.
SPEAKER_0:  what we want to be or what we want to...
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  see, right? So these attempts don't need not to come from a place of fear.
SPEAKER_0:  but it can be ultimately, it can come from a piece of hope and love.
SPEAKER_1:  I think we're just very recently figuring out stuff like we've even just a century ago we're doing atrocities that.
SPEAKER_1:  weren't seen as atrocities at the time.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  Edited
SPEAKER_1:  I think we're learning very quickly of what is right.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, and I work with a lot of
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe because I'm at the university, I get to teach.
SPEAKER_0:  young people every day.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Even at the...
SPEAKER_0:  time of.
SPEAKER_0:  four years or three few years you see.
SPEAKER_0:  Ew.
SPEAKER_0:  generational difference already unfolding in front of you.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe that's why I-
SPEAKER_0:  See hope because
SPEAKER_0:  I think what we...
SPEAKER_0:  get to interact within classrooms.
SPEAKER_0:  Every year.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just getting better.
SPEAKER_0:  day.
SPEAKER_0:  are aware of issues in a way that I sure wasn't.
SPEAKER_0:  Day Rage.
SPEAKER_0:  In some levels I was, but in many levels I...
SPEAKER_0:  didn't think about.
SPEAKER_0:  I wasn't concerned of the problems. Well,
SPEAKER_0:  they maybe have to be concerned because it's...
SPEAKER_0:  hitting the reality, he's hitting them hard.
SPEAKER_0:  Younger people are not afraid of these things an 18 year old can face.
SPEAKER_0:  these brutal facts about the planet in ways that
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think any other generation before them did.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, super cool. And like the, uh,
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there's all these cool technologies that aid in the process.
SPEAKER_1:  of a human being.
SPEAKER_1:  being able to see the truth at deeper, deeper levels like Wikipedia and just the internet in general.
SPEAKER_1:  is enabling education at a level that was unimaginable before the...
SPEAKER_0:  internet. Yes and I think space exploration.
SPEAKER_0:  Even contemplating about these possibilities ultimately...
SPEAKER_0:  And I will-
SPEAKER_0:  Emphasize this again, should make us think about our wrong place.
SPEAKER_0:  in the universe. If we are alone, that is quite fascinating and we definitely have a responsibility to
SPEAKER_0:  Guard what we got better and protect it better and don't take it for granted.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're not the only one, that's also a lot of responsibility to understand.
SPEAKER_0:  What else is out there?
SPEAKER_0:  either proposition as famously being told.
SPEAKER_0:  It's fascinating.
SPEAKER_0:  Is a.
SPEAKER_0:  As a scientist, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think that's the general behavior. Maybe not my fellow scientists listening to this can correct me if they aren't like this, but, to actually dig in I wonder which Brand Maybe I am aware
SPEAKER_0:  You need to have a level of optimism.
SPEAKER_0:  and hope.
SPEAKER_0:  That's something, you know, that...
SPEAKER_0:  things are worth working for.
SPEAKER_0:  worth dreaming.
SPEAKER_0:  worth imagining and we cannot just have.
SPEAKER_0:  fear of suffering or fear of...
SPEAKER_0:  pain.
SPEAKER_0:  stopping us from.
SPEAKER_0:  doing marvelous things.
SPEAKER_1:  I've talked to quite a few people in my life who've gotten a lot of shit done.
SPEAKER_1:  have helped a lot of people.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know a single one of them who's not an optimist.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a place for critics and cynicism in this world, but...
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of actually building things.
SPEAKER_1:  and creating things in this world that help a lot of people.
SPEAKER_1:  I think optimism is a requirement, is a precondition in almost all cases. In my limited.
SPEAKER_1:  humble human experience.
SPEAKER_1:  But I tend to, when I look out there, think that aliens are everywhere.
SPEAKER_1:  I think there's...
SPEAKER_1:  To me, I have a humility about.
SPEAKER_1:  I tend to see us humans as
SPEAKER_1:  being very limited cognitively.
SPEAKER_1:  Like there's so many things we don't understand.
SPEAKER_1:  I think eventually we'll understand. Of course we don't know this, but my gut says-
SPEAKER_1:  we'll understand that.
SPEAKER_1:  Alien Signals
SPEAKER_1:  and life.
SPEAKER_1:  has been all around us.
SPEAKER_1:  and we're too dumb to see it.
SPEAKER_1:  like.
SPEAKER_1:  whatever life is, whatever the life force is, whatever consciousness is, whatever intelligence, or whatever the...
SPEAKER_1:  The mechanism.
SPEAKER_1:  that led to the origin of life on Earth was everywhere.
SPEAKER_1:  or we're just too dumb to see it.
SPEAKER_1:  It's in the physics. It's somewhere, we'll find it somewhere in the physics.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's one of the most...
SPEAKER_0:  is humbling parts of
SPEAKER_0:  also being a scientist.
SPEAKER_0:  that we know.
SPEAKER_0:  that we never know.
SPEAKER_0:  for sure.
SPEAKER_0:  and for the...
SPEAKER_0:  outsiders perhaps. That may be a very...
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Strange.
SPEAKER_0:  The way of living.
SPEAKER_0:  especially when you're...
SPEAKER_0:  pursue is about creating knowledge.
SPEAKER_0:  and that you'll know that what you created can also be.
SPEAKER_0:  and hopefully will be.
SPEAKER_0:  disproven.
SPEAKER_0:  So that another level.
SPEAKER_0:  will rise.
SPEAKER_0:  Boom.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think we've seen that.
SPEAKER_0:  this lack of maybe connection.
SPEAKER_0:  between the approach to science or knowledge.
SPEAKER_0:  versus.
SPEAKER_0:  folks who are maybe not thinking about these problems every day.
SPEAKER_0:  We are okay with being wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  In fact, we know that's the only way to...
SPEAKER_0:  pushed the limits of knowledge.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you think life originated on Earth? We've talked about this.
SPEAKER_1:  but do you have a gut feeling about?
SPEAKER_1:  First of all, actually even to step back, do you think because you were like flirting with this idea.
SPEAKER_1:  Did the translation mechanism came before life?
SPEAKER_0:  I think that you cannot separate.
SPEAKER_0:  from...
SPEAKER_0:  emergence of translation machinery from emergence of life or something like translation machinery, this whole
SPEAKER_0:  Informatic.
SPEAKER_0:  chemical computing system.
SPEAKER_0:  that is also capable of.
SPEAKER_0:  dynamism and evolvability that comes with biology.
SPEAKER_0:  biological behavior.
SPEAKER_0:  from emergence of life itself.
SPEAKER_0:  We've definitely...
SPEAKER_0:  took a lot of steps towards understanding origins.
SPEAKER_0:  able to create molecules from.
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_0:  environment's lightening heat.
SPEAKER_0:  and you make amino acids. So we are able to create the building blocks, the Miller-Urey experiment.
SPEAKER_0:  That's now 60 years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  we are able to create the building blocks. We are able to make them interact with one another. They can get more complex some.
SPEAKER_0:  this messy, there's all this chemistry that's going on, we are able to.
SPEAKER_0:  have these chemicals interact with one another maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  have even some emergent properties that we can quantify.
SPEAKER_0:  Definitely there is this trend towards more systems-level approach to origins, with more introduction of systems-level chemistry.
SPEAKER_0:  or network level chemistry.
SPEAKER_0:  and complex system integration.
SPEAKER_0:  in order to understand how, now that we can make these building blocks, we can make them interact with one another, but how do we make them interact with one another in more intelligent ways that will...
SPEAKER_0:  properties of a biological system will be heritable.
SPEAKER_0:  it will be responding to the environment.
SPEAKER_0:  it will mutate and it will sustain itself.
SPEAKER_0:  That is the final bit, I think, in our original life adventure.
SPEAKER_0:  We are extremely close. I'm very optimistic that our community will.
SPEAKER_0:  get a handle of this problem in this decade.
SPEAKER_0:  This is in fact, I think one of the most exciting times to be doing this work.
SPEAKER_1:  What would be super convincing to you, like?
SPEAKER_1:  incredibly amazing
SPEAKER_1:  would blow your mind.
SPEAKER_1:  if it was done.
SPEAKER_1:  X was done in the lab.
SPEAKER_1:  Like what?
SPEAKER_1:  would you I mean I don't know if you would call it origin of life but something really truly remarkable and special done in the lab. What would that look like to you?
SPEAKER_0:  The- the- the-
SPEAKER_0:  properties that I listed. This was five.
SPEAKER_0:  properties that I listed about and the machinery that is capable of.
SPEAKER_0:  sensing and responding the environment.
SPEAKER_0:  If we can.
SPEAKER_0:  Ehmm.
SPEAKER_0:  I would imagine.
SPEAKER_0:  is similar to Miller-Urey experiment where they...
SPEAKER_0:  only sparked in the
SPEAKER_0:  particular environmental forces and were able to
SPEAKER_0:  produce a chemical.
SPEAKER_0:  that is important for a mix of
SPEAKER_0:  Chemicals are important for life.
SPEAKER_0:  or building blocks, rather.
SPEAKER_0:  I would-
SPEAKER_0:  If I saw that a similar experiment where a well-defined geochemical parameter was
SPEAKER_0:  subjected on a mix of chemistry.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  chemistry too.
SPEAKER_0:  forum.
SPEAKER_0:  some level of
SPEAKER_0:  Computation Informatic.
SPEAKER_0:  biological property and by biological I'm going to keep it to very minimum.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  as I defined early on.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  That would be super exciting to me, is self-organizing.
SPEAKER_0:  chemistry.
SPEAKER_0:  that we can create experimentally in a flask.
SPEAKER_0:  by simulating.
SPEAKER_0:  the conditions of early Earth, be it radiation, be it temperature or...
SPEAKER_0:  Mix of both.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  That would be very cool.
SPEAKER_1:  And doing all the five, the chemical, physical, informatic, computational biology. Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  So like-
SPEAKER_1:  simulation.
SPEAKER_1:  And a computer would not... No.
SPEAKER_0:  It would be great because they help to understand the parameters.
SPEAKER_0:  maybe formulate, maybe quantify, create models.
SPEAKER_0:  but ultimately you need to experiment.
SPEAKER_1:  Unless it's quantum mechanical simulation, but that's going to be extremely difficult. So, let's start by doing some simple simulation from the physics app.
SPEAKER_1:  That's going to be very...
SPEAKER_1:  because you're gonna have to simulate.
SPEAKER_1:  the physical the chemical the informatics i mean honestly it's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's very difficult to start the quantum mechanics.
SPEAKER_1:  and end up in biology.
SPEAKER_1:  alter simulation.
SPEAKER_1:  But the stuff that DeepMind did with AlphaFold and the protein folding is really inspiring. The
SPEAKER_1:  It's inspiring in that.
SPEAKER_1:  you're able to do.
SPEAKER_1:  to solve a difficult biode.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, absolutely. That's why there's definitely a lot of benefit to those models, predictions.
SPEAKER_0:  because they at least helped the experimentalist.
SPEAKER_0:  to come up with the priors and parameterize things better, maybe eliminate.
SPEAKER_0:  very obvious.
SPEAKER_0:  dead ends early on, given that experiments take such a long time and it's a huge investment.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and no one's a better
SPEAKER_0:  experimentalist in nature.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask you, perhaps.
SPEAKER_1:  pressing sad.
SPEAKER_0:  I really want to make me say, you're not going to win.
SPEAKER_1:  I know.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a flame of optimism in you that will never be extinguished. Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  The idea of past permeate.
SPEAKER_1:  You mentioned...
SPEAKER_1:  Would we seed another planet with life?
SPEAKER_1:  Is it possible that our planet
SPEAKER_1:  or seeded with life from elsewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  So what?
SPEAKER_0:  DOOP
SPEAKER_0:  the proposition I made.
SPEAKER_0:  like to think of it as protospermia rather than panspermia because it's even more, it's more proto-state than
SPEAKER_0:  acknowledging because in Panspermia you still have
SPEAKER_0:  itself.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? You still have something that is very, even the cell to me would be very Earth-like.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, I'm...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm talking at sub-sailor level in the proposition of...
SPEAKER_0:  is.
SPEAKER_0:  spreading chemistry.
SPEAKER_1:  So spreading chemical ingredients, not spreading life.
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly. It will be more like the fertilizer that is well...
SPEAKER_0:  Adopted and compatible with that plant everybody in Panspermia you're still.
SPEAKER_0:  imagining either an entire bacteria.
SPEAKER_0:  or microbe.
SPEAKER_0:  or a cell or something that is DNA, which is still...
SPEAKER_0:  Terran.
SPEAKER_1:  So that sounds that would.
SPEAKER_1:  That doesn't matter to you because it's chemistry, that's the initial conditions, doesn't matter how the initial conditions came to be.
SPEAKER_1:  they are where they are and let's go from there.
SPEAKER_1:  and there's all kinds of fascinatingly different.
SPEAKER_1:  initial conditions in terms of chemistry.
SPEAKER_0:  from planets. But in terms of past premium, obviously that's-
SPEAKER_0:  There's going to be always...
SPEAKER_0:  Room 4
SPEAKER_0:  that those sort of discussions or there will be.
SPEAKER_0:  Ew.
SPEAKER_0:  Those discussions will always be present, I think, in any...
SPEAKER_0:  life in the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  Debates?
SPEAKER_0:  But the problem I have is...
SPEAKER_0:  PENSPREMIER is that it removes the problem from...
SPEAKER_0:  the planet to somewhere else.
SPEAKER_0:  It makes it.
SPEAKER_0:  very difficult to answer scientifically.
SPEAKER_0:  You just took the problem away from this planet.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  formulated in a way that I cannot go and...
SPEAKER_0:  try to understand.
SPEAKER_0:  in the lab doing experiments or even through models.
SPEAKER_1:  Self-Herd.
SPEAKER_1:  Brilliant biologists like yourself say that, but I just.
SPEAKER_1:  To me.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, here's how I think of Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  So I actually am able to hold all these possibilities in my head.
SPEAKER_1:  and all of them are inspiring to me.
SPEAKER_1:  I kind of think there's a possibility that Earth is just...
SPEAKER_1:  an experiment by a graduate student, by an alien graduate student.
SPEAKER_0:  So I know the exact episode of Star Trek you're talking about.
SPEAKER_1:  But like there is some, to me that's inspiring.
SPEAKER_1:  If we are...
SPEAKER_0:  But that's not what Panspermia is about.
SPEAKER_0:  You're talking about...
SPEAKER_0:  My proposition. That's not what pen's permea is.
SPEAKER_0:  What's Pinsbury? It just... Also if you perhaps noticed I didn't actually lose to the other players Yeah
SPEAKER_1:  Life just came from elsewhere.
SPEAKER_1:  still that's interesting because
SPEAKER_1:  There's still giant leaps that happened on Earth, it seems like.
SPEAKER_1:  beyond the initial primitive organisms, like.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think fans spur me up usually.
SPEAKER_0:  Eugh.
SPEAKER_0:  articulates at the level of eukaryotes. I think they talk about...
SPEAKER_0:  bacteria primarily.
SPEAKER_0:  I think so. Right.
SPEAKER_0:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's still interesting because all the different leaps of evolution still happen here on earth. That's still interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's definitely...
SPEAKER_0:  interesting to listen to, but I wouldn't.
SPEAKER_0:  place it in, I wouldn't know how to place it in the studies of original life, I guess.
SPEAKER_1:  replace it.
SPEAKER_1:  You have the initial conditions.
SPEAKER_1:  for the origin of life?
SPEAKER_1:  and you try to...
SPEAKER_1:  create life in that way that you've described in the five components, and it keeps failing.
SPEAKER_1:  See.
SPEAKER_1:  what what pants permeate allows you to do
SPEAKER_1:  Is this also considered a question?
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe there's missing components.
SPEAKER_0:  How do you answer that question?
SPEAKER_1:  through exploration, through science, looking outside, looking outside of earth.
SPEAKER_1:  looking at the fundamentals of chemistry.
SPEAKER_0:  in physics. Do you understand that with fundamentals of chemistry in physics?
SPEAKER_1:  How do you understand?
SPEAKER_0:  How do you understand gravity? But you're talking about panspermia, right? Just, I don't understand how would you-
SPEAKER_0:  It's different than if you think it's similar to looking for life.
SPEAKER_0:  in the universe. Is that what you're thinking?
SPEAKER_1:  No, I'm saying there's a missing component.
SPEAKER_0:  that came from elsewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  A whole entire organism is not a missing component right there, right? I mean, when you're thinking about Origin of Life.
SPEAKER_1:  No, no, no, that's an assumption. Your assumption is all the ingredients for the origin of life are here on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  I tend to believe that most likely that's the case.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm just saying it's inspiring.
SPEAKER_1:  to think that there is some ingredients.
SPEAKER_1:  You're going to push back because that's not past program. It's desperation and it's the other way.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  See, okay, so think...
SPEAKER_0:  But yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  It's also kind of fun to push back on you. No, I understand, I understand. If actually a living organism.
SPEAKER_1:  ended up here from elsewhere.
SPEAKER_1:  That means a lot of the exploration we're doing here with the ingredients that we know.
SPEAKER_1:  will not give us the clues to the...
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  to the origin of life.
SPEAKER_1:  It just seems like...
SPEAKER_1:  It's still very useful to try to create.
SPEAKER_1:  life here.
SPEAKER_1:  and then we'll see, wait a minute.
SPEAKER_1:  Don't you think we'll be able to-
SPEAKER_1:  prove, not prove, but show that past sperm is very likely.
SPEAKER_1:  Like if we just keep failing.
SPEAKER_1:  We understand biology.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think so.
SPEAKER_0:  The failure is not going to indicate that this must have been.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think anyone...
SPEAKER_0:  will put the problem to something else just because our failures, our experiments failed.
SPEAKER_1:  So failure means we don't understand chemistry deeply enough.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and we've given the progress we made.
SPEAKER_0:  and how many billions of people are working on this right now.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's definitely more
SPEAKER_0:  I would say that we are approaching this problem in more...
SPEAKER_0:  broader ways, different ways possible.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm confident that we will get there for us. Again, we are interested in...
SPEAKER_0:  early cells and first cells and what followed the origin of life, but we cannot
SPEAKER_0:  given that it's a continuum that's the between...
SPEAKER_0:  origin and emergence of first cells.
SPEAKER_0:  it's hard to separate these two ends.
SPEAKER_1:  from one another. Given that life is a-
SPEAKER_1:  solution to a chemistry problem.
SPEAKER_1:  if we re-ran Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  a million times how different would
SPEAKER_1:  the results be.
SPEAKER_1:  if we look at that wheel.
SPEAKER_1:  How different would be the tree of life do you think? Like what's your gut say?
SPEAKER_0:  My-
SPEAKER_0:  uh, mind asks
SPEAKER_0:  Are you imagining if we're repeating the planet one million?
SPEAKER_0:  times. Are we?
SPEAKER_0:  seeing.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  are these things that happened, I'm not talking at the chemical level, but at the environment level.
SPEAKER_0:  Do they happen at the same time, at the same frequency, at the same intensity?
SPEAKER_0:  every time you're running this tape.
SPEAKER_0:  over and over again.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  You mean like geological?
SPEAKER_0:  stuff. Yeah, like so is the
SPEAKER_1:  You're saying those are important. I mean, the fact that you would ask that question is also fascinating. So that's important. The timing, the frequency, the intensity.
SPEAKER_0:  of geological events? When we run this imaginary rewind and replay experiments in our minds.
SPEAKER_0:  I want to know whether we are positioning all the same geologic events at the same chronological order as well.
SPEAKER_0:  or whether we are also giving them more randomness.
SPEAKER_0:  So if the volcano erupted, it's happening at the same time. If you have a me.
SPEAKER_0:  Our dinosaur's getting wiped off every time with the same-
SPEAKER_0:  Meteorites.
SPEAKER_0:  hitting the same...
SPEAKER_1:  temperature change.
SPEAKER_0:  Change is all that matters. Change is all that matters.
SPEAKER_1:  That's actually, I've heard you say somewhere that.
SPEAKER_1:  One of the things that's fascinating to you about this whole-
SPEAKER_1:  process of evolution is that...
SPEAKER_1:  And the memory...
SPEAKER_1:  the process of evolution, all the mechanisms were invented and developed.
SPEAKER_1:  despite
SPEAKER_1:  all the variation geologically.
SPEAKER_1:  through the hardship that Earth has gone through.
SPEAKER_0:  that the biological innovations persisted despite that?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, despite that.
SPEAKER_1:  which is interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  You kind of think of...
SPEAKER_1:  The biological innovation is kind of happening in their own.
SPEAKER_0:  Because we actually have a center exploring this problem.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  We want to understand.
SPEAKER_0:  weather.
SPEAKER_0:  It's almost like judging a book by its cover, right? Do you just look at an environment and then see whatever is present?
SPEAKER_0:  or scares in that environment. And then
SPEAKER_0:  think that okay, the life form that will exist in this environment will
SPEAKER_0:  obviously have a lot of
SPEAKER_0:  molybdenum in its system. Look at all this molybdenum around here.
SPEAKER_0:  Or will it be... Because if you say that, you are now putting the environment in the more prime.
SPEAKER_0:  driver role, right? You're saying that environment will determine what biology will or will not use.
SPEAKER_0:  But we've.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't study Zdets.
SPEAKER_0:  show that it's not necessarily this straightforward.
SPEAKER_0:  that for instance we looked at going back to nitrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  one thing that's fascinating about
SPEAKER_0:  and waste cells fix nitrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  the ones that can do.
SPEAKER_0:  Is that they also do this through a lot of help of a lot of metals a lot of elemental support really
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  which geologists use to understand where did this metabolism even evolved.
SPEAKER_0:  wear.
SPEAKER_0:  at first place. So we look at ancient oceans, we try to understand the elemental composition of ancient oceans.
SPEAKER_0:  And what we see is that
SPEAKER_0:  in some cases the metabolisms even though they prefer a certain metal.
SPEAKER_0:  or an element that is in the environment.
SPEAKER_0:  That medal wasn't.
SPEAKER_0:  Abandoned in the environment. But still.
SPEAKER_0:  Life shows that.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not that straightforward as though whatever you are.
SPEAKER_0:  You are what you eat, but you don't necessarily eat what is obvious to you.
SPEAKER_0:  Just because there's a lot of that food around it doesn't mean life will ultimately go there. Maybe most of the time it will.
SPEAKER_0:  But it seems like in the case of nitrogen fixation, it didn't, and maybe that made the difference.
SPEAKER_1:  It's so cool that, right, it's not the abundant resource that's going to be the definition of what.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of life flourishes.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  So it's not a straightforward thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, your sense is that.
SPEAKER_1:  the different timing.
SPEAKER_1:  the different conditions of the environment would change.
SPEAKER_1:  the way evolution happens.
SPEAKER_0:  For instance, I think it's in the...
SPEAKER_0:  80s maybe earlier than that.
SPEAKER_0:  Stephen Jay Gould's book, Wonderful Life, which changed, I think, a lot of...
SPEAKER_0:  scientists life, including mine.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  he contemplates on.
SPEAKER_0:  this notion of the tape of life, of course.
SPEAKER_0:  I hope people still know what tape is, but I think your listeners will know what tape is. Do read comments, but note I have brought Rs environment toalk you an overviewm what tape is, gives me time
SPEAKER_0:  It's the...
SPEAKER_1:  Tape? Go on, tell me about the tape. Is it like a TikTok? Can you swipe on it?
SPEAKER_1:  I am so good.
SPEAKER_1:  I apologize.
SPEAKER_0:  the
SPEAKER_0:  I kind of asked for it. But he speculated or suggested this hypothetical experiment.
SPEAKER_0:  weather.
SPEAKER_0:  If life was recorded on or can be imagined to be recorded on a linear, is a linear chain of events recorded on a tape.
SPEAKER_0:  And if we were to rewind the tape, we'd be listening to the same song. Right? So this was an Enid's proposition, I also thought.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, yeah, but are we replaying the tape in the same exact manner or are we?
SPEAKER_0:  meaning all the geological and environmental events, are they happening at the same time? Because then you removed the randomness from equation a little bit.
SPEAKER_0:  You just.
SPEAKER_0:  You moved it.
SPEAKER_0:  you're assuming everything will happen at the same time, at the same intensity. So that's not too contingent.
SPEAKER_0:  That means that the natural selection you're thinking is really operating it more or evolution is operating it more under more random.
SPEAKER_0:  forces.
SPEAKER_0:  then that can be dictated by the environment.
SPEAKER_0:  In our way of understanding or thinking about rewinding, replaying, I don't think we're thinking about the role of the environment as clearly or don't seem to be.
SPEAKER_0:  integrated as much.
SPEAKER_1:  But I'll-
SPEAKER_1:  I also wonder if it's possible that the chemistry ultimately defines the destination.
SPEAKER_1:  That, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  despite all the environmental changes, despite...
SPEAKER_1:  all the randomness will end up-
SPEAKER_0:  But we are not talking about whether life will emerge and sustain itself. We are talking about whether life will emerge and sustain itself in the shape and form that is similar to what we have right now.
SPEAKER_0:  sold.
SPEAKER_0:  You are chemistry, I'm chemistry, we're having this conversation. And your plants are chemistry too. They're also having their own conversation. These plants are fake, but yes.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't want to say that, but they're fake
SPEAKER_1:  Look at my place. Of course that would be fake. Otherwise they would die
SPEAKER_0:  What's wrong with this place? It's wonderful.
SPEAKER_1:  It's, it's, I'm Alice and this is Wonderland.
SPEAKER_1:  This is great.
SPEAKER_1:  This is great, it's just that, you know, this is a place where robots flourish and those plants are fake.
SPEAKER_0:  Are you saying that you and I are the only living organisms? Well, obviously there are microbes in this room.
SPEAKER_0:  but yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, we are the only living organisms.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll take care of getting a dog.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you know, this is not a clean room, so you have microbes.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, many.
SPEAKER_0:  millions. Yes, so you and I and all the microbes in this room.
SPEAKER_0:  your chemical systems that are operating it.
SPEAKER_0:  in a way that we can respond and sense our environments and whatnot.
SPEAKER_0:  But in-
SPEAKER_0:  If you are asking if you're going to be here, then you're imagining that another solution is also possible, which is different.
SPEAKER_0:  Done.
SPEAKER_0:  fundamentals of life because life will do always life will do its life thing
SPEAKER_1:  I guess it goes all the way back.
SPEAKER_1:  to the things we're talking about translation.
SPEAKER_1:  and the stuff you were messing with.
SPEAKER_1:  is figuring out what is the important stuff and what isn't.
SPEAKER_1:  makes me wonder about, you know, just like with the translation.
SPEAKER_1:  machinery
SPEAKER_1:  with human beings, I wonder what's the important stuff. Is it important to have two limbs?
SPEAKER_1:  Is it important to have eyes?
SPEAKER_1:  It was obvious that the sensory mechanism of eyes excite.
SPEAKER_1:  which it developed.
SPEAKER_1:  How many times if you were here on Earth would the sensory mechanism of sight?
SPEAKER_1:  develop.
SPEAKER_1:  And what would it look like? Would it be one giant eye?
SPEAKER_1:  I'll be too.
SPEAKER_1:  What's with the symmetry? Why are we so damn s-
SPEAKER_0:  symmetrical.
SPEAKER_0:  In response to Steve Jay Gould's proposition.
SPEAKER_0:  Most people who...
SPEAKER_0:  who argue that life is convergent and it will in fact lead to a few...
SPEAKER_0:  determined.
SPEAKER_0:  outcomes or the...
SPEAKER_0:  It's not that the outcome is determined per se, but it's...
SPEAKER_0:  The pathways are restricted and
SPEAKER_0:  mutational trajectories that life can act upon.
SPEAKER_0:  are already very limited.
SPEAKER_0:  so that the final outcomes are a few.
SPEAKER_0:  and eyes being one of them.
SPEAKER_0:  the convergence at the eye level was...
SPEAKER_0:  suggested as an example, was presented as an example of why life may actually embark on the same.
SPEAKER_0:  solution over and over again, given that many species evolved it.
SPEAKER_1:  independently from one another. Do you think there's any inkling of truth to that?
SPEAKER_1:  Like, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Is it just us humans thinking we're special?
SPEAKER_0:  I think those innovations came again so far after the...
SPEAKER_0:  I know it's the fun stuff. Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... because it's
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you. I mean, thank you. I think we humans tend to talk about the later stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  but without the earlier stuff. So if I think of earlier there's...
SPEAKER_0:  And I ask this to my students too, I want...
SPEAKER_0:  to close their eyes and think about just nothingness but dust. We don't have trees, we don't have plants.
SPEAKER_0:  When we say an empty place, or visually at least, we are talking about a planet that is really alien.
SPEAKER_0:  So understanding our own past is similar to understanding an alien planet altogether.
SPEAKER_0:  Given that it is a very different planet that did not have any oxygen for 2 billion years.
SPEAKER_0:  There's nothing that is familiar to us that we would even...
SPEAKER_0:  Think about it.
SPEAKER_0:  when we think about life.
SPEAKER_0:  that is present in our past, yet here we are.
SPEAKER_1:  So cool that from that came this.
SPEAKER_0:  Like houses and people. And we are very, very.
SPEAKER_0:  We are the super late arrivals to the party, right? So this is definitely not our planet.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the microbial planets that we live in.
SPEAKER_1:  but the potential to create us was always there.
SPEAKER_1:  I hope you know that.
SPEAKER_1:  because we were created.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  What is it? You think it's possible this?
SPEAKER_1:  Even for the early stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah, maybe if it's super unlikely, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  that we just got super, this is the planet that got really lucky given the chemistry.
SPEAKER_1:  like maybe to create the bacteria is not so lucky.
SPEAKER_1:  but to create complex organisms all the way up to mammals, that's super lucky.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, and it may all come down to a few innovations that happened at the molecular level.
SPEAKER_0:  That may or may not be inevitable.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  that's that so all these
SPEAKER_0:  molecular tricks may have enabled.
SPEAKER_0:  this sort of mere existence of whatever you are able to define as familiar to yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  And you have a hope that science can answer these questions.
SPEAKER_1:  to reconstruct.
SPEAKER_0:  science is answering these questions. I mean, we are limited to going back to the beginning.
SPEAKER_0:  in our ways, right? So we rely on biology, it's just overwritten.
SPEAKER_0:  You're talking about four billion year old records that is ever changing. That again makes it beautiful, but also makes it difficult.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not tractable.
SPEAKER_0:  geology has.
SPEAKER_0:  some degree, to some degree it has a record.
SPEAKER_0:  of a more static.
SPEAKER_0:  frozen.
SPEAKER_0:  State record.
SPEAKER_0:  that is embedded.
SPEAKER_0:  on itself.
SPEAKER_0:  on the surface of this planet if we can find them.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's the key that most of these.
SPEAKER_0:  Recorded.
SPEAKER_0:  um
SPEAKER_0:  Remnants are.
SPEAKER_0:  If we are lucky we find them.
SPEAKER_0:  They are not naturally selected.
SPEAKER_0:  They are the...
SPEAKER_0:  they're found, they need to be found for us to read them. So.
SPEAKER_0:  We work with a.
SPEAKER_0:  very handful set of samples, especially
SPEAKER_0:  when we talk about the deep past.
SPEAKER_0:  planet with no oxygen when we pass the great oxidation event threshold that is about.
SPEAKER_0:  2.5 billion years. So the earliest life is
SPEAKER_0:  Even harder, you are trying to write the story of life.
SPEAKER_0:  based on a handful of rocks and what is recorded on them.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of finding...
SPEAKER_1:  select remnants of our deep past.
SPEAKER_1:  You said that you've been thinking about Nick.
SPEAKER_1:  Neelan's essay on scientific knowledge and scientific abstraction.
SPEAKER_1:  So let me ask you, what do you think scientific questions?
SPEAKER_1:  and answers or in general ideas come from.
SPEAKER_1:  You're a scientist.
SPEAKER_1:  You ask very good questions.
SPEAKER_1:  and try systematically and rigorously to answer them through experiment.
SPEAKER_1:  Where do you think ideas come from?
SPEAKER_0:  Ideas come all the time, right? There are all kinds of ideas. There are good ideas. There are not so good ideas.
SPEAKER_0:  They're really exciting ideas.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, maybe some boring ones.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  If you...
SPEAKER_0:  are really interested in doing something different, then you need to be willing to take the risk to be wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's incredibly difficult, even though...
SPEAKER_0:  We talked about the idealist.
SPEAKER_0:  sort of notion behind science that we ultimately want to be rejected or ideas need to be rejected for it too.
SPEAKER_0:  the entire
SPEAKER_0:  infrastructure to move forward.
SPEAKER_0:  there is a level of risk taking, I think, behind.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  any creative idea.
SPEAKER_0:  And I mean that in a true sense.
SPEAKER_0:  If you are disappointed that your idea didn't work.
SPEAKER_0:  then it wasn't a
SPEAKER_0:  risk.
SPEAKER_0:  because you still hoped that it will work.
SPEAKER_0:  The true risk is that you accept that this may not work.
SPEAKER_0:  so that the failure shouldn't also surprise you.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it when you embark on stuff do you?
SPEAKER_1:  When you embark on an idea...
SPEAKER_1:  Do you actually?
SPEAKER_1:  Contemplate and accept.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, failure?
SPEAKER_0:  Like as a possible I wouldn't say so but I.
SPEAKER_0:  eliminated a lot of the things.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  out of my
SPEAKER_0:  work line by...
SPEAKER_0:  simply.
SPEAKER_0:  not feeling like studying them.
SPEAKER_0:  I was bored.
SPEAKER_0:  chasing certain questions.
SPEAKER_0:  and I
SPEAKER_1:  So you trusted the signal of boredom as a good sign that it's not a good question.
SPEAKER_0:  It should definitely...
SPEAKER_0:  Whatever you're doing should be exciting to you. If there's only one person that should be ever excited about what you're doing,
SPEAKER_0:  That should be you.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's enough for that idea to go somewhere, I think, that you need to believe.
SPEAKER_0:  in the idea, but at the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's important to...
SPEAKER_0:  not fall in love with your mistakes.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, that you if if something isn't working.
SPEAKER_0:  You should.
SPEAKER_0:  Let it go.
SPEAKER_0:  instead of trying to fix it.
SPEAKER_0:  even though you feel that this is a mistake or you know that it's a mistake.
SPEAKER_0:  in order to
SPEAKER_0:  Oh-whip.
SPEAKER_0:  is sorry, instead of.
SPEAKER_0:  trying to fix it.
SPEAKER_0:  You should
SPEAKER_0:  wrap it up and move on to something else, which is incredibly hard.
SPEAKER_1:  Good advice for science, but also good advice for relationships.
SPEAKER_1:  Heh.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, but okay. So like, that's actually really hard, especially, I mean, this is like PhD stuff like
SPEAKER_1:  if you sink in so much of your time, not even PhD, the entire.
SPEAKER_1:  entire scientific careers, it's really tough to let go.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, and there is not a lot of...
SPEAKER_0:  room for true freedom.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  at this certain degree. So first you need to be trained, right?
SPEAKER_0:  It's not.
SPEAKER_0:  that scientists are just brilliant, amazing humans. I mean, they just know and learn how, they know how to do science because they're trained.
SPEAKER_0:  how to do science. So that is important because I...
SPEAKER_0:  As someone who...
SPEAKER_0:  W-wants to definitely-
SPEAKER_0:  I'm hoping that I'm...
SPEAKER_0:  giving the message that this is for everybody.
SPEAKER_0:  That
SPEAKER_0:  There's this notion of science, scientists being super smart people. That's definitely...
SPEAKER_0:  Not true.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  It is a method that you learn to solve a problem. That's really what science is.
SPEAKER_0:  and some are really good at it.
SPEAKER_0:  and they get better at it under really good guidance, maybe good mentorship.
SPEAKER_0:  And ultimately everyone finds their own style of problem solving and what sort of problems they solve but I have not met a scientist that finds their own.
SPEAKER_0:  Pursue boarding.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, it can happen, but they're not going to be effective, just like you said, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  It's kind of interesting because in the age of social media and attention economies and stuff like that
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I've interacted with a lot of folks.
SPEAKER_1:  like YouTubers and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  I think a lot of their work is driven by what others find exciting.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think that ultimately leads to a life that's not fulfilling.
SPEAKER_0:  I can see the reason.
SPEAKER_0:  behind it or perhaps there's again fear of failure.
SPEAKER_0:  that can be a major.
SPEAKER_0:  Terminant
SPEAKER_0:  of that pattern, right? You
SPEAKER_0:  ehh
SPEAKER_0:  try to do something that is accepted by others because that's maybe unlikely to.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  give results right away.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's a long game, it's a very long game. And if you are aiming a long-term change in long-term impact...
SPEAKER_0:  You gotta be very, very patient about it. And you better, um...
SPEAKER_1:  tame your ego.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, on YouTube and those kinds of places, on the internet, on social media.
SPEAKER_1:  You get feedback.
SPEAKER_1:  Like right away.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's even harder to be patient.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes. So in because yeah, but.
SPEAKER_1:  Change in ideas develop over a period of months and years, not decades.
SPEAKER_1:  and the response from social media and so on is.
SPEAKER_1:  and the rate of seconds, minutes and hours.
SPEAKER_0:  So I recommend
SPEAKER_0:  actual physical libraries for people who may wanna
SPEAKER_0:  appreciate or remember.
SPEAKER_0:  sense of time.
SPEAKER_0:  and how long it takes.
SPEAKER_0:  to build something. I think it is.
SPEAKER_0:  You're right, that's the immediacy and the right response of... And the fact that these...
SPEAKER_0:  Buh.
SPEAKER_0:  Please, is over.
SPEAKER_0:  And the algorithm wants you to respond right away and interact with itself, right?
SPEAKER_0:  I can see the appeal.
SPEAKER_0:  What's?
SPEAKER_0:  true innovation, I think, does anyone.
SPEAKER_0:  Scream.
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't, it's not shiny.
SPEAKER_0:  especially in the beginning.
SPEAKER_0:  Ehm
SPEAKER_0:  But it's also important to not fool ourselves and think that everything that people criticize
SPEAKER_0:  has some super important meaning behind it.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's a mix of...
SPEAKER_0:  the technique, the methods and your gut feeling.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and a weird dance between learning and accepting.
SPEAKER_1:  the ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  of the current science.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  at times trusting your gut.
SPEAKER_1:  and rejecting those.
SPEAKER_1:  The science progresses by...
SPEAKER_1:  sometimes rejecting the ideas of the past or sometimes building on them in a way that changes them, transforms them.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, and I think what is hard is to
SPEAKER_0:  really
SPEAKER_0:  drill down.
SPEAKER_0:  into a concept, right? You can create a
SPEAKER_0:  a new thing.
SPEAKER_0:  and then it may
SPEAKER_0:  be appealing and get a lot of.
SPEAKER_0:  gain a lot of traction, but.
SPEAKER_0:  sustain that, to continue that, you really need to show the true expertise.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's not only about defining a problem, but then really systematically solve that problem.
SPEAKER_0:  maybe over the course of decades.
SPEAKER_1:  You mentioned library.
SPEAKER_1:  I've also saw that you've translated scientific documents, or at least I mentioned that you did it.
SPEAKER_1:  at some point in your life.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  So let me ask you how much.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think it's lost in translation?
SPEAKER_1:  in science and in life.
SPEAKER_1:  How many languages do you speak?
SPEAKER_1:  Two.
SPEAKER_1:  How much is lost?
SPEAKER_1:  in translation, in science, and in life between those.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's actually three because science is like another language.
SPEAKER_1:  It is.
SPEAKER_1:  I speak Russian, a little bit of French.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's always fascinating to see how much is lost. And the Soviet Union has a tradition of science and mathematics and so on. And it's interesting that.
SPEAKER_1:  a lot of the wisdom gained from...
SPEAKER_1:  that part of the world.
SPEAKER_1:  is lost.
SPEAKER_1:  basically because it was never translated.
SPEAKER_1:  Well...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not sure if it is lost per se.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe it's more like a gain in some sense.
SPEAKER_0:  because you understand.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Science is ultimately human.
SPEAKER_0:  pursue. So you cannot separate.
SPEAKER_0:  as much as maybe it's the best.
SPEAKER_0:  system that humans ever came up with.
SPEAKER_0:  to seek knowledge to generate and make sense of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  It works most of the time. It doesn't mean it's perfect.
SPEAKER_1:  The kind of translation you do, by the way, was for scientific work.
SPEAKER_0:  Directly translated for scientific work, yes. I think that...
SPEAKER_0:  Again, we will.
SPEAKER_0:  Brains are equally distributed, but opportunities are not. Right.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  want to include, if you want to benefit from all human.
SPEAKER_0:  power, whatever we can generate as human beings, you need to include everybody on the table.
SPEAKER_0:  and that is by extending the opportunity.
SPEAKER_0:  I think most of us that make it.
SPEAKER_0:  tend to think that we did because of something special about ourselves.
SPEAKER_0:  but it is important to know that.
SPEAKER_0:  No, we were given opportunities.
SPEAKER_0:  That's why we are here, not because...
SPEAKER_0:  there was something inherently special about us or...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  or that the system truly selects for the ones that really are.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and language is a part of the opportunity.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, language is an opportunity because it comes with similar to bacteria, right? They speak these languages. They have, even we call this, we call culturing the bacteria, we call it culturing, right? When we grow bacteria that we isolate from the environment in the lab.
SPEAKER_0:  meaning that you create an environment for them to grow and thrive.
SPEAKER_0:  and sustain themselves. That's what we say, but culture is.
SPEAKER_0:  for microbiologists.
SPEAKER_0:  Fort.
SPEAKER_0:  language comes with a different culture, a different perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  And you bring that to...
SPEAKER_0:  the table.
SPEAKER_0:  It brings the sense of diversity that can only be achieved.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  Clashing perhaps two different cultures, two different languages, two different approaches, maybe in some cases four different approaches.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I think language is not just a mechanism of communication. It's a way to, uh,
SPEAKER_1:  It's a dynamic.
SPEAKER_1:  system of exploring ideas and it's interesting to see that different languages explores ideas differently.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, and I think that, so when I said science is like a language itself.
SPEAKER_0:  I said it in two different ways. One is very...
SPEAKER_0:  very literal meaning that you can speak English, but that doesn't mean you will understand the scientific paper.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a different level of English that you need to learn to understand. Even not just for scientific papers, even from discipline to discipline.
SPEAKER_0:  I challenge any chemist to
SPEAKER_0:  read an evolutionary biology paper.
SPEAKER_0:  and vice versa. or p.
SPEAKER_0:  sound extremely different and different language altogether.
SPEAKER_0:  But there's also the language of communicating and because words matter, how we talk matter.
SPEAKER_0:  how we represent our science matters. So yes, just learning English as a second language alone is not going to make you.
SPEAKER_0:  fluent in science either.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's interesting because.
SPEAKER_1:  In that sense, you speak many more than three languages because you're pretty cross-disciplinary.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like you have a foot in.
SPEAKER_1:  in a lot of disciplines, in question, geology, biology.
SPEAKER_1:  Evol-
SPEAKER_1:  evolutionary biology I mean this
SPEAKER_1:  uh chemistry
SPEAKER_0:  Biochemistry, biophysics, even we do a lot of statistics. So there's a lot of mathematics to what we do as well. Yes, we like to think of it as this.
SPEAKER_0:  NOS astrobiology program says I repeat it because it's fun.
SPEAKER_0:  that it is not a...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  fruit salad but it's a smoothie.
SPEAKER_0:  that that's what we're generating.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  not a fruit salad. So a smoothie is a successful.
SPEAKER_1:  is a successful combination of those fields that a fruit salad is not.
SPEAKER_0:  I wouldn't say it's success, necessarily.
SPEAKER_0:  If you put a
SPEAKER_0:  If you put the wrong ingredient and you press the blender and you made it a smoothie, you made it a smoothie.
SPEAKER_0:  It can ruin the entire mix.
SPEAKER_1:  Ken it though, because the
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like yes, I can definitely assess that for ginger first. Those that ruins every smoothie. I don't like ginger. I think so, but it's just a personal thing. And also I don't like cinnamon.
SPEAKER_0:  But, um...
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, the ginger has a cinnamon taste, because I thought ginger was...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think they do but I also don't like was that
SPEAKER_1:  I think they add in a lot of smoothies. I was forced a smoothie. I went to Malibu with a good friend of mine, Dan Reynolds, and he forced me to consume a smoothie.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's probably the first movie I've ever had.
SPEAKER_1:  because I always was very judgmental of the kind of places people that drink smoothies, but it was good.
SPEAKER_0:  That's good. Well, smoothie is very American, so I... Yeah, it is an American thing. I wouldn't say success per se, but it is true that...
SPEAKER_0:  when you dance at the edge of different disciplines, that's when the...
SPEAKER_0:  inevitably the innovation will rise because you will see things.
SPEAKER_0:  maybe a little differently when you're on the edge, right?
SPEAKER_0:  but it will probably take longer.
SPEAKER_0:  and it may not be.
SPEAKER_0:  Understood right away, it may not.
SPEAKER_0:  come into final form quickly.
SPEAKER_0:  given that it is.
SPEAKER_0:  and new
SPEAKER_0:  Doh.
SPEAKER_0:  concept rising.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  therefore the patients will make more sense, I'm sorry, patients will be even more important. So if you are
SPEAKER_0:  In other words, if you are...
SPEAKER_0:  into.
SPEAKER_0:  Immediately.
SPEAKER_0:  appreciation.
SPEAKER_0:  That's probably not the way to go.
SPEAKER_1:  You're one chemical organism
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, so let me ask maybe a little bit more of a personal thing. Where did your life form originate?
SPEAKER_1:  And what fond memory do you have from the early days of childhood?
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  that are representative of your bacteria culture.
SPEAKER_0:  I was born in Istanbul.
SPEAKER_0:  So I grew up in Turkey.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a city that has two...
SPEAKER_0:  continents which
SPEAKER_0:  It's quite interesting you have a.
SPEAKER_0:  You see, a welcome to Europe.
SPEAKER_0:  sign and then welcome to Asia sign.
SPEAKER_0:  same day.
SPEAKER_0:  depending on which part of the bridge you are.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's where I was born and I spent roughly 20 years of my life in the night.
SPEAKER_0:  immigrated to the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a very proud culture, it's a beautiful culture.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a very flavorful culture.
SPEAKER_1:  what aspects of it is part of who you are.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  What are the beautiful aspects that you carry with you in your heart?
SPEAKER_0:  Uhhh
SPEAKER_0:  I think...
SPEAKER_0:  We are very.
SPEAKER_0:  Sincerely, Human.
SPEAKER_0:  as a culture.
SPEAKER_0:  Do we have a saying that don't go to bed?
SPEAKER_0:  if you're
SPEAKER_0:  Neighbors hungry.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you wouldn't...
SPEAKER_0:  eat any food in front of someone where I come from.
SPEAKER_0:  without offering.
SPEAKER_0:  to be shared by.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think those things, however small they may sound.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, really.
SPEAKER_0:  big deal, especially when you are put in a, or move to a place that.
SPEAKER_0:  may not have those attributes.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think that.
SPEAKER_0:  culturally there.
SPEAKER_0:  be a little conscious.
SPEAKER_0:  You just roll deep human.
SPEAKER_1:  The connection, the value of the connection between.
SPEAKER_0:  I think so, yeah. I think I definitely carried that with me.
SPEAKER_1:  We talk a lot about biology. Let me ask you about the romantic question, what role does love?
SPEAKER_1:  in the human condition.
SPEAKER_1:  or.
SPEAKER_1:  in the entirety of life on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not easy to learn.
SPEAKER_0:  have to love if you're not loved.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's something, but the good news is that it is something that's.
SPEAKER_0:  You can learn.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's, you can practice.
SPEAKER_0:  It's interesting, Max, you will tell us about the
SPEAKER_0:  and teach yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  have to.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe give yourself the thing that wasn't given to you. And then ultimately.
SPEAKER_0:  give it to others. I think it would be quite
SPEAKER_0:  Arrogant to think that we will be capable of.
SPEAKER_0:  loving it could be anything really.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, so just like translation, it's a repeating and a dynamical process.
SPEAKER_0:  That you can learn. Yeah, that you can learn. Yes, and you should learn.
SPEAKER_0:  We should even there's no excuse not learning.
SPEAKER_1:  to love.
SPEAKER_1:  Because that's deeply human.
SPEAKER_0:  It is a deeply human thing. It is a very sad thing if any one of us passes this.
SPEAKER_0:  planet without.
SPEAKER_0:  though.
SPEAKER_0:  knowing what love is. And that could be a love to a pet, a love to a plant.
SPEAKER_1:  robot. robot.
SPEAKER_1:  Just kidding.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Or a fake plant.
SPEAKER_1:  We love.
SPEAKER_1:  We can't help who we love.
SPEAKER_1:  What advice would you give to a young person today? What advice would you give to a young person today?
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  how to have a career.
SPEAKER_1:  they can be proud of or how to have a life they can be proud of.
SPEAKER_1:  You said an interesting thing about brains.
SPEAKER_1:  being distributed evenly but opportunities not.
SPEAKER_1:  It's um...
SPEAKER_1:  It's really interesting to think about. I've talked to folks from Africa.
SPEAKER_1:  you realize that there's whole areas of this earth.
SPEAKER_1:  that have so much brilliance.
SPEAKER_1:  But unfortunately so little opportunity
SPEAKER_1:  And one of the exciting things about the 21st century is more and more opportunities are created.
SPEAKER_1:  And so the brilliance is unlocked in all those different places.
SPEAKER_1:  And so all these young people now have the opportunity to like do something.
SPEAKER_1:  to change the world.
SPEAKER_0:  I had a chance to visit.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, pause now.
SPEAKER_0:  So I.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  was invited to give a talk in a very northern most part of the country.
SPEAKER_0:  that was impacted by the war tremendously.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was a...
SPEAKER_0:  public talk.
SPEAKER_0:  was open to everybody in the village.
SPEAKER_0:  And I was told even people drew from Sarajevo to attend.
SPEAKER_0:  whenever I
SPEAKER_0:  think about.
SPEAKER_0:  our role as a scientist or...
SPEAKER_0:  beneficiaries of the knowledge that we create.
SPEAKER_0:  I always think about that night.
SPEAKER_0:  That's how many people were in that room. It was incredibly.
SPEAKER_0:  crowded.
SPEAKER_0:  And the-
SPEAKER_0:  lots of young people.
SPEAKER_0:  who were trying to
SPEAKER_0:  start everything new.
SPEAKER_0:  and not do.
SPEAKER_0:  or not carry.
SPEAKER_0:  replace whatever maybe the feeling that was taken from them with hope and love.
SPEAKER_0:  starts.
SPEAKER_0:  a new beginning, be the seed for the next generation.
SPEAKER_0:  And it moved me so much that they all came.
SPEAKER_0:  to hear about.
SPEAKER_0:  early life.
SPEAKER_0:  Space.
SPEAKER_0:  something maybe different for them that maybe they were always interested in and never thought about.
SPEAKER_0:  but what's
SPEAKER_0:  What stayed with me was the look on their faces and the feeling in the room.
SPEAKER_0:  The energy just was really...
SPEAKER_1:  moving to their willingness to be the seed.
SPEAKER_1:  the first of their.
SPEAKER_1:  family and generation to do that.
SPEAKER_0:  Big news.
SPEAKER_0:  and I will.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's exactly.
SPEAKER_0:  Why I'm telling this whole-
SPEAKER_0:  story because
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  For most of us, we may have to be that seed in our families, that the first one to do something new.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, do to break that cycle, whatever is it that you want to break.
SPEAKER_0:  free from.
SPEAKER_0:  I want, I would want the young people to know that you can be that.
SPEAKER_0:  that there are.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Just.
SPEAKER_0:  Wonderful things.
SPEAKER_0:  to learn from this life. And it's just.
SPEAKER_0:  incredible to be living.
SPEAKER_0:  and I would.
SPEAKER_0:  want them to know that their voice matters and they need to use it, especially
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  those who...
SPEAKER_0:  think that their voice doesn't matter.
SPEAKER_0:  And ultimately, I think what it comes down to is to trust in yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  trusting and respecting your voice.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're not loved...
SPEAKER_0:  Learn how to love. If you were not respected, start by respecting yourself. Learn how to respect yourself. We can teach ourselves things.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's really difficult.
SPEAKER_1:  when you're surrounded by people.
SPEAKER_1:  that don't believe in you.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, I definitely.
SPEAKER_0:  know the feeling and...
SPEAKER_0:  I would just want them to know that.
SPEAKER_0:  They don't need to be defined.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  or reduce down to.
SPEAKER_0:  what others see in them.
SPEAKER_1:  Believe in yourself, have the respect for yourself. Try to develop the respect and the love for yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  And then from that...
SPEAKER_1:  It flourishes.
SPEAKER_1:  You'll find others that'll give you love.
SPEAKER_0:  It may not.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, life is not fair. It's true.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's be prepared that it's a it's a it's not very fair. 4.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I don't want to depict this.
SPEAKER_0:  Disney story that and then yes and everything will be just fine.
SPEAKER_0:  It mostly isn't, but you learn a way. Learn, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Life does it all the time.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of which, what do you think is the meaning of all this?
SPEAKER_1:  What's the meaning of life?
SPEAKER_1:  Why are we here?
SPEAKER_1:  Why we are here.
SPEAKER_1:  all the beauty you've discussed.
SPEAKER_1:  Why?
SPEAKER_1:  is the translational mechanism machinery here.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think there is. As you can see on this video, I broke my rock faster than myilte. So this is it.
SPEAKER_0:  Why so much beauty?
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  It is because we choose to see it that way. It's beautiful.
SPEAKER_0:  What's?
SPEAKER_0:  There is no meaning, I don't think so.
SPEAKER_1:  Why is it so beautiful?
SPEAKER_1:  Why do we choose?
SPEAKER_1:  from where.
SPEAKER_1:  is the imperative.
SPEAKER_1:  to see it as...
SPEAKER_1:  to see so much beauty in a thing.
SPEAKER_1:  that scientifically speaking.
SPEAKER_1:  or
SPEAKER_1:  from a rational perspective is void.
SPEAKER_1:  beauty.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just, it just is.
SPEAKER_0:  Not everybody chooses.
SPEAKER_0:  to see the beauty.
SPEAKER_1:  Hate is gonna hate.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, we have the capacity.
SPEAKER_0:  We have the capacity, so why not use it to the fullest, right? We have the capacity.
SPEAKER_1:  that capacity, isn't that fascinating?
SPEAKER_1:  Have we developed that?
SPEAKER_1:  It feels like that was always laid in there in the whole process of life.
SPEAKER_1:  this ability to...
SPEAKER_1:  to find, to introspect ourselves.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's definitely suiting to things like that.
SPEAKER_0:  but I don't think...
SPEAKER_0:  there is a meaning like that way. It's fascinating that we can understand it.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  But why is it soothing?
SPEAKER_1:  There's a desire, there's a-
SPEAKER_0:  But suiting doesn't mean...
SPEAKER_0:  there's a meaning. Why why is soothing a meaning?
SPEAKER_0:  Let me just put it this way, because there is just, I think, so much unfairness going on.
SPEAKER_0:  I wouldn't even dare myself to think that there's a meaning.
SPEAKER_0:  out of respect to the ones that are suffering.
SPEAKER_1:  I see.
SPEAKER_1:  I-
SPEAKER_1:  stink.
SPEAKER_1:  I think out of suffering emerges flourishing in beauty. I mean, that's what I see. I agree with you. When I went to Ukraine and saw all the people suffering.
SPEAKER_1:  in their eyes.
SPEAKER_1:  and in their stories is a hope for the future, is a love.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  is a love for the people who are still living, is a love for life, so it's there. And that's the dark thing is the suffering.
SPEAKER_1:  and the law somehow intensifies your appreciation.
SPEAKER_1:  of the life that is to the left.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a weird thing too. I think that's-
SPEAKER_0:  There's some.
SPEAKER_0:  something about.
SPEAKER_0:  still doing your best.
SPEAKER_0:  and believing that there's...
SPEAKER_0:  There is
SPEAKER_0:  whatever goodness is worth.
SPEAKER_0:  working for.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  is beyond and to do that without a meaning.
SPEAKER_0:  that there's something more humiliating, humbling.
SPEAKER_0:  and profound about that.
SPEAKER_0:  And I, we have a-
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  this will come out very random. Okay so I just saw tighten sounds.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  In Turkish bathrooms?
SPEAKER_0:  There is this sign.
SPEAKER_0:  that says...
SPEAKER_0:  Leave it.
SPEAKER_0:  is you want to find it.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think...
SPEAKER_0:  That's a pretty good.
SPEAKER_1:  That's your meaning of life found in the turkey. There's wisdom too.
SPEAKER_0:  There's wisdom to that but it also is because the...
SPEAKER_0:  however you leave.
SPEAKER_0:  defines you.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  So I think there's some.
SPEAKER_0:  profound meaning to that too, just leave it as you would.
SPEAKER_0:  wants to find it.
SPEAKER_1:  so that...
SPEAKER_1:  your little scribble.
SPEAKER_1:  in the long story.
SPEAKER_1:  of life on earth.
SPEAKER_1:  is one that ultimately
SPEAKER_1:  did a pretty good job.
SPEAKER_1:  at least kept it the same as you found.
SPEAKER_0:  Or at least I left it in the way that I wish I found it.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, yeah, right.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh man.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, that's that's a wisdom from Turkish best
SPEAKER_1:  That's where I...
SPEAKER_1:  search for wisdom as well and it's...
SPEAKER_1:  as we started with the origin of life and ended.
SPEAKER_1:  with the wisdom of the Turkish Baratheon. I think that's a perfect conversation. You're an incredible person.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... the humor the humanity but also the brilliance of your work
SPEAKER_1:  I really appreciate that you would talk with me today. This was really fun.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for having me.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with Batul Kachar.
SPEAKER_1:  To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now, let me leave you with...
SPEAKER_1:  One of my favorite quotes from Robert Frost.
SPEAKER_1:  In three words, I can sum up everything I've ever learned about life.
SPEAKER_1:  It goes on.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for listening.
SPEAKER_1:  I hope to see you.
SPEAKER_1:  next time.