SPEAKER_1:  I'm here with Mr. Beast, the brilliant mastermind behind some of the most popular videos ever created.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think you'll ever make a video that gets 1 billion views?
SPEAKER_0:  I think maybe one of the videos we've already made might.
SPEAKER_0:  Get a billion views.
SPEAKER_0:  Which one do you think? Probably like the squid game video with enough time. I mean, it's only a year old and it's already on 300 million or...
SPEAKER_0:  Some of the newer ones we've done I've gotten like 100 million views in a month.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So those four projected over 10 years because YouTube's not going anywhere.
SPEAKER_1:  Probably one of those. Over time they don't necessarily plateau.
SPEAKER_0:  It's interesting. We're literally jumping right in. I love it. Uh-
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  I-
SPEAKER_0:  I'm a firm believer that it's much easier to hypothetically get.
SPEAKER_0:  10 million views on one video than 100,000 on 100.
SPEAKER_0:  And part of why it's much easier in my opinion is like, if you make a really good video, it's just so evergreen and it never dies.
SPEAKER_0:  because YouTube.
SPEAKER_0:  When you open up YouTube and look at the videos, they're just serving you whatever they think you'll like the best, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  And so if you just make a great video.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's constantly just above.
SPEAKER_0:  every other video, you know, even two years down the road, then they'll just keep serving it and never stop, you know, which is why it's much easier to make one great video than a bunch of mediocre ones.
SPEAKER_1:  What about 1 billion subscribers?
SPEAKER_1:  You've passed PewDiePie's most subscribed to YouTube channel.
SPEAKER_1:  When do you think you get a billion?
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, let me do some math real quick.
SPEAKER_1:  So we're on 100.
SPEAKER_0:  So you think about this? No I don't honestly I-
SPEAKER_0:  Because one thing you'll find if you want to gain subscribers, if you want to get views, if you want to make money, almost any metric,
SPEAKER_0:  in this video creation space if you want something, it all comes back to, okay, well then just make great videos. So instead of like focusing on all these arbitrary vanity metrics.
SPEAKER_0:  I just kind of focus on the one thing that gets me all that.
SPEAKER_0:  which is make good videos. But, and I do think we will, one day hit a billion subscribers. I don't have a plan on going anywhere.
SPEAKER_0:  Even though we're only on 120 million right now I'm the main channel.
SPEAKER_0:  I think like we're doing around 10 million a month now.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  YouTube just, yeah, I just don't see it going anywhere. And I don't see any reason why I'd ever get burnt out or quit. So I think with enough time, yes.
SPEAKER_1:  I wanted to ask you those family friendly questions before I go to the dark questions.
SPEAKER_0:  We have dark questions right now, but if you wanted to hook them, you would start off with the dark question. That's how you get them. Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, well, let me ask about the...
SPEAKER_1:  A Twitter poll you posted.
SPEAKER_1:  at 10,000.
SPEAKER_1:  dollar death poll.
SPEAKER_1:  He tweeted.
SPEAKER_1:  If someone offered you $10,000 but if you take it, a random person on earth dies.
SPEAKER_1:  Would you take the $10,000?
SPEAKER_1:  and 45% of people said yes.
SPEAKER_1:  That's, at least at the time I checked, 850,000 people committing murder.
SPEAKER_1:  for just eight.
SPEAKER_1:  $1.5 billion in total.
SPEAKER_1:  So what do you learn about human nature from that?
SPEAKER_0:  That's a good question.
SPEAKER_0:  Honestly, this is like late at night when I threw that up too. I was just like, huh, this will be a funny thing. I assumed it'd be 90% no and like 10% yes.
SPEAKER_0:  but there are a lot of serious people.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, for you guys listening, I just did this random Twitter poll. I was like.
SPEAKER_0:  Would you take 10 grand if it meant someone random in the world died?
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of the replies on the tweet were like, hell yeah, why not? And I was just not expecting that.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And so I don't really know. I mean, I feel like your take would be better than mine.
SPEAKER_1:  Was it disturbing to you, surprising to you?
SPEAKER_0:  A little bit, yeah. But obviously a lot of people were trolling, but you read through those replies, I do think like 10% of them were like dead serious. WELL
SPEAKER_1:  I think sometimes the trolling and the lulls reveal.
SPEAKER_1:  thing we're too embarrassed to admit about the darker aspects of our nature.
SPEAKER_1:  So I don't know if you listened to Dan Carlin's Hardcore History Podcast.
SPEAKER_1:  He has an episode on painful tainment.
SPEAKER_1:  which he
SPEAKER_1:  describes throughout history.
SPEAKER_1:  how humans have been really attracted to watching the suffering of others.
SPEAKER_1:  So public executions, all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  and he believes that's in all of us.
SPEAKER_1:  that for example if something like a YouTube
SPEAKER_1:  or different platform.
SPEAKER_1:  stream to public execution.
SPEAKER_1:  or streamed the torture of another human being.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of people would say that's deeply unethical.
SPEAKER_1:  but they will still tune in.
SPEAKER_1:  and watch.
SPEAKER_1:  And that we're...
SPEAKER_1:  We're attracted to that drama.
SPEAKER_1:  and especially the most extreme versions of that drama.
SPEAKER_1:  So I think.
SPEAKER_1:  part of the lulls.
SPEAKER_1:  reveals something that's actually true in that poll.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  Like your answer is so much better than mine.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you?
SPEAKER_1:  Think about that maybe even with the squid game.
SPEAKER_1:  So I think, how many views does this game currently have? 300 million? Something like this?
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  Just imagine...
SPEAKER_1:  thought experiment how many views that video would get.
SPEAKER_1:  It feels like real.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean YouTube is like, we'll turn a blind eye. We won't take it down.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  I've obviously probably have billions of you.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you think you will die and do you think you'll be during a video?
SPEAKER_0:  Probably doing something dumb like going to space when I'm older, like trying to go to Mars or something like that. I know for a fact it won't be on a video. Every video we do with safety experts and stuff like that, so it's not really risk, it's just that a lot of experts are doing it, and it's really helpful to walk down
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I could see myself like, you know, after a million people go to Mars or something like that, I'd probably like, you know what, let's go. And something like that maybe.
SPEAKER_1:  not in the name of a video just for the hallway. No. No.
SPEAKER_1:  Are you open to taking risks when you shoot videos? You just went to Antarctica. I mean, you're putting yourself in the line a little bit, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Of course, but we've had that video on the works for three years and then we consult with tons of experts.
SPEAKER_0:  radar the entire path we're going to walk beforehand to see if there's crevasses. So we know there's no crevasses, we do training, we consult with experts, and we have survival guides there with us and monitor the weather and everything.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like any variable that where we could get harmed, we just pre-plan for it. Same thing with buried alive.
SPEAKER_0:  David Blaine spent a week underground.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I consulted with him and consulted with basically anyone who ever buried themselves alive. You know, the coffin we used to bury me, we did so many tests. Like that coffin was buried 10 times before I was, you know, for way longer than 50 hours.
SPEAKER_0:  it tested the airflow and everything to the point where I was safer in that coffin underground than I was above ground. So we just tend to just not leave anything up to chance, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  Another strange question then.
SPEAKER_1:  So you recorded these videos.
SPEAKER_1:  to yourself five years, 10 years from now.
SPEAKER_1:  Have you recorded a video?
SPEAKER_1:  that's to be released.
SPEAKER_1:  once you die.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, first off...
SPEAKER_0:  I am just glad that not every one of your questions have to do with like views or things like that. You really had me kidding.
SPEAKER_0:  different questions. So this is good.
SPEAKER_0:  No, seriously. It's a little dark. No, no, but it's fine because a lot of people just be like, how much money do you make? You know, it's just something I just, everything's always about money now over for when people talk to me. So it's nice.
SPEAKER_0:  But for the videos I made, for you guys who probably don't follow me too closely, when I had 8,000 subscribers and I was a teenager, I filmed a bunch of videos and scheduled them years in the future. And I said...
SPEAKER_0:  I filmed one where I was like, hi, me in a year. And the video went up a year later and it was just like, hey.
SPEAKER_0:  I think you'll have 100,000 subscribers. And then I did one where I was like, time me in five years.
SPEAKER_0:  I was like, hey, in five years, I think you'll have a million.
SPEAKER_0:  and then one that hasn't come out yet, but comes out in two years.
SPEAKER_0:  was high me in 10 years and I tried to predict 10 years later how many subs I'd have
SPEAKER_0:  what he's referring to.
SPEAKER_0:  And yes, there are some that are scheduled, like...
SPEAKER_0:  20 years in the future. And so if I don't dial, just move them up.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I remember, because I filmed these though, like...
SPEAKER_0:  seven years ago, but it was.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember saying a line like...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, if I'm dead, then I...
SPEAKER_0:  currently just in a coffin and like whatever, blah, blah, blah. And because the only way the video would go up is if I'm not alive and if I'm not alive, then I won't be able to push back the schedule upload date so it will go public automatically. And so yeah, I have a couple of those.
SPEAKER_0:  Like if I knew I was gonna die of like...
SPEAKER_0:  cancer or something and I had like three months to live. I would vlog every day, I'd film so many videos and then I would just schedule upload a video a week for like the next five years so it's like I'm still alive and I would completely act like I'm still alive and everything and I think something like that would be cool.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know why, but I fantasize, not fantasize, but I've dreamt about that a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, if I only had 30 days to live, what would I do? And for me, I would try to make like a decades worth of content and schedule upload it so they automatically go public in the future.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it's just like I never died. I'm just there.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's a kind of immortality, but it's also kind of troll.
SPEAKER_1:  on the concept of time.
SPEAKER_1:  that you can die in the physical space but persist in the digital space.
SPEAKER_1:  I actually, I recorded a video like that.
SPEAKER_1:  ZED
SPEAKER_1:  some concerns and
SPEAKER_1:  I just thought it's also a good exercise to do. A video would like.
SPEAKER_1:  to be released if I die.
SPEAKER_1:  And it was actually a really interesting exercise.
SPEAKER_1:  It's cool. Like it shows like what you really care about. I guess it's like writing a will.
SPEAKER_1:  when you're younger you don't think about that kind of stuff
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly. Mine was just dumb. I'm bones in a coffin. Yours was probably so serious. No, it's fine.
SPEAKER_1:  actually, what you realize is like there's no point to be serious at this point.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a weird.
SPEAKER_1:  thing i guess you've done this but it's a weird thing to address the world when you the physical you is no longer there.
SPEAKER_1:  So like, you know this would only be released if you're no longer there. Exactly.
SPEAKER_0:  You know what's funny? Of all the people listening to this, we're probably the only two people.
SPEAKER_0:  that have made videos for when we die. It's like such a niche thing and the fact that we're bonding over it's kind of funny. I think people should-
SPEAKER_1:  Think about doing that. It's not just about YouTube. It's also social media. Just think about it.
SPEAKER_1:  Like there's gonna be a last tweet.
SPEAKER_1:  And the last, I don't know, Facebook post, the last Instagram post.
SPEAKER_1:  and uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I feel like there's some aspect.
SPEAKER_1:  That's...
SPEAKER_1:  meditative to just even considering making a post like that.
SPEAKER_1:  And also it's a way for the people that love you to kind of...
SPEAKER_1:  Like celebrate. Check ou.
SPEAKER_0:  Think that would help them cope or not.
SPEAKER_0:  Like if someone randomly watching this did film a video.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, for if they accidentally died in some freak accident to be given to their family. Do you think that would?
SPEAKER_0:  And it was like a genuine. I think it would really help.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it depends because like- How would you even intro that?
SPEAKER_0:  Hey Mom!
SPEAKER_0:  If you're seeing this, you know, it means I'm probably dead. Yeah, exactly. That's how you entry. That's the opener.
SPEAKER_0:  I just want you to know. Yeah, I guess.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and I guess you could say in a kind of funny way, but and just talk about the things that mean a lot to you.
SPEAKER_1:  Because otherwise you are at the risk of the last post you have is like.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know talking shit about like.
SPEAKER_0:  McDonald's, screw it by order. Exactly. And then you're dead, that's it, 100 years.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know this.
SPEAKER_1:  I do recommend it, it's like the Stoics meditate on death every day in the same way you kind of
SPEAKER_1:  meditating your death when you make a video like that. Because it's actually not just even talking to yourself, it's talking to the world.
SPEAKER_1:  And it like.
SPEAKER_1:  For some reason, at least for me.
SPEAKER_1:  that made it very concrete.
SPEAKER_1:  that there's going to be an end.
SPEAKER_1:  And I'm like.
SPEAKER_1:  It's almost it's over for me. If I make in the video, it's over for me. It's an interesting thought experiment. I recommend people.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Try it
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  From, are you afraid of death by the way?
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, I- I-
SPEAKER_0:  It's hard because...
SPEAKER_0:  Like, what if you just die and then you just see nothing forever? You know? Yeah, the nothingness. It just fades to blackness and you're just like that for trillions upon trillions to-
SPEAKER_0:  billion squared years.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just, it's scary. But also before you're born, you don't remember those X amount of years either. So.
SPEAKER_0:  That gives me a little comfort, but.
SPEAKER_0:  No, it's definitely.
SPEAKER_0:  Very scary. Something I'd rather not think about until I'm like 80. I'll deal with that problem then.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if I told you this, but.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm kind of hopeful that someone like Elon was like
SPEAKER_0:  smart people just like.
SPEAKER_0:  You know what screw it.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm gonna figure out a way where we can slow down aging, get it where we can live to be two, 300 years old just like set their sights on that.
SPEAKER_0:  and then just kind of save us.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Be really nice. It's like, it's, it's almost.
SPEAKER_0:  absurd.
SPEAKER_0:  to think that in our lifetime, they won't figure out a way to just even slightly slow down aging, where we could live to be like 120, 130. And then that extra time, they won't figure out somewhere where we could live to be 200. Like obviously not immortal.
SPEAKER_0:  but...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't see how in my lifetime.
SPEAKER_0:  the life expectancy doesn't just expand.
SPEAKER_1:  What also could be that the immortality is achieved in the digital realm.
SPEAKER_1:  Could be long after you're gone as a Mr. Beast.
SPEAKER_1:  run by a chargpt-tab system. Exactly.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that consumes everything I ever said, everything I ever wrote, but I don't want that. I want to live.
SPEAKER_0:  What are you smart people out there, figure it out. I'll keep you entertained, but I need you to figure out how to keep me alive. Stay with me till 200, that will make me happy.
SPEAKER_1:  Well that's funny, who owns the identity of Mr. Beast once the physical body is gone?
SPEAKER_1:  Like is it illegal to create another MrBeast that's Chad GPT based? I don't know what the laws are on that.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, once I'm dead, I don't care.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I... Well, you just said you did, Kermit.
SPEAKER_1:  There could be a AI like many Mr. Beast that are created after you're gone.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, that'd be cool to be able to like train up a model and.
SPEAKER_0:  and let them loose so my content lives on, I guess. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  but it somehow feels...
SPEAKER_1:  like it diminishes the value you contribute. Yeah, it's inauthentic, but it's also...
SPEAKER_1:  There's some aspect to the finiteness of the art.
SPEAKER_1:  being necessary for you.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, once the second that thing starts spamming out videos, the videos lose all meaning and it's pointless and it's a money grab.
SPEAKER_1:  If you were on YouTube for a-
SPEAKER_1:  how long she's run it, for a year.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you change it? How do you improve it?
SPEAKER_0:  It's hard because...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, obviously I'm biased because we're doing really well, but.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like.
SPEAKER_0:  When I open up YouTube on my television, I get the videos I wanna watch. I don't-
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know. I don't-
SPEAKER_0:  I don't ever open it and wonder like, what are these? What are these 10 videos on my homepage? When I click on a video, my suggestion, I don't ever wonder what these are, like I...
SPEAKER_0:  I-
SPEAKER_0:  And maybe it's because I'm very adamant about like the kind of videos I watch and I try not to watch videos that I don't want to get recommended more because I just that's how I think but
SPEAKER_0:  I'm very happy with how it is at the moment. I think-
SPEAKER_0:  One thing though that I just hate with the passion is the comment section on YouTube. It's just so bad.
SPEAKER_0:  But I know that's not something that's gonna
SPEAKER_0:  10X the growth of the platform, but if you think about it.
SPEAKER_0:  You go to Reddit to read comments and somehow like, you know, usually the top.
SPEAKER_0:  post on a popular Reddit post.
SPEAKER_0:  or not spam.
SPEAKER_0:  You know what I mean? Like have you ever clicked on something on the front page of Reddit and the most upvoted reply to it is like...
SPEAKER_0:  go check out my site right here. And it's like trying to scam you out of a thousand dollars. Yeah, I can't even think of one instance I've ever had that happen. So this is my channel, my main niche.
SPEAKER_0:  Like Reddit, it's so nice to click on posts and just see what people have to say.
SPEAKER_0:  I almost wish like you had that same feeling when you read the comments on a YouTube video. Instead it's like...
SPEAKER_0:  It's so many people just copy and pasting so many bots that just grab the top comment for your previous video and paste it over. So the top comments on every videos are the same. And the things that break through that are just scammers trying to get you to give them a thousand dollars for a free, you know, fake ad.
SPEAKER_1:  that comment section is one of the most lively on the internet.
SPEAKER_1:  So it would be amazing if YouTube invested in
SPEAKER_1:  creating an actual community, like where people could do high effort comments and be rewarded for it, like on Reddit.
SPEAKER_1:  Like actually right out of...
SPEAKER_0:  That would make me so happy. Cause like when I upload a video.
SPEAKER_0:  I usually go to Twitter to see feedback. I read my comments and I'll flip through newest.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just, I feel like.
SPEAKER_0:  Reddit and Twitter just give me so much better filtered feedback, especially now that
SPEAKER_0:  with Twitter blue because people pay $8 a month.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I've noticed like any tweets I get from verified users now, they're usually not just garbage troll takes. Like these are people paying $8 a month. Like they're-
SPEAKER_0:  usually.
SPEAKER_0:  relatively sensible.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it's been pretty nice. Like after I upload a video, I just go on the verified tab on Twitter and just see what people have to say.
SPEAKER_0:  And anyways, I live for the day that YouTube's like that.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think about it?
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think of all the?
SPEAKER_1:  fun activity happening recently since Elon.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  I bought Twitter.
SPEAKER_0:  I think he should make me CEO, like I tweeted.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I should say sort of we had, we just...
SPEAKER_1:  like a couple hours ago I had a conversation with Elon.
SPEAKER_1:  You guys sent in exchange for some excellent ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I legitimately think, obviously you're exceptionally busy, but...
SPEAKER_1:  I legitimately think.
SPEAKER_1:  It would be awesome if you somehow participate in the future of Twitter. Yeah, it would be fun.
SPEAKER_1:  because there's so much possibility of different ideas. First in the sort of the...
SPEAKER_1:  the content like.
SPEAKER_1:  dissemination, hosting, and all the different recommendations like the search and discovery, all the things that YouTube does well.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the most exciting thing is...
SPEAKER_0:  He's willing to move fast. And so I think there's gonna be a lot of interesting things that come out of it.
SPEAKER_0:  because he's just moving quick and.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of these more mature platforms just take years to do the simplest stuff and they're very bureaucratic.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's gonna...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  It'll be interesting to see which way it goes when you just kind of take a move quick, break things, whatever type approach to social media.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm actually-
SPEAKER_0:  Pretty curious to see what features he rolls out.
SPEAKER_1:  So it will be your first...
SPEAKER_1:  Act as Twitter CEO.
SPEAKER_0:  I can't spoil it.
SPEAKER_0:  I gotta get hired.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think about video on the platform?
SPEAKER_1:  And do you think that's an interesting or is it like messing with the.
SPEAKER_1:  The medium, the nature.
SPEAKER_0:  platform. I think Twitter will always be closer to TikTok than it is to YouTube. Like, at least in its current form. Like, I don't-
SPEAKER_0:  I don't see.
SPEAKER_0:  20 minute, one hour long videos or whatever, even 15 minute videos being watched over there. See more is like the short and snappy stuff closer to TikTok.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  At the same time, Twitter is a really good comments section for the internet.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's almost weird why.
SPEAKER_0:  Like why doesn't Twitter allow you to embed YouTube videos? Like why?
SPEAKER_0:  Why does...
SPEAKER_0:  Understand
SPEAKER_0:  You should just ask Elon that. Like, I don't know if that's a YouTube thing, but...
SPEAKER_0:  When a YouTuber posts a video, why do they have to link to YouTube? Why can't they just embed it on Twitter and just play it there?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean wouldn't that just solve a lot of-
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, but then the two companies have to agree to integrate each other's content. I don't know, but I-
SPEAKER_0:  It seems like a win-win. I mean, well, it's more of a win for Twitter because then people don't have to leave the platform.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean that would be the...
SPEAKER_0:  the easiest solution.
SPEAKER_1:  like when you watch the ads on a YouTube video.
SPEAKER_1:  that's embedded in Twitter. Who guessed them all?
SPEAKER_0:  It would still be YouTube, but at least then right now people just post a link and it takes you off Twitter and it just kills your session time on Twitter.
SPEAKER_1:  That's really interesting. But that, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  because the Twitter, whatever the...
SPEAKER_1:  the dynamics of the comments, especially once the spam bots are taken care of.
SPEAKER_1:  Twitter just works.
SPEAKER_1:  It's really nice. So Reddit is a nice comment section for the internet. It's like slower pace, more deliberate.
SPEAKER_1:  Like higher effort.
SPEAKER_1:  Twitter's like this high-paced.
SPEAKER_1:  like ephemeral kind of stream, but there's the vote, the up voting and the down voting works much better because you can do.
SPEAKER_1:  Retweeting, right?
SPEAKER_1:  because the social network is much stronger than it is on YouTube.
SPEAKER_1:  Like the interconnectivity.
SPEAKER_0:  Un-un-unready you're gonna get-
SPEAKER_0:  The top replies are gonna be the most refined ones whereas Twitter, stuff flows to the top that's not super refined. But like you're saying, more off the cuff stream of consciousness which...
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of people prefer it's a little more personal.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you think Twitter compares to YouTube?
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of how you see its future on role in 2023.
SPEAKER_0:  I think YouTube's gonna be YouTube and-
SPEAKER_0:  Not much is really gonna change, but it's gonna keep growing just because.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, that's.
SPEAKER_0:  what it does because it's owned by Google.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  But Twitter, I don't know, I mean, it's one of those things like you can't predict if like, you know, a year from now, an economy is going to be in a recession or booming and I think Twitter's kind of the same thing.
SPEAKER_0:  One thing's for certain, a lot of things are gonna be rolled out, but who knows, honestly.
SPEAKER_1:  You responded to Elon saying, Twitter's unlikely to be able to pay creators more money than YouTube.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, why do you think that is?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, yeah, because I think the tweet I responded to was one where he was saying
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  The-
SPEAKER_0:  users will jump over if Twitter can potentially pay more.
SPEAKER_0:  than other platforms.
SPEAKER_0:  I was just saying, obviously, because Google has Google AdWords, and that's Google's whole thing, it's putting ads on stuff. They've been doing it better than anyone else in the world for a very long time.
SPEAKER_0:  It's very unlikely in the next few years that...
SPEAKER_0:  Twitter is gonna just magically or any platform, give a creator.
SPEAKER_0:  the ability to make higher CPMs than on YouTube.
SPEAKER_0:  It's... It's...
SPEAKER_0:  Kinda crazy, like some creators...
SPEAKER_0:  in December, you know, Q4 because ad rates are higher because of Christmas and everything. Some creators literally make like 30, $40 per thousand views and that's after YouTube's cut. Like it's almost like hard to think about like how high the RPMs get. And even then, once you pull out of finance and cars the high CPM niches and you move into just normal stuff it's still just...
SPEAKER_0:  They're sheer volume of creators and the fact that all of them get these multi-dollar CPMs at scale.
SPEAKER_0:  It's pretty beautiful.
SPEAKER_1:  So you do.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know what you would call them, but like integrated ads in your videos and you do, I would say masterfully
SPEAKER_0:  It's like part of the video. You know about brand deals?
SPEAKER_1:  Brand deals, is that what you would call that? Did
SPEAKER_1:  So it's a brand deal, it's part of the video.
SPEAKER_1:  It's still really exciting to watch and yet there's a plug for the brand.
SPEAKER_0:  In general, just brand deals since you brought it up, integrating them well. I think that's something a lot of creators...
SPEAKER_0:  Do.
SPEAKER_0:  Like they'll just do a brand deal out of the blue. They'll just be filming a video and then around the three minute mark, just start talking about a random company. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  You.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like if you don't want viewers to click away and you want people to not get pissed off and call you to sell out, you gotta find a way to integrate in the content.
SPEAKER_0:  And ideally, use the money in the video to make it better. Like, the easiest thing you do when you do a brand deal is just tell people.
SPEAKER_0:  how you're using money from the brand deal make your content better
SPEAKER_0:  And if you do that, like no one cares. Now they're supporting you for it. And you go from being a sellout to like, oh.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm doing this to make better videos for you guys. You know, I don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if you can share, but...
SPEAKER_1:  with those brands.
SPEAKER_1:  when you have discussions with them.
SPEAKER_1:  Are they strict about how long you need to be talking about it?
SPEAKER_1:  Or is it more...
SPEAKER_1:  about their living.
SPEAKER_1:  control to you about the artistic element of it.
SPEAKER_0:  The problem is the ones who don't give us artistic element, we just don't really work with anymore. Sure. Thanks for listening, everyone.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, we get 100 million views a video now and...
SPEAKER_0:  confidently say I know how to entertain them and convert them better than.
SPEAKER_0:  these random brands so.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, yeah, if they don't give us that freedom, I just won't work with them.
SPEAKER_1:  So you have that leverage, but for smaller cr-
SPEAKER_0:  It's a lot harder. Yeah, and they're gonna just say
SPEAKER_0:  45 seconds, here's what you say, take it or leave it. And it's like pretty brutal.
SPEAKER_0:  Because I think just in general.
SPEAKER_0:  if brands were more accommodating to let.
SPEAKER_0:  creators tell their story of the brand and talk about the brand in a way that felt a little more natural.
SPEAKER_0:  I think A, it would be less cringe.
SPEAKER_0:  people would be less likely to go.
SPEAKER_0:  and you know tap, tap, tap, skip.
SPEAKER_0:  And obviously it would convert better, but they're just so afraid and they want this standardized thing. Hey, these words.
SPEAKER_0:  and 45 seconds.
SPEAKER_0:  right here at this three-minute mark.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I often think about how...
SPEAKER_1:  resist that.
SPEAKER_0:  You just don't do them, though, right?
SPEAKER_1:  Not on YouTube, right? On audio, I do ads in the very beginning, and I say you can skip them if you want.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... but
SPEAKER_0:  Grant loves that. I don't.
SPEAKER_1:  Like the point is they So the funny thing about podcast is different than YouTube videos
SPEAKER_1:  Podcast people actually.
SPEAKER_1:  do listen to ads a lot because it's a slower pace and they like the the creator voice
SPEAKER_1:  like talking about the thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  But in general I just...
SPEAKER_1:  don't believe you should be talking about a thing for a minute exactly, and that's going to be effective. I wanna see the data for that. I think what's much more effective is the way you do ads.
SPEAKER_1:  Which is like...
SPEAKER_1:  integrated into the content, put a lot of effort into making a part of that, like doing the brand deals.
SPEAKER_1:  I just.
SPEAKER_1:  It's difficult.
SPEAKER_1:  to have that conversation. It's like a very.
SPEAKER_1:  strenuous conversations you have to have with brands. You have to have each one at a time. And I just wish there was more of a culture to say like...
SPEAKER_1:  quality of the ad read matters a lot more.
SPEAKER_1:  than the uh...
SPEAKER_1:  the silly parameters like the timing of it, how long it is, the placement of it, all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  What percentage of your viewers do you think have seen one of my videos before?
SPEAKER_1:  What percentage of the viewers on YouTube, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, your viewers.
SPEAKER_1:  of the viewers.
SPEAKER_0:  YouTube though. Yeah, okay sure or all of them. It's just interesting because you're speaking very specifically like about my brand deal process like for example I made a video going through my personal life like how am I even allowed to.
SPEAKER_0:  And so in my head, I'm like, I wonder what percentage of these people even have any idea what he's talking about.
SPEAKER_1:  That's interesting. I love the thinking about.
SPEAKER_0:  The whole time we were having this conversation, that's all I could...
SPEAKER_0:  Think about it. God dammit, he's-
SPEAKER_0:  There's probably like 50% of these people have no fucking clue what he's saying. Probably. And we're about to torture him for five minutes. Yeah, yeah, probably. But that's something I can't turn off in my brain.
SPEAKER_1:  Less than 50%. Is that a good thing or a bad thing? Is that exciting to you?
SPEAKER_1:  that there's like 50% of people don't.
SPEAKER_1:  I've not watched the MrBeast video. Isn't that an opportunity to like-
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I guess it's an opportunity to grow. I don't know. Honestly, I was just kind of excited to hang out with you. Yeah, me too. I mean, it was a lot of fun. Who cares if there's mics? Yeah, so it's kind of like having a buddy to go along the journey as I'm just kind of eating shit and doing my normal grind. It was like kind of fun. And also you just say really wise stuff constantly.
SPEAKER_0:  So honestly, no, I never even put any thought into like the demographics of what I could gain. It's just interesting because like my retention brain, when you talk about something, I'm instantly like
SPEAKER_0:  What value are they gonna get? How many of them are gonna be interested? What percentage of people do I think will lose? And I'm like running all those calculations in the background.
SPEAKER_0:  And that whole conversation, like the long, it's just something I can't turn off.
SPEAKER_0:  Bells are like.
SPEAKER_0:  Error error, this is bad.
SPEAKER_1:  What are the different strategies for higher attention?
SPEAKER_1:  for your videos in general.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, how do you cook good food? You know what I mean? That's like the same kind of question.
SPEAKER_1:  I see. So there's so many different ways that you, so it boils down to.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think at the level of a story?
SPEAKER_1:  Or do you think like literally watching?
SPEAKER_1:  Five seconds at a time.
SPEAKER_1:  Am I gonna tune out here? Am I gonna tune out here? Am I gonna tune out here?
SPEAKER_0:  It's all of it. You need the overarching narrative and then you also need the micro where every second, you know, needs to be entertaining and you basically
SPEAKER_0:  What's interesting is the longer people watch something, the more likely they are to keep watching.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't have to try as hard in the hypothetically back half of a video as you do in the front. Like, even right now, we're so deep into this where-
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of people listening are probably just gonna keep listening relatively close to the analyst. We just have a really boring part of this conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  because they're just in it, they're immersed.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  A big, like to really boil it down to a simple level, you just wanna get people where they're immersed in the content and then just kind of hold them there.
SPEAKER_1:  We had this discussion offline and by the way, I should mention that.
SPEAKER_1:  This is like late at night.
SPEAKER_0:  It is. What time is it? It's 9 o'clock.
SPEAKER_1:  I only slept one hour last night because I'm an idiot.
SPEAKER_1:  and I flew to the wrong location.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, here, we're like, hey.
SPEAKER_0:  let's just book you a hotel and a flight. He's like, no, I got it. We're like, you sure? We can just do it. We always do this. He's like, no, I got it, I got it. He's gonna have to rub it in. I know, and then.
SPEAKER_0:  today come to find out he flew.
SPEAKER_0:  to the wrong airport, airport with the, or city with a similar name to ours. Just- Same name, same name in a different state. And I was like, that's why you should have let us book it. And so he's on one hour of sleep and he's literally been dying all day. Before this podcast, he downed like two things of coffee. We've been going all day hard.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I've been get to interact with you. That's just say that this gave me an opportunity to I got a.
SPEAKER_1:  a ride from a stranger and it was an incredible person.
SPEAKER_1:  that got to interact with them. So there's so many kind people around here.
SPEAKER_1:  Just like this kind of Southern energy.
SPEAKER_1:  And then I got to go to a diner because I could.
SPEAKER_1:  There's only one hour between me arriving and having to fly out. So I went to a diner, and there's a really kind waitress that called me honey.
SPEAKER_1:  That was a beautiful moment, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  I was so confused, you tweeted about that, and I...
SPEAKER_0:  Steel's like.
SPEAKER_0:  Lex, my assistant was like, Lex isn't here yet. And I saw your tweet and I was like...
SPEAKER_0:  he's here, so he was like, no, he's still flying. I was like, an hour ago, he just tweeted about a nice diner. I didn't realize you flew to the right. It was a diner in a different state. And then you had to fly over here. And then I called you and you didn't answer. I was like, hmm. I was like, something's not adding up.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I feel like it's such an idiot because I'm...
SPEAKER_1:  Apparently the world
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  has cities like Springfield, right?
SPEAKER_1:  Like every single state has a Springfield. Oh really?
SPEAKER_1:  I think so.
SPEAKER_0:  That's like a Simpsons
SPEAKER_1:  joke right that like it's
SPEAKER_1:  the city and in some sense the Springfield and I think every single state or most of them have a Springfield. And the same is true for like a
SPEAKER_1:  Georgetown, I think the most popular, I forget what the most.
SPEAKER_1:  There's like a list of things people get.
SPEAKER_0:  When they run out of ideas, they just keep using the same thing all over. They're your Achilles heel.
SPEAKER_1:  Anyway, I got to meet a bunch of people from...
SPEAKER_1:  from your team is just an incredible human being. So let me just ask on that topic.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you hire a great team? What have you learned about hiring?
SPEAKER_1:  for, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  everything for the main channel that you do.
SPEAKER_1:  for the the react again the the gaming channel
SPEAKER_1:  to Mr. Beesburger to...
SPEAKER_1:  uh... feasible so that
SPEAKER_0:  The big thing is, especially in this content creation, because it's not like anything that's done on Netflix or-
SPEAKER_0:  or different content mediums.
SPEAKER_0:  I really need people who are coachable and like.
SPEAKER_0:  really see the value in.
SPEAKER_0:  I care about because it's a very specific way of going about things and it's a
SPEAKER_0:  like a thing, there's no one like plug and play. Like if Netflix wanted to hire someone to do a documentary.
SPEAKER_0:  there's probably tens of thousands of people you could hire that have worked on documentaries before.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you want to hire someone to make.
SPEAKER_0:  super viral YouTube videos, you know, like we do.
SPEAKER_0:  There's just no one you can really pull from. Like sometimes I'll hire people from a-
SPEAKER_0:  game shows, right? They have all these preconceived notions about pacing and how a video should be, and you have to spend like the first year like breaking all these habits and-
SPEAKER_0:  and they think they're better than you. Like a lot of people in traditional think they're better than what we do.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  For me, it's almost easier to hire people.
SPEAKER_0:  that are just hard workers that are obsessed and
SPEAKER_0:  really coachable and just train them how to like.
SPEAKER_0:  be good at content creation and production than to hire someone from like
SPEAKER_0:  traditional, which is the only way to really do it. Cause there's not that many YouTube channels that have scaled up. So it's not like there's a huge talent pool of people who've worked on YouTube channels.
SPEAKER_0:  So
SPEAKER_0:  It's easier just to train someone than just pull them from traditional because traditional people just thumb in the macau and date.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, they have all these opinions and things and they just think our way of going about things is dumb.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so.
SPEAKER_1:  You want people who have the humility to have a beginner's mind even if they have experience.
SPEAKER_0:  I can see the value, like actually.
SPEAKER_0:  You'll still get it. It's so crazy. Especially some of my other friends that are scaling up their YouTube channels. There's people that will come on and you'll ask them, like, what do you want to be doing in five years? And instead of saying, oh, I want to be working on this channel, they'll be like, oh, I hope to be working on movies or this or that. And they see like.
SPEAKER_0:  working on a YouTube channel as a launchpad to go into traditional. And it's like, no, like you just don't get it. This is the future. This is the end goal. This is your career.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And so I'm just so tired of having those kinds of conversations. I feel like.
SPEAKER_0:  people really should be coming around.
SPEAKER_1:  Are there like...
SPEAKER_1:  recurring interview questions that you ask.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there ways to get...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, but the biggest thing is like, what do you wanna be doing in 10 years? And if their answer isn't making content on YouTube, or if their answer is anything like movies or traditional, stuff like that, it's like just a hell no. Like it just won't even remotely work. I see you're
SPEAKER_1:  I really want people to believe in the vision.
SPEAKER_0:  of YouTube. Yeah, I mean, ideally, it's like, oh, working here, you know what I mean?
SPEAKER_1:  So it's less about the medium and more about just being a great team that's doing epic stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, well, and yeah, the media as well, because those
SPEAKER_0:  It's just.
SPEAKER_0:  It's hard to-
SPEAKER_0:  put it into words, but...
SPEAKER_0:  It's just two completely different ways of going about things. You know, like our videos aren't scripted and you know, it's a lot more run and gun and-
SPEAKER_0:  when we, if we hypothetically blow up a giant car or whatever, like you only have one take, you know what I mean? So, and it's not scripted and so you have to over film, overshoot things, overcompensate for like the dumb way of going about it. And a lot of traditional people would be like, well, just plan what you're going to say and just plan the angles. You can cut the cameras in half, you can save 50 grand here, you can save, you know, $75,000 in editing, this and that. And it's like, yeah, but.
SPEAKER_0:  That's not authentic. That's, you know, blah, blah. You get it. It's almost so obvious that it hurts to have to like constantly have these conversations, but.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what we live in.
SPEAKER_1:  There's also detail like there's a taste, like I've watched a bunch of videos with you.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's clear to you that you've gotten really good.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know what the right word is, style or taste, to be able to know what's good and not in terms of retention, in terms of just stylistically, visually.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't have to think, I can just watch a video and it just...
SPEAKER_0:  screams in my head like this is what this is what should change based on the you know million videos i've watched and all these viral videos are consumed like this is bubble what's optimal
SPEAKER_0:  Things like that. It's almost like.
SPEAKER_0:  Your brain's like a...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, like a neural net and like if you consume enough viral videos and enough.
SPEAKER_0:  good content that you just kind of start to like train your brain to like see it and see these patterns that happen in all these viral videos and
SPEAKER_0:  So that anytime I watch a video or a movie or anything, I just can't stop thinking about.
SPEAKER_0:  what is optimal and so it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  It gives me a headache sometimes when I watch something too slow or I don't think it's optimal. Obviously my taste isn't the end all of y'all.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  but that's something that kind of torments me, if that makes any sense.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, you can't enjoy a slow-moving movie. And that's not to say there's no... The retention on Godfather is horrible. Yeah, no, exactly. I've tried to watch that movie like three times. But that's not to say slow movies are bad. Like there's an audience for it. It's just obviously not what I've trained my brain to like.
SPEAKER_0:  and social media and YouTube right now, like this is not the meta.
SPEAKER_1:  And in general, like you said, in neural network, you're training your brain.
SPEAKER_1:  in part on actual data.
SPEAKER_1:  Right, so you're actually data driven. So you're looking at like in terms of thumbnails and titles.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  different aspects of the first 5-10 seconds.
SPEAKER_1:  and then throughout the video the retention all that you're looking at all that
SPEAKER_1:  uh, for your own videos to understand how to do it better. So that's where the neural network is training.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically.
SPEAKER_0:  There are ways you can kind of see like the most few videos on YouTube every day and stuff like that.
SPEAKER_0:  I just kind of consume those every single day and I've been doing that for way too many years.
SPEAKER_0:  And then you just start to notice patterns.
SPEAKER_0:  The thumbnails on the most of your videos are videos that go super viral, tend to be clear, tend to not have much clutter, tend to be pretty simple. Titles tend to be less than 50 characters. Intros tend to be this. Stories tend to be this. You just kind of like, after you see those thousands and then tens of thousands of times.
SPEAKER_0:  It just starts to click in your head like this is what it looks like. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  So how are you able to?
SPEAKER_1:  Transfer that taste that you've developed to the team.
SPEAKER_1:  So for like, because you said like broad things, but I'm sure there's a million detailed things.
SPEAKER_1:  Like what zoom to use on the face to use in the thumbnail, right?
SPEAKER_0:  The answer is whatever makes the best video.
SPEAKER_0:  Because the problem is the more...
SPEAKER_0:  I have so many friends who are like this, they'll make like checklists for their editors. They'll make, you know, this beat and this beat and you need to have like a three-part arc and then this, but the problem is that's how you.
SPEAKER_0:  the more constraints you put on the team, the more repetitive and-
SPEAKER_0:  less innovation you get and the more like, you know, after 10 videos, people are going to be like, all right, I've already seen this. So
SPEAKER_0:  To me, and I'm 24, and you know, probably my mindset will change over the next 10 years. I just haven't.
SPEAKER_0:  been in this industry too long, but.
SPEAKER_0:  The only way to really make innovative content and keep things fresh is to not put constraints on, or put as little as possible.
SPEAKER_0:  And so that's why I'm very hesitant on all that stuff because the more-
SPEAKER_0:  I say the more they're gonna be like, oh, then that's what we do. And then.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I'll say one time like, oh, you know, ideally there's a cut every three seconds. And then next thing you know, every video, there's a cut every three seconds or whatever. So
SPEAKER_0:  It's hard because I try to...
SPEAKER_0:  Give, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  as little
SPEAKER_0:  not training, but as a little...
SPEAKER_0:  facts or as possible and more just make suggestions if that makes any sense. You mean publicly or to your team? on
SPEAKER_1:  What was so you talked about sort of teaching your voice or your style, whatever we want to call it to other people on the team so they can be kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  Mr. Beast replacement.
SPEAKER_1:  So what's the process of teaching this? feito d transformer
SPEAKER_0:  No, I got you. You're more talking about like what I would call almost like cloning, right? Like Tyler and other people like that. Yeah. So.
SPEAKER_0:  When we were hanging out today I was showing him how
SPEAKER_0:  We have multiple people and they come, it's almost like talking to the camera, it's a habit. Yeah, you turn slowly to the camera. I was like, it was a habit. Is it weird to you?
SPEAKER_1:  not be looking at the camera.
SPEAKER_0:  This whole
SPEAKER_0:  Interview I
SPEAKER_0:  constantly I've been turning towards the camera, I'm talking to him, it's a habit. My whole life I've just been talking to a camera.
SPEAKER_1:  What were you thinking about when you were looking at the camera?
SPEAKER_1:  Do you like imagine?
SPEAKER_0:  I'm fully thinking about the person just sitting watching it and I almost
SPEAKER_0:  It's weird when I'm looking at the camera, I don't see a camera.
SPEAKER_0:  in a taze, picturing what the viewer is seeing when they watch it, if that makes sense.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's where...
SPEAKER_0:  I'll be saying things or doing something and then like when I'm watching, I'm like, that's not what I want. And then I'll freeze up. It's very weird when I'm filming. I'm melted.
SPEAKER_0:  For people who haven't worked with me too much, don't think like.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, it's very weird, like how I go about it. Cause I'll just be doing whatever, like lighting a firework. All right, this is a thousand dollar firework go to lighting a ve-
SPEAKER_0:  and I'll like freeze, because in my head I'm like, this, I don't know, I don't like how that floated or how that shot looked, because it's weird. I can perfectly picture.
SPEAKER_0:  what I'm filming by just looking at the camera and then putting myself through the lens of the camera while irgendwann.
SPEAKER_0:  making content. I can do it at the same time.
SPEAKER_1:  So you're like real time editing.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that's something that...
SPEAKER_0:  Didn't at the start come natural to me, but in the last probably like five years it's happened.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I would say it's one of my greatest strengths, I don't know how I developed it.
SPEAKER_0:  But anytime I'm filming anything, like, it's almost like...
SPEAKER_0:  like right side of my brain, I just can just look at it and I see exactly what I'm filming and I can just picture it.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, that's probably.
SPEAKER_1:  recording the video.
SPEAKER_1:  Being the talent for the video and then watching the editing.
SPEAKER_1:  and like analyzing it carefully and do that over and over.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, you do that 10,000 times. Yeah, you do the editing.
SPEAKER_1:  editing more than being in front of the camera.
SPEAKER_1:  So like.
SPEAKER_1:  is
SPEAKER_1:  you start to see yourself from that third person perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  Exactly. That actually helps with the nerves of it too.
SPEAKER_1:  Like.
SPEAKER_1:  you see it as creating a video versus performing.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, yeah, I think so.
SPEAKER_0:  It's weird, I've never...
SPEAKER_0:  been nervous talking to a camera. It's harder for me to talk to a person than to talk to a camera, which I feel like a lot of people say that though that are.
SPEAKER_0:  whatever, make content, right? Interesting. I've heard that so many times.
SPEAKER_0:  Or maybe not, maybe I'm just awkward and dumb. Maybe they're practiced, I-
SPEAKER_1:  to me it's
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, both are terrifying, but being in front of the camera by yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  is much easier.
SPEAKER_0:  Really? Yeah, so much. I prefer it a million times over.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's my whole life. You know, so it's just, that's why it's interesting. Like you've spent more of your time talking to people. It comes natural, you know that, but it's really interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  I talked to her.
SPEAKER_0:  piece of plastic. Are you huggin' me?
SPEAKER_1:  I guess you're talking to a person too. They're just on the other side of the camera. Yeah, they're just a pixel.
SPEAKER_0:  on a screen.
SPEAKER_1:  So cloning, how do you...
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yeah, that's right. That's the whole rabbit trail. So.
SPEAKER_0:  I was showing him that I have a lot of people in the company who are able to think like me and
SPEAKER_0:  uh, basically make decisions.
SPEAKER_0:  I would make if I was like, if you were asked, hey, in this video, should we climb a mountain or should we dig a hole? Right. And like, you know, they would pick the same answer I'd pick 90 plus percent of the times. And so one example is Tyler who I was showing you.
SPEAKER_0:  He was pitching stuff for content. And you can see, like this, he was on point.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Basically for just.
SPEAKER_0:  Four or five years, we just spent an absurd amount of time together.
SPEAKER_0:  and worked on every single video together and we worked side by side.
SPEAKER_0:  And same thing with my CEO, James. He literally lived with me for a couple years.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm a big fan of just finding people who are super obsessed and-
SPEAKER_0:  All in and A players that
SPEAKER_0:  You know, they really just want to be great. And they're just dumping everything I have in them.
SPEAKER_1:  And like you were saying, because I'd love to find that.
SPEAKER_1:  and develop that.
SPEAKER_1:  You're saying you're basically for.
SPEAKER_1:  a long time just said everything you were thinking to them.
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly. Like James, the guy who's basically my right hand man right now.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Two years he lived with me and we probably talked on average over those two years, seven hours a day.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, anytime I had a phone call, I'd throw it on speaker and I'd let him listen. Anything I was reading, any content I was consuming, like really just training his brain to think like me. So that way...
SPEAKER_0:  um... he could just...
SPEAKER_0:  do things without my input, without me having to constantly watch over him or give him advice. And that's where we've gotten. Like, so for the first six months he didn't do anything. He just studied me and studied everything I cared about and how I spoke and.
SPEAKER_0:  blah, blah, and then the next six months, he started taking on some responsibilities and now he can just run the company and you know.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't ever really have to check it on him. Most of the decisions he makes are exactly what I would do.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and so.
SPEAKER_0:  I call that cloning, I don't know what other people would, but it's just like finding people that are really obsessed and they just kind of really want it and just being like giving them an avenue to like... you
SPEAKER_0:  Get it, if that makes any sense.
SPEAKER_1:  Another way to see it is you're converging towards a common vision, and that makes like brainstorming.
SPEAKER_1:  much more productive.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it just makes it where I don't have to be so involved in everything because I just have these people I know will
SPEAKER_0:  think like I will, at least relatively.
SPEAKER_0:  close to it. So I can kind of almost be in multiple places at once per se. And so these things that...
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  I still approve every idea we film in, you know, everything before we film in all the creative, I approve it, but I don't have to like be in the weeds and nuances and do all this minor stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  I can just let them handle it. I can just do the more macro things.
SPEAKER_1:  i got a chance to sit in
SPEAKER_1:  to a lengthy brainstorming session with Tyler and others.
SPEAKER_1:  That was really cool.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you talk about the process of that?
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  people pitching ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  and you.
SPEAKER_1:  pitching alternatives or shutting down ideas just going plowing through ideas very quickly
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, you kind of just lit.
SPEAKER_0:  described exactly what we did. Yea.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, but the ideas are really...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, really good. She's tossing out.
SPEAKER_1:  like different categories of ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  and then also fine tuning them to see like.
SPEAKER_1:  How do I change, like thinking about the titles and...
SPEAKER_0:  I work so well off of inspiration.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, that's a something.
SPEAKER_0:  Like give me any word, I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  And Vince
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, like I went to space, you know, what happens if you blow up a nuke in space or I went to the moon, I went to Mars, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Because you said that one word, it was able to inspire me to come up with four ideas. So.
SPEAKER_0:  That's just, it's for me.
SPEAKER_0:  If you, the way to get a hundred million views on videos, you need something original, creative, something people really need to see, ideally never been done before, all these like things.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you need like.
SPEAKER_0:  If you want to consistently go super viral, you need just a constant stream of ideas. And the only way I've really found that I can consistently come up with a hundred million view videos is to intake inspiration and then see what my brain outputs.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  That's kinda at its core foundation, what I'm doing there. It's just like, intaking a lot of random inspiration to see what spawns in my mind so I can...
SPEAKER_1:  output it. The network of your brain is generating.
SPEAKER_1:  The video, the title, the thumbnail, all that.
SPEAKER_0:  jointly exactly and that only comes because
SPEAKER_0:  I spent 10 years of my life just obsessively studying all that stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like you would literally.
SPEAKER_1:  potentially shut down a video just because you can't come up with a good title.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, 100% or a thumbnail. Yeah, I mean, that's what happened to 70% of those in that pitch session. It's like.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, what was one of them? Genius vs. 100 people or...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, like maybe average intelligence versus genius.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I was like, what the heck is the thumbnail even if the title was good? Yeah. Yeah, I mean this
SPEAKER_0:  So many, but yeah, people don't click, they don't watch.
SPEAKER_1:  That's so interesting, but you developed over time the ability to kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  Give it what what makes for a good title?
SPEAKER_1:  short.
SPEAKER_0:  Not just sure, it's also-
SPEAKER_0:  I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  If someone reads it, are they like, do they have to watch it? Is it just so intrinsically interesting that it's just gonna
SPEAKER_0:  Fuck with them if they don't click on it. You know what I mean?
SPEAKER_1:  So it doesn't have to be short, but it has to be.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you almost want to have a retention.
SPEAKER_1:  to word by word read.
SPEAKER_0:  Ideally, it's a title also that...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, because the titles don't live in a vacuum, right? So it has to lead into the content. So ideally the title represents.
SPEAKER_0:  content that you would want to watch for 20 minutes. So if it's a 20 minute video and the title is I stepped on a bug.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not gonna, because it's all of it combined. The click through rate is gonna be much lower.
SPEAKER_0:  And then if it was like a five second video, people might click it. So you gotta, like even nuances of the length of the video based against the title will affect whether people wanna click it because sometimes they just don't add up.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's that.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, ideally you want it below 50 characters because above 50 characters on certain devices, you run the chance of it going dot, dot, dot.
SPEAKER_0:  So like.
SPEAKER_0:  I took a light pole and I saw how many...
SPEAKER_0:  dollar bills I could stack on top.
SPEAKER_0:  and they would just go dot dot dot because it's too long and it can't finish it. And that's the worst thing because then people don't even know what they're clicking on. And so it's going to do even worse.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Short.
SPEAKER_0:  Simple, ideally, and just so freaking interesting to have to click.
SPEAKER_0:  And it is a good segue into the content and it represents the length of the cut.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's probably stuff it's hard to convert
SPEAKER_1:  convert into words for you like.
SPEAKER_1:  I stepped on a bug versus.
SPEAKER_1:  stepping on a bug versus Mr. Beast stepped on a bug.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, well, I mean that...
SPEAKER_0:  It's funny you bring that up, so it's like...
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, the more extreme the opinion, typically the higher the click-through rate. If you can, like.
SPEAKER_0:  Ah.
SPEAKER_0:  pay it off in the content, then it just supercharges it. So like,
SPEAKER_1:  So you have a kind of estimate of the.
SPEAKER_0:  extremely sad this this water right you're like
SPEAKER_0:  CG water sucks.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that'd do fine.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you said Fiji water.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the worst water bottle.
SPEAKER_0:  or the worst water I've ever drank in my life. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  way more extreme opinion would do way better. you have to deliver.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, but then you have to deliver, because the more extreme you are, the more extreme you have to be in the video.
SPEAKER_1:  That's almost inspiration for you to step up.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, you can be more extreme in a positive way. It's easier though.
SPEAKER_0:  Pause it.
SPEAKER_0:  Duh.
SPEAKER_0:  Negative clickbait is much easier than positive clickbait. It just is. It's so much easier to get negative clicks.
SPEAKER_0:  And so a lot of people are just.
SPEAKER_0:  In my opinion, you know, a little bit lazier and...
SPEAKER_0:  They just take the route like, oh, well, this one gets the same amount of clicks and it's easier, less effort.
SPEAKER_0:  The positive one is.
SPEAKER_1:  doing a large number of numbers of something.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I spent this number of hours doing
SPEAKER_0:  But whatever, if you just wanted to help people or... Alright, it's just harder to...
SPEAKER_0:  get 10 million views on a video helping people than it is to get 10 million views on a video tearing down a celebrity, you know what I mean? or whatever negative video you want to insert there.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, that said, most of your videos are pretty positive.
SPEAKER_0:  So what's... But not a lot of people do those kinds of videos because they're hard. Yeah, they're hard.
SPEAKER_1:  Some of that is giving away money, right?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. What's the secret to that?
SPEAKER_1:  What's, how do you do that right?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, like give away.
SPEAKER_1:  money or? In a video that made it to make it compelling.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, is it? So there's a number that
SPEAKER_1:  is better than another number.
SPEAKER_0:  for it, right? The higher number is always better than the lower number. Yeah, for the most part. You know, it's interesting like.
SPEAKER_0:  Some videos will give away a million dollars. Some videos will give away half a million. There's not really-
SPEAKER_0:  I guess so. I'm retracting what I just said. I was more joking with that, but there's no difference whether I put 500K or a million. There's probably not even really a difference between 100K or a million. I haven't really looked into it.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of our, most of your videos are not us giving away a million dollars and sometimes the million dollar videos just don't do as well as the other ones. So.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a certain point where
SPEAKER_0:  A dollar amount is just a large dollar amount to an average human. And so I think that point is 100K. Like anything above 100K.
SPEAKER_0:  The average human is just like, that's a lot of money. It doesn't, a hundred K and a million like...
SPEAKER_0:  Doesn't really move the needle, if that makes sense.
SPEAKER_0:  Which that's a very nuanced piece of information that applies to very few people but...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. I don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  It's fascinating. It's fascinating. Our relationship with money is fascinating.
SPEAKER_1:  Why is it so exciting?
SPEAKER_1:  to get.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, the times I found like 20 bucks in the ground.
SPEAKER_1:  I like.
SPEAKER_1:  Incredible.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know why.
SPEAKER_0:  Why are you so happy?
SPEAKER_1:  I'm happy. Like what exactly, so joyful about that. I mean, it depends where you are in life, what the situation is.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, there's also a gamified aspect to it. It's exciting.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I get it. Like why people want to see people win money. It's just interesting that past 100 grand, it's it doesn't really seem to make a difference. Like it's the same basically.
SPEAKER_1:  So you found that to be true with all the money you've given away that-
SPEAKER_0:  click through it. Like, obviously, in terms of someone receiving it, yeah, a million dollars changes their life drastically more.
SPEAKER_0:  Like that's the difference, like, oh, if you wanted to, you could really quit your job.
SPEAKER_0:  I suppose 100K is like, not really.
SPEAKER_1:  You probably do like a scientific study.
SPEAKER_1:  Like a formula.
SPEAKER_1:  giving away money to click through rate.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there could be some kind of a return. It definitely the returns level off dramatically after 100K. That's basically the premise. What about 10000?
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, no, there's 10, 100,000.
SPEAKER_0:  It's funny because it's such a...
SPEAKER_0:  small niche thing but yeah, 100,000 does it from what I see in our videos get more clicks than 10,000.
SPEAKER_0:  But the difference between 100,000 and a million is just so little. I think big number, big number to a lot of people past that point.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so for 100,000 you can...
SPEAKER_1:  Like a given average salary, you can probably live for a year, given, given what the average salary is in America. So that's like a big, that feels.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think it's also just more when they read the title. It's just like it's a lot of zeros.
SPEAKER_0:  Focloads, zeros, okay, click.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh man, that's fascinating. So on the thumbnail side, again, that's...
SPEAKER_1:  gonna be much harder to say probably.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, but-
SPEAKER_1:  offline, I got a chance to look at a bunch of thumbnails.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's fascinating which ones do well and which ones don't.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there something you could say about what are the elements of the thumbnail that work well? Is this also...
SPEAKER_0:  deeply in sync with something. Well, that's where, yeah, it's the same thing, like how do you cook good food? But it's easier if you pull up a thumbnail and I can be like, that's why that's good, that's why that's bad. The
SPEAKER_0:  Like an example would be like...
SPEAKER_0:  One of my friends, he just uploaded a video recently.
SPEAKER_0:  I called him and I was like, what is this? Because he's a very, very smart guy.
SPEAKER_0:  And in the thumbnail...
SPEAKER_0:  He's getting chased by cops, but...
SPEAKER_0:  The cops were wearing yellow vests, so they didn't look at cops. I was like...
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  Why are the cops in your thumbnail wearing yellow vests? Because that makes it so much more...
SPEAKER_0:  Boring.
SPEAKER_0:  And he was like...
SPEAKER_0:  carrying a flag, but the pole and the color of the flag were the same color, so it's like, it's a little harder to see the flag. I was like, also you're wearing like a shirt with like five different colors, so it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  It's hard to tell.
SPEAKER_0:  what even what your outline is and then in the background there are cars and I was like well if you have cops chasing you why not
SPEAKER_0:  Make the cars, cop cars.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  You know, and.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, cause in my head, I'm like, dang, if you just did those like four or five things, Der would have to be a completeeffect so he could watch the whole video like, so you
SPEAKER_0:  Probably would have got like seven X of views.
SPEAKER_1:  How much?
SPEAKER_1:  I also got a chance to see the number of iterations you do on a
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, just the brain. It's a problem now.
SPEAKER_0:  It's an addiction.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it so you can kind of
SPEAKER_1:  Because a lot of the versions were really good.
SPEAKER_0:  How do you know when to like stop? I love how you, when we pulled up that, the burger one and we were flipping through them, you're like, that's really good. It's like, oh, that's.
SPEAKER_0:  version like one of like a thousand.
SPEAKER_1:  But even the sketch, the idea was good. Like already even the original idea is strong.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so one of our coming up videos, we made the world's largest plant-based burger.
SPEAKER_0:  And the thumbnail we were thinking is like me standing beside the bird because it's six feet tall.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what he's talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  So like just picture a giant six foot tall burger, super wide.
SPEAKER_0:  thousands of pounds and then I'm beside it.
SPEAKER_0:  and then it's like eating the World's Largest Burger.
SPEAKER_0:  Like you, that's just something you have to click. Like, so you were saying like, how would you describe a good thumbnail? Like that, you know what I mean? Like
SPEAKER_1:  But I think you said the one I noticed first that was good, where you were very small in it.
SPEAKER_1:  relative to the, and you do.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't like that one, I think. I needed to come forward a little bit. And also, the photo we took was just my upper body. So they photo-manipulated and created my legs.
SPEAKER_0:  Photoshop and that's why I said I didn't like it because my right leg was a little like off. It was like bent the wrong way. You notice I was like this. Because they had to build those legs in Photoshop. Help me to make a cool bluetooth durable bike.
SPEAKER_1:  Love you.
SPEAKER_1:  Does the physics on the thumbnail have to even make sense? I mean, you can just like exaggerate the head size and all that.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, 100%. Yeah, things don't have to be relative.
SPEAKER_0:  You can.
SPEAKER_0:  You have a car in the background, it'll be three times the size.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, every one of my thumbnails, my face is in the...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, left side, very big.
SPEAKER_0:  So brand recognition, so just people know.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, especially because now that a lot of people copy our videos, it's just nice to like...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, everyone else might make thumbnails like this, but this is mine.
SPEAKER_0:  And obviously we usually over deliver and do bigger stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  Would you recommend to other creators that want to make it big to...
SPEAKER_1:  and they see Mr. Beast and they look up to you.
SPEAKER_1:  to copy some elements of you or to really try to be unique.
SPEAKER_1:  Unique.
SPEAKER_0:  100% unique. You're not.
SPEAKER_0:  The next Mr. Beast, quote unquote, it feels weird saying that in third person, but whatever, is not gonna do what I'm doing better. They're gonna just invent their own way. Like you're just not gonna do what I do better than me.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I have so many, I literally have the best people in the world working here and I reinvest everything I make even to this day. You know what I mean? Like it's absurd the amount of money I spend on content. And I don't care, I'll just stop sleeping and I'll just film every other day. Like you're just not gonna beat me at my own game and that's fine, you shouldn't. Like.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't get where I am by just beating someone else at their own game. I just found my own lane and innovated and adapted. And so...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there's a lot of people that do copy me and it's fine. Whatever do it, but just know you're not going to get to where I am doing that. Um, and so I'd advise you don't.
SPEAKER_1:  You give away a lot of the secrets, basically everything about how you operate. Is there a-
SPEAKER_0:  I don't hold anything back. Go for it. How do you think about that?
SPEAKER_1:  that's also that's pretty rare.
SPEAKER_0:  I think...
SPEAKER_0:  And this is definitely not a...
SPEAKER_0:  Most people in my stance, I don't think would take this stance, but
SPEAKER_0:  I see every other YouTuber or person on social media, is where I also focus super heavily on YouTube.
SPEAKER_0:  But last year we were also the most followed TikTok creator in the world as well. Actually we were most subscribed to YouTube channel in the world and the most followed TikTok account in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  But uh...
SPEAKER_0:  In general, I just see everyone else as collaborators, not competitors. I don't-
SPEAKER_0:  Think giving advice and helping other creators do well in any way harms me and I think it only brings more value to my life.
SPEAKER_1:  How is it?
SPEAKER_1:  jumping on TikTok and trying to understand that platform from scratch. Yeah. So from being a successful YouTuber to understand a totally different algorithm, fundamentally different algorithm.
SPEAKER_0:  It's interesting. Well, not even just the algorithm, just the content. Like I'm going from.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically 15 minutes short films.
SPEAKER_0:  One.
SPEAKER_0:  sub one minute vertical content. It's a whole different.
SPEAKER_0:  Just ballpark.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and so.
SPEAKER_0:  The first little while I was doing TikTok, it was just kind of figuring out.
SPEAKER_0:  What does Mr. Beast look like in this short form content? But recently we've really started to catch our stride and come up with some original concepts and figure out.
SPEAKER_0:  how to innovate over there, just like we did on YouTube. because
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't want it to just be shitty YouTube videos, you know? So, like an example is um...
SPEAKER_0:  We played the rock for 100K and rock paper scissors and the loser had to donate 100K to charity. We did um...
SPEAKER_0:  We went to random people on a campus and we offered them.
SPEAKER_0:  So I said, I'll give you a hundred dollars if you fly to Paris and give me a baguette. And then they said, no. And I was like, I'll give you $300.
SPEAKER_0:  If a lot of parents give me a picket, I was expecting this person to say no, and it'd go up to like 10 grand. And he's like, yes.
SPEAKER_0:  And so he flew to Paris.
SPEAKER_0:  got a baguette and brought it back and gave it to me.
SPEAKER_0:  And that across everything got like 450 million views. Cause it's just really cool just to see this random guy get on a plane, spend a day in Paris, and we cut it up real nicely and bring it back.
SPEAKER_0:  And so we're starting to find just tons of original content over there.
SPEAKER_1:  but it seems like an epic video to make for a-
SPEAKER_0:  a minute. No one on short form is doing it. That's the thing. It's like...
SPEAKER_0:  It's just so funny because like TikTok has been big for a while now, years.
SPEAKER_0:  And then, um...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, as we started to really figure out things on the YouTube channel and get it cranking where I have some free time.
SPEAKER_0:  We set our sights on TikTok and like, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  What are people not doing? How do we make it better, put in more effort, make it good?
SPEAKER_0:  And we did the same thing we did at YouTube, just different over on TikTok and it worked. And now we're the fastest growing or most followed TikTok account in 2022.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's just funny that...
SPEAKER_0:  No one else did that.
SPEAKER_0:  And you're not afraid to do epi-
SPEAKER_1:  stuff, which also during the brainstorming.
SPEAKER_1:  some of the ideas you like, that's better as a short.
SPEAKER_1:  That's crazy.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, can you remember one? Cause I remember I said that a bunch, but I can't think of one. Previously.
SPEAKER_1:  Remember
SPEAKER_1:  is that they were like
SPEAKER_1:  Epic Videos.
SPEAKER_1:  Like really, you're going to do that for a one minute video?
SPEAKER_1:  That's crazy. So like, are you posting similar content to a YouTube short as a TikTok?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, those we just double up. It's just hard. You know, what's actually pretty fascinating and people who do social media listening to this will probably find this pretty interesting is.
SPEAKER_0:  Picture like the Consecration meta three years ago versus now where you can make sub one minute vertical content and it go viral on TikTok.
SPEAKER_0:  and go viral on YouTube shorts.
SPEAKER_0:  go viral on Instagram Reels, it goes viral on Facebook, it goes viral on Instagram Reels, it goes viral on Facebook,
SPEAKER_0:  Reddit, you know, you swipe through vertical content now, and Twitter when you click on a video and you flip through it. So this is actually.
SPEAKER_0:  Very weird. This is the first time in the history of, I guess, Western social media that one form of content could actually go super viral on every single platform. It's never been like that before.
SPEAKER_1:  So they're going viral individual.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, like I can post something on TikTok that'll get 100 million views and then post it on shorts and it'll get 200 million views and then post it on Instagram and it get 50 million views and then, you know, I haven't yet, but you know, you can then turn around and tweet it and get tens of millions of views and you can post on Reddit and get tens of millions of views and Facebook and get tens of millions of views. And that just wasn't a thing. Three years ago, Twitter didn't have...
SPEAKER_0:  Because a lot of you probably don't even know this, but when you tap on a video now and you swipe down, it just turns into TikTok. That wasn't a thing even a year ago.
SPEAKER_0:  Reddit, that wasn't a thing a year ago.
SPEAKER_0:  probably two years ago, that wasn't a thing on Instagram.
SPEAKER_0:  Three years ago, that wasn't a thing on YouTube, right, with YouTube shorts. So this is all new. And I don't, it's weird, I haven't heard a single person talk about it.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the first time where...
SPEAKER_0:  content can actually.
SPEAKER_0:  Go viral on every single platform. And you don't have to write or film a video for Facebook, film a 12 minute video for YouTube, film a sub 60 second video for TikTok, write a tweet for Twitter and post this on Reddit. You can just do the same thing on every platform.
SPEAKER_1:  And the fact that your content has gone viral on multiple platforms regularly means that
SPEAKER_1:  Virality is not accidental.
SPEAKER_1:  Sometimes it can be of course.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's just not it can be engineered. It's yeah, so many people say it's luck and they're like, you're just lucky or this or that but
SPEAKER_0:  What do we have to probably like a thousand videos over 10 million views. Like we don't ever have a dud. Like you can call it luck, but I think it can be trained. I counsel YouTubers all the time and show them how to.
SPEAKER_0:  Go from getting a couple million views a month to 10 million views a month very easily.
SPEAKER_0:  even certain ones like
SPEAKER_0:  just one of my friends, like he was just really struggling. And so I just started showing him.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically everything I know and just doing like.
SPEAKER_0:  once every week, sometimes once every two weeks calls.
SPEAKER_0:  Anyone from-
SPEAKER_0:  $10,000 a month on YouTube to over $400,000. Just doing these little counseling calls. And so...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, people can make excuses all they want and say it's just luck or say, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Anyways, I don't even want to quote all the other stuff, but...
SPEAKER_0:  It's just...
SPEAKER_0:  It is, it is a teachable skill, it's a learnable skill. You can.
SPEAKER_0:  Study your way to consistently make viral videos, no matter how small your channel is, even if you have zero subscribers.
SPEAKER_0:  you could if you actually studied hard enough. And like, basically if you knew what I knew and some of these.
SPEAKER_0:  so I don't sound so arrogant. Also, like some of these other friends I have that I'd say are the smartest people in the world when it comes to content creation online. If you had the knowledge that was in-
SPEAKER_0:  Our heads?
SPEAKER_0:  You could do it very easily. I see people do it all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  of.
SPEAKER_0:  And what's even more interesting is I go on podcasts and I say everything I know. And these people are also very open. Some of them I know.
SPEAKER_0:  It's all out there.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of people, instead of just studying that and trying to absorb and apply it in their own way, they're just like, no, it's just luck, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  You do lay it all out there, but I gotta push back to one.
SPEAKER_1:  Interesting thing, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  A crucial component of your success is the idea stage.
SPEAKER_1:  the idea generation.
SPEAKER_1:  the brainstorm that I heard today, but getting really good at generating ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  This is not.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not just.
SPEAKER_1:  the selection of the thumbnail and the title, that creative process. It's also just the
SPEAKER_1:  the engine of generating really good ideas. Of course. I mean, I.
SPEAKER_1:  I would say that.
SPEAKER_1:  is probably the thing that needs to be trained the most for most creators, right? That they just don't put enough ideas on paper.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, but also a lot of creators also just don't.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, which I didn't either for the longest time, just didn't don't make enough content, you know, content that's worthy of getting 10 million.
SPEAKER_1:  In the idea or the execution of the idea? Both.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, like, think about...
SPEAKER_0:  how many people just make videos they film in under 20 minutes and they don't really put any effort into it and like you know
SPEAKER_0:  It's like.
SPEAKER_0:  My first 500 videos didn't deserve to get a million views. Like there's a reason they did. They were terrible, you know? But at the time I thought they did, right? And I'm in the mindset of a lot of small YouTubers where I thought those videos deserved a million views and I thought that algorithm hated me. But I watch them back now and I can tell you exactly why. The videos were just fucking horrible. You know what I mean?
SPEAKER_1:  So what was the breakthrough for you to start realizing, to start having a self-awareness, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  about.
SPEAKER_1:  these videos aren't good enough. You're probably still going through that. You're probably still growing to see.
SPEAKER_0:  Every six months you should look back and hate your videos or at least see things you could improve and be like, Oh my gosh, I could have done this better, that better. If not, then you're not learning quick enough.
SPEAKER_0:  In my opinion at least.
SPEAKER_1:  Where's the source of that learning even for you now?
SPEAKER_0:  It's rough.
SPEAKER_0:  Just look at the metrics. I just got back from a mastermind where I just got like 10 of the smartest people I knew and we just locked ourselves in a cabin and taught each other stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  Constantly, every day.
SPEAKER_0:  Not every day now, probably every other day I go on a walk and I just call random people. I'll just say, yeah, teach me something.
SPEAKER_0:  And I mean, it's just.
SPEAKER_0:  You just have to have a never ending thirst for learning.
SPEAKER_0:  Link, that's very imperative, especially if you want, like if you wanna get on top and then stay on top. The only way to do it is just to constantly be learning. Or someone who is learning is just gonna.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I'll have a leg up on you in the knowledge game.
SPEAKER_1:  And what kind of stuff are you? Cause you've talked about offline that.
SPEAKER_1:  You just love learning of all kinds. It doesn't matter.
SPEAKER_1:  In terms of videos, are you studying videos, are you studying?
SPEAKER_0:  Recently not as much, I'm more-
SPEAKER_0:  Because to get to the videos I want, I have to build this business and scale up and hire. So more my recent time has been like my teenage years were spent studying virality and studying content creation. Now I'm studying how to build a content company so I can actually produce the crazy ideas I want to produce if that makes any sense.
SPEAKER_1:  So yeah, and that's the business side.
SPEAKER_1:  We talked about hiring. Do you have trouble firing people?
SPEAKER_0:  No, I'm pretty sure almost every person...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, actually, every person I've ever fired, we just give them severance and
SPEAKER_0:  I like to see it more as...
SPEAKER_0:  It's no ill will. Like if I fired you, if there's some other job you want me to help you get, I'll DM them on Twitter.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, if you want to go work for...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, insert whatever, MTV.
SPEAKER_0:  Give me someone to DM, I'll DM him. Like, you know, I try to make it more like a transition and do whatever we can to make it as easy as possible.
SPEAKER_1:  something was just not working for you. cuz you want people like you said super passionate.
SPEAKER_0:  Because at the end of the day, if you hold someone that you onto someone that you don't see being here in 10 years, you're just doing them a disservice. You're just giving them more ingrained, more enroute and where they are.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And the sooner you do it and help them move on to their new life, the better.
SPEAKER_1:  given all the wisdom you have now, if you were to give advice to somebody or if you were
SPEAKER_1:  to start over again.
SPEAKER_1:  out.
SPEAKER_1:  You had no money.
SPEAKER_1:  What would be the first 10 videos you tried to make?
SPEAKER_1:  on a new channel. I guess that's advice for a new person.
SPEAKER_1:  And nobody knows you.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, nobody knows me. Yeah, I have a mask.
SPEAKER_1:  And you also I guess don't have the wisdom.
SPEAKER_0:  But if I don't have what I have in my head then.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say just.
SPEAKER_0:  fail. Like just a lot of people get analysis paralysis and they'll just sit there and
SPEAKER_0:  They'll plan their first video for three months. I'm
SPEAKER_0:  any of you listening, especially if you have zero viewers on your channel, your first video is not going to give views.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not, your first 10 are not gonna give you. I can very confidently say that.
SPEAKER_0:  So stop.
SPEAKER_0:  sitting there and thinking for months and months on end and just get to work and start uploading.
SPEAKER_0:  All you need to do, this applies to people who have not uploaded videos, but have dreams of being a YouTuber, is make 100 videos.
SPEAKER_0:  and improve something every time. Do that. And then on your 101st video, we'll start talking. Like maybe you can get some views.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, your first 100 are gonna suck. There are very freak cases like-
SPEAKER_0:  Vysokosha or Emma Chamberlain who have really good personalities and it doesn't take them some as many videos.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's just like.
SPEAKER_0:  people who are seven foot five and making an NBA. Like, yes, there are free cases you can find, but for the average person like us, who don't have these exceptional personalities and backgrounds in filmmaking, just make 100 videos, improve something each time, and then talk to me on your 101st video.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, the improve something is times the tricky one. How do you improve something each time?
SPEAKER_0:  The second one just.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, put more effort into the script. The third one, try to learn a new editing trick. The fourth one.
SPEAKER_0:  Try to figure out a way that you can have better inflections in your voice. The fifth one, try to study a new thumbnail tip and implement it. The sixth one, try to figure out a new title. There's infinite ways. That's the beauty of content creation online. There's literally infinite ways, from the coloring to the frame rate to the editing to the filming to the production to the jokes to the pacing to every little thing can be improved and they can never not be improved. There's literally no such thing as a perfect video.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  If you knew everything you know now.
SPEAKER_1:  but no money.
SPEAKER_0:  Step one, I just brainstorm like.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, I don't have money.
SPEAKER_0:  What are some viral things? What are some viral things?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  The first thing that comes to mind is something as simple as when I count to 100,000, which is what I did do when I was poor. And I like that work, but like what's something like that I could do that would be even more...
SPEAKER_0:  attention grabbing. maximum time to explore that word,
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, as part of the brainstorm.
SPEAKER_1:  You would throw out a lot of ideas, people throw out a bunch of ideas, and one of the questions is, is this even doable?
SPEAKER_1:  Right? Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  First off, come up with ideas you think would do well, and then ask yourself later if they're doable. Because there's different ways you can accomplish something.
SPEAKER_1:  Don't be cynical about the do-ability of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, because there really are so many different ways you can...
SPEAKER_0:  Accomplish a goal like
SPEAKER_0:  when we give away an island, like we gave our 100 million subscriber an island. subscribe
SPEAKER_0:  You can't find private islands that, you know, don't look like shit for less than $10 million. So this isn't doable, right? All right. It doesn't exist, not doable.
SPEAKER_0:  Exit off.
SPEAKER_0:  But then, you know, you dig into it and you...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, find different alternatives and you find, okay, what if we just buy a $2 million Island that sucks?
SPEAKER_0:  and then spend a million dollars, you know, importing some sand, let's build a beach, let's import 300 trees, let's build a little bit of canals, let's set some paths.
SPEAKER_0:  Boom.
SPEAKER_0:  Now it's a really nice island.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's actually affordable because we don't have $10 million to spend on a video, but we can afford to spend three and a half and lose whatever, a million dollars on that video. So like, that's an example of like...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, if you just went off the gut test, you'd be like, this isn't doable. Every island's $10 million, we're screwed. If we go cheaper, it's just a-
SPEAKER_0:  Terrible Island, no.
SPEAKER_0:  And so if you like.
SPEAKER_0:  There are so many different ways you can achieve what you want. You really got to push through notes, which not a lot of people do. You have to have like a...
SPEAKER_0:  more of a dominant personality and just a willingness to.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, when people tell you it's not possible, just.
SPEAKER_0:  actually go through all the variables and eliminate them all yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  have a stubbornness.
SPEAKER_1:  and resilience to failure maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  For what we do and creators online, it's very imperative that you have
SPEAKER_0:  A no isn't a no deal. You really have to like think and just
SPEAKER_0:  Like we take a personality test and like just having a dominant personality is a better indicator that when someone tells you, oh, there's no way you're gonna build a brick wall for under a hundred grand, you know, you'll be like, okay, and then still go check the next 10 vendors and figure it out.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, what advice would you give to an already established channel like with one, two, three, four million subscribers, how to like 10 exit.
SPEAKER_1:  Like increase it.
SPEAKER_1:  Um f-
SPEAKER_0:  without losing maybe. Yeah, that's where it's very specific. Like.
SPEAKER_0:  channel by channel. You can't give general advice. Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Because if I do...
SPEAKER_0:  millions of creators are gonna...
SPEAKER_0:  see this and then they're gonna do it and I'm gonna fuck them over you know
SPEAKER_1:  I say see
SPEAKER_1:  So let's say I'd like two million subscribers on this podcast. Yeah. Thank you.
SPEAKER_1:  10x that without sacrificing what it is.
SPEAKER_1:  10X your stuff. Does it matter? You've talked about
SPEAKER_0:  with success.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's different for everyone. Like is 10Xing your definition of success? No.
SPEAKER_0:  Well then.
SPEAKER_0:  Right off the bat, it's hard because if you don't give a shit about 10X, it's even harder than 10X. He does this because he likes helping people. That's one thing I've found throughout this day. Every time I talk to Data, it's so funny with him.
SPEAKER_0:  Cause it's like
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you could do this to get more views and he'll just be like blank. I feel like that doesn't register anything. He just like doesn't care, which is it's really cool.
SPEAKER_1:  nervous about that. I'm really nervous about the numbers affecting...
SPEAKER_1:  Cause it's so fun.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's so fun to focus on the numbers and I'm really worried about that. But at the same time you should be
SPEAKER_1:  cognizant of that because
SPEAKER_1:  You've created not.
SPEAKER_1:  just some of the most watched videos, but some of the most amazing videos ever. So it's...
SPEAKER_1:  There's a strong correlation there. It's not like you're selling your soul to make a highly viewed video.
SPEAKER_1:  is actually if you look at the metrics.
SPEAKER_1:  It helps you understand what is compelling and not.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I feel like.
SPEAKER_1:  I am.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like there's some value to investigate.
SPEAKER_1:  What work when people tune out and when not.
SPEAKER_1:  to be more data-driven, even on podcasts.
SPEAKER_0:  But I'm really afraid of that. But on the flip side, I think part of the appeal is that you don't care about that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  But there could be stuff...
SPEAKER_1:  that doesn't have to do anything with that.
SPEAKER_1:  and it has to do with stylistic choices of lighting and cameras.
SPEAKER_1:  Or maybe with, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  For example,
SPEAKER_1:  topics.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, like even what you've asked me here is like different than what most people ask me
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so it could be that I mean, and it'd be nice to understand that. But yeah, again, I'm worried about it.
SPEAKER_0:  polluting the creative process. At the end of the day, this is a true case of it's your own intuition. You know your viewers better than anyone else.
SPEAKER_0:  It's whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  See, I'd like to push back on that. I really don't.
SPEAKER_0:  You do.
SPEAKER_0:  Who else? Name one person who knows your viewers better than you.
SPEAKER_1:  Somebody that looks at numbers of positive
SPEAKER_0:  No, you know your viewers, you know
SPEAKER_0:  You're the only how many episodes have you done? Uh, 350. Exactly. But I'm not paying attention. You're the only one who's watched every second of all 350 of them. Probably. It's not no-
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I haven't, but the.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, because you did it, so you do know what's in the album.
SPEAKER_0:  It's your content, it's you people. I'm telling you.
SPEAKER_0:  You do, and this is just one of those moments where...
SPEAKER_0:  You're an intelligent guy and you just have to trust your like.
SPEAKER_0:  Instincts like.
SPEAKER_0:  Just think.
SPEAKER_0:  What is the typical X viewer and what do they want?
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think like that.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's all you would have to do. And whatever your gut tells you, that would be the best guess.
SPEAKER_1:  You don't know what the typical viewer is though. I don't, I don't, cause to investigate that would be very, very difficult. And then you have to start looking at the numbers. You have to start to consider demographics.
SPEAKER_1:  The only way I know that anybody even watches it is because I'll sometimes run into people, like when I run along the river, and they'd be like, I love you, Lex. It's like, okay, well that.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the data point.
SPEAKER_1:  And they're like cool people, but you know, I don't know. I don't have any other.
SPEAKER_1:  It's difficult man, it's difficult to know.
SPEAKER_1:  It's difficult to know who listens to boxes. It's difficult to, do you have a sense of who's, I mean, like you're so huge that everybody watches.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, but no, I still do. I'd say.
SPEAKER_0:  If you were to just
SPEAKER_0:  put a gun to my head and you're like, all right, we're gonna pick a random person that watched your last video, and you have to roughly guess what they are, and if you're not close, we'll kill you.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say probably like.
SPEAKER_0:  a teenager that plays video games. Like that would be probably the typical one. And then there are people that are maybe a little bit younger, a lot of people that are older as well.
SPEAKER_0:  And a random sample size? Yeah, it's probably like-
SPEAKER_0:  I'm a male boy that plays video games. Like that's the best way I would describe it.
SPEAKER_0:  But I don't try to pertain to them. I just make whatever I think is interesting and good content.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is what we were talking about before, even though hypothetically 35 to 40% of my audience is women, which is less than a majority.
SPEAKER_0:  If we get 100 million views a video, that's still 30 to 40 million females that watch every video.
SPEAKER_0:  which is probably the largest.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, views per video.
SPEAKER_0:  for women on the whole platform, but you wouldn't think that, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  Like I can't think of a single
SPEAKER_0:  other creator that gets more women to watch their videos than that.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just anything, even like people above the age of 30, even if it's only like three or 4%.
SPEAKER_0:  That's still three to 4% of 100 million views is a lot of people that age. So we
SPEAKER_0:  We hit a large group of, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  of kind of every demographic.
SPEAKER_0:  That makes sense. WHILE TO TAKE CARE OF M what do you say about so
SPEAKER_1:  What if we look at other?
SPEAKER_1:  maybe more challenging kinds of channels or not, but.
SPEAKER_1:  If you look at educational, for example, like lectures, or free.
SPEAKER_1:  Look, yeah, educational. It could be short videos. How would you?
SPEAKER_1:  text that.
SPEAKER_1:  like something on.
SPEAKER_1:  of robotics and biology and science and engineering and all that.
SPEAKER_1:  that's more educational focused.
SPEAKER_0:  We would honestly just have to pull the day because it's the same way if you went to Gordon Ramsay you said
SPEAKER_0:  How about a-
SPEAKER_0:  New cook, cook better. You know, it's like, you gotta- Even then.
SPEAKER_1:  that's not even a specific, you have to go channel.
SPEAKER_0:  You really do or I'm giving horrible advice because if there was these just golden rules everyone would do it you know what I mean like if there's these magical little principles.
SPEAKER_1:  how quickly do you get when you look at a channel can you kind of
SPEAKER_0:  Give advice.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like surface love at the start and then the more, if we watch 10 videos, I feel like I'd have a good profile and I could tell you.
SPEAKER_0:  In my opinion.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, especially once I look at the analytics and I get more ingrained in like, okay, the typical view is this, they're from here, here's how they're feeling.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, because there are people.
SPEAKER_0:  make videos for rednecks. And like the rednecks taste of content is just so much different than obviously women watching makeup videos, they're so much different than, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  teenage boys watching a Minecraft video. They're just all different. So the biggest thing you have to do is put your head in the head space of the viewer and see the content how they would. Because if you just try to only give your taste, which is what a lot of people do, and things from your perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  It's very biased and it's just not gonna work for everyone. And that's actually how you do more harm than good, which is something I'm very careful of.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, but at the same time, just generating a lot of ideas. I think the first time I've talked to you was on Clubhouse, actually. I mentioned something about robots.
SPEAKER_1:  And like almost immediately you went to generating a bunch of ideas.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yeah, he's like...
SPEAKER_0:  It's just a hundred robots versus a hundred humans. Yeah. Yeah, how far can a robot throw a potato? I think your idea like
SPEAKER_1:  I think the first idea was, you just said so many ideas I never even thought of.
SPEAKER_1:  but it shows the value of.
SPEAKER_1:  basically brainstorming with people that think.
SPEAKER_0:  But at the end of the day, my ideas are probably, you know...
SPEAKER_0:  might lean towards.
SPEAKER_0:  some people a little bit younger than your audience. some of the stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there's still ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  I think the first one you said, cause we're talking about a quadruped like.
SPEAKER_1:  I wrote by dogs.
SPEAKER_1:  You said to replace.
SPEAKER_1:  a biological dog.
SPEAKER_1:  with the robot dog and see if the owner notices something. You were just quickly brainstorming different ideas of how to do things
SPEAKER_0:  This was years ago, I remember that.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. Which is just, I mean, it's like, oh yeah, I never really thought about that kind of, sorry, it's the basic.
SPEAKER_1:  the tension between what does it take for a robot in our AI system to replace the biological systems that we, the biological creatures that we love.
SPEAKER_1:  And a lot is there.
SPEAKER_1:  But that was the...
SPEAKER_1:  pace of idea generation.
SPEAKER_1:  was the thing that struck me today and in general.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like, that's how you get it.
SPEAKER_1:  good videos as you keep.
SPEAKER_0:  It makes it much easier to
SPEAKER_0:  make a video around a good idea, obviously, then a bad one. You just send yourself up for success.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, so that's for...
SPEAKER_1:  10x seniority popular channel.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the hardest number? You said, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  the numbers that matters, click through rate, average view duration, and surveys.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the hardest number to uh...
SPEAKER_1:  optimized for.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably surveys, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you have any, do you have an insight into the service at all? No.
SPEAKER_0:  Not really, but if you just click on a bunch of random videos online, you'll eventually get a survey.
SPEAKER_0:  What's this video? It's informative, heartwarming, inspiring.
SPEAKER_0:  What people rate does make a difference.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like you can.
SPEAKER_0:  give people a click of it, you can get them to watch it, but you can't really fake whether or not they're satisfied. Like they don't lie, the service, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  You know, maybe one person here, they're my troll but once you aggregate enough, it's a pretty clear telltale of the video.
SPEAKER_0:  So either you're making a great video or you're not.
SPEAKER_1:  What is it?
SPEAKER_1:  minimizing the none.
SPEAKER_1:  Regrettability.
SPEAKER_0:  I think Elon tweeted that that's what he's tried to do.
SPEAKER_1:  for Twitter. And that's interesting. That's basically the survey metric, how happy you are that you've been using the platform. Well, that's about at 18%.
SPEAKER_0:  Elon tweeted, we want to limit the amount of regrettable minutes people spend on Twitter.
SPEAKER_0:  And the first thing I thought is like, that's something YouTube already has a lot. Like their whole survey system and feedback loop.
SPEAKER_1:  How tough is it to take on you, do you think?
SPEAKER_1:  Like, uh... For Twitter? Yeah, for Twitter, for anybody else.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  It's gonna be basically impossible. I mean YouTube's not going anywhere and
SPEAKER_0:  Alright.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, I don't think anyone's gonna do what YouTube does better than them.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... at least not in the next ten years
SPEAKER_1:  You asked on Twitter, would you rather have $10 million or 10 million subscribers on YouTube?
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  What would your own answer be at various stages in your...
SPEAKER_0:  If I...
SPEAKER_0:  If I had nothing, I would say $10 million.
SPEAKER_0:  Because with $10 million, you can hire some people.
SPEAKER_0:  pump out content.
SPEAKER_0:  with like a million or two, get 10 million subscribers and then keep the other eight million.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's if you believe in your ability to grow a channel. That is if you
SPEAKER_0:  But if you don't believe in your ability to grow a channel.
SPEAKER_0:  then you shouldn't take the 10 million subscribers because you're just gonna kill the chance. So the 10 million is definitely, a better question would be, would you rather have a million dollars for 10 million subscribers? That's where it gets a little tricky.
SPEAKER_0:  Because now it's like, hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, a million dollar is a life changing amount of money.
SPEAKER_0:  But you know if you semi-know what you're doing, you probably make a million dollars off a 10 million subscriber channel.
SPEAKER_0:  There is a little bit of risk.
SPEAKER_1:  a million dollars might not be enough to build a strong team.
SPEAKER_1:  because you don't know how to do it, so you might waste all
SPEAKER_0:  of that money. Yeah, or they just keep it and retire. Yeah. Okay, that's true. Yeah, because 10 million is just so high. It's like just
SPEAKER_0:  Never work again, who cares? For the average human, that's so much money.
SPEAKER_1:  It's interesting to me also to the value of the subscriber versus the value of the dollar.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  I suppose how valuable is a subscriber?
SPEAKER_1:  for.
SPEAKER_1:  What percentage of the videos like how active the subscribers in watching the video?
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  for you.
SPEAKER_0:  That's hard, I don't know. I was actually thinking more about the subscriber to dollar. Like if someone has 10 million subscribers, have they made $10 million? I don't know why that kind of popped in my head.
SPEAKER_0:  transitioning.
SPEAKER_1:  thought.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... do you ever
SPEAKER_1:  when you analyze videos, do you ever analyze videos like we've talked about offline of other?
SPEAKER_1:  videos across the two in general to understand trans and since also be
SPEAKER_0:  All your, not all, but a lot of the questions are analytics based. Yeah. Yeah, it's so funny.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean it's just a giant social experiment, right? Like what people like to watch, what people share.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's like a fascinating.
SPEAKER_0:  So I hate that. So like I said before, what percentage of your audience do you think care about this kind of stuff?
SPEAKER_0:  like this deeply about YouTube Analytics.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  A large amount.
SPEAKER_1:  care about.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  curiosity and exploration of interesting ideas. So in that sense, yeah, this would fit it.
SPEAKER_0:  I love it. This is funny. This isn't me like trying to make, I love you. I love your Magnus one and even your Hikaru one was really good, a bunch of other ones. But I think we're getting to the point now where only analytics junkies would want to keep hearing more analytics talk. And the normie is probably like...
SPEAKER_0:  They've had their dose of YouTube talk for the next three years.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe I'm wrong. Hey, comment if I'm wrong. I could be. I don't know your audience. See, this is where you would tell me, shut up, I know my audience, you dumb ass.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't at all. I actually, I just follow the thread of curiosity.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think there's just a lot of curious humans in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  And to me, it's like.
SPEAKER_1:  So the question about analytics is the question of.
SPEAKER_1:  basically stepping away.
SPEAKER_1:  stepping outside of yourself and thinking, why the hell do I like TikTok so much? Why do I like Twitter so much? Why do I like YouTube so much?
SPEAKER_1:  And getting, even if you're not a creator, getting an insight into that is really interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  What?
SPEAKER_1:  because
SPEAKER_1:  because all these platforms are fundamentally changing.
SPEAKER_1:  the nature of content.
SPEAKER_1:  People are reading books less, they're probably going to be watching movies less and less.
SPEAKER_1:  They're probably going to be watching Netflix less and less.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you ever think about the sort of the darker side of YouTube?
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  with shadow banning of censorship and all the kind of topics.
SPEAKER_1:  especially if you see it on other platforms like Twitter.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  that uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Elon recently...
SPEAKER_1:  highlighted the shadow banning that was happening.
SPEAKER_1:  and in general the censorship that was happening on those platforms. Do you think about the role?
SPEAKER_1:  of centralized control which information isn't or isn't.
SPEAKER_1:  are made available through search and discovery.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll be honest.
SPEAKER_0:  I never really think about it.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh... Just uh...
SPEAKER_1:  We just try to make fun videos that.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I'm more I'm kind of more in my own lane, but it's not like that. I don't just specifically think about I just like a lot of stuff in general. I just kind of my own lane thinking about my own stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, now that you asked, I'm curious, what are your thoughts on YouTube and that kind of stuff?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I'm generally against-
SPEAKER_1:  centralized.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  censorship or shadow ban shadow ban is the worst one.
SPEAKER_1:  Because...
SPEAKER_1:  Not that.
SPEAKER_1:  the goal of creating a healthy platform where you're having great conversations.
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  videos that are not spreading misinformation, that sounds like an admirable goal.
SPEAKER_1:  But that's too difficult of a job for a centralized entity. That's too big of a...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there's the misinformation stuff and then there's also just like...
SPEAKER_0:  The videos were...
SPEAKER_0:  they do something that causes a what happened back there that work
SPEAKER_0:  at apocalypse, you know, a lot of creators revenue plummets because people are
SPEAKER_0:  doing videos that advertisers don't seem acceptable. And then now all these big advertisers are pulling and the little guys are getting hit because ad rates dropped by 30%. And the person who just quit his job to go full-time conjugation.
SPEAKER_0:  now can't sustain it.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's also...
SPEAKER_0:  It's like a lot of different variables as well. That makes it so complicated.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I think the big thing is transparency, especially around shadow banning.
SPEAKER_0:  I agree. On Shadow of Anning, you should be transparent. You should let people know.
SPEAKER_0:  It, you know, obviously there has to be some type of controls. People can't just post whatever. And so if you're
SPEAKER_0:  pulling those levers, they should at least know.
SPEAKER_1:  Yesterday Noah had to...
SPEAKER_1:  improve their content they can understand that they can be a
SPEAKER_1:  If it's a wrong shadow banning.
SPEAKER_1:  Like as a society that we should not shadow ban this kind of content that means you should be publicly glamorous
SPEAKER_0:  discussing it and having that. If it's not known.
SPEAKER_0:  then it's just kind of like, well, then who's pulling the strings and like.
SPEAKER_0:  How do we know they're not just manipulating things to get whatever message they want out there and silence other ones?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, that could be sort of in the background government influence, which is where actual freedom of speech.
SPEAKER_1:  comes into play that the government should not have any control.
SPEAKER_1:  or be able to put pressure on censorship.
SPEAKER_1:  of speech.
SPEAKER_1:  And it gets weird if none of that is being, there's no transparency around it.
SPEAKER_1:  That's it.
SPEAKER_1:  To be fair...
SPEAKER_1:  That's a huge responsibility. The amount of-
SPEAKER_1:  content that YouTube is uploaded on YouTube.
SPEAKER_1:  It is.
SPEAKER_1:  shared by YouTube.
SPEAKER_0:  But even more of a reason why it would probably make sense to be transparent.
SPEAKER_0:  because then people can help fact check it.
SPEAKER_1:  That's right, but that requires building a platform that makes that easy.
SPEAKER_1:  Right, like...
SPEAKER_1:  to make fact checking easy to make the...
SPEAKER_1:  like who Twitter now has, like being able to share context and all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  that crowdsource it. Crowdsources the way Wikipedia crowdsources.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean there's...
SPEAKER_1:  It's right.
SPEAKER_0:  And then you open a random Wikipedia article.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for watching!
SPEAKER_1:  But like, you know, people criticize Wikipedia because there is...
SPEAKER_1:  a political lean to the editors of Wikipedia and then they get
SPEAKER_1:  There's some articles that definitely have a bias to them and all that kind of stuff. It's a difficult problem. It's a difficult problem to solve that.
SPEAKER_1:  Ultimately.
SPEAKER_1:  As much as possible, it would be nice for the viewer to have control of that versus the.
SPEAKER_1:  the entity that's hosting it.
SPEAKER_1:  So for the viewer to decide.
SPEAKER_0:  that stuff out. I'm just gonna make
SPEAKER_0:  Cool videos. Yeah. Yeah. Let's go to Antarctica again.
SPEAKER_0:  How was that? How was going to you-
SPEAKER_1:  I just came back from Antarctica. I watched the video.
SPEAKER_1:  That was.
SPEAKER_1:  That was fun. That was a really fun video.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot of things I can comment about that, but what was the hardest part?
SPEAKER_0:  part of making that video.
SPEAKER_0:  The hardest part was just getting out there. It's just so remote.
SPEAKER_0:  and you know, you land the plane on just this ice runway and it's so sketchy. And then once the plane takes off, you're just there.
SPEAKER_0:  You're the most remote place on the planet.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It's just very breathtaking. I don't-
SPEAKER_0:  If you have the chance to ever go to Antarctica, I would recommend it.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably like the, in the video we climbed a mountain that wasn't named so we can name it.
SPEAKER_0:  and like standing on top of that mountain and just seeing.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm telling nothing. Cause once you.
SPEAKER_0:  get outside the outskirts and you get deep in Antarctica, there's no penguins, nothing lives there at all.
SPEAKER_0:  And so there's just nothing in every direction. It's just snow and these crazy, beautiful mountains and some of them stick into the clouds and...
SPEAKER_0:  If you go during summertime, the sun never goes down. So the sun's up 24 seven and it's just like spinning in circles at the top of the planet or whatever. It looks like the top.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, you guys commented several times how beautiful it was. Yeah, and so it's just, yeah, it was just very...
SPEAKER_1:  What about shooting itself, like the technical aspects of shooting it?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, well, so.
SPEAKER_0:  But somehow we lucked out one of the days was like the warmest day in like forever that's been in Antarctica. It was like, it was positive degrees, but at certain parts it was also like negative 20, negative 30.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's where the cameras, you constantly have to be switching out the batteries and heating them up and like putting them basically in like your pants or they'll just get way too cold.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh...
SPEAKER_0:  We were prepared for much worse, but it ended up being much better than we thought.
SPEAKER_1:  So for that video, but in general, maybe some other challenging videos, how do you go from the idea stage to the actual execution to the final video? Can you take me through like a full process of?
SPEAKER_1:  Of course, we're talking about some crazy wild ideas today. How do you go from that?
SPEAKER_1:  to a final video where you click publish.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I mean, obviously first things first, you gotta figure out the idea and then it just depends. I mean, pick any video you can think of on my channel. I can take you through it.
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh...
SPEAKER_1:  Well, what about the, in a circle, you have to stay in a circle for 100 days.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so for that one step one one of the most popular. Yeah, that video did really well. Yeah, so we
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Promise, we have to...
SPEAKER_0:  This is where you get really into the nuances of the company.
SPEAKER_0:  We have a lot of videos going out. You can't just in a vacuum be like, all right, we're not doing anything for 100 days, we're only filming this. So step one is we had to build an independent crew that could actually do that for 100 days. That way everyone else could keep working on the normal videos and not just screw everything up. I had to, um.
SPEAKER_0:  So step one, you build that team. Okay, we got the team. Now what do we need?
SPEAKER_0:  Well...
SPEAKER_0:  to do this, we need probably like.
SPEAKER_0:  10 cameras at least rolling at all times. So.
SPEAKER_0:  We're probably going to need to get a trailer and hook up a bunch of storage and stuff to
SPEAKER_0:  just carry out the sheer volume of footage we're gonna have. so
SPEAKER_0:  get a trailer, set up the cameras.
SPEAKER_0:  go out in the field, paint a circle, now we need a house, go buy a house, bring it out there.
SPEAKER_0:  And then it's like, oh wait
SPEAKER_0:  I think it'd be funny if I brought the house in on the intro, but you know, find a crane that can lift up a house so I can drive it in and drop it in the intro. And that's like an iterative.
SPEAKER_1:  process where you're like okay this will be funnier so this is not all up front these reunion
SPEAKER_0:  Ideally it would be, but as you kind of see things you get inspired and then you think of more and more
SPEAKER_0:  uh... and as a bit better
SPEAKER_1:  with a crane.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  It'd be better if I dropped out of that.
SPEAKER_1:  the house. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  That was crazy that you decided to do that.
SPEAKER_1:  So fearless in the kind of crazy stuff you're willing to do.
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly. I'm a broken record, but whatever makes the best video possible. Yeah. That's, that's all you, you focus on.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so...
SPEAKER_1:  What about the delegation of like who gets to...
SPEAKER_1:  What are the camera man, like the people operating the cameras, what uh...
SPEAKER_1:  who's responsible for different things.
SPEAKER_1:  This is like a distributed pro-
SPEAKER_0:  Well that's where whoever the lead cam would be on that video would just decide it. We got one because we shot over 100 days.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of it was just Sean, the guy who was in the circle, just vlogging, I mean, just getting my camera and he figured it out and then we'd have like, for him, just set hours each day that a cameraman would come, so if he had any content, he needed extra hands instead of just having someone on standby 24-7.
SPEAKER_0:  It made more sense to do set hours. Pick up the phone and click the red button to check these qualities with your SM There's a lot going on between us now, on social media
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  It was hard, but explaining it in hindsight sounds so simple, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  And I guess like the mo-
SPEAKER_1:  more.
SPEAKER_1:  Cause that one is relatively simple, I guess, because it's a low number.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, the hard part about that is just the time.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, you know, I checked in on him so many different days and.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like an hour here, two hours there, three hours there.
SPEAKER_0:  over 100 days adds up to be a ton of time.
SPEAKER_0:  And even then, like, you know, if you have a...
SPEAKER_0:  10 person crew, you know, paying them daily rates for 100 days, it just all of it adds up.
SPEAKER_1:  What about like the 100 vs 100? 100 uh...
SPEAKER_1:  adults versus other kids.
SPEAKER_1:  What was that? What was...
SPEAKER_1:  uh... bring that to life that's a section challenging
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, basically the thought process was we did 100 kids versus, or sorry, 100 boys versus 100 girls. Yeah. I loved it. Honestly, I didn't think they'd like it as much as they did.
SPEAKER_0:  Video did really, really well.
SPEAKER_0:  So the second I saw that video was crushing, I was like, all right.
SPEAKER_0:  doing it again.
SPEAKER_0:  But last time we did it, we did it in our studio. So we built a giant room, put 100 girls in it. Sounds bad when I explain it like this. And then a giant room, put 100 boys. And we're like, after 100 hours, whichever room has the most people, give them half a million dollars.
SPEAKER_0:  So did well, so we're like, all right, we're gonna do it again.
SPEAKER_0:  So we threw out all these different ideas. It was like...
SPEAKER_0:  100 football players versus 100 cheerleaders, 100 this, 100 that.
SPEAKER_0:  100 prisoners versus 100 cops, just craziest ideas. We settled on 100 kids versus 100 adults.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  and then...
SPEAKER_0:  The next step was like, how do we make it better? The kids versus adults, or the, sorry, boys versus girls, the first one we did was inside.
SPEAKER_0:  The problem was every time it was night when we did these long time lapses, you couldn't see the sun go up and down.
SPEAKER_0:  So we're like, okay, this time I want to do it outside. That's why the cubes are outside.
SPEAKER_0:  And instead of doing circles, we want to make them cubes.
SPEAKER_0:  And then.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, is figure out do we want the
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, just...
SPEAKER_1:  Those videos came up at least today as ones that are like really complicated in terms of the audio in terms of how
SPEAKER_0:  how to film it. Yeah that's the problem. We had a lot of audio issues because
SPEAKER_0:  And the first one we didn't have a roof on it. The second one, there was a roof, so there's a lot of reverb.
SPEAKER_0:  which then in editing made it brutal like
SPEAKER_0:  half the shots weren't usable and it really screwed us over. So we had to do a lot of Frankensteining the editing to make up for it.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically by ignorance.
SPEAKER_1:  So you mentioned that you were surprised how well that one did.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of creators...
SPEAKER_1:  Talk about getting depressed.
SPEAKER_1:  when uh...
SPEAKER_1:  the videos don't do as well as they kind of expected. There's a kind of feeling.
SPEAKER_1:  You can get really worn out by that.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you yourself feel that?
SPEAKER_1:  and also give advice for others that.
SPEAKER_1:  Feel this.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's weird because I am a numbers guy, but also.
SPEAKER_0:  It used to.
SPEAKER_0:  It used to very much, especially when I was like betting.
SPEAKER_0:  everything I had on a video when it did bad.
SPEAKER_0:  I was devastated, man. I'd cry and I'd be depressed for days.
SPEAKER_0:  It really would have a severe impact on my mood, but.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, now it doesn't really matter. It's a-
SPEAKER_0:  look for video displays.
SPEAKER_0:  look at it and I'm like, oh, why'd this video do that?
SPEAKER_0:  Probably, oh, there's a little retention dip there.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think people like the thumbnail, maybe we should switch it. I just look at it objectively, unemotional, and then just move on. And I feel like that's a much healthier way of going about it.
SPEAKER_0:  If a creator is listening, like that is the ideal way.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  respond to a video that's doing bad.
SPEAKER_0:  remove a motion from the equation and just look at it and figure out how you can improve the next one.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there tricks to being able to detach yourself from the?
SPEAKER_1:  from that because...
SPEAKER_0:  Because I can
SPEAKER_1:  In your case, I mean that's true for creators, but in your case...
SPEAKER_1:  This is like a lot of money on the line.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, well, this video cost my life. Yeah, so much time, but.
SPEAKER_0:  No, I mean, you just...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I don't know, the only real answer is it's just a conscious effort. You just have to unemotionally.
SPEAKER_0:  We'll get the video, determine the problems, and then move on.
SPEAKER_0:  There is no secret, you know what I mean? It's just-
SPEAKER_0:  That's it's that and if you really can't bring yourself to do it, then you're just screwed. Honestly, maybe you're not meant for this game.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so that's part of the development as a creator is like being able to be
SPEAKER_0:  longevity. Yes, yeah. You have to unemotionally be able to...
SPEAKER_0:  look at videos that flop and figure it out. Because if not, just can't, and not every video can be a one out of ten.
SPEAKER_0:  So when a video does bad.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, that just stress and depression, it's just going to eventually get to you in the long run.
SPEAKER_1:  So you said you've failed in a bunch of videos.
SPEAKER_1:  So
SPEAKER_1:  taking them to completion. So what are some of the-
SPEAKER_1:  biggest fails.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, weirdly enough, as we've matured and we've done this more, we don't have that problem as much, especially now that we're getting some multi-million dollar budgets per video.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, failure's not really an option anymore. So I'm a little more particular about what I do, but back in the day...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, like we would do a video where we spent 24 hours on a deserted island.
SPEAKER_0:  and we filmed it, did it all and...
SPEAKER_0:  I just.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't like it after the edit, so I just grabbed the voice and we went back to the deserted island and spent another 24 hours there and refilmed it.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_1:  Or uh... Could that have been caught?
SPEAKER_1:  and prevent it at the idea stage.
SPEAKER_0:  No, it's a good idea. It was just poor execution. To be honest, when we were out there it was hot.
SPEAKER_0:  We're just like, we all at one point just kind of wanted to die. It was just miserable.
SPEAKER_1:  Hario
SPEAKER_0:  avoid that these days. Well, I just went with what is a little cooler, to be honest. And then we had, literally, the amount of fun we had in the video was like 10 times higher.
SPEAKER_1:  interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  So you like there's some practical details that you just learned. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't- videos that where it's very hot.
SPEAKER_0:  or it's on water, because I get super seasick. It's like a, kinda like.
SPEAKER_0:  10 things that
SPEAKER_0:  If they have these variables.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm down to do it.
SPEAKER_0:  My fun meter is.
SPEAKER_0:  not as high as normal. Uh, like we tried to sp, um,
SPEAKER_0:  Anytime we do anything on a boat, like when we spent 24 hours in a beer meter triangle.
SPEAKER_0:  Or when I tried to spend like, which it didn't get upload, but I tried to spend like a hundred hours at sea or whatever, just like on a raft.
SPEAKER_0:  It just like, it makes me want to throw up and I get so seasick I came in sea straight.
SPEAKER_0:  But there are just some videos that require me to be on a boat. So just second up.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_1:  to when you spend months in creating a video.
SPEAKER_1:  I know this is probably stressful to some creators.
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  Like how much stress?
SPEAKER_1:  How do you feel when you have to click publish?
SPEAKER_1:  video now not much here
SPEAKER_0:  to detach yourself. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, and old me.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I'd be like...
SPEAKER_0:  scratching and nervous and like my hands will be sweating like to the point where I'm almost about to puke I'm like
SPEAKER_0:  I really hope people like this, but.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, I think that's just part of maturing it. There's different, as a content creator, there's different phases and-
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  You just like, once you...
SPEAKER_0:  Get over the fear that you're just gonna wake up one day and be irrelevant, you know, and you just, you know, accept that, like, you believe in yourself, you believe in your content, and that you can continue to be relevant.
SPEAKER_0:  then you don't.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, you kind of, it's a little bit easier to attach yourself, I guess.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's, it's a much healthier place to be. You can't do this for 10 years of every little-
SPEAKER_0:  thing just.
SPEAKER_0:  causes these huge emotional reactions. It's like-
SPEAKER_0:  That's why I love it.
SPEAKER_0:  creators go a little mentally insane.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to get out of that game.
SPEAKER_0:  because it really messes with you.
SPEAKER_1:  We've talked about this a little bit, but...
SPEAKER_1:  How do you define and how do you suggest others define success?
SPEAKER_1:  I need you.
SPEAKER_0:  Some people's success is retiring their mom.
SPEAKER_0:  Literally, you know, for you, success is inspiring people and educating them and, you know, whatever, people seeing this, peak in their curiosity.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, um...
SPEAKER_0:  For other people, it's just quitting their job.
SPEAKER_1:  So you have to self-reflect on what your definition of success is. Because I think a lot of creators kind of...
SPEAKER_1:  don't really think.
SPEAKER_1:  Think.
SPEAKER_1:  Don't introspect.
SPEAKER_1:  Like...
SPEAKER_1:  They kind of want to keep getting more and more subscribers kind of thing.
SPEAKER_0:  But subscribers is just a vanity metric, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't.
SPEAKER_0:  Subscribers don't correlate to views.
SPEAKER_0:  Sure, or views. Yeah, I know, but that was more directed to you. That was more directed to people listening, because a lot of people do really care about subscribers or even followers, like on TikTok. But if you look...
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_0:  Your view, on YouTube, very, very few percent.
SPEAKER_0:  even a percent of your views come from the subfeed.
SPEAKER_0:  They're almost all home feeders suggested. When's the last time you clicked on your sub feed to watch a video?
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, almost never, yeah. Yeah, maybe five years ago. It used to be a thing. It's not anymore..
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and it's getting harder and harder to find.
SPEAKER_1:  to way too many channels I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that's what everyone does. And you subscribe to 10 channels, they're great, but two years later, your taste evolves and it's a mess. And so.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Subscribers don't really matter.
SPEAKER_0:  followers on TikTok don't really matter.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So anyways.
SPEAKER_0:  They really are the definition of a vanity metric. But what about views?
SPEAKER_0:  They do, obviously, because if people are showing up time and time again, that's what matters.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  So that.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a good thing to define a success. I just feel like.
SPEAKER_1:  that too can be a problem.
SPEAKER_1:  Cause, uh.
SPEAKER_1:  I would say.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, if I wanted to be successful, like as a young creator, I might start copying Mr. Beast or something like that, right? Like there's, you start trying to take shortcuts as opposed to find your own unique voice.
SPEAKER_1:  Bye.
SPEAKER_1:  So like chasing views is a problem too, it feels like.
SPEAKER_1:  or no.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, it's as long as you detach yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  If you had the-
SPEAKER_0:  sounds like you're lazy and you just want to copy someone else and not experiment and find your own way.
SPEAKER_0:  But, I mean, you can't make that excuse for them. If someone just-
SPEAKER_0:  isn't coming up with original stuff and putting in the effort. You can't just say, oh, it's because they're chasing views. We need some different metric for them to chase. No, they just need a.
SPEAKER_0:  find their own way.
SPEAKER_1:  It just feels like unique type of content.
SPEAKER_1:  will often lead to sacrifice in the number of views in the short term.
SPEAKER_0:  By the long term, you win.
SPEAKER_0:  Or if you do win, you win more.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess would be a better way of putting it.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think you will IPO miss-
SPEAKER_1:  Mr. B's burger or feastables in the next 5, 10 years.
SPEAKER_0:  Beast burger or Feastables? No, I kind of think...
SPEAKER_0:  Actually, you know what? I just realized this is our first time talking about those.
SPEAKER_0:  We're like an hour and a half in, that's so funny.
SPEAKER_1:  We started talking about what...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, my retention brain kicked in.
SPEAKER_1:  I wonder if you have retention brain for like la-
SPEAKER_0:  itself.
SPEAKER_0:  I do every time I'm talking to someone I can I'm like, okay
SPEAKER_1:  loved ones.
SPEAKER_1:  Like.
SPEAKER_1:  spending time with Lava thinking like, we could be doing something much better right now.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, no, that is a serious problem.
SPEAKER_0:  with... well, so we'll pause the vSpr question, yes, but that's why my current girlfriend...
SPEAKER_0:  uh... which i was telling you before when we were talking about this is
SPEAKER_0:  She has a genuine love for learning. And that's something I have. Like I always feel like I need to be learning something to justify.
SPEAKER_0:  the time I'm spending. And so that's why it's such a nice trait because
SPEAKER_0:  feel like the time is being used optimally, because whether we're watching a documentary or we're going and you know...
SPEAKER_0:  taking IQ tests or reading about whatever, just why modern art is a thing, I don't know, whatever weird thing we decide to do. I'm always learning and improving, so it justifies the time.
SPEAKER_1:  to maximize retention in your relationship.
SPEAKER_1:  You want to spend that time learning as much as possible.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, which...
SPEAKER_0:  Conveniently, I don't have to force, right? Or I want to be recharging. So when I do work, I can hit the ground harder. And luckily, we're into a lot of the same things, which
SPEAKER_0:  you know, having to be learning, sometimes it's not learning, like maybe watching an anime or something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm a big believer in your either.
SPEAKER_0:  If you will.
SPEAKER_0:  If your goal is to be like a super successful entrepreneur, you need to either be working,
SPEAKER_0:  or you need to be doing something that.
SPEAKER_0:  decompresses and recharges you so you can work again. If your goal is to be like a really-
SPEAKER_0:  Kickass opportunity. To r pendant
SPEAKER_0:  boring this down to like a very basic thing. And so
SPEAKER_0:  the things you're doing and you're doubtful.
SPEAKER_0:  time when you're not working if it doesn't recharge you, you're screwed.
SPEAKER_0:  You're just a ticking time bomb waiting to implode.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and so.
SPEAKER_0:  You gotta like.
SPEAKER_0:  heavily recharged and like, so like.
SPEAKER_0:  watching for me anime or whatever it is playing a board game.
SPEAKER_0:  that is actually kind of crucial to my success, which...
SPEAKER_0:  It takes a lot of maturing to...
SPEAKER_0:  to that conclusion because I used to be the kind of guy that wanted to work.
SPEAKER_0:  every hour of the day.
SPEAKER_0:  tried to train myself to not need that stuff and I, you know, and I
SPEAKER_0:  almost resented like that. I have to do these kinds of things and it would piss me off because it's not optimal. And you know, I just really want to make content to entertain people.
SPEAKER_0:  but.
SPEAKER_0:  As someone who's gone down that road and you just work every day for two, three months straight and every hour of the day and then you just bomb waiting to explode and lose your mind.
SPEAKER_0:  And the only real sustainable thing is to just like.
SPEAKER_0:  Give yourself time to recharge in between working.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's a kind of balance you have to.
SPEAKER_0:  to find. You have to. I hate it more than anyone else.
SPEAKER_0:  You hate not working.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, because it's just not optimal for time. Like it's, it's, it's.
SPEAKER_0:  as a human.
SPEAKER_0:  I do need to occasionally watch a mindless show and play a board game.
SPEAKER_0:  And it took me a very long time to like come to peace with that and not.
SPEAKER_0:  I would have like.
SPEAKER_0:  borderline panic attacks when I do it because I just...
SPEAKER_0:  What am I doing right now? Why am I doing this? I should be, you know, like.
SPEAKER_0:  What if one day I have to lay off an employee because we're not doing so well? How could I justify watching this show or whatever I'm doing right now? There's a lot of things like that that go on in your head, but...
SPEAKER_0:  That's sir.
SPEAKER_1:  before we return to Mr. Beast Burger.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, what is like a-
SPEAKER_1:  Since we're on the topic, what is the.
SPEAKER_1:  Perfect day in the life, perfectly productive day in the life of MrBeastLookLike.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh boy. Well, I mean. Or like a standard. I mean, the perfectly productive day as we film a main channel video.
SPEAKER_0:  because those
SPEAKER_0:  get 100 million to pop, I mean, it doesn't really get any better than that.
SPEAKER_1:  What about like the average day when you're not on the set?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, because you're running a lot of
SPEAKER_0:  things right yeah so right now we have
SPEAKER_0:  our snack brand Feastables, we have a Russian chain feast burger.
SPEAKER_0:  And then we basically, which we haven't even really launched any products yet, but we have the data company that I was showing you where we're going to roll out some tools for creators.
SPEAKER_0:  And then we have the REACT channel, the gaming channel, the main channel, and then we have my charity, which also has a channel.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  Kinda.
SPEAKER_0:  Wow, I've structured my life right now.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  is whenever I have free time, we just kind of go, Hey guys.
SPEAKER_0:  Jimmy's got an hour.
SPEAKER_0:  From 2 p.m. to...
SPEAKER_0:  3pm and everyone's just like, I need this, I need this. And this channel's like, I need this thing filmed or, you know, whatever, the guy who runs my TikTok's like, I need this TikTok filmed or...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, Beast Burger's like, I need this menu item approved. Do we need to talk about this marketing thing? And then we kind of just look at-
SPEAKER_0:  what everyone needs and we're like.
SPEAKER_0:  That one looks like the most important, we'll do that. And then, so.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just kind of like.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, if I just did that for every company in a day, then that's optimal. If I just kind of like an optimal day for me would be going down the eight companies and just.
SPEAKER_0:  whatever their like two to three biggest pain points or things they need from me and just doing those. Marsha
SPEAKER_1:  priority and then try to keep it as short as possible. Yeah. To just the things that you.
SPEAKER_0:  needed on it doesn't get more often than that if I clear the bottlenecks or some bottlenecks for all my companies then
SPEAKER_0:  It's...
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, that's a perfect day.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean, even just me, because you're like...
SPEAKER_1:  You show me around and you're being a great and gracious host.
SPEAKER_1:  But on top of that, you're just doing all these meetings. technician.
SPEAKER_0:  I felt bad at some point. I was like, oh, I just tricked him into going to meetings with me. He's like my little meeting buddy.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess it was fun. It was fun to see it. It was fun to see how
SPEAKER_1:  effectively you've delegated.
SPEAKER_1:  You basically trust the team to do a really good job on the various things and there's just a strong team that's able to...
SPEAKER_1:  carry the five on all the different tasks.
SPEAKER_1:  From the brainstorming in the main channel to the reacts and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's really interesting. I mean, it's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's really interesting what it takes to build a team like that, because you very quickly build a very large team that's able to scale.
SPEAKER_0:  which is very scary because this is my first
SPEAKER_0:  you know
SPEAKER_0:  R- uh-
SPEAKER_0:  I'm 24, you know, and I think I was telling you this earlier.
SPEAKER_0:  It's funny because six years ago I had to raise my hand to use the bathroom, and now I'm in charge of hundreds of people.
SPEAKER_0:  and entertain.
SPEAKER_0:  hundreds of millions of people.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it is crazy just how quick it comes up.
SPEAKER_0:  I wish I was a-
SPEAKER_0:  little bit older so I could
SPEAKER_0:  have ran a couple of companies and failed a few companies in the past and like learn from those and apply those here. Cause I know for a fact.
SPEAKER_0:  When I'm 34, I'm 24 now, when I'm 34.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll know so much more about running a business and scaling and hiring and, and how to lead people and better effectively communicate and all these different skillsets that will make me a better leader.
SPEAKER_0:  That, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  That's the only thing that sucks is I just don't have those because I just haven't been through the lessons and
SPEAKER_0:  I just have such a lucrative thing.
SPEAKER_0:  on my plate right now and it just sucks that I have to learn the lessons of the lucrative thing you know I mean
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, because you already have so much influence, so much impact.
SPEAKER_1:  You have effectively scaled what what what lessons do you draw from that how to effectively scale as a 24 year old.
SPEAKER_0:  Like you. Yeah, that's something I feel like I actually could give a lot of value to, to young people who are doing it. Like older people who've built five companies or whatever they do. Um, I probably couldn't, you know, they're going to be like, Oh, this is so obvious, but.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  nu damn it
SPEAKER_0:  uh, younger first time business owners.
SPEAKER_0:  You got it.
SPEAKER_0:  just experiment to be honest. And for us, like it's just a new space. No one had really ever scaled up.
SPEAKER_0:  100 person team to build big content on YouTube. So there wasn't no, uh,
SPEAKER_0:  I spent all this time like...
SPEAKER_0:  I hired one person from Disney at one point to come in and help.
SPEAKER_0:  Obviously that was a dumb idea looking back on it, but you know I thought, oh they make-
SPEAKER_0:  great stuff people want to watch and they come over here and help me build a team.
SPEAKER_0:  and you know that bill that more the traditional way not like how should be online and
SPEAKER_0:  And so then it's like, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Now I'm not trying to trash people, like they all tried their best, but then I hire this one person who does this.
SPEAKER_0:  different type of media and runs a hundred person team. And then you come in here and they try to build it that way. And they don't really listen to you or value or see the difference. And I tried.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically.
SPEAKER_0:  building this company with like four or five different people worked in different
SPEAKER_0:  Veins of
SPEAKER_0:  Media.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  You know, every single time.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just like, they just don't get it. And they don't understand my world.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  The eventual solution was just like to roll up my sleeves and do it myself, you know, with like James or a hitman and.
SPEAKER_0:  Just like.
SPEAKER_0:  No, no one's ever done this and like, no one's going to just give us a golden carrot and tell us how to build this company. We got to figure the fuck out ourselves.
SPEAKER_1:  you have to kind of build up people from scratch.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, exactly. All the stuff I was talking about earlier and all the lessons I learned along the way.
SPEAKER_0:  And so for me, that was a big part of like, stop.
SPEAKER_0:  trying to have someone.
SPEAKER_0:  build this company for me and just.
SPEAKER_0:  do it myself, because it's scary. Like I spent my whole life studying YouTube videos virality, not business building.
SPEAKER_0:  But fuck it, I was like, I guess we just gotta do it ourselves then.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's where things really start to click and we got the exponential growth. And we started getting the right people and training them the right way. And, you know, just throwing conventional stuff out the door and focusing on what's actually practical for YouTube, which is.
SPEAKER_0:  completely different than.
SPEAKER_0:  traditional media.
SPEAKER_1:  So you train people and then those people train people and so on.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, it's just even like.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, how you do the lighting on sets or like how you do the audio or
SPEAKER_0:  or um.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, not writing scripts. So, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  we're just not as efficient with our filming. Sometimes I have to have 30 cameras running.
SPEAKER_0:  Why? Because it's not scripted.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know what Chris is gonna do when we start.
SPEAKER_0:  filming, he might run over there. But guess what? We gotta have it planned, because there's only one shot. I can't tell him not to do that.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, that's the shooting, but then there's also the editing.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and then the editing as well and not having guardrails and kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, at the end of the day, it's whatever I want. The video.
SPEAKER_0:  Their job is to make a video that they think I'll like because it's my channel, but...
SPEAKER_0:  You can achieve that kind of however.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it's just, everything's just different. You know, it's much more, I guess, like a startup as opposed to.
SPEAKER_1:  Are you often surprised like with the result like?
SPEAKER_1:  You think a certain, like we watched a video today, those really nice.
SPEAKER_1:  that was different than you would have potentially edited it. Are you sometimes surprised by a decision that it makes? It's like, okay.
SPEAKER_1:  That's not the way I would have done it, but it's actually this is a cool idea.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, of course. Yeah, no, um.
SPEAKER_0:  The thing, my biggest fear is I don't ever want to get trapped in like a...
SPEAKER_0:  bubble of, you know, because we are getting 100 million views of video on the main channel. Like, but I don't want to get in this feedback loop of just.
SPEAKER_0:  My ideas are greater. I do not have feedback loop, but stop learning and improving.
SPEAKER_0:  because it
SPEAKER_0:  It's easy sometimes to be like, what we're doing is working. We need to just keep doing it. I want to keep learning and trying.
SPEAKER_0:  new things and
SPEAKER_0:  I guess one way I'd put it is like...
SPEAKER_0:  You don't... when you're on a...
SPEAKER_0:  a come up where you're growing. You don't want to, uh,
SPEAKER_0:  test new things.
SPEAKER_0:  Once you start to plateau or have a downtrend.
SPEAKER_0:  Because if you're like, you know, you're skyrocketing, right, you're up, up, up, and then you level off, you start to go down and you're like, oh, this isn't working anymore, let's start experimenting. Well, if you have a bad experiment.
SPEAKER_0:  Now you're in like a tailspin, you're nose diving and you have one more bad experiment, you're like screwed, kinda, I'm over simplified.
SPEAKER_0:  You wanna test things while you're still growing to keep the growing.
SPEAKER_0:  from happening because once you have, again, very oversimplifying that like, you know, kind of level off.
SPEAKER_0:  You do a couple of tests, they go wrong. You're like screwed. You're already out the door, and now you're just confirming that you're out the door.
SPEAKER_0:  and online entertainment. So that's.
SPEAKER_0:  Kinda how I see it.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think it's very imperative that you're constantly always experimenting and trying things even if you're getting crazy unheard of growth.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that.
SPEAKER_1:  Outside of the thing.
SPEAKER_1:  that brought you to the dance you just dived right into.
SPEAKER_1:  Mr. Beast burger and feastables. This is a whole nother industry
SPEAKER_0:  Like what was that like? What's up, Beast Burger?
SPEAKER_0:  We kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  It was supposed to be like just a-
SPEAKER_0:  Like we just partnered with someone who had 300 restaurants and we were just like
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's just sell Beastburgers for a day or two. Let's see what happens. But first I wanna show my family some more race on h pri Baik.
SPEAKER_0:  really think it would be as big as it was, but those...
SPEAKER_0:  first like that first day, you know, we do six figures in sales.
SPEAKER_0:  and they all sell out and they're running to local Walmart, they can't keep up with the demand.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like, okay, well.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe let's just leave it open.
SPEAKER_0:  a week, whatever, and we're just doing.
SPEAKER_0:  crazy revenue and it's like, okay, well.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's add some more restaurants and let's just leave them open for a month.
SPEAKER_0:  And we're just still doing six figures a day. And it kind of just went from this thing that was.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know. It wasn't really, I didn't really plan on running a restaurant chain, but here I am.
SPEAKER_0:  But it did not ins...
SPEAKER_1:  some sense also open your mind to something like festivals.
SPEAKER_0:  Feastable is something I've always wanted to do. Cause I, I think,
SPEAKER_0:  Just in general, American snacks are just.
SPEAKER_0:  full of so much.
SPEAKER_0:  horrible ingredients to be honest and they're not.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know. I feel like there also just hasn't been any innovation in American snacks in quite a while.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And so that's just something I've always been pretty passionate about. The thing we built that from scratch. So we hired the CEO and built a team around them and we spent.
SPEAKER_0:  probably over two and a half years before we even launched. Just like building the right team, figuring things out and making sure it was actually ran the way I wanted.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  which festivals has just been crushing is.
SPEAKER_0:  It's very interesting. This is something I've never talked about publicly, but-
SPEAKER_0:  Having products in retail, it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  Before Feastables, everything I had done was online. So if you wanted to, you know, anything from the Cocoa Peace brand.
SPEAKER_0:  you'd have to buy it online and ship it to you. But...
SPEAKER_0:  festivals now that you know, because our first product chocolate bars, we started putting that in retail locations. So like for example Walmart
SPEAKER_0:  It's-
SPEAKER_0:  It's crazy. Like it's just, it doesn't make sense. How if you're
SPEAKER_0:  Which I guess it does.
SPEAKER_0:  for, because we get a hundred million views videos. So a lot of people know us. If I go stay in a Walmart, those people recognize me and ask for photos. Like if I stood there long enough, I could take 150 photos today in Walmart, 200, whatever it is.
SPEAKER_0:  So obviously it makes sense those people go to festivals, but then you just multiply that by every woman in America it just gets so crazy.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't think we'd be doing the kind of revenue we are.
SPEAKER_0:  And we're about to...
SPEAKER_0:  Launching some other I don't know if I'm allowed to say so whatever but other big retail
SPEAKER_0:  locations and convenience stores and
SPEAKER_0:  Like by the end of next year, we could be in like 40, 50,000.
SPEAKER_0:  locations.
SPEAKER_0:  the numbers just don't make sense.
SPEAKER_1:  interesting challenges about scaling there.
SPEAKER_1:  that surprised you.
SPEAKER_0:  The biggest problem, which I didn't think would be, was just keeping the sh-
SPEAKER_0:  shelves and Walmart stock, to be honest. So that supply chain. It was brutal. Well, even then sometimes like, you know, you get them the stuff and they're like, it takes them like a day or two to put it out in that specific location.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I had to stop promoting it because every time I'd mention it.
SPEAKER_0:  like 40% of people would just be like.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not there. It's not in Walmart or I can't buy it. And so there's like a
SPEAKER_0:  3D.
SPEAKER_0:  ish month period where I just
SPEAKER_0:  didn't promote feastables because I was scared that someone would go by it and it's just not there. It took us a very long time to catch up to the demand.
SPEAKER_0:  Also, it's not like we have unlimited money. But now we're relatively caught up in keeping up, but it's gonna be interesting because now this year in 2023, we're gonna...
SPEAKER_0:  Basically.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  10x the amount of locations we're in. So we're, and we're going to try to launch new products. So we're in for an interesting ride, but.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I just hate, I hate when I-
SPEAKER_0:  help people.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, like, hey, go try this product. And then they go on their local Walmart and eventually other places and it's not there. It's just so brutal.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, they made that whole journey out there and they can get it. And so
SPEAKER_0:  That's really it.
SPEAKER_0:  Besides that...
SPEAKER_0:  No, it's been doing way better than I ever thought.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  You've talked to a couple places about
SPEAKER_1:  maybe doing mobile games or computer games in the future.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. Is that something you're still considering?
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  Because
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, you know, do you normally talk with people as much as we talked beforehand?
SPEAKER_0:  Is that a-
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  No, that was the problem. We spent all day today talking about this. I just looked in my head, everything you asked me is stuff we already talked about. Not really. Well, no, no, no, not everything. I take it back, but sorry. The last two questions, yes. And so it's just funny.
SPEAKER_0:  Cause what? No, I tried.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's a different style of asking those questions because I on purpose didn't dig further
SPEAKER_0:  you I could tell yes I can tell you okay this is by the way okay all right this is the
SPEAKER_1:  First time I've ever talked to somebody.
SPEAKER_1:  as much as I did with you.
SPEAKER_1:  beforehand.
SPEAKER_0:  On the same day
SPEAKER_0:  We spent all day together and I only slept one hour. Yeah, so yeah...
SPEAKER_0:  Literally, it's funny. This is a w-
SPEAKER_0:  hilarious and awesome social experiment. I picked him up from his hotel and I just like-
SPEAKER_0:  harassed him all day to hang out with me. And then here we are now. I love it. I was secretly recording.
SPEAKER_1:  the whole time just saying I'm just kidding.
SPEAKER_1:  Anyway, so what was the question?
SPEAKER_0:  So the interesting thing is with Beast Burger and Feastables.
SPEAKER_0:  that um
SPEAKER_0:  There's physical goods.
SPEAKER_0:  as opposed to like making mobile games or PC game, which everyone may end up doing, which is software.
SPEAKER_0:  and I actually have a giant international audience.
SPEAKER_0:  Most of my audience is obviously outside of America.
SPEAKER_0:  And so the problem we're running into is it just takes time to build up the supply chain and
SPEAKER_0:  get feastables in Southeast Asia, get feastables in India, get feastables in Brazil and Mexico and all these other places where we have giant pockets of our audience.
SPEAKER_0:  And same thing with Beast Spur, it's just, it's gonna take...
SPEAKER_0:  Probably years, unless we partner with someone who already has the distribution, which we're figuring out.
SPEAKER_0:  Beauty of software.
SPEAKER_0:  is I can make a hypothetical game or whatever we end up doing.
SPEAKER_0:  All my fans can...
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  Use it tomorrow.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... the day i mentioned it and so
SPEAKER_0:  If I promote something in a video to 100 million people and it's like a, you know, basically like a game, they can all download it. So there, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  But if I promote a feastables bar...
SPEAKER_0:  Right now it's only in America because we're struggling just to keep up with American demand. We haven't even gotten the chance to go outside of America. So I alienate a majority of my audience and it feels sort of shitty.
SPEAKER_0:  to just mention something that most of them can't buy. But on the flip side, you can't just...
SPEAKER_0:  spawn this crazy infrastructure and just have
SPEAKER_0:  tens of millions of bars.
SPEAKER_0:  and all your products in every single store across the world before you promote it so you can't put the
SPEAKER_0:  egg before the chicken. And so...
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like that's, that's what I'm excited about. I want to get into-
SPEAKER_0:  less physical stuff and more
SPEAKER_0:  Stuff that everyone can actually use. It's the proper answer.
SPEAKER_1:  there's a social element to the gaming too.
SPEAKER_1:  because it's not unlike feastables, that's a product you consume.
SPEAKER_0:  You missed it when you're setting up for this we were doing some
SPEAKER_0:  Basically just laying out every-
SPEAKER_0:  everything that we're planning for. So our interface is where we're want to start hiring the team to build it. And we're kind of just laying out the game and
SPEAKER_0:  I was actually really curious to get your thoughts, but I can't say it.
SPEAKER_0:  Because whatever I say...
SPEAKER_0:  Someone's just gonna take it and run with it. But I have a pretty good idea. About the kind of games you-
SPEAKER_1:  You're thinking about? Yeah, I mean, I can imagine. We also talked a little bit about it.
SPEAKER_0:  Super awesome. So much good talk. I have the juicy talks having you. She's like, I gotta go set up.
SPEAKER_0:  Well...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I already heard a lot of awesome stuff, but that is a different.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of team you need to hire.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that a little?
SPEAKER_1:  Never acting like going into a new
SPEAKER_1:  field.
SPEAKER_1:  and trying to a little bit.
SPEAKER_0:  But then I remember stuff like Steve Jobs didn't know how to code, right? And you know, he just...
SPEAKER_0:  You just knew what a good product was. And I feel like as someone who wasted so much of his life playing video games, I have a good sense of it. And that might be ignorance. Well, that's really important, right? It's not a-
SPEAKER_1:  about coatings about what makes for a.
SPEAKER_0:  good game. Exactly. And again, that might genuinely be ignorance. Maybe I end up
SPEAKER_0:  you know, can bend the butt because of what I'm saying now, but.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Just like with YouTube, I just want to obsess over making a great product and things that I think my audience will love. I think as long as I keep that as my North Star, it will do well.
SPEAKER_1:  What is the path to being worth a hundred billion look like?
SPEAKER_0:  There's a path to being worth a hundred billion look like.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know. Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, let me just pause, you're 24.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's so much awesome scaling.
SPEAKER_1:  So many great ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think about different trajectories?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. With those.
SPEAKER_1:  possible trajectory might look like.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, if the goal was to just be worth $100 billion, yes. I am andother
SPEAKER_0:  My goal, I'm a broken record, is to make the best video possible because I know whatever else I want will come, obviously. You heard that. So the video is the foundation. Yeah, exactly, so.
SPEAKER_0:  to a path to $100 billion.
SPEAKER_0:  keep getting 100 million views a video, you know what I mean?
SPEAKER_0:  Um, but, or more or more, exactly. If we can keep growing, but you know, if we can.
SPEAKER_0:  keep Feastables growing, right? And we eventually expand international and one day we're in a hundred thousand retail locations and we're selling the same amount of skews or units per skews like we're currently doing.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... i mean that would crush and then
SPEAKER_0:  Obviously, ideally one day we open up hundreds of beast burgers. We get it where we churn out, you know, like Supercell, a couple hit games. I don't want to make.
SPEAKER_0:  dozens or hundreds of games. I just want to make games that are just great and you know we rarely drop them but we do their bangers.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  and just, you know, whatever other stuff we end up doing.
SPEAKER_0:  All that combined, I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  It's just-
SPEAKER_0:  Interesting because like what what's a show that's pulled 100 million views per episode basically
SPEAKER_0:  Nice.
SPEAKER_0:  like we're doing.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I mean, like the Super Bowl gets praised because they get 100 million viewers, but I can't think of a show.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe it reruns or something.
SPEAKER_1:  show that has a
SPEAKER_1:  has a singular kind of figure that you can now use.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't have a network telling me what to do. I don't have anyone. I can do it every once.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a very interesting position because.
SPEAKER_0:  I put out content and 100 million people show up. And then I also have a gaming channel. I put out content and 15 million people show up. And a reaction, I put out content and 10 million people show up. I have a TikTok and I put out content and on average 20 million people show up.
SPEAKER_0:  And like.
SPEAKER_0:  And I, so.
SPEAKER_0:  As long as I can keep that going and then we build these businesses, it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  It's honestly...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm pretty scared to see what will happen over the years because Feastables launched.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, last year, 2022, so it's a relatively new thing. And Beast Warrior, we just started scaling up the physical side and we haven't obviously even launched any mobile games yet. So.
SPEAKER_0:  Think about the antithesis of it.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't see a world where my YouTube channel is irrelevant in the next couple of years. I just, this is what I live for.
SPEAKER_0:  And so if I can keep that going and then really start to expand these businesses that leverage off of it.
SPEAKER_0:  then.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, hopefully there's a day when, or I can give away a billion dollars in a video, honestly.
SPEAKER_1:  That would be one hell of a video.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask you the ridiculous question since you went from being broke.
SPEAKER_1:  to being.
SPEAKER_1:  Rich, although you keep...
SPEAKER_1:  spending all your money. Does money buy happiness?
SPEAKER_1:  How has money changed sort of your?
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, man. Your contentment, your happiness in life.
SPEAKER_0:  Money by happiness.
SPEAKER_0:  No, not, I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  To a point, yes. Once you can take care of your-
SPEAKER_0:  Health.
SPEAKER_0:  You can take care of like.
SPEAKER_0:  any immediate dangers and you can take care of your family relatively.
SPEAKER_0:  No, it doesn't. But those things do. When I first came into money, one of the first things I did was retire my mom.
SPEAKER_0:  And like that brought me tons of happiness, you know what I mean?
SPEAKER_0:  then like.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, if my brother had a medical emergency and...
SPEAKER_0:  and we couldn't afford it and I made money to afford it, that brings tons of happiness, you know? So once you take care of those basic necessities, so we'll say makeover hypothetically a million dollars.
SPEAKER_0:  No, it really doesn't. Like adding an extra zero, going from 10 million to a hundred million or whatever it is.
SPEAKER_0:  makes no difference.
SPEAKER_1:  So you're.
SPEAKER_1:  given that I was just fearless in spending the money.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, well, let me reframe. I guess it could for some people if-
SPEAKER_0:  If you really...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, you spent your whole life obsessing over cars. It probably would bring you a little bit of joy to buy a nice Lamborghini. I'm coming more from the frame of mind of an entrepreneur, someone who's really obsessed with business building. For me and a lot of my friends and people I hang around.
SPEAKER_0:  What brings us happiness is winning and building companies and
SPEAKER_0:  do, you know, changing the world. Like that.
SPEAKER_0:  That is fun. It's a complex problem you can wake up every day and it gives you something to obsess over and devote your life to.
SPEAKER_0:  Where it's just...
SPEAKER_0:  Having money doesn't, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  I wanna-
SPEAKER_1:  Interesting question for you psychologically, so because you...
SPEAKER_1:  have become wealthy and because you give, like part of your work is giving away a lot of money.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Do you find it hard to find people you can trust?
SPEAKER_1:  Do people see you basically as a source of money? As opposed to another human being?
SPEAKER_0:  It's weird because you would think yes, but I think
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like I also know the right places to look.
SPEAKER_0:  But yeah, if I just walked into Target and try to make friends with 10 random people, of course.
SPEAKER_0:  You gotta...
SPEAKER_0:  Uhhh...
SPEAKER_0:  So you can kind of sense who has the right thing in their heart.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's so obvious. I don't even want to go into it.
SPEAKER_0:  descriptions but
SPEAKER_0:  But honestly, a lot of my friends are like Chandler.
SPEAKER_0:  I played Little League with him.
SPEAKER_0:  and Tyler, the guy, I mean, I went to school with him.
SPEAKER_0:  Chris, he was my first subscriber.
SPEAKER_0:  Carl was here after we got big, but whatever, he's just friends with the boys.
SPEAKER_0:  It is a lot of.
SPEAKER_0:  my closer friends, even like my YouTube friends, I knew before I was big. So.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe there is some merit to that. Maybe it is. I don't know. I've never really put too much thought into it. Maybe there's a reason I hang around a lot of these people I knew before I got Hiiya!
SPEAKER_0:  It's much easier.
SPEAKER_1:  and they help you keep like your radar sharp of.
SPEAKER_1:  who can and can't be trusted, because you know you can trust them.
SPEAKER_1:  It's difficult you become richer and richer and more powerful
SPEAKER_1:  Well.
SPEAKER_0:  One thing you'll also find when you get
SPEAKER_0:  Not even richer, but more famous. One thing I thought is, as I climbed this like-
SPEAKER_0:  ladder of YouTube and got bigger. I thought there would be tons of people like me.
SPEAKER_0:  people.
SPEAKER_0:  Like that takes like the kamikaze approach to building a business. You just throw all your money in it. You throw all your time, you throw all your energy, you throw everything. You're just like, fuck it. It's this or I'm dead. I thought there would be hundreds of me. And there isn't. There isn't. There's like maybe one or two.
SPEAKER_0:  and I talk to those motherfuckers every single day. I'm sick and tired of talking to them, but I love them.
SPEAKER_0:  but
SPEAKER_0:  It's just so interesting because like every level I got up, like I'd get a million subscribers. Like.
SPEAKER_0:  Where's all these guys with the million subscribers that are fucking psychopaths? And then you don't-
SPEAKER_0:  You know, they're like.
SPEAKER_1:  become conservative as they get.
SPEAKER_0:  Especially as they get bigger, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  and you know, 20 million subscribers, 30. It's like every step of the way, it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  I just got more and more lonely to be honest.
SPEAKER_0:  Sounds cliche and you hear that kind of shit in movies and you're like, yeah, that's not how it works, but.
SPEAKER_0:  It is like there's there's just not many people that just want to give up everything goal in then obsess over making the greatest goddamn videos every single day of their life like.
SPEAKER_0:  They're really hard to find.
SPEAKER_1:  and be able to sacrifice everything for that video.
SPEAKER_1:  Like basically you put all the money right back in.
SPEAKER_0:  people doing it, they're on just a small scale and if I talk to them, it's just 99.9% of the time I'm teaching them things.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's lonely because there's not.
SPEAKER_1:  too many people.
SPEAKER_1:  especially in the creative space that is crazy as you.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it is 100%. It's so.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not what I was expecting. I was expecting there would be a lot of people like me.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I guess.
SPEAKER_1:  the guy we talked to Elon Musk is a bit like you in that sense. Yeah, just in a different domain. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Exactly. Just willingness to put it all.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's why I found right now a lot of the people I relate to don't even make YouTube videos. I'm just like, I'm viewing more and more.
SPEAKER_0:  away from fellow content creators and more to just.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm just looking for those other people who just share a little bit of it so I don't feel so fucking crazy all the time. Like, you know what I mean?
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and like people I feel normal around and they tend to just be doing the randomest things, but you know.
SPEAKER_0:  loving it.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I think that's really inspiring. It's uh.
SPEAKER_1:  I think the Bukowski line, where you love and let it kill you, is really-
SPEAKER_1:  Put everything.
SPEAKER_1:  put everything into the thing you love.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's like the way to really create special stuff, but it's also the way to.
SPEAKER_0:  Live out your life mostly. You have to be careful giving this advice because
SPEAKER_0:  They're like, they're like.
SPEAKER_0:  bodybuilders will be like.
SPEAKER_0:  Go to the gym, be disciplined. I'm disciplined, go to the gym.
SPEAKER_0:  I would argue.
SPEAKER_0:  For those people.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, it's not even discipline. They just enjoy weightlifting.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Because there are people who are jacked, but they don't make much money or run a business. Right? In the McClinton area in Thailand.
SPEAKER_0:  they would be hitting every area of their life. They just really like business. And there's people.
SPEAKER_0:  Like me, who just to an extreme level, love building companies, right? It's not even discipline for me. It's just in my blood. It's what I wake up, I don't think about it. I don't push myself. I don't need to watch a fucking motivational video to go work.
SPEAKER_0:  I just do it, it's programmed in me at this point. And I couldn't imagine a world where I don't wake up and do it every day.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  But I think that...
SPEAKER_0:  A little bit of it is genetics and just how you're hardwired. Not that it can't be trained or taught and not that, you know, and obviously the friend group you're in influences these things. And over time, I think can change it, but someone's just not going to be able to flip a switch.
SPEAKER_0:  and then just.
SPEAKER_0:  start doing a kamikaze approach to building a business.
SPEAKER_0:  Just like a lot of people try to flip a switch and start bodybuilding and then quit majority of the time.
SPEAKER_0:  That's just not innate to them.
SPEAKER_1:  I think a lot of us have the capacity to do that in some domain.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think if you went about it strategically, if you surrounded yourself with...
SPEAKER_0:  fellow like-minded people and slowly over time switched it.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you just try to like hardcore do it, you're just gonna lose your mind
SPEAKER_1:  Do you ever worry about your mental health?
SPEAKER_1:  Did you take steps to protect it?
SPEAKER_1:  to like for the long run to make sure you have the mental strength to go.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, weirdly enough, the best thing for my mental health was giving into my nature to work. The most depressed I get is when I try to restrict it and like, I don't work weekends or I don't work this day.
SPEAKER_0:  What's best for me is just to work when I feel like working and then.
SPEAKER_0:  just not work when I don't, and just have no constraints. Because there are just some nights where I don't want to sleep.
SPEAKER_0:  whatever reason I feel compelled to go all night.
SPEAKER_0:  Whatever, like just do it, you know, do whatever you want.
SPEAKER_0:  is what I told my like.
SPEAKER_0:  working brain.
SPEAKER_0:  and I just give into it. And I feel that's where I feel the happiest.
SPEAKER_0:  And then, you know, it's typically like.
SPEAKER_0:  But when I'm really in the grind mode, it'll be like seven or eight days, just nonstop going going.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll realize like, oh.
SPEAKER_0:  I need some recharge time and then go fucking binge a season of anime. Yeah. But, but that's the thing. Like people will tell you don't work weekends or don't do this or don't work past this or blah, blah, give you all these constraints, but for me.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's unconventional, I just give into it. I think there's something-
SPEAKER_1:  really to be said.
SPEAKER_1:  for that, I try to surround myself with people that.
SPEAKER_1:  Like when I pull an all-nighter, they don't go like you should get more sleep.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a reason I pulled that all nighter. Like if I'm really passionate about something, they say they basically encourage it.
SPEAKER_1:  I have no problem.
SPEAKER_1:  getting sleep and getting rest.
SPEAKER_1:  What I need in my life is people that encourage you to kind of keep going, keep going with the stuff that you're passionate about.
SPEAKER_0:  Normal people, they don't want that life and they probably shouldn't. It's not good for you.
SPEAKER_0:  But yeah, if you hang around people, just what different people.
SPEAKER_0:  you're gonna feel crazy and it's gonna wear on you whereas if you're around similar people
SPEAKER_0:  It's just so much easier. Like, if you-
SPEAKER_0:  You know, um, I've started weightlifting more and like one thing that's helped is just having Jack.
SPEAKER_0:  people around me because they naturally just eat healthier. They do. They naturally just have.
SPEAKER_0:  freaking grilled chicken and all this shit and high protein meals. And it's just like easier for me to just piggyback and be like, oh, can you just order me whatever you're getting? And they're like, I gotta go to the gym. I'll be like, oh shit, I'll just join you, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like, it's just, it's cheat codes, you know, you just surround yourself with people that you want to be. And it makes it like 70% easier, in my opinion. It's like, that is the cheat code to life.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And I wish...
SPEAKER_0:  Obviously your audience is definitely a lot older, but you know, two of the older people listening, like if you've
SPEAKER_0:  are in a place of mentorship for someone younger or have influence over younger people.
SPEAKER_0:  you should really try to drill that in their heads. Like the people they are around 100% dictates the outcome. I would not be on 120 million subscribers if.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't find when I was around a million.
SPEAKER_0:  I had a couple friends that were just also psychopaths.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  I outgrew them, but at the time it was great. I wouldn't be where I am today if it wasn't for them.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  and just all along the way the friends that
SPEAKER_0:  I hung out with had such a dramatic impact on where I am.
SPEAKER_0:  I probably have.
SPEAKER_0:  80 million less subscribers. You know, if I wasn't so strategic about hanging out with people that I add value to and they also.
SPEAKER_1:  So the advice for young people would be to...
SPEAKER_1:  be very selective about the people you're signing.
SPEAKER_0:  So selective. It's crazy.
SPEAKER_0:  Chris, you know, he's...
SPEAKER_0:  He's really funny and that's why he's great for the videos. And part of why he's so funny is he consumes copious amounts of cartoons and just funny content.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I'll find, like when I spend more time with Chris, I'll start just quoting these weird cartoons and shows. Like my speech will literally change just after like a week of spending more time with him. It has like, it's like that click out of effect.
SPEAKER_0:  Now picture that over the course of years. I mean, yeah, it has such a huge influence.
SPEAKER_0:  Like.
SPEAKER_0:  pluck one of their friends out and hypothetically put me in there and...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there's...
SPEAKER_0:  no doubt if they're trying to become a content creator, there are odds of success is 10X, right? Obviously you can't do that, but you gotta find your closest version of it.
SPEAKER_1:  And just be selective. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  But this also applies not just to younger, to older people too.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay. But they, it's, it's even more.
SPEAKER_0:  I like.
SPEAKER_0:  When I was a teenager, I just, you know, I couldn't relate to many people. I just thought it was like a fucking freaking nature because no one was obsessed with building businesses or any of this kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  And so like back then.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, that advice would have been helpful. Maybe not that particularly, but just knowing that...
SPEAKER_0:  There are, it's not that you're a freaking nature, you just haven't found people that have the same interest..
SPEAKER_1:  because.
SPEAKER_1:  Not if you're sorry for yourself or somehow change yourself, it's more-
SPEAKER_0:  to find the people you fit in with. Yeah. Assuming you're not getting complimented.
SPEAKER_0:  and assume it's not something bad. Right? Like if you're hobby is shooting things, or shooting things you shouldn't be shooting, don't find people that encourage that.
SPEAKER_1:  But outside of that for sure.
SPEAKER_1:  actually as an answer to what is the best advice someone ever gave you, you said.
SPEAKER_1:  You're crazy until you're successful, then you're a genius.
SPEAKER_0:  100% all along the way.
SPEAKER_0:  People gave me so much.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  advice on why I shouldn't be doing it, why I'm crazy. Every step of the way people wanted to tell me why I shouldn't be doing this and should get a live should.
SPEAKER_0:  stop being too obsessed, everything under the book.
SPEAKER_0:  And then once I'm successful, those same people are like, dang.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_0:  You're a genius. Wow, you really, you pulled that off. Those are prob-
SPEAKER_1:  the same people that will give you advice now.
SPEAKER_1:  you're the most successful video creator.
SPEAKER_1:  of all time, stick to that.
SPEAKER_1:  Anytime you want to do something new, right? Don't worry, there'll be another channel here!
SPEAKER_1:  pressure you not to do the um...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, feastables or mobile gaming or whatever lays beyond.
SPEAKER_1:  It's funny how people don't.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, honestly, they're the type of people I just don't talk to anymore. Yeah, sure. I don't even know what they have to say now.
SPEAKER_0:  So most people on the team.
SPEAKER_1:  are like yes and they're like whatever the idea you got they
SPEAKER_1:  They're with it.
SPEAKER_0:  No, I mean, it's weird. We actually have a-
SPEAKER_0:  My team pushes back on me pretty hardcore. Which I want. I don't want Yes Man. And they're like uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Third.
SPEAKER_0:  James, you know, the CEO who helped me build all this.
SPEAKER_0:  He's very adamant, like we're not yes men. And he trains people to really think for themselves. And even when I give them orders, like really think like, is this optimal? Is there context or information Jimmy could be missing that I can provide that could help him make a more updated decision? Like I'm not.
SPEAKER_0:  God, you know what I mean? Like I'm human and I make errors. And so.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't take what I say as the Bible.
SPEAKER_1:  So even like in the brainstorming and so on, they can.
SPEAKER_0:  that can push back. Yeah, you can see it, like Tyler, anytime I said something, he would give me feedback and push back, which is what I want. I don't want him just to be like, yes, you're a fucking genius, good job, Jimmy. You know, I don't need that, you know, I need negatives.
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhhhhh
SPEAKER_1:  You talked about being in a relationship. What role?
SPEAKER_1:  Jimmy does love playing the human condition.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, all this love. The big thing is that love can be scary, because this is-
SPEAKER_0:  you know, the human you're gonna spend the most amount of time with.
SPEAKER_0:  in your life.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, and so for project that over 50 years, they can be a liability art asset. You know, I love, no, but seriously, it's gotta be someone that makes you better for me. I can't truly love someone that.
SPEAKER_0:  doesn't make me better because in the long run across the years. Because if not, then it's like, it's a negative, you know, to everything I spent my life building.
SPEAKER_0:  But luckily I'm very happy with the partner I have like we were talking about before. I do think she makes me better. There's a lot of actually positives I've noticed, even things as simple as like.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I struggle to turn off my brain at night because I'm just thinking about all the businesses and how we could do better or whatever weird thing I have on my mind, but you know, just chatting with her and hanging out with her helps me. Like.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically just.
SPEAKER_0:  shut my brain off and like mellow out. And even like, there's just a ton of little things like that that I've noticed are positives, especially when you really look for them.
SPEAKER_0:  that are easy to gloss over if you're not.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  For me, yeah, I have someone who I think is very beautiful, very intelligent, makes me better, is constantly pushing me, okay with me, working hard, makes me smarter and just all these different things that...
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  For me, love.
SPEAKER_0:  just makes me a better person, you know what I mean? Which makes me love her even more. Does that make sense?
SPEAKER_0:  Absolutely what advice
SPEAKER_1:  would you give on finding somebody like that?
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Just.
SPEAKER_0:  Really, don't give up until you find someone that, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  There's so many people on the planet. I mean, there really is. There's billions of- The odds are in your favor. Of, yeah, like just don't settle and find someone that, you know-
SPEAKER_0:  Makes you happy.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, just like you said, surround yourself with people.
SPEAKER_1:  that make you a better person. In the same case, surround yourself with that one special person that really makes you a better person.
SPEAKER_0:  And maybe that's just an entrepreneur brain looking at it. Not everyone wants to hyper-optimize their life like me, but for me to like truly love someone, they have to.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe a better person. In every way, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, what do you hope?
SPEAKER_1:  You're 24. We started talking about death. Let's- let's-
SPEAKER_1:  Let's finish talking about death. What do you hope your legacy is?
SPEAKER_1:  when you
SPEAKER_1:  When we look 100 years from now and the alien, the AI has completely taken over.
SPEAKER_1:  and the aliens visit and discuss with the AI.
SPEAKER_1:  what this last of special humans that existed on Earth was like. What do you hope they say about you?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  It's a deep one.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  Travis, just.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  Because it's hard, right? Like I said before, Elon.
SPEAKER_0:  Over double my age, I could live every second.
SPEAKER_0:  I've lived up to this point in my life and still not even be Elon's age. So I have so much time.
SPEAKER_0:  I just hope whatever it is that-
SPEAKER_0:  It's a net positive on the world and it impacts billions of people.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh...
SPEAKER_0:  positive way.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  Mix.
SPEAKER_0:  Lasting change.
SPEAKER_1:  So you admire people like Steve Jobs and Elon Musk for having.
SPEAKER_1:  sort of reached for that goal as well.
SPEAKER_1:  Of course.
SPEAKER_1:  to help.
SPEAKER_0:  to help millions. I mean, the iPhone's the most successful product ever invented. It's hard not to admire what he created. It's hard 0.0
SPEAKER_1:  The same with sort of as Johnny Ive talks about.
SPEAKER_1:  Like.
SPEAKER_1:  the passion, the effort they put into the designing.
SPEAKER_1:  iPhone.
SPEAKER_1:  that little bit of love is transferred to the whole world. to get to experience the joy of that from the design.
SPEAKER_0:  It's what it's
SPEAKER_0:  beautiful thing to do. You know, I couldn't think of anything better.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  to create something that.
SPEAKER_0:  Even after you're dead for decades just has such a
SPEAKER_0:  profound impact on basically half the human population.
SPEAKER_0:  wild.
SPEAKER_1:  brings joy to people.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I hope you do just that, man. You've already done it for millions and millions and millions and millions of people, and I hope you keep doing it.
SPEAKER_1:  I can't.
SPEAKER_1:  Like.
SPEAKER_1:  It's so exciting to see what happens this year and next year.
SPEAKER_1:  I know. That's the limit.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I can't, I mean, no.
SPEAKER_1:  the videos, but all the other businesses you're in, and you as a human being as you grow.
SPEAKER_1:  I can tell, I know as everyone knows you have a kind heart.
SPEAKER_1:  and the fact that you're really damn good.
SPEAKER_1:  at uh...
SPEAKER_1:  actually using that kind of hard to help a lot of people.
SPEAKER_1:  It's awesome to see, man. I appreciate it.
SPEAKER_0:  More importantly, before we go.
SPEAKER_0:  Are we gonna play Dune tonight?
SPEAKER_1:  Some board not gonna play dune. I have to
SPEAKER_0:  I have to wait one hour. You don't want to play board games with me?
SPEAKER_1:  and one of the..."
SPEAKER_0:  More games?
SPEAKER_1:  If only I wasn't an idiot.
SPEAKER_1:  and actually flew to the right airport.
SPEAKER_0:  If you don't play board games with me, they're gonna dislike the video.
SPEAKER_0:  Laughter
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with Mr. Beast.
SPEAKER_1:  To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now, let me leave you with some words.
SPEAKER_1:  from the poet and philosopher.
SPEAKER_1:  Rabindranath Tagore
SPEAKER_1:  Reach high.
SPEAKER_1:  for stars lie hidden in you.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for listening.
SPEAKER_1:  and hope to see you.
SPEAKER_1:  next time.