SPEAKER_1:  So the BBC reached out and said, we want to interview you.
SPEAKER_1:  I said, we've got this idea. We want to take you to a park and have you meet one of the protesters.
SPEAKER_1:  who's been wielding his gun.
SPEAKER_1:  outside your mosque.
SPEAKER_1:  and talk to him.
SPEAKER_1:  It was really interesting because they'd interviewed him before meeting me.
SPEAKER_1:  and the things that he was able to utter.
SPEAKER_1:  before meeting me and before meeting Syrian refugees.
SPEAKER_1:  Was just awful.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, the most dehumanizing rhetoric that you can imagine.
SPEAKER_1:  but then at the park.
SPEAKER_1:  he meets me.
SPEAKER_1:  talks to me.
SPEAKER_1:  he meets a Syrian refugee family.
SPEAKER_1:  one of the girls whose leg
SPEAKER_1:  had been blown off in an airstrike.
SPEAKER_1:  And he said, I feel like an idiot.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, he expressed all sorts of regret.
SPEAKER_1:  and was teary eyed.
SPEAKER_1:  that he could.
SPEAKER_1:  dehumanize people the way that he was. And so my whole thing was.
SPEAKER_1:  and is.
SPEAKER_1:  Come inside the mosque, put your gun down.
SPEAKER_1:  disarm yourself and learn.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  you'll be surprised what you'll walk away with.
SPEAKER_1:  and only took one meeting with Him.
SPEAKER_1:  so completely.
SPEAKER_1:  shift.
SPEAKER_1:  his worldview at the time.
SPEAKER_1:  which
SPEAKER_1:  was made up of heroes and villains, the Muslims unfortunately being the villains that had to be wiped off the face of the earth so that the earth could continue.
SPEAKER_0:  The following is a conversation with Imam Dr. Omar Suleiman.
SPEAKER_0:  He's a Muslim scholar.
SPEAKER_0:  civil rights leader.
SPEAKER_0:  founder and president of the Yakin Institute for Islamic Research.
SPEAKER_0:  and he's a professor of Islamic studies.
SPEAKER_0:  at Southern Methodist University.
SPEAKER_0:  He's one of the most influential Muslims in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  and as a fearless, kind-hearted human being.
SPEAKER_0:  who I'm now proud to call a friend.
SPEAKER_0:  As a side note, allow me to say a few words about Israel and Palestine.
SPEAKER_0:  While this conversation with Omar Suleiman
SPEAKER_0:  was mostly exploring the history and beauty of Islam.
SPEAKER_0:  and the Muslim community.
SPEAKER_0:  We did delve briefly into the topic of Israel and Palestine.
SPEAKER_0:  This topic is an extremely challenging one.
SPEAKER_0:  and an extremely important one.
SPEAKER_0:  It has deep roots and implications in US politics.
SPEAKER_0:  in global geopolitics, in military and religious conflicts, wars, and atrocities.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  basic struggle of all human beings to survive, to protect their loved ones, and to flourish as individuals and as communities.
SPEAKER_0:  I did not want to cover this topic.
SPEAKER_0:  in a solely scholarly fashion.
SPEAKER_0:  much like with the war in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  It is not simply a story of history, politics, religion, and
SPEAKER_0:  national identity.
SPEAKER_0:  It is also a deeply human story.
SPEAKER_0:  in the way that my gut and my heart says to do it.
SPEAKER_0:  I have to talk to everyone.
SPEAKER_0:  to leaders and people on all sides.
SPEAKER_0:  Muslim and Jewish.
SPEAKER_0:  Israeli and Palestinian.
SPEAKER_0:  from refugees to soldiers, from scholars.
SPEAKER_0:  to extremists.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not sure if that's possible.
SPEAKER_0:  or wise.
SPEAKER_0:  But like Forrest Gump said...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not a smart man.
SPEAKER_0:  and maybe you know how the rest of that goes.
SPEAKER_0:  I just like to follow my heart.
SPEAKER_0:  to whatever place it leads.
SPEAKER_0:  I ask.
SPEAKER_0:  the Muslim and the Jewish communities.
SPEAKER_0:  for your patience and support as I explore this topic.
SPEAKER_0:  I will make many mistakes.
SPEAKER_0:  and I'll be listening to all voices so I can learn and do better.
SPEAKER_0:  I've become distinctly aware.
SPEAKER_0:  that my approach of talking to people from all walks of life with empathy and compassion
SPEAKER_0:  but with backbone.
SPEAKER_0:  can create enemies on all sides.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't quite yet understand why this is.
SPEAKER_0:  but I'm learning to accept.
SPEAKER_0:  It is the reality of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Hopefully, in the end.
SPEAKER_0:  Whatever happens.
SPEAKER_0:  Whatever silly thing I do.
SPEAKER_0:  as a chance of adding a bit of love to the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Thanks for going along.
SPEAKER_0:  with me.
SPEAKER_0:  this journey.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the Lex Freakman Podcast. To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_0:  And now...
SPEAKER_0:  Dear friends.
SPEAKER_0:  Here's Omar.
SPEAKER_0:  Salman.
SPEAKER_0:  Assalamu alaikum Umar, we've been trying to do this a long time. It's the world tried to prevent it through the funny ways that the world does. But here we are. I'm a huge fan of yours. It's a huge honor to talk to you.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for making the sacrifice and coming down, or coming up, I guess, to Dallas. I appreciate it.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a short flight, but a-
SPEAKER_0:  long journey.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's start with the biggest question, who is God?
SPEAKER_0:  according to Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  God is...
SPEAKER_1:  the most compassionate, the most merciful, the Creator of the heavens and the earth.
SPEAKER_1:  He is one God.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  He begets not, nor is he begotten.
SPEAKER_1:  He is unique.
SPEAKER_1:  He is omnipotent.
SPEAKER_1:  He is beyond the limitations of man.
SPEAKER_1:  He is beyond the constructs of our imagination.
SPEAKER_1:  but he is ever accessible.
SPEAKER_1:  sincere supplication.
SPEAKER_1:  when you call upon him.
SPEAKER_1:  alone.
SPEAKER_1:  One God.
SPEAKER_1:  He is closer to you than your jugular vein, the Qur'an tells us.
SPEAKER_1:  He's known by many names and attributes, but his essence is one. He's one God.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... no human likeness
SPEAKER_1:  No human imperfection can be attributed to him.
SPEAKER_1:  no partners.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... no image
SPEAKER_1:  of him.
SPEAKER_1:  can be constructed.
SPEAKER_1:  And that is God.
SPEAKER_0:  So God represents, He is.
SPEAKER_0:  feeling of closeness that is accessible to every human being.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, God's not a feeling. God is known by names and attributes.
SPEAKER_1:  We call upon God.
SPEAKER_1:  But.
SPEAKER_1:  There is certainly a feeling of closeness.
SPEAKER_1:  when you access him. So I think the beauty of Islam is that.
SPEAKER_1:  as perfect as God is described.
SPEAKER_1:  He's also so accessible to the imperfect.
SPEAKER_1:  And so the idea of sincere supplication and connection to him, we worship him alone. We call upon him alone. There's no clergy. There's no barrier.
SPEAKER_1:  between
SPEAKER_1:  God end.
SPEAKER_1:  and us.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  that encourages.
SPEAKER_1:  a sincere devotion and commitment to Him alone.
SPEAKER_1:  And so he is certainly described.
SPEAKER_1:  Supreme.
SPEAKER_1:  end.
SPEAKER_1:  God speaks to us through the Quran.
SPEAKER_1:  and we speak to him through sincere supplication.
SPEAKER_1:  and his attributes are the furthest.
SPEAKER_1:  from us in terms of their perfection.
SPEAKER_1:  but He is ever close to us.
SPEAKER_1:  through our supplication, through our prayers, and through our connection to Him.
SPEAKER_1:  to open the door.
SPEAKER_0:  to that connection, to have a connection with God. How difficult is that process? How difficult was it for you?
SPEAKER_0:  how difficult those are for the people that...
SPEAKER_0:  for the many, many, many Muslims that you've interacted with.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I think that there are different layers of difficulty, right? There is the personal difficulty.
SPEAKER_1:  Submitting yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  to God, you know, Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  requires a complete submission to him.
SPEAKER_1:  And
SPEAKER_1:  one of the things that.
SPEAKER_1:  happens is that if we
SPEAKER_1:  project.
SPEAKER_1:  some of our bad experiences with authority.
SPEAKER_1:  onto our relationship with God.
SPEAKER_1:  then we immediately perceive him in a certain way.
SPEAKER_1:  that might not allow us to gain a closeness to him because maybe we didn't have the best relationship with our parents growing up. Maybe we didn't have the best relationship with authority figures.
SPEAKER_1:  in our lives and so this idea of an ultimate authority.
SPEAKER_1:  to whom you submit yourself can be very difficult.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, Malcolm X who...
SPEAKER_1:  one of the most prominent converts to Islam in American history.
SPEAKER_1:  We talked about the difficulty of prostration for the very first time, putting your head on the ground.
SPEAKER_1:  putting your face on the ground and praying.
SPEAKER_1:  God is a very humbling
SPEAKER_1:  think.
SPEAKER_1:  Submitting all of your affairs to him is very humbling.
SPEAKER_1:  and ultimately you have to relinquish control.
SPEAKER_1:  and you can't relinquish control without trust. So you have to learn to trust God.
SPEAKER_1:  to trust God, you have to know him.
SPEAKER_1:  and to know him is to love him.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  for me personally.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  growing up.
SPEAKER_1:  going through certain difficulties.
SPEAKER_1:  having a sick parent.
SPEAKER_1:  who struggled in her life with.
SPEAKER_1:  cancer and with strokes.
SPEAKER_1:  dealing with racism in South Louisiana.
SPEAKER_1:  growing up.
SPEAKER_1:  It was important for me.
SPEAKER_1:  to learn about God.
SPEAKER_1:  through my difficulties, for example, rather than let those difficulties turn me away from them.
SPEAKER_1:  many times.
SPEAKER_1:  people put a barrier between them and God.
SPEAKER_1:  because they can't make sense of the things that are happening in their own lives.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  they project anger.
SPEAKER_1:  towards God and at the same time.
SPEAKER_1:  deny their own belief in him.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  do away with this natural disposition that every one of us has to believe in Him.
SPEAKER_1:  So there are intellectual barriers, certainly.
SPEAKER_1:  there are experiential barriers.
SPEAKER_1:  but I think that one of the...
SPEAKER_1:  beautiful things about Islam is clarity.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  there's an explanation.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  his existence, there's an explanation for our existence, there's an explanation for the existence of difficulties and trial and explanation for...
SPEAKER_1:  the existence of desires and distractions.
SPEAKER_1:  and it all comes together so beautifully and coherently.
SPEAKER_1:  in Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that for many of us...
SPEAKER_1:  We want to be our own gods.
SPEAKER_1:  and ultimately we create and fashion gods.
SPEAKER_1:  in ways that allow us to still be the ultimate determiners of our own fates, of our own.
SPEAKER_1:  story.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  That's very unfulfilling.
SPEAKER_1:  when you fail at your own plan.
SPEAKER_1:  but when you realize that there is one who is all-knowing.
SPEAKER_1:  that there is one who is all wise.
SPEAKER_1:  you actually find peace in submitting yourself to Him. And so submitting your will to Him, submitting your...
SPEAKER_1:  desires, submitting your own fate to him.
SPEAKER_1:  becomes actually an experience of liberation.
SPEAKER_1:  because you trust the one that you're submitting to. You trust his knowledge over yours. You trust his wisdom over yours.
SPEAKER_1:  and that gives you a lot of peace, and then you have direct access to them.
SPEAKER_1:  You pray to Him, you call upon Him, you supplicate.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Everything in your life suddenly has meaning.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, in our faith.
SPEAKER_1:  Everything is about intention.
SPEAKER_1:  and there is an intentionality even behind the most.
SPEAKER_1:  most mundane actions.
SPEAKER_1:  Amor Sol.
SPEAKER_1:  of food.
SPEAKER_1:  in the mouth of...
SPEAKER_1:  your spouse, your family.
SPEAKER_1:  is looked at as a great charity.
SPEAKER_1:  the way that you enter into a place and exit out of a place, what foot you step in, what foot you step out with. There's an intentionality. There's a word of remembrance that's spoken.
SPEAKER_1:  There is a word of praise before and after you engage in any action.
SPEAKER_1:  There are things that you say before you eat, before you sleep.
SPEAKER_1:  There is meaning even to your sleep. One of the great.
SPEAKER_1:  Companions of the Prophet Muhammad, peace and blessings be upon him, he said,
SPEAKER_1:  that I seek the reward for my sleep just as I seek the reward for my prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  because you sleep.
SPEAKER_1:  refresh yourself so that you can once again do great things and the intentionality behind that.
SPEAKER_1:  allows even the sleep to be rewardable.
SPEAKER_1:  You eat to nourish yourself so that you can do great things. You seek toSMARTNATHS1, THANK YOU forünü 상
SPEAKER_1:  be in a position of independence and
SPEAKER_1:  of being sustained so that you can sustain others. So the Prophet peace be upon him says for example that the upper hand
SPEAKER_1:  is better than the lower hand. The upper hand is the giving hand, the lower hand is the receiving hand. So to seek.
SPEAKER_1:  a position where you can help other people. Everything becomes intentional.
SPEAKER_1:  and there's no such thing as
SPEAKER_1:  you know, something that is meaningless and without.
SPEAKER_1:  purpose.
SPEAKER_1:  So every pursuit is ultimately a pursuit of God.
SPEAKER_1:  and when you pursue God sincerely.
SPEAKER_1:  then he rewards you not just with paradise in the afterlife, but he rewards you with a great sense of serenity and self satisfaction here.
SPEAKER_1:  You mentioned part of the struggle.
SPEAKER_0:  growing up was having a parent, your mom.
SPEAKER_0:  who was sick, what do you remember?
SPEAKER_0:  Bye bye, mom.
SPEAKER_0:  What are some happy, pleasant memories?
SPEAKER_1:  So my parents were...
SPEAKER_1:  or my father.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank God is still alive.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  My mother was a...
SPEAKER_1:  Pious woman, beautiful woman.
SPEAKER_1:  a righteous woman, a woman who was known for treating everyone with a great deal of love and respect.
SPEAKER_1:  She was a poet.
SPEAKER_1:  She used to write poetry about oppressed peoples around the world.
SPEAKER_1:  From her homeland in Palestine to the genocide in Bosnia, she...
SPEAKER_1:  followed every conflict before social media.
SPEAKER_1:  and poured her heart into it.
SPEAKER_1:  She was a woman of great charity.
SPEAKER_1:  So when I think back to my mom growing up.
SPEAKER_1:  She was known for her smile. My mom was always smiling.
SPEAKER_1:  And in fact...
SPEAKER_1:  every picture of her.
SPEAKER_1:  She's smiling.
SPEAKER_1:  and at her funeral.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, people talked about her smile.
SPEAKER_1:  that she would smile at everyone. And that was kind of her thing. So if you were left out of a gathering, she was smiling at you and she'd kind of welcome you in.
SPEAKER_1:  I remember my mom to be content. She was a woman of prayer and a woman of content.
SPEAKER_1:  So I used to see her in her prayer clothes all the time.
SPEAKER_1:  In fact, when I think back to her growing up, I think of her more in her prayer clothes than in her normal clothes because that's how often she was engaged in prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think of her.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  making sure that everyone was included in a conversation. So she was very interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  in that she had several strokes.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  and each one of those strokes.
SPEAKER_1:  impaired.
SPEAKER_1:  one of her senses to some extent. So she was partially deaf because of one stroke.
SPEAKER_1:  and she'd be sitting in a gathering and she'd be pretty.
SPEAKER_1:  quiet with a big smile on her face, very serene.
SPEAKER_1:  And she would tell me, you know, which means thank God, all praise be to God that.
SPEAKER_1:  I can't hear because
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  I can tell when people are gossiping, when people are saying negative things around me about other people, because she says even the look on people's faces changes. So it was really interesting because she was that spiritually.
SPEAKER_1:  rooted and...
SPEAKER_1:  deep that she said like you could see.
SPEAKER_1:  on the looks on people's faces when they started to speak ill about other people that their faces would change, that their demeanor would change. He said, I would actually praise the Lord.
SPEAKER_1:  that I couldn't engage in those conversations and that I wasn't sinful for hearing them.
SPEAKER_1:  And what she would do is what people said.
SPEAKER_1:  at her funeral.
SPEAKER_1:  which was really beautiful to me. It was very comforting to me. And I took it as a life mission.
SPEAKER_1:  that if you were new to a place or if you were kind of in the corner and not.
SPEAKER_1:  not known to other people in the community and you felt left out. She was the one that literally would look around the room.
SPEAKER_1:  and she'd see who was standing in the corner.
SPEAKER_1:  and who was new to the community or new to whatever place. And she'd go and try to include that person in the gathering. So even when she had impaired speech and impaired hearing.
SPEAKER_1:  With her smile and with her warmth, she was able to welcome people.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... wherever that was and so the amount of people that came
SPEAKER_1:  to her funeral and the stories that I continue to hear till this day, 15 years later, after it passing away.
SPEAKER_1:  of people that said, you know, no one ever treated me the way your mother treated me.
SPEAKER_1:  And she connected that to God.
SPEAKER_1:  So that was actually part of my faith journey when I think of great people.
SPEAKER_1:  when I think of people of faith.
SPEAKER_1:  She's the first person that comes to my mind because
SPEAKER_1:  despite her challenges.
SPEAKER_1:  She was always.
SPEAKER_1:  the greatest person that you would meet, anyone that met her.
SPEAKER_1:  And that knew her would say, I'd never, I've never met anyone that kind. That was her reputation.
SPEAKER_1:  and she was deeply empathetic.
SPEAKER_1:  would shed tears over people that she had no connection to. This is again before social media, before-
SPEAKER_1:  you know, the, the, the heavy exposure that we have to people in conflict zones.
SPEAKER_1:  She had to engage every single human being in her life.
SPEAKER_1:  in a deep and profound way because she had a profound connection to God and she believed that that was her calling.
SPEAKER_1:  and none of her challenges made her bitter. In fact,
SPEAKER_1:  They only made her more connected to God.
SPEAKER_1:  and they only made her a better person.
SPEAKER_1:  until the last breath that she took.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you miss her?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, yes.
SPEAKER_1:  Absolutely. But I.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like everything I do is an extension of her.
SPEAKER_0:  So you try to carry.
SPEAKER_0:  what she stood for.
SPEAKER_0:  Absolutely. As part of yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  The Prophet Muhammad peace be upon him said that when a person passes away...
SPEAKER_1:  There are only three things.
SPEAKER_1:  that continue to benefit them, that continue to extend them.
SPEAKER_1:  a continuous charity.
SPEAKER_1:  or
SPEAKER_1:  A
SPEAKER_1:  piece of knowledge that continues to benefit people.
SPEAKER_1:  or a righteous child that prays for them.
SPEAKER_1:  And I want to be that child that prays for her, but also does charity in her name, extends her charity, extends what she taught me.
SPEAKER_1:  by being the person that she was.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... to everyone around me and there's some times where i
SPEAKER_1:  Don't feel like getting out of bed sometimes where I don't feel like.
SPEAKER_1:  doing for myself, but I actually feel like doing for her.
SPEAKER_1:  So everything in my life that I try to do.
SPEAKER_1:  I try to make it an extension of her.
SPEAKER_1:  And
SPEAKER_1:  That's been...
SPEAKER_1:  My calling.
SPEAKER_1:  And, you know, I believe I'll.
SPEAKER_1:  Meet her again.
SPEAKER_1:  I believe I'll be with her again.
SPEAKER_1:  I believe.
SPEAKER_1:  that everything I do that is good.
SPEAKER_1:  will be of benefit to her.
SPEAKER_1:  and I believe that it would make her proud.
SPEAKER_1:  And so as much as I miss her.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  as much as I am.
SPEAKER_1:  fueled to do for her.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I continue that and that's kind of become part of my life. It's been my life story.
SPEAKER_1:  as a child and as an adult, it's been sort of the centerpiece of my life.
SPEAKER_1:  to do.
SPEAKER_1:  things that
SPEAKER_1:  Extend Her.
SPEAKER_1:  And ultimately in the process, hopefully benefit me because I, I believe that she's.
SPEAKER_1:  A woman who...
SPEAKER_1:  I pray as Dustin for paradise and I want to do the things that would get me there too.
SPEAKER_1:  What did you learn about...
SPEAKER_0:  death.
SPEAKER_0:  About life.
SPEAKER_0:  from.
SPEAKER_0:  losing her.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like the facade of...
SPEAKER_1:  the material world.
SPEAKER_1:  was made evident to me at a very young age. You know, most children grow up.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for watching.
SPEAKER_1:  Their parents want to protect them from everything.
SPEAKER_1:  And I felt that too, you know, my mother wanted to downplay her own tragedy so that me and my brother could live a fruitful and fulfilling life. My father wanted to protect us.
SPEAKER_1:  from.
SPEAKER_1:  the hardship of her life.
SPEAKER_1:  so that we could live fulfilling lives. He was, he'd often be the only.
SPEAKER_1:  father on a field trip, even though he was a distinguished professor. I mean, he was a busy man.
SPEAKER_1:  He, he was a very busy man, but he tried to show up at a field trip and
SPEAKER_1:  try to make our lives as normal as possible.
SPEAKER_1:  In the process, we always understood that there was more to life than...
SPEAKER_1:  what other children were seeing it as. And now I know that as an adult, there's more to life than what other adults see it as, the material world.
SPEAKER_1:  disappointed early on so that we could see beyond it. And I often tell people that.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  There are many that grow up in tragedy, orphan children.
SPEAKER_1:  com.
SPEAKER_1:  refugees.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  grow up and do incredible things because they immediately see past.
SPEAKER_1:  The...
SPEAKER_1:  facade.
SPEAKER_1:  They see through.
SPEAKER_1:  all of the material promises of this world, the deception of it.
SPEAKER_1:  And that.
SPEAKER_1:  you can choose to be bitter.
SPEAKER_1:  as a result of that.
SPEAKER_1:  or you can choose.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  be better.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  I think that for me, I had to consciously make that decision that I was going to live a life.
SPEAKER_1:  of prayer. I was going to live a life of charity. I was going to live a life of commitment.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  in that process.
SPEAKER_1:  Invest in something that's greater.
SPEAKER_1:  Invest in something that doesn't disappoint.
SPEAKER_1:  and so I believe in God.
SPEAKER_1:  I believe in the hereafter.
SPEAKER_1:  and I believe that God will not let any trial.
SPEAKER_1:  or effort.
SPEAKER_1:  in this life go to waste without it being repaid in the hereafter. And so I work towards that. And so life and death.
SPEAKER_1:  I understood existence to be transcendent.
SPEAKER_1:  early on.
SPEAKER_1:  that if I believed that.
SPEAKER_1:  there was nothing to life except for life, I would be a very bitter person, but because-
SPEAKER_1:  I know that there is more to it than this.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm able to.
SPEAKER_1:  exist in it.
SPEAKER_1:  without being.
SPEAKER_1:  depressed by it.
SPEAKER_0:  Existence is transcendence.
SPEAKER_0:  What happens after we die?
SPEAKER_0:  after.
SPEAKER_0:  the
SPEAKER_0:  material instantiation.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... fades away.
SPEAKER_1:  So the Quran tells us.
SPEAKER_1:  that God brought us from the
SPEAKER_1:  darkness of the womb.
SPEAKER_1:  into this life.
SPEAKER_1:  You were nothing but a dirty drop of fluid and you became this fully.
SPEAKER_1:  proportioned human being from the darkness of the womb you come into this life.
SPEAKER_1:  You experience it.
SPEAKER_1:  And then you go to the darkness of the grave only to be resurrected once again.
SPEAKER_1:  and that.
SPEAKER_1:  We are.
SPEAKER_1:  souls.
SPEAKER_1:  with bodies.
SPEAKER_1:  not bodies with souls. And there's a huge difference between those two things.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the vehicle that contains us here.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the...
SPEAKER_1:  material world.
SPEAKER_1:  that we encounter here.
SPEAKER_1:  but we are not this.
SPEAKER_1:  and this is not our entire existence. And so the soul continues. This is a life in which...
SPEAKER_1:  We...
SPEAKER_1:  seek to worship Him?
SPEAKER_1:  and seek to live.
SPEAKER_1:  in accordance with the purpose that He has set out for us.
SPEAKER_1:  and after we pass away our soul
SPEAKER_1:  continues.
SPEAKER_1:  onwards.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  either to reward or to
SPEAKER_1:  punishment.
SPEAKER_1:  or to a mixture of both.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's a realm of accountability.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Hopefully it's a realm of reward.
SPEAKER_1:  Should we?
SPEAKER_1:  exist in a way that he wants us to exist.
SPEAKER_1:  So you said that you...
SPEAKER_0:  We can look to God for wisdom to make sense of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a lot of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  us humans.
SPEAKER_0:  that's difficult to make sense of.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  like you losing your mother.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a lot of cruelty in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a lot of suffering in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  What?
SPEAKER_0:  wisdom.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Have you been able to find?
SPEAKER_0:  from God about why there is suffering in the world, why there is cruelty.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there's a saying that I wanted to ask God about why he allows hunger and war.
SPEAKER_1:  and poverty.
SPEAKER_1:  but I was afraid he might ask me the same question.
SPEAKER_1:  God has certainly given us enough food. There is enough food in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  for everyone to have a 3200 calorie diet a day.
SPEAKER_1:  God has certainly given us enough guidance.
SPEAKER_1:  for us to not inflict on each other.
SPEAKER_1:  the cruelty that we inflict.
SPEAKER_1:  When we look to the world around us, first and foremost, we have to have a sense of accountability. We are accountable for our own actions. We don't blame God.
SPEAKER_1:  for the evil of man.
SPEAKER_1:  That's one.
SPEAKER_1:  But at the same time, we understand that God and His wisdom...
SPEAKER_1:  allows
SPEAKER_1:  for certain outcomes that we cannot encompass with our own.
SPEAKER_1:  and that...
SPEAKER_1:  to isolate these incidents.
SPEAKER_1:  and to try to make sense of them.
SPEAKER_1:  is no different than...
SPEAKER_1:  A baby in the womb.
SPEAKER_1:  that doesn't understand the world that it's coming into and trying to explain to that baby that hasn't yet developed its own senses and its own perception of this world.
SPEAKER_1:  what is happening to it.
SPEAKER_1:  I often think of the example of a child.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, having.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  been at this point now through the experience of.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm still learning. I'm just going into...
SPEAKER_1:  having a teenager with three kids.
SPEAKER_1:  and being a softie for my kids, you know, when you have to tell your child.
SPEAKER_1:  that they can't have something.
SPEAKER_1:  that they really, really want.
SPEAKER_1:  and that child.
SPEAKER_1:  you hate them at some point, you know, because...
SPEAKER_1:  Why are you stopping me from?
SPEAKER_1:  pudding.
SPEAKER_1:  this toy in my mouth.
SPEAKER_1:  and choking myself.
SPEAKER_1:  They don't get it, right? But at the same time.
SPEAKER_1:  you prevent them out of love.
SPEAKER_1:  They're not in a position to understand that you're preventing them out of love.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  to isolate these incidents with God and to say the wisdom.
SPEAKER_1:  what's the wisdom? You're trying to make sense of a pixel when you can't see the bigger picture.
SPEAKER_1:  Your mind is nuts.
SPEAKER_1:  at a place where you can make sense of the bigger picture. You haven't seen the bigger picture.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  for him to even explain to us every incident.
SPEAKER_1:  would completely defeat the purpose.
SPEAKER_1:  of putting your trust in him.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  We believe in a God.
SPEAKER_1:  that is all-encompassing in his knowledge and wisdom.
SPEAKER_1:  that gives us, and Islam is very specific by the way that there is what God...
SPEAKER_1:  tells us to do and there's what God allows to happen.
SPEAKER_1:  So what God tells us to do in terms of the roadmap towards good, and then what God allows to happen in His divine wisdom that no outcome can escape.
SPEAKER_1:  Him.
SPEAKER_1:  but at the same time we are accountable for our own actions and our own deeds.
SPEAKER_1:  So when you.
SPEAKER_1:  come to someone and say, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Why did God allow this to happen to this person?
SPEAKER_1:  I can't rationalize that.
SPEAKER_1:  for you because.
SPEAKER_1:  My understanding is relegated.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  the immediate experience in front of me.
SPEAKER_1:  If I know God.
SPEAKER_1:  and if I learn about God.
SPEAKER_1:  then.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't have to make sense of the plan.
SPEAKER_1:  but I can tell you that I trust the planner.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think that that's where peace is found.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, a lot of times you look for the light at the end of the tunnel. What's the light at the end of the tunnel?
SPEAKER_1:  In Islam, there's emphasis on God and the hereafter.
SPEAKER_1:  because to try to make...
SPEAKER_1:  sense of.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  Divine Decree and
SPEAKER_1:  why certain things happen in this world.
SPEAKER_1:  without the existence of a God or without the existence of a hereafter.
SPEAKER_1:  will always fail you.
SPEAKER_1:  So the existence of a God.
SPEAKER_1:  that is all knowing what we don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  I know what you don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  that understands what we don't understand.
SPEAKER_1:  the existence of a God who is not.
SPEAKER_1:  subject to our constrictions.
SPEAKER_1:  And...
SPEAKER_1:  the existence of a hereafter.
SPEAKER_1:  where...
SPEAKER_1:  All things find recourse.
SPEAKER_1:  where there is divine recourse.
SPEAKER_1:  allows for this world to be situated within the existence of something greater and not treated in isolation.
SPEAKER_1:  So when you're trying to treat.
SPEAKER_1:  an incident of this world in isolation.
SPEAKER_1:  you're going to fail. And when you try to treat existence in this world and of this world in isolation, you're also going to fail. And so the emphasis is the belief in God.
SPEAKER_1:  A God that is not limited.
SPEAKER_1:  like you are.
SPEAKER_1:  and a belief in the hereafter.
SPEAKER_1:  that is not limited like this life.
SPEAKER_1:  And so everything continues onwards.
SPEAKER_1:  and there's divine recourse for everything.
SPEAKER_1:  Each and everything, you know, the Prophet Muhammad, peace and blessings be upon him, mentions that.
SPEAKER_1:  on the day of judgment, a person who lived the most difficult of lives.
SPEAKER_1:  will be dipped into paradise one time.
SPEAKER_1:  and will be told, have you ever seen any sadness, any hardship? Now when you think about the most difficult,
SPEAKER_1:  life.
SPEAKER_1:  Some of the commentators in Islam, they said that...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, this is perhaps referring to the Prophet Job.
SPEAKER_1:  Ayub. Peace be upon him.
SPEAKER_1:  because Job lived obviously a life of great difficulty.
SPEAKER_1:  but that a person who lived a very hard life would be dipped into paradise one time.
SPEAKER_1:  And just with a dip.
SPEAKER_1:  be asked, have you ever seen any hardship?
SPEAKER_1:  Have you ever seen any misery?
SPEAKER_1:  And that person would say, what is sadness? What is hardship? What is misery? Now, if you don't believe in-
SPEAKER_1:  Hereafter, if you don't believe in-
SPEAKER_1:  anything beyond this life, then
SPEAKER_1:  The recourse has to happen in this life. And because we see so many people pass through this life.
SPEAKER_1:  without recourse.
SPEAKER_1:  of cruelty without recourse.
SPEAKER_1:  of suffering.
SPEAKER_1:  Then we're forced to try to make sense of it. And if you are someone who believes that this entire world came into existence,
SPEAKER_1:  through.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, randomness that were just an existence of.
SPEAKER_1:  random atoms that...
SPEAKER_1:  collide with each other and that all of this comes together out of nothing.
SPEAKER_1:  then how can you put your trust in anything that is greater?
SPEAKER_1:  So as a.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you asked me as a child of a parent who suffered.
SPEAKER_1:  I believe that.
SPEAKER_1:  every moment.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  My mother.
SPEAKER_1:  suffered.
SPEAKER_1:  that she will be rewarded.
SPEAKER_1:  that she will be elevated, that all of that...
SPEAKER_1:  made her or contributed to the beautiful person that she was.
SPEAKER_1:  and will contribute to the beautiful.
SPEAKER_1:  reward that she receives and the
SPEAKER_1:  recourse.
SPEAKER_1:  is certain to me as a believer in that.
SPEAKER_1:  to the right approach.
SPEAKER_0:  to making sense of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  especially making sense of suffering and cruelty is that of humility.
SPEAKER_0:  that we as humans
SPEAKER_0:  cannot possibly understand.
SPEAKER_0:  fully.
SPEAKER_1:  Absolutely. In fact, in the Quran, it's very interesting when God creates Adam.
SPEAKER_1:  the angels say to God.
SPEAKER_1:  Are you going to create?
SPEAKER_1:  a race or a species.
SPEAKER_1:  that will spill blood.
SPEAKER_1:  and cause corruption?
SPEAKER_1:  And God says to the angels in response to that question.
SPEAKER_1:  I know that which you don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  So even the angels have to humble themselves for a moment. The angels who adore God, who love God, who...
SPEAKER_1:  Worship Him Who...
SPEAKER_1:  obey Him unconditionally.
SPEAKER_1:  They are told.
SPEAKER_1:  By God, I know that which you don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  What we extract from that, what many of the early interpretations extract from that is that
SPEAKER_1:  God knows that there are human beings.
SPEAKER_1:  that will come out of this enterprise.
SPEAKER_1:  of humanity.
SPEAKER_1:  that make the entire existence of it worth it.
SPEAKER_1:  And so just as yes, there will be.
SPEAKER_1:  criminals and corrupt ones.
SPEAKER_1:  There will be profits and
SPEAKER_1:  beautiful people that come out of this and sages and saints that come out of this.
SPEAKER_1:  show.
SPEAKER_1:  dot
SPEAKER_1:  a human being.
SPEAKER_1:  who unlike an angel who has no choice but to worship God, an angel has no sense of will, no sense of choice, an angel.
SPEAKER_1:  is created to worship.
SPEAKER_1:  and has no desires, a human being who has the choice.
SPEAKER_1:  of desire.
SPEAKER_1:  and worship, the choice of righteousness and wickedness, that there are human beings who will choose worship and righteousness.
SPEAKER_1:  that will choose charity over cruelty.
SPEAKER_1:  that will choose.
SPEAKER_1:  service and choose dedication and devotion.
SPEAKER_1:  over death and destruction.
SPEAKER_1:  there are human beings that will in fact ascend the angels in rank.
SPEAKER_1:  because they will live lives where they...
SPEAKER_1:  choose that capacity, that part of themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  And they lean into that.
SPEAKER_1:  and worship God lovingly.
SPEAKER_1:  and obey him.
SPEAKER_1:  You see, some of the sages and Islam scholars, they describe this as saying that the human being has the capacity.
SPEAKER_1:  to be anywhere from.
SPEAKER_1:  an animal.
SPEAKER_1:  to an angel.
SPEAKER_1:  or even worse, to be a devil.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, to an angel.
SPEAKER_1:  not in the sense that we ever actually become angels or become animals, but...
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  an animal.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  for the most part.
SPEAKER_1:  seeks.
SPEAKER_1:  its desires over everything, doesn't really think about.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, many of the things that we are supposed to calculate as human beings doesn't think about.
SPEAKER_1:  which territory it's infringing upon.
SPEAKER_1:  or how much of its appetite it should fulfill. It simply exists to fulfill its appetite and that many human beings simply exist to fulfill their appetite. And they choose that over worship or reason or anything that is greater.
SPEAKER_1:  They literally take their selves as gods in that sense.
SPEAKER_1:  cells have no limitation on appetite. So they just keep filling that appetite and filling that appetite and filling that appetite whereas
SPEAKER_1:  A human being can also go to the extent.
SPEAKER_1:  of choosing something greater.
SPEAKER_1:  and disciplining their desires, disciplining themselves because they're seeking a greater reward.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, we know many people that are to you great things.
SPEAKER_1:  in the worldly sense.
SPEAKER_1:  because they choose to study over sleep, for example.
SPEAKER_1:  they choose to exert themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  towards their careers, towards their education.
SPEAKER_1:  because they believe that ultimately the outcome of those pursuits are more rewarding.
SPEAKER_1:  than the immediate fulfillment of their desires.
SPEAKER_1:  So as believers, we choose...
SPEAKER_1:  that love of God and we choose that outcome.
SPEAKER_1:  that we seek.
SPEAKER_1:  And we discipline ourselves to where we can even ascend past the angels in rank. Now, of course.
SPEAKER_1:  said we can go as low as an animal or as low as a devil.
SPEAKER_1:  And we have tyrants.
SPEAKER_1:  past and present and future as well.
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  can become satanic.
SPEAKER_1:  and their nature.
SPEAKER_1:  because they allow their desires to take such control over them.
SPEAKER_1:  that they not only worship them, but that every other...
SPEAKER_1:  existing being around them.
SPEAKER_1:  simply becomes.
SPEAKER_1:  A piece.
SPEAKER_1:  of their own puzzle in pursuit of their own lordship and their own satisfaction. They will kill. Thank you.
SPEAKER_1:  Discard.
SPEAKER_1:  Not because, you know, and I always say this, it's not that tyrants.
SPEAKER_1:  necessarily like.
SPEAKER_1:  killing people, it's that.
SPEAKER_1:  people's lives.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, pose.
SPEAKER_1:  somewhat of an indifference to them. They're indifferent to people's existence. And so you become.
SPEAKER_1:  either an object for
SPEAKER_1:  or against me. And so.
SPEAKER_1:  they're willing to discard.
SPEAKER_1:  children discard people.
SPEAKER_1:  discard the rights of others.
SPEAKER_1:  because they ultimately have chosen.
SPEAKER_1:  that the greatest pursuit of themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  is the maximum position of power.
SPEAKER_1:  and a place to where they can fulfill what they want to.
SPEAKER_1:  of themselves without any limits and everyone else becomes.
SPEAKER_1:  either a threat or an opportunity in that regard.
SPEAKER_1:  So we can be devils, we can be angelic like, we could be animals.
SPEAKER_1:  We're somewhere on that spectrum.
SPEAKER_0:  And every moment contains a set of choices you can make.
SPEAKER_1:  Absolutely. Every single moment contains a set of choices.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's where the intentionality comes in.
SPEAKER_1:  All right, so.
SPEAKER_1:  the Prophet Muhammad.
SPEAKER_1:  As Peace Be Upon Him says that I saw a person strolling in paradise because he removed something harmful from the road.
SPEAKER_1:  He-
SPEAKER_1:  tells us about a woman that lived the life in prostitution, but that
SPEAKER_1:  Repented.
SPEAKER_1:  to God when she was thirsty one day.
SPEAKER_1:  and she saw a dog that was also thirsty.
SPEAKER_1:  And she said that I was thirsty and God gave me water. So I'm gonna choose to give water to that thirsty dog. And God enters her into paradise as a result of that.
SPEAKER_1:  sometimes the small moments.
SPEAKER_1:  with
SPEAKER_1:  A small sincere deed.
SPEAKER_1:  can have a huge impact on a person's trajectory.
SPEAKER_1:  So every moment is a moment of choices.
SPEAKER_1:  and.
SPEAKER_1:  when we choose.
SPEAKER_1:  belief righteousness.
SPEAKER_1:  a pursuit of something greater.
SPEAKER_1:  then
SPEAKER_1:  We find ways.
SPEAKER_1:  to turn things.
SPEAKER_1:  that are otherwise mundane.
SPEAKER_1:  and two.
SPEAKER_1:  miraculous acts, right? Where we can.
SPEAKER_1:  We can-
SPEAKER_1:  choose God over ourselves.
SPEAKER_1:  and in the process.
SPEAKER_1:  choose a better fate for ourselves.
SPEAKER_0:  How difficult is the process of?
SPEAKER_0:  knowing.
SPEAKER_0:  understanding what is the righteous action.
SPEAKER_0:  of uh...
SPEAKER_0:  knowing what it means to be a good man.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh good woman.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, the truth has consequences.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  Don't seek out the truth unless you're willing to.
SPEAKER_1:  Abide by what you find. So a lot of people want to mold.
SPEAKER_1:  their journey in accordance with.
SPEAKER_1:  a predetermined pursuit that they already have. And so when they approach religion, they approach it like...
SPEAKER_1:  another product, you know, there was a.
SPEAKER_1:  An article that was actually written by a rabbi, I've spoken about this in several sermons. It was called The Allure of Narcissistic Spirituality.
SPEAKER_1:  the allure of narcissistic spirituality where he talks about
SPEAKER_1:  you know how religion becomes just another product of your own.
SPEAKER_1:  self-adoration and worship.
SPEAKER_1:  to where you only approach religion.
SPEAKER_1:  the extants.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  It gives you...
SPEAKER_1:  more happiness in the worldly sense. You only approach of it what is therapeutic. So it becomes just.
SPEAKER_1:  as
SPEAKER_1:  secular.
SPEAKER_1:  in its nature as any other practice of meditation or whatever it may be or some other product.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of mentions, you know how.
SPEAKER_1:  He took that from a person that...
SPEAKER_1:  is praying in a temple.
SPEAKER_1:  ends.
SPEAKER_1:  A guy walks into the temple and bumps into him, and then he curses the guy out.
SPEAKER_1:  So he didn't see his.
SPEAKER_1:  behavior towards that person as...
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  part of his.
SPEAKER_1:  trajectory of worship. the
SPEAKER_1:  just saw his being godly.
SPEAKER_1:  as the worship that he was engaged in.
SPEAKER_1:  The truth has.
SPEAKER_1:  consequences, the truth.
SPEAKER_1:  has.
SPEAKER_1:  circumstances that are required of you, actions that are required of you that
SPEAKER_1:  may be somewhat inconvenient. So you have to be willing to engage in a sincere pursuit of truth and look for truth for what it is.
SPEAKER_1:  and not simply look for comfort and convenience.
SPEAKER_1:  And when you engage in that journey of
SPEAKER_1:  wanting to know.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to engage it thoroughly.
SPEAKER_1:  End.
SPEAKER_1:  sincerely and try your best to remove any bias. I think that's what makes the
SPEAKER_1:  the religion of Islam such a phenomenon for people.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  with all the Islamophobia and the bigotry towards it, still the fastest growing religion in the United States and the fastest growing religion in the world. No, that's not all birth rate.
SPEAKER_1:  You
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, we have a lot of kids.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Many people, you know, you met someone.
SPEAKER_1:  just before we started this interview, many people in fact in a post-9-11 world.
SPEAKER_1:  solve what they saw of Islam in the media.
SPEAKER_1:  and they actually...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, went and checked out copies of the Quran and started to read about the religion and their sincere pursuit of truth.
SPEAKER_1:  End it up.
SPEAKER_1:  embracing religion that they believed was the greatest source of destruction in the world and now it's the greatest source of peace for them.
SPEAKER_1:  in their own existence, in their own lives.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to be willing.
SPEAKER_1:  to engage in a sincere pursuit of
SPEAKER_1:  wanting to know?
SPEAKER_1:  and then be willing.
SPEAKER_1:  to engage in sincere commitment after you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Otherwise, the heart rusts. And so there's a process in the Quran talks about this of making the heart.
SPEAKER_1:  like fertile soil.
SPEAKER_1:  towards truth.
SPEAKER_1:  So you have a sincere pursuit, but then at some point, if you come to know, and then you ignore what you come to know,
SPEAKER_1:  then the heart rusts and it becomes harder to recognize it the second time around and the third time around. F
SPEAKER_1:  When people come to me and they say, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm looking for something. I'm looking for God. I'm looking for...
SPEAKER_1:  My purpose.
SPEAKER_1:  The first thing I tell them is I say, listen.
SPEAKER_1:  What you need to do is...
SPEAKER_1:  if you're really looking for God and you believe in God. And there are often people that say, I believe in God, but I don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  where to go with this. Right? In Islam we call that the Fitra.
SPEAKER_1:  a natural disposition towards.
SPEAKER_1:  the belief in the existence of God.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  But where do I go from here? You know, what do I do now? And I say, the first thing you need to do is
SPEAKER_1:  You need to sincerely.
SPEAKER_1:  Say, Oh God, guide me to the truth.
SPEAKER_1:  Call upon God sincerely, Sam, calling upon you alone, and I'm asking you to guide me to the truth.
SPEAKER_1:  Show me what it is.
SPEAKER_1:  All right.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  That's the heart function.
SPEAKER_1:  then you need to actually investigate and try to suspend bias.
SPEAKER_1:  right? Investigate the world religions, investigate.
SPEAKER_1:  the claims to truth.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... investigate
SPEAKER_1:  uh, use, you know, rational inquiry to the extent that.
SPEAKER_1:  the heart becomes satisfied.
SPEAKER_1:  End.
SPEAKER_1:  Suspend bias.
SPEAKER_1:  and you'll be surprised.
SPEAKER_1:  And so for a lot of people.
SPEAKER_1:  They come to me and they say, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  this about Islam, I'm like, look, I'm...
SPEAKER_1:  If you're just going to talk to me about what you've seen of Islam in the media, if you were serious about it.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, if you're serious about it, then.
SPEAKER_1:  You're not simply
SPEAKER_1:  going to be satisfied.
SPEAKER_1:  with.
SPEAKER_1:  The.
SPEAKER_1:  highly edited images and distorted facts that come towards you.
SPEAKER_1:  about this.
SPEAKER_1:  Religion.
SPEAKER_1:  What are you looking for? Right? Are you looking for a scapegoat?
SPEAKER_1:  Islam poses a threat to many people. Right? Are you looking for a scapegoat? Are you looking for the big, bad, scary foreign enemy?
SPEAKER_1:  or are you looking at?
SPEAKER_1:  a religion that one fourth of the world adheres to.
SPEAKER_1:  and if one fourth of us were bad.
SPEAKER_1:  the world would not exist.
SPEAKER_1:  Right, so are you looking towards this religion that one fourth of the world adheres to? Are you going to read about the Prophet Muhammad peace be upon him? Are you going to read the Quran yourself? Are you going to...
SPEAKER_1:  Investigate for yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  what it is that this faith has to offer and find in it.
SPEAKER_1:  a great sense of.
SPEAKER_1:  of wisdom, a great sense of beauty, a great sense of truth.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think that for a lot of people.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, they find that Islam has such a beautiful combination of
SPEAKER_1:  the intellectual proofs as well as the spiritual experiences that.
SPEAKER_1:  often combine?
SPEAKER_1:  what people seek in the Western and the Eastern religion. So I had an interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  two weeks.
SPEAKER_1:  Two weeks in a row.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, this was August, two weeks in a row. I had someone who converted to Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  that went from being
SPEAKER_1:  that started off as a Methodist.
SPEAKER_1:  went from being a Methodist to being a Buddhist to being a Muslim.
SPEAKER_1:  So two weeks in a row I had a Methodist turned Buddhist turned Muslim.
SPEAKER_1:  Great journey. Yeah, I called my Methodist friends. I have a lot of-
SPEAKER_1:  Methodist pastors in the city that I work with. And I said, what's going on here, man, you sending people onto this interesting journey of Buddhism and then Islam?
SPEAKER_1:  But both of them had a very similar story, which is that they had sought in Buddhism, for example, the...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, some of the meditative practices that are found.
SPEAKER_1:  that really Western religion, which has been dominated by.
SPEAKER_1:  capitalism and
SPEAKER_1:  dominated by very material things.
SPEAKER_1:  can be very unfulfilling. They found that in some of the Eastern philosophies and the meditative practices and then they came to Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  and it combines their belief in sort of the Abrahamic way.
SPEAKER_1:  It emerged.
SPEAKER_1:  their belief in one God and
SPEAKER_1:  profits.
SPEAKER_1:  like Abraham and Moses and Jesus, peace be upon them all, with.
SPEAKER_1:  a deep tradition.
SPEAKER_1:  of meditative practices, of consciousness, of connection to God on a regular basis, and they found that to be very fulfilling.
SPEAKER_1:  both intellectually.
SPEAKER_1:  and spiritually.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I was like, that's interesting, you know, two people in two weeks that went through that journey. So I think Islam is very wholesome.
SPEAKER_1:  comprehensive when people actually approach it.
SPEAKER_1:  with
SPEAKER_1:  humility.
SPEAKER_1:  And uh...
SPEAKER_1:  and appreciate what it has to offer.
SPEAKER_0:  As you mentioned,
SPEAKER_0:  In the minds of some Americans, after 9-11, the religion of Islam was associated with
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe you could say evil in the world. Maybe you can say.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, terrorism.
SPEAKER_0:  How can you respond to this association?
SPEAKER_0:  How does it make you feel, first of all, as a devout Muslim yourself?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  How can you overcome it?
SPEAKER_0:  Personally, how can you overcome it as a community and as a religious leader?
SPEAKER_1:  It's interesting because 9 11 now.
SPEAKER_1:  We're talking over 21 years ago.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there's people born.
SPEAKER_0:  after 9-11. It's crazy.
SPEAKER_1:  them all the time.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so when I'm talking to young Muslims, I'm talking about post-9-11, post-9-11, they're like, I didn't-
SPEAKER_1:  I was born in 2005. What are you talking about post 9-11? I'm like, well, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  I remember being a teenager. I remember being in high school and this happened. Right. A lot of us.
SPEAKER_1:  that experienced 9-11 as high schoolers or as college students and remember distinctly what it was like to be a Muslim.
SPEAKER_1:  pre-911 and post-911.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... we can relate to that experience and we could we could identify
SPEAKER_1:  That juncture.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, very clearly.
SPEAKER_1:  and talk about it and speak to the change in the perceptions of Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  that happen here in the United States and around the world.
SPEAKER_1:  but a lot of.
SPEAKER_1:  young people are born into that reality and are experiencing.
SPEAKER_1:  the aftermath.
SPEAKER_1:  of it.
SPEAKER_1:  And, um,
SPEAKER_1:  You don't unfortunately have to deal with the bigotry that has.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Not just...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, taken.
SPEAKER_1:  greater shape in.
SPEAKER_1:  Media Constructions of Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  but also policies, right? a lot of the civil liberties of the muslim community
SPEAKER_1:  uh... we're taking away from us you read about the patriot act to read about the securitization
SPEAKER_1:  of the Muslim community.
SPEAKER_1:  and some of the unfair practices that have been engaged by the Bush administration, the Obama administration, the Trump administration.
SPEAKER_1:  and continue into the Biden administration.
SPEAKER_1:  international Islamophobia.
SPEAKER_1:  the hatred of Muslims and the bigotry.
SPEAKER_1:  That is...
SPEAKER_1:  wielded against.
SPEAKER_1:  Muslims on the basis of this idea that we are.
SPEAKER_1:  are barbaric people.
SPEAKER_1:  ascribed to a religion of hate and violence.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  has had immediate.
SPEAKER_1:  consequences for us no matter where we are in terms of our age.
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of our experience. We have dealt with that in different ways. Now,
SPEAKER_1:  The Association of Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  terrorism.
SPEAKER_1:  is a lazy association.
SPEAKER_1:  It's one that ignores.
SPEAKER_1:  both.
SPEAKER_1:  The history of violence.
SPEAKER_1:  as well as its everyday occurrence.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, we're good for how many mass shootings a year.
SPEAKER_1:  When's the last time you heard of a Muslim carrying out a mass shooting in America?
SPEAKER_1:  Alright, how many of those mass shootings?
SPEAKER_1:  if you were to scrub the social media, what 400, 500 mass shootings a year,
SPEAKER_1:  were to scrub the social media of some of those that carried out those shootings.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, we're good for one or two idiots a year, right?
SPEAKER_1:  unfortunate that you're going to have people that.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... that carry out despicable acts of violence
SPEAKER_1:  But.
SPEAKER_1:  when we as Muslims hear someone in the media say
SPEAKER_1:  Terrorism has been ruled out as a possibility.
SPEAKER_1:  while the blood is still on the floor of that Walmart?
SPEAKER_1:  We already know that.
SPEAKER_1:  The police chief just said that that wasn't a Muslim.
SPEAKER_1:  Don't worry.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, that wasn't all, sorry, the guy or an ISIS guy.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  It was one of our own.
SPEAKER_1:  Right. And so it's, it's become
SPEAKER_1:  frankly ridiculous.
SPEAKER_1:  Because...
SPEAKER_1:  the association of violence with Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  is one that is used.
SPEAKER_1:  to actually
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  Carry out acts of violence against Muslims worldwide. It justifies bad policy towards Muslims worldwide.
SPEAKER_1:  and then in the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's just factually so lazy.
SPEAKER_1:  There was a study just about how the media gives more attention to acts of violence done by Muslims.
SPEAKER_1:  and immediately.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... stamps it with the slam
SPEAKER_1:  up to 300% more than it will.
SPEAKER_1:  with another act of violence carried out in the name of anything else. So.
SPEAKER_1:  you don't hear about the acts of violence that are carried out by others.
SPEAKER_1:  You don't hear about the religion of the perpetrators.
SPEAKER_1:  You don't associate terrorism with actions, frankly, of state terrorism.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, when
SPEAKER_1:  Governments.
SPEAKER_1:  Launch.
SPEAKER_1:  chemical attacks or drone weddings.
SPEAKER_1:  and do so while explicitly dehumanizing the people.
SPEAKER_1:  just because they do so.
SPEAKER_1:  with the government apparatus doesn't make it any less.
SPEAKER_1:  terroristic.
SPEAKER_1:  than if it's a lone person that goes out and commits an act of violence trying to achieve a political goal.
SPEAKER_1:  So the association is lazy, historically speaking.
SPEAKER_1:  crusades. I grew up in Louisiana. I saw clan rallies, Ku Klux Klan rallies my whole life. People said, well, that's a thing of the past. Well, guess what? We see.
SPEAKER_1:  many some ones as many acts.
SPEAKER_1: .
SPEAKER_1:  are carried out with the same.
SPEAKER_1:  vitriol that was generated by the Ku Klux Klan.
SPEAKER_1:  We have people standing in front of our mosques.
SPEAKER_1:  that belong to right-wing hate militias carrying...
SPEAKER_1:  AR-15s talking about wanting to inflict harm on Muslims.
SPEAKER_1:  I have been.
SPEAKER_1:  to Christchurch, New Zealand.
SPEAKER_1:  and buried the victims.
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  a white supremacist terrorist who was inspired by
SPEAKER_1:  the political rhetoric here in the United States, in his own words, in his manifesto, to go and kill.
SPEAKER_1:  50 innocent people.
SPEAKER_1:  and Christchurch in Zealand, one of the most peaceful cities in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  And by the way, Lex, I mean, it's really interesting, like with Christchurch.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  the man wanted and I won't even say his name.
SPEAKER_1:  But his next target after the two mosques, had he not been stopped, was to go to a Muslim daycare.
SPEAKER_1:  So what drives someone?
SPEAKER_1:  to dehumanize people.
SPEAKER_1:  to that extent that he was willing to go to a daycare and murder a bunch of kids because he saw them.
SPEAKER_1:  as a demographic threat to civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  so Muslims are terrorized.
SPEAKER_1:  because.
SPEAKER_1:  They are falsely.
SPEAKER_1:  depicted as terrorists.
SPEAKER_1:  Muslims suffer.
SPEAKER_1:  domestically and globally because of this false association. It's a lazy association.
SPEAKER_1:  And when someone comes around and says, well...
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Fine, not all Muslims are terrorists, but all terrorists are Muslims. I say that.
SPEAKER_1:  you clearly don't read statistics.
SPEAKER_1:  whether we're talking about.
SPEAKER_1:  the
SPEAKER_1:  20th century.
SPEAKER_1:  and I'm a student of history and I believe you are as well.
SPEAKER_1:  all the isms.
SPEAKER_1:  World War I, World War II had nothing to do with religion, certainly had nothing to do with Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  fascism.
SPEAKER_1:  Soviet atheism, right? Many of these systems where people were murdered.
SPEAKER_1:  in the millions, Nazism.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, the Holocaust, Rwanda, Cambodia, I can go on and on.
SPEAKER_1:  the Rohingya today.
SPEAKER_1:  the greatest atrocity towards the Uyghurs.
SPEAKER_1:  Where is Islam fit in all of this?
SPEAKER_1:  People do horrible things.
SPEAKER_1:  they stamp it with religion at times.
SPEAKER_1:  but the only group of people that seem to suffer.
SPEAKER_1:  after an act of violence is committed.
SPEAKER_1:  are Muslims because any act of violence that is committed by a Muslim will immediately
SPEAKER_1:  Be blamed on Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  billion people will have to carry the burden.
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  the act of a single perpetrator.
SPEAKER_0:  End.
SPEAKER_0:  Just to reiterate.
SPEAKER_0:  In case the numbers are not known, you mentioned Christchurch.
SPEAKER_0:  Those are two mask shootings.
SPEAKER_0:  51 people killed and 48 were injured in New Zealand
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's uh...
SPEAKER_0:  It's hate manifesting itself in.
SPEAKER_0:  And then uh...
SPEAKER_0:  actual human suffering and destruction.
SPEAKER_0:  Absolutely.
SPEAKER_0:  Is there similarities between?
SPEAKER_0:  anti-Semitism and anti-Muslim hate.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Is there a-
SPEAKER_0:  Something deeper to say about hate in general here.
SPEAKER_0:  that is beyond just.
SPEAKER_0:  particularly hate towards Muslims.
SPEAKER_1:  Absolutely. Look, um,
SPEAKER_1:  in Pittsburgh.
SPEAKER_1:  the synagogue shooting, the perpetrator particularly target.
SPEAKER_1:  targeted that.
SPEAKER_1:  synagogue because tree of life
SPEAKER_0:  synagogue tree of life synagogue 11 killed 6 wounded in 2018
SPEAKER_1:  because
SPEAKER_1:  He believed that they were.
SPEAKER_1:  taking in Syrian refugees or supporting Syrian Muslim refugees.
SPEAKER_1:  You think about that.
SPEAKER_1:  The San Diego.
SPEAKER_1:  synagogue shooting that took place shortly after.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... he went to a mosque and then he went to a synagogue
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Look, the idea of.
SPEAKER_1:  scapegoating minority populations.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  attributing to them.
SPEAKER_1:  a disproportionate sense of power and a nefarious element where they can't be trusted.
SPEAKER_1:  and unless we wipe them out.
SPEAKER_1:  then they're going to wipe us out.
SPEAKER_1:  underlies many of the bigotries that exist. I mean, look, um...
SPEAKER_1:  after Trump announced his Muslim ban.
SPEAKER_1:  There was a shooting in Canada.
SPEAKER_1:  an attack in Canada on a mosque in Quebec.
SPEAKER_1:  or six people were killed.
SPEAKER_1:  the shooter explicitly said that.
SPEAKER_1:  the reason why he went to that mosque in Quebec.
SPEAKER_1:  and shot dead six Muslim worshipers was because he was afraid that because of the ban.
SPEAKER_1:  on Syrian refugees in the United States, they would come to Canada. And he didn't want them to feel welcomed in Canada.
SPEAKER_1:  So there is a connection.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think it's when you are able to dehumanize large groups of people.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  A tribute.
SPEAKER_1:  a nefarious element to them.
SPEAKER_1:  than unfortunately in a world that's becoming more and more polarized where people
SPEAKER_1:  are able to construct their entire world views.
SPEAKER_1:  based on an algorithm.
SPEAKER_1:  that their social media.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, caters to.
SPEAKER_1:  you're going to have...
SPEAKER_1:  some of these.
SPEAKER_1:  Attacks happen.
SPEAKER_1:  and there's going to be an unfortunate connection between them.
SPEAKER_1:  So what I, what I tell people is that, you know, I think with all of these people that shoot up synagogues and shoot up mosques and even before that actually the
SPEAKER_1:  Charleston.
SPEAKER_1:  South Carolina.
SPEAKER_1:  I was shooting at an AME church.
SPEAKER_1:  You know?
SPEAKER_1:  when he went there.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, he actually said that before he murdered.
SPEAKER_1:  nine worshipers in that church.
SPEAKER_1:  He was taken aback by how nice they were to him. He sat there for two hours before he turned a gun on.
SPEAKER_1:  many people who are over the age of 80 years old.
SPEAKER_1:  and murdered them in cold blood.
SPEAKER_1:  So this is what I talk about when I say that as human beings, we have the propensity, unfortunately.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  to become worse than devils or we can choose.
SPEAKER_1:  to be angelic.
SPEAKER_1:  when we choose worship and righteousness.
SPEAKER_1:  over ourselves.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's a spiritual crisis as well.
SPEAKER_1:  and a crisis of meaning and emptiness.
SPEAKER_1:  where I think.
SPEAKER_1:  People are willing to inflict great pain on others when they can't make sense of their pain in their own lives.
SPEAKER_0:  I'd like to try to figure out together with you sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  A way out.
SPEAKER_0:  to try to.
SPEAKER_0:  decrease the amount of hate in the world, but...
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe it's useful to talk about the BBC documentary.
SPEAKER_0:  that uh...
SPEAKER_0:  It's kind of interesting that people should check out. It's called United States of Hate, Muslims Under Attack.
SPEAKER_0:  and you appear in that, you have conversations with people who are.
SPEAKER_0:  anti-muslim.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's, I believe most of it takes.
SPEAKER_0:  place here in Dallas.
SPEAKER_0:  And can you just tell me about this little documentary about that time, what it was like to interact?
SPEAKER_0:  What was the group in the documentary and what was it like to interact with them?
SPEAKER_1:  you know in the very beginning of uh...
SPEAKER_1:  The Rise.
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  At that time actually, Ted Cruz, Donald Trump, like when Islamophobia...
SPEAKER_1:  uh, was at the center of many of the presidential candidates campaigns at the time. So this must've been 2015. Yes,
SPEAKER_1:  2015.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  the mayor of Irving at the time, Beth Van Dyne, who is now a congresswoman.
SPEAKER_1:  had
SPEAKER_1:  put out the idea.
SPEAKER_1:  that Muslims were operating a Sharia court.
SPEAKER_1:  in Irving, Texas.
SPEAKER_1:  and suddenly there was hysteria.
SPEAKER_1:  Because again, there's the idea that Muslims are here to dominate, Muslims are here to overthrow.
SPEAKER_1:  everything.
SPEAKER_1:  that you have.
SPEAKER_1:  in the United States. There was hysteria here.
SPEAKER_1:  And it was unfortunate because, um,
SPEAKER_1:  what it unleashed.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, especially with the national discourse at the time, again, the presidential campaign, you know, Donald Trump says, I think Islam hates us.
SPEAKER_1:  When he uses those words, I think Islam hates us.
SPEAKER_1:  when Ted Cruz suggests that Muslim neighborhoods could be patrolled or should be patrolled.
SPEAKER_1:  and then you have the Irving Mayer.
SPEAKER_1:  saying that.
SPEAKER_1:  one of the most populated cities with Muslims in America.
SPEAKER_1:  they're operating under an alternative.
SPEAKER_1:  legal and alternate legal system.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Funny enough, the year before that she'd come to the mosque and she praised the diversity of Irving.
SPEAKER_1:  she was talking about how welcome she felt in the mosque and the next thing we know.
SPEAKER_1:  You have these crazy white supremacist groups, openly white supremacists that affiliate themselves with...
SPEAKER_1:  The Clan and others.
SPEAKER_1:  protesting regularly in front of our mosques with their AR-15s.
SPEAKER_1:  end
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  telling people to go back home and I'm like.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm from New Orleans. I'm not planning to move back to New Orleans. I'm home. We're, we're, we're home. We're good. You know, we're, we're staying put.
SPEAKER_1:  and we refuse to be intimidated.
SPEAKER_1:  But then when the Syrian refugee crisis is unfolding as well.
SPEAKER_1:  Dallas has
SPEAKER_1:  bin.
SPEAKER_1:  one of the more popular destinations, if you will. I'm not talking about it like a vacation destination, but where a lot of refugees have come to just because of the infrastructure that we have set up here.
SPEAKER_1:  to receive refugees.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that hysteria.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... was
SPEAKER_1:  an unfortunate.
SPEAKER_1:  perfect combustion.
SPEAKER_1:  of the national discourse with the local discourse with the incoming.
SPEAKER_1:  refugees.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  We would do all sorts of welcome refugee events.
SPEAKER_1:  And we do that.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, and we don't.
SPEAKER_1:  only do that for Muslim refugees by the way. There are refugees from other parts of the world as well.
SPEAKER_1:  But we would host events at our mosques, you know, to welcome refugees, to help integrate them into the community, to...
SPEAKER_1:  do things for them. So you have these armed protests happening, right?
SPEAKER_1:  horrible because...
SPEAKER_1:  Think about the trauma to the children.
SPEAKER_1:  that are hearing about Tree of Life and hearing about some of these other incidents that are unfolding. And really one of the first communities that was targeted was the Sikh community in Madison.
SPEAKER_1:  That was one of the first shootings and then the AME Church Charleston.
SPEAKER_1:  and then you just had.
SPEAKER_1:  tons of places of worship being targeted, right? So they're seeing this unfold and they're seeing these guns in front of their mosques and-
SPEAKER_1:  the result.
SPEAKER_1:  many as well. I just don't want to get shot. I don't want to go to the mosque. I don't want to have this happen to me.
SPEAKER_1:  So when BBC reached out and said, we want to do a documentary about this.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  Unfortunately, Dallas was the only place in America where you had regular.
SPEAKER_1:  armed groups in front of our mosques. So it was happening around the country infrequently, but here it was happening.
SPEAKER_1:  every week.
SPEAKER_1:  So the BBC reached out and said, we want to interview you.
SPEAKER_1:  I said, we've got this idea. We want to put you, we want to take you to a park.
SPEAKER_1:  and have you meet one of the protesters.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, who's been wielding his gun.
SPEAKER_1:  outside your mosque.
SPEAKER_1:  and talk to him.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  It was really interesting because they'd interviewed him before meeting me.
SPEAKER_1:  and the things that he was able to utter.
SPEAKER_1:  before meeting me and before meeting Syrian refugees.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  Was just awful.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, the most dehumanizing rhetoric that you can imagine.
SPEAKER_1:  but then at the park.
SPEAKER_1:  He meets me.
SPEAKER_1:  talks to me.
SPEAKER_1:  he meets a Syrian refugee family.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, one of the girls whose leg
SPEAKER_1:  had been blown off in an airstrike.
SPEAKER_1:  And he said, I feel like an idiot.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, he expressed all sorts of regret.
SPEAKER_1:  and was teary eyed.
SPEAKER_1:  that he could.
SPEAKER_1:  dehumanize people the way that he was. And so my whole thing was.
SPEAKER_1:  and is.
SPEAKER_1:  Come inside the mosque, put your gun down.
SPEAKER_1:  disarm yourself and learn.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  you'll be surprised what you'll walk away with.
SPEAKER_1:  and only took one meeting with Him.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  so completely.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah, shift.
SPEAKER_1:  his worldview at the time.
SPEAKER_1:  which
SPEAKER_1:  was made up of heroes and villains, the Muslims unfortunately being the villains that had to be wiped off the face of the earth so that the earth could continue.
SPEAKER_1:  So that was a...
SPEAKER_1:  That was an interesting documentary and it was an interesting social experiment.
SPEAKER_0:  What's it feel like to have...
SPEAKER_0:  all these.
SPEAKER_0:  people that hate you.
SPEAKER_0:  and others in the community, people you love.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  with guns.
SPEAKER_0:  threatening violence.
SPEAKER_0:  basically that we don't want you here.
SPEAKER_0:  in this country on this
SPEAKER_1:  Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  It's not nice.
SPEAKER_1:  That's not great. I mean, it's um...
SPEAKER_1:  Definitely a challenge, but...
SPEAKER_1:  Look, there are...
SPEAKER_1:  challenges that we face as Muslims.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, being in the United States, being in a hostile climate, there are different types of challenges and, uh,
SPEAKER_1:  I think what we've had to do as a Muslim community.
SPEAKER_1:  is see beyond both the guns and the roses.
SPEAKER_1:  end
SPEAKER_1:  Think about who we are first.
SPEAKER_1:  because frankly...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Islamophobia exists in different forms and from different sides.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  We try to use this as an opportunity to instill an hour.
SPEAKER_1:  Young people.
SPEAKER_1:  not just a sense of belonging, but a sense of purpose.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh.
SPEAKER_1:  Do not be intimidated.
SPEAKER_1:  and in fact show them.
SPEAKER_1:  the best of your Islam, live your life. Because at the end of the day,
SPEAKER_1:  the goal that is sought.
SPEAKER_1:  through intimidation is silence.
SPEAKER_1:  And so we have to carry ourselves as.
SPEAKER_1:  proud American Muslims. We don't have to impress anyone.
SPEAKER_1:  and we don't need to relinquish an iota of our faith.
SPEAKER_1:  to coexist with anyone.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  We are.
SPEAKER_1:  Satisfied.
SPEAKER_1:  with who we are.
SPEAKER_1:  We don't see.
SPEAKER_1:  contradiction.
SPEAKER_1:  between.
SPEAKER_1:  our place.
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  residence and our religion.
SPEAKER_1:  our nationality, our religion, we don't see that as a problem. Right. So that's a
SPEAKER_1:  That's something for them to work out, not for you to work out.
SPEAKER_1:  That's what I would tell young Muslims that continue to live your faith fully.
SPEAKER_1:  and demonstrate the beauty of it.
SPEAKER_1:  and do not let the ugliness of the world consume you.
SPEAKER_0:  But for those young Muslims.
SPEAKER_0:  What would you say?
SPEAKER_0:  how they should feel towards the people that hate them.
SPEAKER_0:  The natural human.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a desire still to have anger, to have...
SPEAKER_0:  or is that meant to have hate back?
SPEAKER_0:  people that hate you.
SPEAKER_1:  the Quran says respond to that which is evil with that which is better.
SPEAKER_1:  and you will find...
SPEAKER_1:  Nah.
SPEAKER_1:  Sometimes your enemy will become.
SPEAKER_1:  your close friend.
SPEAKER_1:  So respond with that which is better.
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't mean
SPEAKER_1:  Be passive.
SPEAKER_1:  sometimes.
SPEAKER_1:  there needs to be a demonstration of strength.
SPEAKER_1:  Sometimes there needs to be a demonstration.
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  ignoring.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... people altogether
SPEAKER_1:  But ultimately you can't let the way people treat you shape who you're going to be in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that's why I say we have to look beyond the guns and the roses. We have to look beyond.
SPEAKER_1:  the hostility of our enemies.
SPEAKER_1:  and the
SPEAKER_1:  Temporary.
SPEAKER_1:  an opportunistic embrace of some of those who claim to be our allies.
SPEAKER_1:  and be us.
SPEAKER_1:  and treat the world and treat the people of this world in accordance with your standards.
SPEAKER_1:  not with theirs.
SPEAKER_1:  So don't teach them.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, or don't let them teach you bad character, you teach them good character.
SPEAKER_1:  So live your life and live your faith.
SPEAKER_1:  beautifully.
SPEAKER_1:  and let people see the beauty of it through your.
SPEAKER_1:  through your bink.
SPEAKER_1:  and do not let their ugliness
SPEAKER_1:  consume you.
SPEAKER_1:  but at the same time.
SPEAKER_1:  Sometimes you've got to give people room to express frustration.
SPEAKER_1:  to say that.
SPEAKER_1:  This is unacceptable.
SPEAKER_1:  to have demonstrations of strength.
SPEAKER_1:  and...
SPEAKER_1:  I think that those things don't have to all contradict each other.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think about...
SPEAKER_0:  These kinds of protests are not allowed in many parts of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think about?
SPEAKER_0:  one of the most to you directly personally painful manifestations of the first amendment
SPEAKER_0:  of the people's right to freedom of speech and to protest.
SPEAKER_0:  to say hateful things.
SPEAKER_0:  You've been at the receiving end.
SPEAKER_0:  of the worst of it.
SPEAKER_0:  What, what, what, what do you feel about this particular freedom?
SPEAKER_0:  that's at the core of the founding of this country.
SPEAKER_1:  Look, I think that you have to take it away from the.
SPEAKER_1:  text and look at it within reality. Let's be real. Would Muslims be able to protest in front of churches with guns on a weekly basis in this country? I don't think so.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's a tip.
SPEAKER_0:  Pragmatically speaking, there's a hypocrisy too.
SPEAKER_1:  What's a lot of not?
SPEAKER_1:  Major hypocrisy. Free speech.
SPEAKER_1:  is an ideal that is weaponized.
SPEAKER_1:  against.
SPEAKER_1:  the Muslim community and against other communities.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  in such a hypocritical way. You know, you take, for example, some countries in Europe.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's kind of move away from this.
SPEAKER_1:  look at the hypocrisy of.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  place like France where
SPEAKER_1:  the caricaturing and the portrayal of the Prophet Muhammad peace be upon him in derogatory ways.
SPEAKER_1:  will be used as the hallmark of free speech.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  Muslims that.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, caricature.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah, Macron.
SPEAKER_1:  Arrrr
SPEAKER_1:  Challenge.
SPEAKER_1:  some of the values of France, the supposed and trying values of France.
SPEAKER_1:  will end up in prison and end up deported.
SPEAKER_1:  And so here in the United States, there's a great hypocrisy. I don't think that-
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  places of worship should have armed protesters in front of them. I think that that poses a security risk. I think that it's.
SPEAKER_1:  Not okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think that.
SPEAKER_1:  speech is weaponized against the Muslim community.
SPEAKER_1:  and often.
SPEAKER_1:  is held up as this great value.
SPEAKER_1:  but really to attain.
SPEAKER_1:  very lowly things.
SPEAKER_1:  and is often to our detriment.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, just even watching that documentary.
SPEAKER_0:  It's hard to put into words, but somehow that...
SPEAKER_0:  does not capture.
SPEAKER_0:  what maybe the founders intended.
SPEAKER_0:  What I would see is the great ideal of the freedom of speech.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know what the solution to that is.
SPEAKER_0:  I think taking it outside of words.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  that requires a community a cultural pressure.
SPEAKER_0:  to be better.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  It's not about the law, it's more about just the culture of pressure. What is and isn't okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Is there something deeply wrong about that kind of hate?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, because it was dehumanizing other...
SPEAKER_0:  people that are here in America.
SPEAKER_1:  that they're Americans.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean, it's, it's, we have to interrogate.
SPEAKER_1:  the foundations.
SPEAKER_1:  of our country when our country is in such turmoil.
SPEAKER_1:  and such chaos.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  no country in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  has the mass shootings that we have.
SPEAKER_1:  No country in the world has.
SPEAKER_1:  some of the polarization that we have, we have to interrogate that and say.
SPEAKER_1:  what it is that we're doing wrong that's leading to that.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think again that...
SPEAKER_1:  it's reaching a point where it's unsustainable.
SPEAKER_1:  if we don't do better.
SPEAKER_1:  and try to solve.
SPEAKER_1:  some of the rifts right now.
SPEAKER_1:  that exists in our society.
SPEAKER_1:  then we're going to end up in...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, in a place where.
SPEAKER_1:  We may not be able to climb out of this.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think about?
SPEAKER_0:  You mentioned the Muslim ban. What do you think about executive order 13769?
SPEAKER_0:  titled Protecting the Nation from Foreign Terrorist Entry into the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  Often referred to as the Muslim ban or the Trump travel ban, it was
SPEAKER_0:  and executive order.
SPEAKER_0:  by President Trump that was in effect from January 27th, 2017.
SPEAKER_0:  for just a few months until March 6th, 2017.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  What was this executive order and what was it?
SPEAKER_0:  effect on your life and on
SPEAKER_0:  the life of the Muslim community and
SPEAKER_0:  It's just the life of Americans.
SPEAKER_1:  It was...
SPEAKER_1:  disgraceful it was a
SPEAKER_1:  tactic that was used.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, at the time.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  very similar to the whole build the wall rhetoric.
SPEAKER_1:  um... to to play to a particular political
SPEAKER_1:  sloganeering and
SPEAKER_1:  carrying out those types of acts against the Muslim community.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, you're not going to face.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  much opposition typically in any meaningful way that would be politically costly.
SPEAKER_1:  when he rolled it out.
SPEAKER_1:  at the time.
SPEAKER_1:  there were people in flight.
SPEAKER_1:  on their way to the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  that were held in airports around the country.
SPEAKER_1:  um... children.
SPEAKER_1:  elderly people.
SPEAKER_1:  that were held in these small rooms.
SPEAKER_1:  End.
SPEAKER_1:  treated.
SPEAKER_1:  Awfully before being put back on a plane and sent to where they were. There were families that.
SPEAKER_1:  had medical needs that were never able to.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... come together he
SPEAKER_1:  specifically targeted.
SPEAKER_1:  Muslim countries.
SPEAKER_1:  to play to that idea of a complete ban of Muslims, which he knew was not feasible.
SPEAKER_1:  at the time.
SPEAKER_1:  Now.
SPEAKER_1:  Personally, you know Dallas had the
SPEAKER_1:  the largest amount, the largest number.
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  detainees.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... in the airport
SPEAKER_1:  We have one of the largest airports in America and.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... we took to the airport
SPEAKER_1:  and we stayed there for a few days.
SPEAKER_1:  It was one of the New York Times pictures of the year when we did our prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  because when we had to do our prayer, it wasn't just Muslims that came to the airport.
SPEAKER_1:  It was many people that came to the airport of different faiths.
SPEAKER_1:  were outraged by what they had seen.
SPEAKER_1:  So when we do our prayer, there was a protest chant that, you pray we stay.
SPEAKER_1:  And so the airport had to.
SPEAKER_1:  Make room for us because...
SPEAKER_1:  like a thousand people that need to have our five daily prayers.
SPEAKER_1:  So we would do our prayers in the airport. We waited. We continued.
SPEAKER_1:  until the detainees were.
SPEAKER_1:  Freed.
SPEAKER_1:  At least temporarily.
SPEAKER_1:  Unfortunately, some elements of that legislation remained and it was an ongoing...
SPEAKER_1:  struggle.
SPEAKER_1:  Look, what I'll say is that-
SPEAKER_1:  Those are some of the more obvious manifestations of...
SPEAKER_1:  anti-Muslim bigotry.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  Again.
SPEAKER_1:  There's hypocrisy on all sides of the political aisle here in the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  There is Islamophobia of different flavors. I think even the term Islamophobia can become contentious because there are people that
SPEAKER_1:  attack us in different ways and that might not be as overtly bigoted, but.
SPEAKER_1:  nonetheless are infringing on our rights.
SPEAKER_1:  B.
SPEAKER_1:  full American Muslims.
SPEAKER_1:  and Muslims find themselves in a very strange political place.
SPEAKER_1:  Where?
SPEAKER_1:  You've got one side.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  seemingly wants to annihilate you.
SPEAKER_1:  and another side that only accepts you.
SPEAKER_1:  if you're willing to assimilate.
SPEAKER_1:  but no one really allows you to be a full on American Muslim. So Muslims find themselves in a very strange place right now.
SPEAKER_1:  with
SPEAKER_1:  all of the political sides with the political parties.
SPEAKER_0:  Where do Muslims sit politically?
SPEAKER_0:  Are they politically engaged?
SPEAKER_0:  in the functioning United States where they find themselves politically as a community.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  Muslims find themselves in an awkward place politically.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the best way to put it.
SPEAKER_1:  We.
SPEAKER_1:  our religious community.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  we don't find ourselves welcomed.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... by the left which has a hostility towards religion
SPEAKER_1:  And most left spaces and most liberal spaces.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know because it's...
SPEAKER_0:  of religion has many conservative elements.
SPEAKER_1:  Right. So the Muslim community is in its nature conservative for what that's worth. Right. It's a conservative community.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a community that has certain orthodoxies and practices.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  wood.
SPEAKER_1:  make it disagreeable in its nature and its practice to many on the left.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Many on the right just see us as a group of foreigners.
SPEAKER_1:  and a threat in that regard.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  We find ourselves in this awkward place. There's also the-
SPEAKER_1:  presence of sort of the pro-Israel.
SPEAKER_1:  dominance of both parties, the foreign policy of both parties is detrimental to Muslims globally
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  the securitization of the Muslim community.
SPEAKER_1:  in the name of countering violent extremism. Unfortunately, the Muslim community has had both Republican and Democratic administrations run over its rights.
SPEAKER_1:  So we find ourselves kind of in this awkward space, right? We are a religious community that's also-
SPEAKER_1:  minority.
SPEAKER_1:  the racialization of the Muslim community.
SPEAKER_1:  sort of robs us of who we are.
SPEAKER_1:  and how we get to engage them with different platforms and different peoples.
SPEAKER_1:  around us.
SPEAKER_1:  we find ourselves in a very awkward place. Is there in general...
SPEAKER_0:  a lack.
SPEAKER_0:  of representation.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  places of power.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't think representation is everything. I think that representation can actually be detrimental sometimes because you can have people that.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, represent you.
SPEAKER_1:  but that don't actually represent your.
SPEAKER_1:  your priorities as a community, as a faith community. So we don't want to be tokenized as a community.
SPEAKER_1:  We want to be engaged and engage.
SPEAKER_1:  fully as Muslims.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  be respected as American Muslims. I wrote something at the time actually of Muslim ban.
SPEAKER_1:  I wrote an article for CNN called, I am not your American Muslim.
SPEAKER_1:  I am not your American Muslim.
SPEAKER_1:  Because we are not a tool.
SPEAKER_1:  of liberals against conservatives.
SPEAKER_1:  nor are we simply to be made out to be.
SPEAKER_1:  your villain or your victim.
SPEAKER_1:  where...
SPEAKER_1:  people of faith.
SPEAKER_1:  were people that...
SPEAKER_1:  have values where people that want to see our places of worship thrive?
SPEAKER_1:  where people that have something to offer.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  to this country, to the people around us of good.
SPEAKER_1:  but ultimately we want to engage.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  be engaged with on the basis of who we actually are, not who you need us to be right now.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's been the problem.
SPEAKER_1:  that we've had, so it's not a lack of representation.
SPEAKER_1:  as much as a lack of authentic engagement.
SPEAKER_1:  You mentioned...
SPEAKER_0:  Daily Prayer.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  If I may, looking at the time, this might be time.
SPEAKER_0:  If it's okay, I would love it if you allow me to.
SPEAKER_0:  follow along at least in movement as you pray.
SPEAKER_0:  Absolutely.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you for allowing me to join you.
SPEAKER_0:  in that.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't-
SPEAKER_0:  Can you maybe describe?
SPEAKER_0:  What?
SPEAKER_0:  What does the prayer represent? What is the actual practice of prayer like? What is the process like?
SPEAKER_1:  Sure, so.
SPEAKER_1:  Prayer is the...
SPEAKER_1:  central pillar if you will of Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  It is.
SPEAKER_1:  The life of the believer.
SPEAKER_1:  encapsulated.
SPEAKER_1:  in
SPEAKER_1:  to a very specific act.
SPEAKER_1:  of devotion that's done.
SPEAKER_1:  at least five times a day.
SPEAKER_1:  So there are different types of prayer. There's prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  There's supplication.
SPEAKER_1:  So the five daily prayers are called Salah.
SPEAKER_1:  as the obligatory prayers.
SPEAKER_1:  And then beyond that, there are voluntary prayers.
SPEAKER_1:  that are done.
SPEAKER_1:  throughout the day as well.
SPEAKER_1:  So you can pray before and after.
SPEAKER_1:  obligatory prayers and then there are other times of the day that you can pray also. And the best prayer, voluntary prayer, is at night, in the middle of the night, because the time that you're closest to God.
SPEAKER_1:  sincere.
SPEAKER_1:  away from the eyes of people.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  just in the still of the night and you'd pray in a similar way with the standing and the bowing the prostration reciting the Quran
SPEAKER_1:  And then you have supplication and words of remembrance that you are to do throughout the day.
SPEAKER_1:  between all of them. So when people say, do you pray five times a day? I say at least five times a day.
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_0:  What are the words of this application? Do they come from the Quran or do they come from your own heart? Where do they come from?
SPEAKER_1:  So basically you say Allahu Akbar.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... which means i'm going to kill you right
SPEAKER_1:  Or so they say, right?
SPEAKER_1:  God is greater.
SPEAKER_1:  You start off with that expression of God's greatness, and then you recite the opening chapter of the Quran.
SPEAKER_1:  which is known as Al-Fatiha. It's the first chapter of the Qur'an.
SPEAKER_1:  In the name of God, the most compassionate, the most merciful. All praises be to God, the Lord of all the worlds, most compassionate, most merciful, Master of the Day of Judgment.
SPEAKER_1:  You alone we worship and from you alone we seek help.
SPEAKER_1:  Guide us to the straight path, the path of those who have earned your favor.
SPEAKER_1:  not those who have earned your wrath nor those who have gone astray.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's a translation of the first.
SPEAKER_1:  chapter, the opening chapter of the Quran.
SPEAKER_1:  which is known as At-Fatiha. So we recite that in every one of the units of prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  And then after that, we recite something else from the Quran.
SPEAKER_1:  So some other portion of the Quran, and then we say Allahu Akbar.
SPEAKER_1:  Once again.
SPEAKER_1:  God is greater. God as greater than other beings Christ.
SPEAKER_1:  bowing.
SPEAKER_1:  And in bowing we say, Subhanarabbiyaalazim, Subhanarabbiyaalazim, Subhanarabbiyaalazim, which means,
SPEAKER_1:  Glory be to God.
SPEAKER_1:  The Almighty. Glory be to God, The Almighty.
SPEAKER_1:  Glory be to God the Almighty. And then you come back up.
SPEAKER_1:  and you say...
SPEAKER_1:  God has heard the one who has praised him.
SPEAKER_1:  And then...
SPEAKER_1:  The response is, رَبَّنَا وَلَكَ الْحَمْتِ, unto you, O Lord, belongs all praise.
SPEAKER_1:  and then we go into prostration.
SPEAKER_1:  and prostration is at the heart of the prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  It is the most beautiful.
SPEAKER_1:  portion of the prayer and it is.
SPEAKER_1:  the most beloved position.
SPEAKER_1:  for a servant of God and that which is most pleasing to God.
SPEAKER_1:  It's when you
SPEAKER_1:  say at that point.
SPEAKER_1:  Subhanah Rabbia Al-A'la
SPEAKER_1:  All glory be to God the Most High.
SPEAKER_1:  All glory be to God the most high. So while you put yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  in the lowest position.
SPEAKER_1:  You acknowledge.
SPEAKER_1:  God being the Most High and the Prophet peace and blessings be upon him said that the closest that a person is to God.
SPEAKER_1:  is when they are in prostration.
SPEAKER_1:  That is the time that your supplications are most precious and beloved.
SPEAKER_1:  That is the time that you can.
SPEAKER_1:  Cry your heart out. That is the time that you really feel a sense of great closeness.
SPEAKER_1:  and devotion to God. And as I was telling you earlier,
SPEAKER_1:  the time that your, your mind is under your heart for a change, right? the only position, physical position.
SPEAKER_1:  that your mind is actually under your heart.
SPEAKER_1:  And you really have a chance to pour your emotions out.
SPEAKER_1:  and to connect deeply to God.
SPEAKER_1:  It's the prayer of all of the prophets. Jesus, peace be upon Him, as described.
SPEAKER_1:  even biblically as falling on his face in prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  And so it really is, I think, the most intimate moment that you get with God.
SPEAKER_1:  End.
SPEAKER_1:  the deepest part of the prayer. the word Masjid.
SPEAKER_1:  which is mosque in Arabic means place of sujood, place of prostration.
SPEAKER_1:  So think of the rest of prayer as an introduction to.
SPEAKER_1:  that particular part of the prayer where you really.
SPEAKER_1:  Immerse yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  not that you shouldn't be immersed in your prayer throughout.
SPEAKER_1:  but when you're in seduce, when you're in prostration.
SPEAKER_1:  That's where you're really closest and most connected to God. So we do that.
SPEAKER_1:  And so some prayers.
SPEAKER_1:  are
SPEAKER_1:  two units.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, the first prayer of the day.
SPEAKER_1:  which is before sunrise, the earliest prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  is two units.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  The second prayer, which is around noon.
SPEAKER_1:  is four units.
SPEAKER_1:  And then afternoon, another four units.
SPEAKER_1:  And then the sunset prayer is three units. And then the evening prayer is four units.
SPEAKER_1:  So each prayer has a different number of units to it.
SPEAKER_1:  and some voluntary prayers that surround it.
SPEAKER_1:  when you come back up.
SPEAKER_1:  You express also a form of greeting towards God.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  channeling your prayers.
SPEAKER_1:  and your blessings towards God.
SPEAKER_1:  You reiterate the Shahadah, which is the first pillar of Islam. I testify that there is only one God.
SPEAKER_1:  and that Muhammad is his servant and messenger.
SPEAKER_1:  And then you read what's called Salah Ibrahimiyah, which is the Abrahamic prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  So you send peace and blessings upon Muhammad and his family and Abraham and his family.
SPEAKER_1:  Abraham, peace be upon him, is really at the core of this religion.
SPEAKER_1:  At the end of the prayer, you...
SPEAKER_1:  You son.
SPEAKER_1:  Peace and blessings and prayers upon, again, both Muhammad and his family and Abraham and his family.
SPEAKER_1:  And then you have another chance to make some of your own personal prayers.
SPEAKER_1:  And then you say, Assalamu alaikum warahmatullah.
SPEAKER_1:  Peace be on to you in the mercy of God.
SPEAKER_1:  to your right.
SPEAKER_1:  Peace be unto you and the mercy.
SPEAKER_1:  of God.
SPEAKER_1:  your left and that means everything and everyone to your right.
SPEAKER_1:  everyone and everything to your left. So you imagine a congregation.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, when you're in worship, right, you're, you're sending that to.
SPEAKER_1:  the angels and the human beings next to you, your fellow worshippers next to you.
SPEAKER_1:  And you'll even say you'll seek forgiveness from God afterwards. There are supplications that surround the prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  And you will say Allahumma anta assalam wa minkasalam.
SPEAKER_1:  that O Allah, O God, you are peace and from you is peace.
SPEAKER_1:  and to you belongs all glory.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  All praise.
SPEAKER_1:  almost to say that you received something in this prayer, that you receive a great sense of inner peace and now you're spreading that. So as it
SPEAKER_1:  Really comes into you then.
SPEAKER_1:  you can give.
SPEAKER_1:  You can give to the world around you what you generate in your own heart.
SPEAKER_1:  And in prayer, you generate a great sense of tranquility, a great sense of peace.
SPEAKER_1:  The Quran says, verily in the remembrance of God do hearts find.
SPEAKER_1:  contentment.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  prayer is.
SPEAKER_1:  an exercise in the remembrance of God.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  That is again, obligatory five times a day.
SPEAKER_1:  no matter where you are.
SPEAKER_1:  So, anywhere in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Anywhere you find yourself in your life and in...
SPEAKER_0:  uh... different life circumstances anywhere
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. So outside coffee shop in the grass.
SPEAKER_1:  outside of the coffee shop.
SPEAKER_0:  as it did a few days ago. So anywhere at all, and that means.
SPEAKER_1:  airports included
SPEAKER_0:  given the context of our previous conversation of.
SPEAKER_0:  I hate your toe words.
SPEAKER_0:  people of Muslim faith.
SPEAKER_0:  That means...
SPEAKER_0:  uh... you probably through the practice of prayer
SPEAKER_0:  It attracts people.
SPEAKER_1:  I've attracted curiosity, I've attracted hate. I've had people walk up to me like, hey man, you okay? You know, in the airport. Everything.
SPEAKER_0:  So most probably these conversations of curiosity and opportunity to actually...
SPEAKER_0:  talk about the values.
SPEAKER_1:  And I try to make it a point to tell people.
SPEAKER_1:  If I'm about to pray in front of them. So like in an airport, let's say, for example, go to the corner.
SPEAKER_1:  next to a gate.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. And if there are people sitting there like, Hey, I'm about to
SPEAKER_1:  engaged in a prayer, I hope you don't mind. They'll really appreciate the courtesy most of the time.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  But no, I mean, when those five times come in they're kind of windows, right?
SPEAKER_1:  we have to pray.
SPEAKER_1:  and uh...
SPEAKER_1:  That means at work, that means at school, that means when you're traveling. Although there are some concessions that allow you to combine prayers at.
SPEAKER_1:  certain times when you're traveling, for example.
SPEAKER_1:  Even then, you're going to have to pray.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that
SPEAKER_1:  what that does.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  bring you back to God.
SPEAKER_1:  no matter what you're doing.
SPEAKER_1:  It's actually.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you think of it this way, you're in a meeting.
SPEAKER_1:  You're engaged in something.
SPEAKER_1:  You're really stressed out.
SPEAKER_1:  And you also have the ablution before the prayer where you wash up.
SPEAKER_1:  Wash your face, wash your limbs.
SPEAKER_1:  and engage in prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  what it does for you.
SPEAKER_1:  and anchoring you in...
SPEAKER_1:  something more meaningful.
SPEAKER_1:  when you are in the turmoil.
SPEAKER_1:  of a lot of times what's not so meaningful.
SPEAKER_1:  is incredible.
SPEAKER_1:  And so it's a gift from God.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  It is an obligation.
SPEAKER_1:  It's something that we have to do as Muslims.
SPEAKER_1:  but.
SPEAKER_1:  If you...
SPEAKER_1:  actually learn its essence then.
SPEAKER_1:  it can feel.
SPEAKER_1:  more like a joy than it is an obligation.
SPEAKER_1:  and then you're called to at night, especially again the night prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  as a big part of who we are as Muslims.
SPEAKER_1:  waking up in the last part of the night.
SPEAKER_1:  The Prophet Muhammad peace be upon him said that the
SPEAKER_1:  The best prayer and the best fasting was of that of David, peace be upon him. So we think of David.
SPEAKER_1:  David. He's a prophet in Islam as well. I'm sure you'll ask me about the whole concept of prophethood.
SPEAKER_1:  You're hearing Abraham and David and others, right? So David peace be upon him, he said that.
SPEAKER_1:  David used to fast every other day.
SPEAKER_1:  And he used to pray the last third of the night.
SPEAKER_1:  He'd stand up and pray in the last dirt of the night.
SPEAKER_1:  So, fasting.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... is a big part of who we are
SPEAKER_1:  and praying in the last third of the night.
SPEAKER_1:  Meaning before that early morning prayer, you know, waking up if you can at 4 a.m., 430 a.m., 5 a.m.
SPEAKER_1:  and praying even for a few minutes.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  there's something in the serenity of the night.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  can unlock anew.
SPEAKER_1:  a sense of inner joy and peace that nothing else in the world can give you.
SPEAKER_0:  And again, that pulls you away from all the turmoil of day-to-day life.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  If it's little things or if it's big things, just pause it.
SPEAKER_0:  pulls you out of it to remember what is.
SPEAKER_0:  more important than life.
SPEAKER_1:  So when we think about access.
SPEAKER_1:  In the last third of the night, we're taught that God says, is there anyone seeking forgiveness that I may forgive them?
SPEAKER_1:  Is there anyone seeking refuge that I may grant it to them?
SPEAKER_1:  Is there anyone asking for anything?
SPEAKER_1:  that I may give it to them.
SPEAKER_1:  So whatever you're calling upon him with at that time.
SPEAKER_1:  He's responding to you.
SPEAKER_1:  in a way that befits him.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  It's closeness as well.
SPEAKER_1:  And.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, you would think that you sleep less.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  You're probably.
SPEAKER_1:  More cranky, but...
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  The happiest people in the world are the people that.
SPEAKER_1:  stand up in that last third of the night and pray.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, there's a deeply meditative, contemplative.
SPEAKER_0:  aspect to it today.
SPEAKER_0:  I think...
SPEAKER_0:  Probably.
SPEAKER_0:  strengthens your sleep if anything else once you return to it.
SPEAKER_1:  There you go.
SPEAKER_1:  See, people underestimate that. There was a great sage in Islam. He was asked, he said, how come?
SPEAKER_1:  the people who pray at night.
SPEAKER_1:  are.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, the most beautiful of people and they're, they're, they're fresh in the day, it doesn't make sense. And he said, because they secluded themselves with the most merciful and he dressed them in his light.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a beauty that it generates.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's why we're to aspire to that really as believers, that's kind of your highest thing. Like don't just pray the five prayers. If you can pray at night, pray at night.
SPEAKER_1:  and connect at that time.
SPEAKER_0:  Good friend of mine, Andrew Huberman, who's a neuroscientist from Stanford. He has an amazing podcast called Huberman Lab.
SPEAKER_0:  but he's also a scholar of sleep.
SPEAKER_0:  Among many other things and so I would love him to he probably knows the science on this too
SPEAKER_0:  There's probably good science that actually studies...
SPEAKER_0:  practicing Muslims to see what
SPEAKER_0:  wuh uh
SPEAKER_0:  the benefits of sleep I would love to actually...
SPEAKER_1:  see what that says. We have amazing, I don't want to cut you off, we have amazing hygiene because of how much we have to wash up for prayer. That's true. And it's great for our limbs as well, right?
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, and that's one of the added benefits, right? It's good for us.
SPEAKER_1:  Worship that we do is not torturous. It's actually good for us.
SPEAKER_1:  However, the core objective of worship has to remain.
SPEAKER_1:  That it's.
SPEAKER_1:  something you do out of worship and something you do out of a sense of obligation and gratitude to God.
SPEAKER_1:  not because of those things. Like I'm not gonna fast because it's good for my health, but I know it's good for my health to fast.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's pretty cool when you walk into, I'll share this with you. There is a man.
SPEAKER_1:  He was a...
SPEAKER_1:  a scholar from Turkey, an Islamic scholar from Turkey. And he had visited us in Dallas and he was 108 years old.
SPEAKER_1:  and he could still pray.
SPEAKER_1:  bowing and prostrating.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, his limbs and you think about that, like someone at that age still being able to do that. So,
SPEAKER_1:  it's good for your limbs, good for your health, good for your gut, good for your sleep, good for your mind.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the mind one is the really one we've been talking about and that's really, really the big one.
SPEAKER_0:  and in the small day-to-day psychological sense and in the big philosophical sense what it means to be a human being.
SPEAKER_0:  I, we should also mention that.
SPEAKER_0:  and during the prayer.
SPEAKER_0:  as you've explained you.
SPEAKER_0:  should face Mecca.
SPEAKER_0:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  So what is Mecha and...
SPEAKER_0:  What's the experience of visiting Mecca like?
SPEAKER_1:  So, Mecca.
SPEAKER_1:  is
SPEAKER_1:  The Home
SPEAKER_1:  that Abraham, peace be upon him, built along with his son, Ishmael, peace be upon him.
SPEAKER_1:  and it gives the Muslims a unified direction of prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  It's
SPEAKER_1:  sort of at the center geographically.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh huh.
SPEAKER_1:  of who we are.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, and.
SPEAKER_1:  when we pray towards it.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not that.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not that-
SPEAKER_1:  that's the only place that you can supplicate, turn towards, but it gives us a unified sense of direction. It gives us a unified sense of prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  Mecca is...
SPEAKER_1:  our Qibla, it's our place of direction.
SPEAKER_1:  when we are alive and when we are dead. So actually we pray facing towards it. When we die we are also faced towards it in our graves.
SPEAKER_1:  And it kind of gives us that unifying spirit. So this is-
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  The Valley of Becca.
SPEAKER_1:  also in the Bible spoken about the Valley of Beqa.
SPEAKER_1:  and where other biblical scholars would also mention Mount Perrin.
SPEAKER_1:  and it is the place.
SPEAKER_1:  dot
SPEAKER_1:  Adam.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  In the Quran, Adam peace be upon him first had a place constructed there as a place of worship.
SPEAKER_1:  from the angels towards God and then...
SPEAKER_1:  when Abraham.
SPEAKER_1:  settles.
SPEAKER_1:  Hagar and Ishmael in Mecca.
SPEAKER_1:  they build this house of worship.
SPEAKER_1:  And that is where.
SPEAKER_1:  The Gushing Springs.
SPEAKER_1:  of Zem Zem are mentioned, where God sends an angel.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  Give a miracle to Hagar and Ishmael.
SPEAKER_1:  that they can sustain themselves from.
SPEAKER_1:  as they're not left in the desert. So Ishmael being the firstborn son of Abraham.
SPEAKER_1:  is
SPEAKER_1:  given a place.
SPEAKER_1:  and there's a story and a history that's going to unfold.
SPEAKER_1:  from that place of Mecca.
SPEAKER_1:  And then Isaac is born, peace be upon him, 13 years later.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's a story and a history that comes from that. But ultimately...
SPEAKER_1:  Mecca is...
SPEAKER_1:  the center, Mecca is where we turn towards.
SPEAKER_1:  for prayer, Mecca is where we perform the pilgrimage.
SPEAKER_1:  The Hatch Pilgrimage.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  once in our lives at least if we can.
SPEAKER_1:  physically and financially if we find ourselves capable, we at least perform the Hatch Pilgrimage.
SPEAKER_1:  once in our lifetimes.
SPEAKER_1:  but there are other.
SPEAKER_1:  pilgrimages throughout the year you can go.
SPEAKER_1:  at any time of the day.
SPEAKER_1:  Any time of the year, you will find people.
SPEAKER_1:  that will be performing the pilgrimage.
SPEAKER_1:  an iteration of the pilgrimage in Mecca.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's.
SPEAKER_1:  an incredible practice.
SPEAKER_1:  It really is a place where.
SPEAKER_1:  you feel like you're no longer in this world. I mean, it's, it's, it's, it's incredible. So we all go there, donning.
SPEAKER_1:  what's known as the Ihram garb.
SPEAKER_1:  so the man will wear.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  just these white.
SPEAKER_1:  Garments.
SPEAKER_1:  which are...
SPEAKER_1:  resembling or they resemble the garments that we will be buried in.
SPEAKER_1:  And whether you're a king or a
SPEAKER_1:  Prince R-
SPEAKER_1:  a peasant in, you know, in classical terms, whoever you are.
SPEAKER_1:  whatever distinction you have.
SPEAKER_1:  You're all the same and the women will wear it.
SPEAKER_1:  simple garment.
SPEAKER_1:  as well.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  You go there.
SPEAKER_1:  You relinquish.
SPEAKER_1:  all of the pretensions and...
SPEAKER_1:  concerns and superficial barriers and distinctions.
SPEAKER_1:  that exist in this life.
SPEAKER_1:  And we do what's called the WAF.
SPEAKER_1:  circle around.
SPEAKER_1:  the capa.
SPEAKER_1:  symbolically putting God at the center of our lives.
SPEAKER_1:  We are.
SPEAKER_1:  do seven rounds between Safa and Marwa, the two mountains where Hagar.
SPEAKER_1:  when she wants.
SPEAKER_1:  ran between those two mountains with her baby Ishmael.
SPEAKER_1:  looking for water, trusting God was provided for, we too.
SPEAKER_1:  go between the two mountains of Safa and Marwa.
SPEAKER_1:  to express that trust in God and to follow in that way.
SPEAKER_1:  And these are ultimately, these are the rituals that.
SPEAKER_1:  Abraham himself engaged in.
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  in our tradition and
SPEAKER_1:  Prophet Muhammad peace be upon him engaged in. And so we engage in the exact same rituals and there are divine wisdoms to them that
SPEAKER_1:  we might not even be able to.
SPEAKER_1:  unpack and reflect upon.
SPEAKER_1:  But it really is in that place where.
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  you find.
SPEAKER_1:  most beautiful global expression of Islam. You see people from all over the world.
SPEAKER_1:  People that don't speak the same languages, people from all sorts of backgrounds, and they're all doing the exact same thing.
SPEAKER_1:  and in a matter of seconds when the call of prayer comes.
SPEAKER_1:  in a matter of seconds.
SPEAKER_1:  two, three million people get arranged in perfect rows for prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  and it just, it looks like.
SPEAKER_1:  this perfect optical.
SPEAKER_1:  you know uh...
SPEAKER_1:  vision of just beauty.
SPEAKER_1:  when you see people.
SPEAKER_1:  in unison.
SPEAKER_1:  Standing, bowing, prostrating.
SPEAKER_1:  and you don't know who the person next to you is.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's where, you know, you, you know, Malcolm X, you read about the history of Malcolm X when he went to Hajj, that's where his entire worldview shifts.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  not just.
SPEAKER_1:  his previous.
SPEAKER_1:  baggage.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, but.
SPEAKER_1:  The dream.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  he then had the
SPEAKER_1:  possibilities that he saw.
SPEAKER_1:  for people to be able to overcome some of the false distinctions that we have.
SPEAKER_1:  race and class.
SPEAKER_1:  and to see.
SPEAKER_1:  God as one and to come together.
SPEAKER_1:  and worship Him alone and also seeing each other, equal participants in that worship.
SPEAKER_1:  If we could just linger it.
SPEAKER_0:  on it a little bit.
SPEAKER_0:  I think you've mentioned that Malcolm X...
SPEAKER_0:  has been in part misunderstood.
SPEAKER_0:  What are some aspects of him that are misunderstood?
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I think reading is autobiography is.
SPEAKER_1:  for anyone that wants to understand him, right? So you read him his own words.
SPEAKER_1:  Malcolm lived the tragedy.
SPEAKER_1:  of being.
SPEAKER_1:  a young, disenfranchised.
SPEAKER_1:  black man in America who went through
SPEAKER_1:  all of the difficulties that were posed.
SPEAKER_1:  in a 1950s America.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  towards him. I mean, he went through the system and it was...
SPEAKER_1:  awful for him and he had to pull himself out of that and make himself into
SPEAKER_1:  an incredible orator and incredible leader.
SPEAKER_1:  that suddenly had a pretty empowering vision and a calm and
SPEAKER_1:  And.
SPEAKER_1:  Nonetheless, courageous, but a calm presence to him.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, and was able to bring together people.
SPEAKER_1:  especially uplift black people in America to believe in themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  young
SPEAKER_1:  Young men in America and in prisons in particular will read the autobiography of Malcolm X and see hope for themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  to come out of.
SPEAKER_1:  The darkness.
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  you know, being in prison, not just by.
SPEAKER_1:  the bars in front of them.
SPEAKER_1:  but also by.
SPEAKER_1:  what they thought to be.
SPEAKER_1:  their own worth.
SPEAKER_1:  prior to that moment. And so Malcolm climbs out of
SPEAKER_1:  that and he goes through multiple phases.
SPEAKER_1:  Malcolm dies as an orthodox Muslim.
SPEAKER_1:  Who?
SPEAKER_1:  does not believe in the superiority of one race over the other.
SPEAKER_1:  finds.
SPEAKER_1:  Great tranquility.
SPEAKER_1:  in the practice of the Hajj.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  great clarity and I think you read his letters from Mecca.
SPEAKER_1:  And he talks about his change, his transformation in particular. And it was a process. It's a process for him.
SPEAKER_1:  but he inspires the likes of Muhammad Ali to become the person that he becomes.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  inspires many other people.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... till today
SPEAKER_1:  to really
SPEAKER_1:  see themselves and see the world differently in light of that.
SPEAKER_1:  understanding of monotheism.
SPEAKER_0:  So he was deeply a man of faith.
SPEAKER_0:  and throughout his life the nature of that faith has.
SPEAKER_0:  changed.
SPEAKER_0:  As he grew as he...
SPEAKER_0:  interact with.
SPEAKER_0:  I would say a cruel society that he was living.
SPEAKER_0:  You mentioned he inspired Muhammad Ali who
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think it's an overstatement to say it's probably.
SPEAKER_0:  the most, quite possibly the most famous.
SPEAKER_0:  American Muslim from America
SPEAKER_0:  Could you maybe make a few comments?
SPEAKER_0:  as an athlete yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  what impact did...
SPEAKER_0:  Islam have on Muhammad Ali's life and what and vice versa, what impact did he have as a leader, as a religious figure?
SPEAKER_0:  on the Muslim community.
SPEAKER_1:  I think Muhammad Ali, his quotes on...
SPEAKER_1:  Islam are precious because he talks about how he sought the wealth of this world and he found it in Islam. He found a greater meaning and he attributes everything that he became.
SPEAKER_1:  To his faith.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, his sense of, of strength and commitment.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, the willingness to
SPEAKER_1:  take a stand.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  for the truth.
SPEAKER_1:  when it was extremely unpopular.
SPEAKER_1:  on the basis of his faith and on the basis of his integrity.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that.
SPEAKER_1:  He inspired people with his confidence.
SPEAKER_1:  end.
SPEAKER_1:  his coherence.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, he was incredibly eloquent.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, poetic.
SPEAKER_1:  and is unwavering.
SPEAKER_1:  seemed unbreakable.
SPEAKER_1:  as relentless as he was in the ring.
SPEAKER_1:  He was even more so outside of the ring. The man could not be broken.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Everything was stacked up against them.
SPEAKER_1:  but he perseveres and he does so then through Parkinson's.
SPEAKER_1:  and chooses to live a life of.
SPEAKER_1:  of giving, a life of service, a life of using his platform.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  bring up issues of importance and to.
SPEAKER_1:  champion the rights of others, so he wasn't.
SPEAKER_1:  satisfied at any point in his life with simply being a boxing great.
SPEAKER_1:  boxing champion.
SPEAKER_1:  uses it for so much more.
SPEAKER_1:  And so he goes down as one of the most famous Americans period of the 20th century one of the most transformative Americans period.
SPEAKER_1:  of the 20th century, not just American Muslims.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  and a lot of people that loved him when he died.
SPEAKER_1:  would not have loved him.
SPEAKER_1:  if they were around in the 1960s and the 1970s.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, they said they loved him when he couldn't speak anymore.
SPEAKER_1:  many of those who celebrated him at the time of his death.
SPEAKER_1:  would have been his greatest opponents.
SPEAKER_1:  at the peak of his career.
SPEAKER_1:  And when he was taking the stance that he was taking.
SPEAKER_0:  fearless and part of this his faith was helping him.
SPEAKER_0:  take the fearless stance.
SPEAKER_0:  but throughout all of it.
SPEAKER_0:  Given the strength, I think he's also a symbol of compassion.
SPEAKER_0:  Trolls, bye.
SPEAKER_0:  through all the fun kinda.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, the poetic nature of who he was.
SPEAKER_0:  and the fearless nature of who he was, there's always like a...
SPEAKER_0:  and like a deep love for the sport.
SPEAKER_0:  and for humanity.
SPEAKER_1:  Absolutely. And that's the thing, right? It was so obvious that.
SPEAKER_1:  despite everything that had happened to him.
SPEAKER_1:  He never loses himself.
SPEAKER_1:  neither to the fame nor to the fear.
SPEAKER_1:  He always...
SPEAKER_1:  stays himself, he's authentic.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  And you know, when I went to his funeral and it was one of the most beautiful.
SPEAKER_1:  things I've ever seen because...
SPEAKER_1:  Everyone.
SPEAKER_1:  in Louisville, Kentucky, had a story with Muhammad Ali, right? The guy that he saves.
SPEAKER_1:  from committing suicide.
SPEAKER_1:  The
SPEAKER_1:  school kids, the hotel.
SPEAKER_1:  shuttle driver, the gas station worker, everyone has a story of Muhammad Ali in Louisville, Kentucky.
SPEAKER_1:  And when he...
SPEAKER_1:  when he passes away.
SPEAKER_1:  Everybody comes out.
SPEAKER_1:  and stands in front of their homes and they take...
SPEAKER_1:  casket and they drive around the streets of Louisville.
SPEAKER_1:  and he had this dream. I'm very close to some of his children.
SPEAKER_1:  Incredible people, by the way, just incredible human beings.
SPEAKER_1:  and he had this dream that he shared with them.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  He was jogging around the streets of Louisville, Kentucky.
SPEAKER_1:  and everyone.
SPEAKER_1:  had come out to wave to him.
SPEAKER_1:  And so he's running around jogging and, and, and waving to everybody in the streets of Louisville, Kentucky.
SPEAKER_1:  Then he gets to the cemetery.
SPEAKER_1:  and he says he flies into the heavens.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  his dream and he had this dream years ago.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, if you look at his funeral.
SPEAKER_1:  It's such a beautiful.
SPEAKER_1:  You can't make it up. It's such a b-
SPEAKER_1:  beautiful
SPEAKER_1:  moment where it seems to come to reality because everybody in Louisville just comes out and just waves by says casket. And then when he gets to the
SPEAKER_1:  cemetery, the gates close and...
SPEAKER_1:  He goes off to be with his Lord and we pray that it's a good place for him.
SPEAKER_1:  So Muhammad Ali
SPEAKER_0:  He's probably one of the great 20th century representatives of Islam.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  For me personally at least.
SPEAKER_0:  Hopefully I'm not showing my bias. One of the great modern representatives is Khabib Naremberg Medov, who's a great fighter and a great human being. So you've gotten a chance to meet him.
SPEAKER_0:  I should also say you're friends, you're good friends with a lot of really interesting Muslim people. I mean, it's such a widespread religion. There's just so much variety of different people that are practicing Muslims.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Does Khabib represent what do you like about him as a Muslim? What do you like about him as a person, as representative of the religion?
SPEAKER_1:  I think Habib...
SPEAKER_1:  First of all, he is a great person.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  humble person.
SPEAKER_1:  He's shown.
SPEAKER_1:  And now Islam as well, kind of following in that. They're really showing the beauty of.
SPEAKER_1:  faith in their lives.
SPEAKER_1:  their culture, their values.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Everything from the way.
SPEAKER_1:  that he carried himself in a principled way.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, you know, like, like.
SPEAKER_1:  Every Muslim kid grew up.
SPEAKER_1:  in a public school cafeteria.
SPEAKER_1:  before Islamic schools were a thing in the United States, people were not eating pork for example.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of being the odd person out.
SPEAKER_1:  So when you got a fighter...
SPEAKER_1:  and uh...
SPEAKER_1:  in the UFC scene.
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't drink alcohol.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of maintains like a very.
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  insistence.
SPEAKER_1:  principles.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  to his religion.
SPEAKER_1:  It really is inspiring. Growing up, we had Hakeem El-Ajwan in the 1990s.
SPEAKER_1:  basketball who was fasting in the NBA.
SPEAKER_1:  I think Habib is that for a lot of people, there's a lot of young people today.
SPEAKER_1:  and people in general. I think beyond that, the values.
SPEAKER_1:  how he honored his father.
SPEAKER_1:  and how he honors his mother.
SPEAKER_1:  and how he continues to put family first.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a beautiful part of a slump.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a beautiful part of our value system.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  We have a lot of emphasis on family.
SPEAKER_1:  Family is central to Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  and his honoring of his father was so beautiful.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  And again, what he's willing to do for his mother.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's just so beautiful. And I think that.
SPEAKER_1:  We saw it frankly even with Morocco.
SPEAKER_1:  in the World Cup.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there is a lot of Islamophobia.
SPEAKER_1:  in this recent world cup episode, you know, a lot of.
SPEAKER_1:  The criticism of Qatar.
SPEAKER_1:  while no government is beyond reproach.
SPEAKER_1:  Certainly no government is beyond reproach.
SPEAKER_1:  had very obvious blatant Islamophobic undertones. And then with Morocco rising.
SPEAKER_1:  being the first African Muslim.
SPEAKER_1:  Arab team, you know, to get that far in the world cup. What did you see beyond the consistent honoring of Palestine? You also saw the honoring of the mothers every single.
SPEAKER_1:  time.
SPEAKER_1:  the game would end, they go into a prostration of gratitude. So just like we prostrate in prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  prostration of gratitude.
SPEAKER_1:  And then they go and they kiss their mother's foreheads.
SPEAKER_1:  dance with their mothers on the field, hug their moms, and honor their moms.
SPEAKER_1:  That's Islam for you.
SPEAKER_1:  Habib.
SPEAKER_1:  After his fight, what does he do? He prostrates.
SPEAKER_1:  points up to the heavens. It's God and then he prostrates.
SPEAKER_1:  The whole Moroccan team.
SPEAKER_1:  beautifully prostrates, even when they lost.
SPEAKER_1:  They prostrated out of gratitude. They honored their mothers.
SPEAKER_1:  So I think sometimes athletes are able to demonstrate.
SPEAKER_1:  some of these beautiful values of Islam in a way that the world can maybe see them in a different light.
SPEAKER_0:  values of humility.
SPEAKER_0:  and the values of love.
SPEAKER_0:  Love broadly, but love for family.
SPEAKER_1:  And look how everyone around Habib talks about it.
SPEAKER_1:  Right?
SPEAKER_1:  No one ever, no one ever.
SPEAKER_1:  says he's a jerk, no one ever says he's mistreated them.
SPEAKER_1:  They've all got stories, right? That's what a beautiful Muslim does.
SPEAKER_1:  beautiful human being.
SPEAKER_1:  You.
SPEAKER_1:  treat the people in such a way that all these stories come out later.
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  how good you were to everyone that came into contact with you.
SPEAKER_1:  And Habib was that person.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, he is that person. He does a great job of.
SPEAKER_1:  treating people with a lot of respect.
SPEAKER_1:  Obviously no one is.
SPEAKER_1:  Perfect, right? I mean, imperfections are for everybody, but...
SPEAKER_1:  I definitely think that.
SPEAKER_1:  He did a beautiful job representing.
SPEAKER_1:  his faith in those moments.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, beyond punching people in the face. That's kind of a different subject. Smashing faces.
SPEAKER_1:  Not the smashing faces part.
SPEAKER_1:  the prostration part and the humility.
SPEAKER_1:  I tell you, man, he's not humble in the ring, right? He's a, he, he, he would maul his opponents, right? But, uh,
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, as as
SPEAKER_0:  The practitioner is a fan of the sport, of all grappling sports for me. There's also a beauty to the art of grappling and the fighting sports, but yes.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I think his, again, humility, his honor outside.
SPEAKER_0:  the cage is exemplary.
SPEAKER_0:  The money.
SPEAKER_0:  The Fame.
SPEAKER_0:  The power hasn't changed a bit.
SPEAKER_1:  No, not at all. And that's, that's actually, I think the most beautiful part when I met him.
SPEAKER_1:  I found him to be.
SPEAKER_1:  as humble.
SPEAKER_1:  as he is on screen.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's always very endearing and all of the stories of the people that have been around him for a much longer time.
SPEAKER_1:  Very humble man.
SPEAKER_1:  I pray for him, honestly, I pray for Islam, I pray for...
SPEAKER_1:  that family.
SPEAKER_1:  that God keeps them grounded and protected and together.
SPEAKER_1:  and that they maintain that beautiful spirit.
SPEAKER_1:  Cause even if you, if you just watch the lead up to the last, uh,
SPEAKER_1:  the last fight with Islam, just the way they carry themselves their day to day.
SPEAKER_1:  They never relinquish their prayers.
SPEAKER_1:  They never relinquish their family.
SPEAKER_1:  ties the things that
SPEAKER_1:  make them who they are to be better fighters because they don't see
SPEAKER_1:  That's...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, they have to let go of those things. In fact, they attribute all of their worldly success.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... to them
SPEAKER_1:  that faith and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  Beautiful examples and I think that.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  It's good for young Muslims to see.
SPEAKER_1:  themselves in that and it's good for other people to see Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  I threw that as well.
SPEAKER_0:  when you mention the prophets.
SPEAKER_0:  You often say, peace and blessings be upon them. Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  What is that phrase?
SPEAKER_0:  Mean.
SPEAKER_0:  is why do you say it, is it to celebrate the people, is it a constant reminder that these are figures that should be celebrated?
SPEAKER_1:  Absolutely. So it's part of our tradition that when we say the name of a prophet, at least the first time in the conversation, we say, peace be upon him.
SPEAKER_1:  And then...
SPEAKER_1:  afterwards, it's still praiseworthy to say Peace be upon him.
SPEAKER_1:  So if you're reading an Islamic article and you see in parentheses.
SPEAKER_1:  TBUH.
SPEAKER_1:  Peace be unto Him or peace be upon Him.
SPEAKER_1:  When I was in high school, I often tell the story I wrote an article about Jesus, peace be upon him, in Islam and Christianity.
SPEAKER_1:  and my uh...
SPEAKER_1:  teacher comes up to me and she says, you can't do that. I said, what? She like slams the paper on, on the desk.
SPEAKER_1:  She says, you can't say Jesus.
SPEAKER_1:  I said, no, no, PBUH, peace be upon him.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  That's what it means and something that we reserve for the prophets.
SPEAKER_1:  of God and we honor them with.
SPEAKER_1:  So who is Muhammad?
SPEAKER_1:  So the Prophet Muhammad peace be upon him.
SPEAKER_1:  is the descendant of Abraham, peace be upon him, through Ishmael.
SPEAKER_1:  God promises.
SPEAKER_1:  Hagar and Ishmael.
SPEAKER_1:  that he will make of him a great nation.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  There are prophets that are descended from Isaac.
SPEAKER_1:  And then...
SPEAKER_1:  from the Brothers of Isaac.
SPEAKER_1:  comes the prophet Muhammad.
SPEAKER_1:  And he is the final prophet of a long line of prophets. And we do not distinguish between the prophets in regards to.
SPEAKER_1:  their role.
SPEAKER_1:  And so Islam has a very...
SPEAKER_1:  accessible theology. It's something that resonates with.
SPEAKER_1:  A professor.
SPEAKER_1:  and an Ivy League university and.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, a person who
SPEAKER_1:  maybe even illiterate, this idea of one God that sent many prophets and all of the prophets out a singular message.
SPEAKER_1:  Worship one God.
SPEAKER_1:  and respond to the messages of that one God through his messengers.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  Adam.
SPEAKER_1:  through Muhammad you have.
SPEAKER_1:  many of the prophets that are mentioned in the Old Testament.
SPEAKER_1:  Moses, peace be upon him, being the most spoken about prophet in the Quran, in fact Abraham.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Jesus, peace be upon him, many of these prophets that aren't familiar.
SPEAKER_1:  to people all of them are considered prophets in Islam the prophet Muhammad.
SPEAKER_1:  Peace be upon him being the last of them.
SPEAKER_1:  He comes at a time where
SPEAKER_1:  there was still a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  of confusion.
SPEAKER_1:  about what the world had just encountered in Christ, in Jesus Christ, peace be upon them.
SPEAKER_1:  You gotta think about it this way, that this is still.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, you know, he's born in the sixth century.
SPEAKER_1:  There.
SPEAKER_1:  is still great debate.
SPEAKER_1:  about who Jesus was.
SPEAKER_1:  The Council of Nicaea happens in the 4th century.
SPEAKER_1:  where you kind of have a standardizing of Western Christianity.
SPEAKER_1:  but then you have Eastern.
SPEAKER_1:  Christians that are still maintaining very different theologies and very different conceptions of Christ.
SPEAKER_1:  There is no Arabic Bible at the time.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  he kind of brings together.
SPEAKER_1:  The
SPEAKER_1:  message and the mission of all of those prophets and it fits perfectly.
SPEAKER_1:  into
SPEAKER_1:  A singular.
SPEAKER_1:  string of thought.
SPEAKER_1:  where
SPEAKER_1:  You don't have to reject Jesus, peace be upon him, but Islam also is staunchly opposed to the idea of a trinity, the idea of a begotten son of God.
SPEAKER_1:  that all the conceptions of the Messiah, and there were many claimants of the Messiah.
SPEAKER_1:  prior to Christ, peace be upon Him.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  None of them included.
SPEAKER_1:  an idea of...
SPEAKER_1:  Trinity or of Him actually being a part of.
SPEAKER_1:  God himself, a begotten son of God, but rather a great and mighty prophet.
SPEAKER_1:  that would
SPEAKER_1:  Restore Glory.
SPEAKER_1:  on Earth, so he...
SPEAKER_1:  he really captures theologically.
SPEAKER_1:  or rather.
SPEAKER_1:  we would say God captures through him theologically.
SPEAKER_1:  a coherence and a unifying message of all of the prophets.
SPEAKER_1:  that there's only one God.
SPEAKER_1:  and that that God has sent.
SPEAKER_1:  messages.
SPEAKER_1:  and scriptures.
SPEAKER_1:  to ultimately guide people back towards him.
SPEAKER_1:  and that all of the profits are equal.
SPEAKER_1:  and the sight of God. There is no distinction between them.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's...
SPEAKER_1:  We are.
SPEAKER_1:  to live our lives in accordance with the message.
SPEAKER_1:  as best manifested by the messenger.
SPEAKER_1:  And so the prophets are exemplary human beings. And this is where we kind of sometimes maybe have.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... a difference in a somewhat say well
SPEAKER_1:  You know, Noah did this and David did this. As Muslims, we don't believe.
SPEAKER_1:  We don't hold many of the stories that have been attributed to these prophets.
SPEAKER_1:  to be true.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  We don't believe that the prophets are capable of major sins. We believe they're exemplary human beings.
SPEAKER_1:  and that they kind of give us.
SPEAKER_1:  manifestation of the scriptures that they were sent with.
SPEAKER_1:  of how to live noble lives and the most documented human being in history.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, is the
SPEAKER_1:  Prophet Muhammad peace be upon him. We know everything about him, his family life.
SPEAKER_1:  his day to day, the way he would greet you, the way he'd look at you, everything about his physical appearance.
SPEAKER_1:  It's documented in immaculate detail and Muslims have a standard.
SPEAKER_1:  that they then seek to live up to.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... with
SPEAKER_1:  how to treat your family, how to be in your community, how to be in your worship, how to be in your social interactions.
SPEAKER_1:  how to carry yourself with your neighbors. it's a full complete.
SPEAKER_1:  guidebook.
SPEAKER_1:  through his example.
SPEAKER_1:  where
SPEAKER_1:  We have the Quran, which is the word of God. And then you have...
SPEAKER_1:  biography of the Prophet Muhammad peace be upon him, which is
SPEAKER_1:  a living manifestation.
SPEAKER_1:  of that word.
SPEAKER_1:  that has been documented for us to live by.
SPEAKER_1:  until the end of time.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Muhammad.
SPEAKER_0:  If I may peace be upon him.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  is really the...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, like you said, the manifestation is the thing to be, the example of a good man.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  Example of a good human being.
SPEAKER_1:  Is the Quran the word of God?
SPEAKER_1:  So the Quran, and this is what distinguishes the Quran in many ways.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... from other scriptures as Muslims we do believe
SPEAKER_1:  That.
SPEAKER_1:  God has sent divine revelation prior.
SPEAKER_1:  We believe that the original
SPEAKER_1:  scriptures.
SPEAKER_1:  prior to the multiple versions and...
SPEAKER_1:  the changes and revisions throughout history, the original scriptures that were given to the prophets.
SPEAKER_1:  whether it was the Telerot.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  to Moses.
SPEAKER_1:  or the Gospels.
SPEAKER_1:  were all original divine revelations.
SPEAKER_1:  but they have been changed over time. The Quran is the word of God with a promise that He will guard it.
SPEAKER_1:  for all of time.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's probably one of the greatest miracles because in 1400 years.
SPEAKER_1:  We have.
SPEAKER_1:  the Quran preserved through oral transmission and through written transmission.
SPEAKER_1:  and there are almost 2 billion Muslims in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  And they all recite this book the exact same way. And there's only one version of it.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  when I'm reciting the Quran.
SPEAKER_1:  If I say, ooh, or ee, or ah.
SPEAKER_1:  differently.
SPEAKER_1:  and Ethiopian Muslim.
SPEAKER_1:  a Chinese Muslim.
SPEAKER_1:  A Yemeni Muslim can correct me, an eight year old kid in any one of those countries can correct me because they will know that this is not how it's memorized. So it was memorized.
SPEAKER_1:  from the start committed to.
SPEAKER_1:  Memory
SPEAKER_1:  in the time of the Prophet Muhammad peace be upon him.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  preserved in writing.
SPEAKER_1:  and pass down.
SPEAKER_1:  and memorized by millions and millions of people around the world.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's 600 pages.
SPEAKER_1:  And you can't go to a city in America.
SPEAKER_1:  a city in the United States of America.
SPEAKER_1:  and not find at least one person or group of people that memorize it.
SPEAKER_1:  that have committed it to memory. And so there's an emphasis on
SPEAKER_1:  committing it to memory.
SPEAKER_1:  as well as understanding it and applying it.
SPEAKER_1:  and practicing it as much as we can.
SPEAKER_1:  What are some...
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe...
SPEAKER_0:  deep.
SPEAKER_0:  or insightful differences.
SPEAKER_0:  between the Quran, the Torah, and the Bible.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, like I said, so you've got the original revelations of those scriptures.
SPEAKER_1:  but there are so many versions of those scriptures and there are times throughout history where
SPEAKER_1:  there have been changes just from an objective perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  What is the original scripture that was given to?
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  Moses, peace be upon him.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  what was initially communicated to Jesus, peace be upon Him, those things.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  have changed over time.
SPEAKER_1:  However...
SPEAKER_1:  there's still some truth.
SPEAKER_1:  that remains even in those scriptures. And so it stops there.
SPEAKER_1:  There are still things that line up, especially with.
SPEAKER_1:  the Old Testament.
SPEAKER_1:  and Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  there are still many things that line up between the two.
SPEAKER_1:  the Bible as well, the New Testament. Now,
SPEAKER_1:  Matthew, Mark, Luke and John.
SPEAKER_1:  It's different because these are not.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  original scriptures. These are testimonies that were obviously collected.
SPEAKER_1:  around.
SPEAKER_1:  the entire phenomenon of the coming of Christ, but the authors themselves, the biographies.
SPEAKER_1:  the documentation even of those original testimonies and gospels, what made.
SPEAKER_1:  the cut in terms of being included within the Gospels and what didn't, because there were many Gospels at the time in that sense.
SPEAKER_1:  is different from what we believe was Scripture communicated to Jesus, peace be upon Him.
SPEAKER_1:  the Quran
SPEAKER_1:  is different.
SPEAKER_1:  in several ways.
SPEAKER_1:  it confirms.
SPEAKER_1:  what came before it.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's the document and preserved Word of God to be recited throughout.
SPEAKER_1:  throughout time.
SPEAKER_1:  So it confirms much of what came before it.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, and it resides amongst us and within us.
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh
SPEAKER_1:  for the rest of time.
SPEAKER_1:  and threw it.
SPEAKER_1:  We honor.
SPEAKER_1:  those revelations.
SPEAKER_1:  that came through.
SPEAKER_1:  the prophets of old.
SPEAKER_1:  because
SPEAKER_1:  The essence, the core of what came through those revelations is preserved in the Quran and with us. I tell people this.
SPEAKER_1:  all the time that.
SPEAKER_1:  The Prophet Muhammad, peace be upon him, introduced
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Jesus peace be upon him.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  even Moses, peace be upon him, to much of.
SPEAKER_1:  the world.
SPEAKER_1:  There are Muslims around the world that are named Isa, that are named Jesus. There are Muslims around the world that are named Ibrahim, Abraham. Muslims around the world named Musa.
SPEAKER_1:  and they learned of these figures through
SPEAKER_1:  The Revelation.
SPEAKER_1:  that came to the Prophet Muhammad peace be upon him. nuu料dimensional
SPEAKER_1:  Maryam, one of the most popular names in Islam, Mary.
SPEAKER_1:  peace be upon her. Whole chapter in the Qur'an named after
SPEAKER_1:  Mariam, which is actually what I was reciting in the prayer was the chapter of Mariam, the chapter of the story of Mary, peace be upon her.
SPEAKER_1:  So the Quran contains the stories it contains.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  legislation and law, but primarily it was revealed over 23 years. So it actually was coming in accordance with
SPEAKER_1:  some of the events that were unfolding in the life of the Prophet Muhammad peace be upon him.
SPEAKER_1:  The first...
SPEAKER_1:  Thirteen years of that was primarily belief in God.
SPEAKER_1:  belief in the hereafter.
SPEAKER_1:  and things that surrounded the core creed of Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  And then.
SPEAKER_1:  Legislation.
SPEAKER_1:  law, stories of the prophets.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  came down in accordance with the unfolding events.
SPEAKER_1:  as well as prophesying some of the things that were to come.
SPEAKER_1:  and speaking about some of the things that had just happened. And it is completed in the lifetime of the Prophet Muhammad peace be upon it, memorized and then communicated to generation after generation after generation.
SPEAKER_1:  so that we have it in its.
SPEAKER_1:  pristine fashion. no.
SPEAKER_0:  billions of people.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  All across the world, all the different cultures, all...
SPEAKER_0:  memorizing the same words.
SPEAKER_0:  One of the pillars, or maybe I should say one of the central practices, is the month of Ramadan.
SPEAKER_0:  What is the importance of this month?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  What does the process of it entail?
SPEAKER_1:  also.
SPEAKER_1:  So Islam has, I think it'd be good to maybe lay this out for people, the articles of faith in the pillars of Islam. So the articles of faith, there are six articles of faith and this kind of lays the foundation for my noodleinpsь.
SPEAKER_1:  the creed of Islam. So belief in God.
SPEAKER_1:  belief in the angels.
SPEAKER_1:  belief in the messages, belief in the messengers.
SPEAKER_1:  belief in the Day of Judgment and belief in divine decree.
SPEAKER_1:  So these are the six.
SPEAKER_1:  Articles of Faith.
SPEAKER_1:  Belief in God, belief in the angels, belief in.
SPEAKER_1:  The messages being the scriptures, belief in the messengers being the prophets.
SPEAKER_1:  belief in the day of judgment and belief in divine decree.
SPEAKER_1:  That's what you have to believe to be a Muslim. You have to believe in those six things, right?
SPEAKER_1:  and then you go to.
SPEAKER_1:  The pillars of faith, the five pillars of faith.
SPEAKER_1:  are.
SPEAKER_1:  sort of, or they make up the structure.
SPEAKER_1:  of those articles of faith.
SPEAKER_1:  practice of the Muslim. So what are you learning?
SPEAKER_1:  to be a Muslim.
SPEAKER_1:  You testify.
SPEAKER_1:  that there's only one God.
SPEAKER_1:  worthy of worship.
SPEAKER_1:  and unconditional obedience, and then you testify that Muhammad is the final messenger of God.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the first pillar, the actual testimony entering into Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  Then it's the five daily prayers.
SPEAKER_1:  practicing the five daily prayers at least as a bare minimum obligation.
SPEAKER_1:  The
SPEAKER_1:  mandatory charity,
SPEAKER_1:  which is called the zakat, that Muslims have to give at least 2.5%.
SPEAKER_1:  of their retained earnings.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... to specific categories of charity
SPEAKER_1:  then it is the fasting of the month of Ramadan.
SPEAKER_1:  the mandatory fasting of the month of Ramadan.
SPEAKER_1:  And then it's the Hajj, if you can do so, the pilgrimage, if you can do so once in your lifetime. So those are the five pillars of Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  So, Ramadan.
SPEAKER_1:  is a month in which Muslims engage in this incredible spiritual bootcamp.
SPEAKER_1:  Now...
SPEAKER_1:  Fasting can mean different things to different people.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  when we fast.
SPEAKER_1:  We fast from before sunrise to sunset for an entire month.
SPEAKER_1:  and there's no food or water.
SPEAKER_1:  Period.
SPEAKER_1:  and no intimacy as well. So…
SPEAKER_1:  you would abstain from intimacy with your spouse as well.
SPEAKER_1:  in that time.
SPEAKER_1:  No food or water, no bread, no nothing.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, you don't eat or drink, even if you live in Texas.
SPEAKER_1:  where you get these long hot days in the summer.
SPEAKER_1:  And of course Islam is on a lunar calendar, so it moves every.
SPEAKER_1:  every year, about 10 days earlier.
SPEAKER_1:  during that time.
SPEAKER_1:  You restrict.
SPEAKER_1:  the intake.
SPEAKER_1:  to the body.
SPEAKER_1:  so that you can focus on the intake of the soul.
SPEAKER_1:  So instead of being focused on consumption, constant consumption,
SPEAKER_1:  You are consuming words of remembrance, words of prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  You're to be hyper conscious of not doing anything that would spiritually validate your fast.
SPEAKER_1:  just as you would physically. So just like you won't eat or drink, you certainly won't engage in sin, though you shouldn't engage in sins throughout the year, but...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you're not going to speak.
SPEAKER_1:  words of evil, you're not going to gossip or slander.
SPEAKER_1:  You try to fast with your eyes, not look at things that are not praiseworthy.
SPEAKER_1:  So you try to engage.
SPEAKER_1:  and a wholesome.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... act of
SPEAKER_1:  Disciplining yourself with the consciousness of God.
SPEAKER_1:  But then...
SPEAKER_1:  channel that.
SPEAKER_1:  into engaging the soul instead, exercising the soul instead.
SPEAKER_1:  And what you'll find with Muslims and this act of God consciousness, where they reduce the consumption is they become far more grateful for the blessings of God because throughout our lives we just take sips of water, we eat what we can, we snack.
SPEAKER_1:  when
SPEAKER_1:  You're abstaining from that. You become so much more grateful for that sip of water, so much more grateful for that bite of food.
SPEAKER_1:  so much more aware of the one who provided those blessings to you, so much more aware of those that don't have the same access to those blessings that you have.
SPEAKER_1:  So you also develop.
SPEAKER_1:  sense of empathy for the poor that don't have access to those blessings on a regular basis that can't help but fast.
SPEAKER_1:  And on top of that again.
SPEAKER_1:  spiritually.
SPEAKER_1:  You are engaged in extra reading.
SPEAKER_1:  At that time, people are listening to more lectures.
SPEAKER_1:  people are.
SPEAKER_1:  engaged in extra acts of devotion, extra acts of charity. Muslims are most charitable.
SPEAKER_1:  in the month of Ramadan.
SPEAKER_1:  So you just feel great and it's hard to explain to someone that doesn't do it because it sounds like torture to people. Right. What in the world are you doing?
SPEAKER_1:  you know, four o'clock on a hot Texas day.
SPEAKER_1:  not eating or drinking, you're probably dehydrated and cranky.
SPEAKER_1:  have a caffeine headache and...
SPEAKER_1:  You probably can't wait for this month to be over.
SPEAKER_1:  But in reality, you talk to Muslims their favorite time of the year is Ramadan.
SPEAKER_1:  You feel amazing.
SPEAKER_1:  you feel absolutely incredible.
SPEAKER_1:  because you taste a different type of consumption.
SPEAKER_1:  You feed your soul for a change.
SPEAKER_1:  And in that process.
SPEAKER_1:  You connect.
SPEAKER_1:  with God in a way?
SPEAKER_1:  that you simply could not without the distractions of the day to day throughout the year.
SPEAKER_1:  Now it's good that it's one month of the year because it's honestly physically taxing, right?
SPEAKER_1:  It gives you a chance.
SPEAKER_1:  to experience it for that one month, but then you're encouraged to fast a few days of the year as well outside of the month of Ramadan.
SPEAKER_1:  to keep that connection.
SPEAKER_1:  What are the hardest parts that-
SPEAKER_0:  But maybe...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  for people outside of...
SPEAKER_0:  the Muslim faith.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, we'll be curious about.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I think the hardest part is...
SPEAKER_1:  Physically the physics
SPEAKER_0:  or is it the spiritual? hello, I'm super Muscat and I think the
SPEAKER_1:  So as Ramadan goes on.
SPEAKER_1:  your acts of worship increase. So in the last 10 nights of Ramadan,
SPEAKER_1:  Um, there is an intense.
SPEAKER_1:  period.
SPEAKER_1:  of prayer throughout the night. So every night in Ramadan, we have something called the Tarawih prayers. The Tarawih prayers are about an hour, hour and a half of prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  outside of the five daily prayers. So the mosques are packed every night in Ramadan.
SPEAKER_1:  the last ten nights of Ramadan.
SPEAKER_1:  People will engage in prayer throughout the entire night. So the only sleep that you're probably getting
SPEAKER_1:  is actually a couple of hours in the morning before you go to work.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's everything sort of put together the.
SPEAKER_1:  disruption of schedule, the disruption of diet.
SPEAKER_1:  the
SPEAKER_1:  physically exerting yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  but
SPEAKER_1:  the way you feel.
SPEAKER_1:  is unmatched.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, you feel...
SPEAKER_1:  so fulfilled.
SPEAKER_1:  through that deprivation and it's actually the point. You know, it all ties back together when you talk about.
SPEAKER_1:  even tests and trials.
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  God does not deprive us of anything except that He gives us something greater.
SPEAKER_1:  in return.
SPEAKER_1:  and you do not deprive yourself of anything for the sake of God.
SPEAKER_1:  except that he gives you something greater in return.
SPEAKER_1:  And so fasting is an exercise in patience that unlocks an infinite sense of gratitude.
SPEAKER_1:  and a greater connection to God.
SPEAKER_1:  Many people predict that.
SPEAKER_0:  Islam will surpass Christianity as the largest religion.
SPEAKER_0:  by the end of the century.
SPEAKER_0:  by the number of its adherents and practitioners.
SPEAKER_0:  What responsibility does that place on people like you?
SPEAKER_0:  who is a religious leader, who is somebody who teaches, who grows, who cares for the community, for the Muslim community, but actually for all people.
SPEAKER_1:  I think what that means is that.
SPEAKER_1:  We have a responsibility to
SPEAKER_1:  Teach and live our faith in the most beautiful of ways not.
SPEAKER_1:  its values and
SPEAKER_1:  ideals.
SPEAKER_1:  are not just expressed by you, but experienced by everyone around you.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  What I often teach my community is that look, if a Muslims in the area, what are they?
SPEAKER_1:  What are your neighbors experiencing of you?
SPEAKER_1:  What are people experiencing of you?
SPEAKER_1:  You know, and there's...
SPEAKER_1:  There are statistics to Muslims being
SPEAKER_1:  most charitable communities in America.
SPEAKER_1:  We're a community of great service the community of volunteer in a community that
SPEAKER_1:  greatly enriches the world around us.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that oftentimes people forget the history.
SPEAKER_1:  of Muslims.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, being at the forefront of contributing.
SPEAKER_1:  the areas of medicine and science.
SPEAKER_1:  all sorts of ways, education.
SPEAKER_1:  really changing the world.
SPEAKER_1:  through their commitment to faith.
SPEAKER_1:  but on a deeply personal level.
SPEAKER_1:  You know?
SPEAKER_1:  It's important for us.
SPEAKER_1:  to be representatives.
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  the Prophet Muhammad peace be upon him in a way that makes Islamophobia impossible.
SPEAKER_1:  I tell people this, that.
SPEAKER_1:  it's very hard you know you mentioned united states of hate uh... the remarkably
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  the one man, the protester who...
SPEAKER_1:  met me and sort of changed his world view.
SPEAKER_1:  It's very hard for...
SPEAKER_1:  people to believe.
SPEAKER_1:  what they hear about Islam.
SPEAKER_1:  if they see you live it.
SPEAKER_1:  Now that does not excuse bigotry, that doesn't excuse the prejudice against Muslims.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's important for us.
SPEAKER_1:  to sort of take it as.
SPEAKER_1:  a responsibility as Muslims.
SPEAKER_1:  to channel our faith in the most beautiful of ways.
SPEAKER_1:  God describes faith in the Quran.
SPEAKER_1:  in the chapter of Abraham, peace be upon him, as a tree with firm foundations.
SPEAKER_1:  the firm foundation being the testimony of faith, the oneness of God, so the tree of monotheism with firm foundations.
SPEAKER_1:  and then branches high in the sky.
SPEAKER_1:  providing shade to everything and everyone around you.
SPEAKER_1:  and producing fruit at all times.
SPEAKER_1:  the tree of faith of a Muslim.
SPEAKER_1:  is not seasonal, so.
SPEAKER_1:  you should be producing f-
SPEAKER_1:  with your faith at all times, good works and things that.
SPEAKER_1:  people can
SPEAKER_1:  can actually experience. And I think that Muslims have historically contributed to the world around them.
SPEAKER_1:  and I think that Muslims today are still contributing.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, to the world around them. But I think that.
SPEAKER_1:  we can.
SPEAKER_1:  Never.
SPEAKER_1:  do enough of.
SPEAKER_1:  holding ourselves accountable.
SPEAKER_1:  to the message.
SPEAKER_1:  That's it.
SPEAKER_1:  We hold dear to our hearts.
SPEAKER_1:  and trying to be the best representatives of that message and of that messenger.
SPEAKER_1:  to the world around us.
SPEAKER_0:  So not only are you a...
SPEAKER_0:  a religious leader in the Muslim community, but you have a lot of friends.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, horror.
SPEAKER_0:  from different religions, you have a lot of Jewish friends.
SPEAKER_0:  As we've talked about a lot offline.
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  and we'll probably hopefully get a chance to talk to as well here.
SPEAKER_0:  I wouldn't.
SPEAKER_0:  On that topic, let me bring up.
SPEAKER_0:  another tragic event that
SPEAKER_0:  was just a little bit less than a year ago in this very community here in Dallas.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a synagogue hostage crisis.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you describe what happened and what was your experience like through it and afterwards?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  what were the bad things you saw and what are the good things you saw in the community?
SPEAKER_1:  The Colleyville.
SPEAKER_1:  synagogue, a situation.
SPEAKER_1:  It's kind of surreal that we're coming up on a year of that.
SPEAKER_1:  But I'll actually tell you exactly what happened that morning.
SPEAKER_1:  I was out with the family.
SPEAKER_1:  and that morning...
SPEAKER_1:  I kid you not that very morning I was telling my kids the story of Muhammad Ali.
SPEAKER_1:  talking that man.
SPEAKER_1:  out of committing suicide off the roof. And I showed them the YouTube video. My wife pulled it up on her phone. Kids were sitting in the backseat.
SPEAKER_1:  We talked about that video.
SPEAKER_1:  and talked about that importance of helping people.
SPEAKER_1:  We also went to visit a loved one in the cemetery that day.
SPEAKER_1:  And we went to breakfast. So we're out as a family that day, right? And there's a lot of meaning that's sort of coming together.
SPEAKER_1:  for us and a lot of discussion, deep discussion we're having as a family.
SPEAKER_1:  And then.
SPEAKER_1:  some of our community groups, we get this message that.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a synagogue.
SPEAKER_1:  That's been taken.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  hostage.
SPEAKER_1:  A rabbi and his congregation taken.
SPEAKER_1:  as hostages and.
SPEAKER_1:  go to this Facebook link and it was the feed.
SPEAKER_1:  of the synagogue.
SPEAKER_1:  and you could hear the gunman.
SPEAKER_1:  shouting.
SPEAKER_1:  and it became apparent.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  very early on that.
SPEAKER_1:  It was a man that was claiming to be Muslim
SPEAKER_1:  that was holding them hostage.
SPEAKER_1:  Now all these...
SPEAKER_1:  Synagogue massacres, all these places of worship.
SPEAKER_1:  We're not attacked by Muslims, right? This is...
SPEAKER_1:  uh... a different type of situation but
SPEAKER_1:  My first instinct.
SPEAKER_1:  was
SPEAKER_1:  Like all that happened this morning was not random.
SPEAKER_1:  So I told my wife.
SPEAKER_1:  I told my kids I'm gonna go down there.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah, it's a callee bill.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  She was very supportive.
SPEAKER_1:  Obviously there was a moment of shock.
SPEAKER_1:  like
SPEAKER_1:  kids were like.
SPEAKER_1:  Wait, what? And I said, look, remember what we talked about this morning?
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  We can't be indifferent to the stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  We still go back and revisit that day. You know, like it's crazy how it was all falling into place. It's not an accident, right?
SPEAKER_1:  So I dropped them off at home.
SPEAKER_1:  And I started to drive to Colleyville.
SPEAKER_1:  I called the, um.
SPEAKER_1:  Irving.
SPEAKER_1:  police department and I asked them to
SPEAKER_1:  called the Colleyville Police Department.
SPEAKER_1:  So that.
SPEAKER_1:  they could kind of know that I'm coming down there.
SPEAKER_1:  I called.
SPEAKER_1:  some of the faith leaders in the community.
SPEAKER_1:  to see if they could put me in touch with those on the ground.
SPEAKER_1:  that I wouldn't get shot when I showed up there.
SPEAKER_1:  and eventually I had to wait out.
SPEAKER_1:  outside until they got clearance to come through.
SPEAKER_1:  and to just offer whatever support I could, pastoral support.
SPEAKER_1:  support with
SPEAKER_1:  trying to free the hostages.
SPEAKER_1:  of the synagogue at the time. It was operating out of a church right across the street from.
SPEAKER_1:  the synagogue.
SPEAKER_1:  Um
SPEAKER_1:  day long.
SPEAKER_1:  just wondering, you know, what was going to happen.
SPEAKER_1:  looking at.
SPEAKER_1:  the family of the Rabbi.
SPEAKER_1:  the time.
SPEAKER_1:  wondering what was going to happen.
SPEAKER_1:  and trying to just be as supportive as I possibly could.
SPEAKER_1:  at that time.
SPEAKER_1:  Thankfully, they all
SPEAKER_1:  God out.
SPEAKER_1:  in the evening.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think that...
SPEAKER_1:  you know
SPEAKER_1:  Looking back on that.
SPEAKER_1:  day.
SPEAKER_1:  My wife actually asked me, she said, would you have done it differently? And I said, no, I really wouldn't because I think that
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  Things happen sometimes, you've got to act on your good instinct sometimes, right? When you talk about like being calculated.
SPEAKER_1:  think sometimes.
SPEAKER_1:  we're calculated when we shouldn't be. And that's when that good instinct comes in.
SPEAKER_1:  where you're called to do something else.
SPEAKER_0:  What did it feel like to be a-
SPEAKER_0:  Most of them in a situation like that.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, were you a human being? Were you a religious?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I don't, I don't, I don't see, I can't, I can't separate anything about myself.
SPEAKER_1:  in that situation, right? so
SPEAKER_1:  When I had to pray, I had to pray.
SPEAKER_1:  to help people out.
SPEAKER_1:  give people words of comfort.
SPEAKER_1:  to try to appeal.
SPEAKER_1:  to the senses of...
SPEAKER_1:  whoever I could at the time.
SPEAKER_1:  I didn't see myself as, like, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  a guy trying to...
SPEAKER_1:  trying to show.
SPEAKER_1:  a particular part of Islam there. I just saw myself as someone that was trying to-
SPEAKER_1:  help a family get there.
SPEAKER_1:  their husband and father back, right? And so it was more of just like that part of me was there.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you can, you can kind of see yourself, right? This is the irony of it.
SPEAKER_1:  when Christ Church New Zealand happened.
SPEAKER_1:  That was kind of our worst nightmare as Texas Muslims, because we've had armed groups in front of our mosques threatening to do what that man did in Christchurch.
SPEAKER_1:  And so when you see a wife and kids.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  wondering if they're going to get their dad back.
SPEAKER_1:  you kind of see yourself there.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I just saw myself in that situation.
SPEAKER_1:  What would I want people to be doing for me in that moment?
SPEAKER_1:  What would I want people to be telling my family in that moment?
SPEAKER_1:  So that's really where I went to and that's really where.
SPEAKER_1:  where I dug into and I prayed a lot that day.
SPEAKER_1:  a lot, a lot for the right words, for the right actions, what I could do.
SPEAKER_1:  to just help.
SPEAKER_0:  What are the lessons now a year later?
SPEAKER_0:  that you take away from that day.
SPEAKER_1:  in the days. Less than Thanks
SPEAKER_1:  Don't be indifferent.
SPEAKER_1:  Don't be indifferent to the suffering around you or even that's distant from you.
SPEAKER_1:  because it's somehow related to you.
SPEAKER_1:  So just don't be indifferent.
SPEAKER_0:  So you're proud that you stepped up and you went there and then.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, look, I don't think...
SPEAKER_1:  I don't think I did much.
SPEAKER_1:  being really honest, this is not me trying to be humble here. I don't think I did much. I think I did what I did.
SPEAKER_1:  I was.
SPEAKER_1:  what I was called to do.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  I wish.
SPEAKER_1:  that it never happens, right? as a whole, but.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm glad that.
SPEAKER_1:  the relationships that have been built over time.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  came into being in that day, right? We could call upon people that we knew, call upon each other and as a community where they come together, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Dallas has been through a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of pain.
SPEAKER_1:  but we've come together through a lot of pain as well.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  It's, it's kind of one of those things where we're united in our pain, you know, when you suffer together.
SPEAKER_1:  you build certain bonds together.
SPEAKER_1:  So Dallas has been through a lot as a community.
SPEAKER_1:  But we've come together through a lot as a community.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, the thing about violence and war.
SPEAKER_0:  It destroys.
SPEAKER_0:  It caused so much suffering, but it also sort of brings out some of the best aspects of human nature and unites people.
SPEAKER_0:  It's an interesting way how our human civilization functions.
SPEAKER_1:  functions.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, that's the beauty that you don't just want to see, but you also want to be.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, we're living in a climate where.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot of that, right? So how do you actually...
SPEAKER_1:  Oh.
SPEAKER_1:  get through that and actually.
SPEAKER_1:  not allow yourself to succumb to that.
SPEAKER_1:  and be another voice in that polarization.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems that there are...
SPEAKER_0:  history and still in the world today.
SPEAKER_0:  Religion has been a source of some of the
SPEAKER_0:  of a lot of polarization.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of conflict, even war.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Why do you think that is?
SPEAKER_1:  Listen, I think at the essence of it.
SPEAKER_1:  As always.
SPEAKER_1:  some sort of political instability.
SPEAKER_1:  that leaves behind a brutalized population.
SPEAKER_1:  and vulnerabilities that can be exploited.
SPEAKER_1:  As I said in the 20th century.
SPEAKER_1:  with.
SPEAKER_1:  the bloodiest century that we've had to date.
SPEAKER_1:  Where does religion fall on any of that? Where does religion fall in the isms? Where does religion fall?
SPEAKER_1:  in the world wars.
SPEAKER_1:  Where does religion fall?
SPEAKER_1:  And much of that, even when we talk about things like the crusades remove.
SPEAKER_1:  the Islamic framing.
SPEAKER_1:  The crusades, the crusades.
SPEAKER_1:  Were they really about religion?
SPEAKER_1:  the Mongols and the destruction of the Mongols.
SPEAKER_1:  Was it about religion?
SPEAKER_1:  Myanmar and the Rohingya.
SPEAKER_1:  day.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it about Buddhism?
SPEAKER_1:  So I think that these are essentially.
SPEAKER_1:  political.
SPEAKER_1:  issues.
SPEAKER_1:  political causes.
SPEAKER_1:  where you have people that.
SPEAKER_1:  Rise up.
SPEAKER_1:  and that use.
SPEAKER_1:  religion to disguise things that are far, far, far from religion.
SPEAKER_1:  And if you want to manipulate.
SPEAKER_1:  a religious scripture. You could turn any book.
SPEAKER_1:  Any scripture.
SPEAKER_1:  into a violent scripture if you have a violent aim.
SPEAKER_1:  So I think that that's where you find people manipulating versus.
SPEAKER_1:  manipulating religion.
SPEAKER_1:  to justify sick ideologies.
SPEAKER_1:  that are based.
SPEAKER_1:  and thrive in political instability.
SPEAKER_0:  So these are fundamentally political geopolitical conflicts.
SPEAKER_1:  Not religious conflicts. Absolutely. Look, when you talk about a group like ISIS.
SPEAKER_1:  Islam has been in Iraq for a very, very long time.
SPEAKER_1:  Iraq has been bombed by now five consecutive presidents.
SPEAKER_1:  or four.
SPEAKER_1:  It's been.
SPEAKER_1:  bombed into the stone ages.
SPEAKER_1:  there is no political infrastructure.
SPEAKER_1:  devastation and destruction.
SPEAKER_1:  and desperation as a result of that.
SPEAKER_1:  Many of the old Saddam loyalists and Saddam's regime was a secularist regime.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, are now heads of ISIS, right? It just moved into that.
SPEAKER_1:  when you create that type of chaos.
SPEAKER_1:  you generate.
SPEAKER_1:  and environments.
SPEAKER_1:  Where...
SPEAKER_1:  groups like ISIS are bound to rise out of.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  Islam did not.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, cause this.
SPEAKER_1:  People didn't wake up in Iraq one day and say, hey, let's create a group called ISIS.
SPEAKER_1:  because Islam tells us to.
SPEAKER_1:  Alright.
SPEAKER_1:  Iraq was bombed.
SPEAKER_1:  into.
SPEAKER_1:  this place.
SPEAKER_1:  and we have to.
SPEAKER_1:  Not just.
SPEAKER_1:  free religion.
SPEAKER_1:  from.
SPEAKER_1:  the responsibility from having to bear the responsibility.
SPEAKER_1:  of much of.
SPEAKER_1:  the hatred and violence.
SPEAKER_1:  but we have to interrogate.
SPEAKER_1:  The.
SPEAKER_1:  political instability that was caused.
SPEAKER_1:  where we justified.
SPEAKER_1:  as Americans.
SPEAKER_1:  These are taxpayer dollars.
SPEAKER_1:  were we justified.
SPEAKER_1:  with what was done in Iraq.
SPEAKER_1:  Do we even know what was done in Iraq and Afghanistan?
SPEAKER_1:  These drones that...
SPEAKER_1:  drop.
SPEAKER_1:  using our tax dollars under Democratic and Republican regimes.
SPEAKER_1:  End.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  thousands of innocent people.
SPEAKER_1:  in weddings in Yemen and Somalia.
SPEAKER_1:  Are these justified?
SPEAKER_1:  When you think about dehumanization.
SPEAKER_1:  Can the average American name a single victim of the Iraq War?
SPEAKER_1:  Is there a picture that comes to your mind? Is there a person? Absolutely not, because that's the dehumanization.
SPEAKER_1:  I often talk about Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.
SPEAKER_1:  his progression.
SPEAKER_1:  as a faith leader in America, as a political leader in America.
SPEAKER_1:  Dr. King was deeply unpopular when he took his stand on Vietnam.
SPEAKER_1:  and he mentions how first.
SPEAKER_1:  He had to see.
SPEAKER_1:  Vietnam.
SPEAKER_1:  through the lens of the soldiers, because many of the soldiers that were lost, they were American soldiers, right? And that was...
SPEAKER_1:  That was a crime that they were sent to fight a war that they should not have been sent to fight.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  there was an injustice that was done towards them. He said, but things really changed when he started to see it from the other side of the bullet.
SPEAKER_1:  when he started to see the world.
SPEAKER_1:  through.
SPEAKER_1:  Vietnam through the Vietnamese child.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's where...
SPEAKER_1:  he resorted to breaking the silence.
SPEAKER_1:  That's where he changed his tune.
SPEAKER_1:  Because we dehumanize our victims so much that they're not even relevant to our discourse.
SPEAKER_1:  until they become able villains.
SPEAKER_1:  to our story.
SPEAKER_1:  And then now they're attacking us because they hate us.
SPEAKER_1:  Now they're blowing us up because they hate us. Their religion tells them to do this to us. What have we allowed to be done to them?
SPEAKER_1:  using our tax dollars.
SPEAKER_1:  in our name.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that we have to interrogate.
SPEAKER_1:  the political chaos that was caused.
SPEAKER_1:  Not just.
SPEAKER_1:  not just free religion.
SPEAKER_1:  from.
SPEAKER_1:  the groups that were created.
SPEAKER_1:  But what
SPEAKER_1:  was done.
SPEAKER_1:  to those countries and what continues to be done in many of these places. If winner
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  the pride that people had about America.
SPEAKER_0:  where everybody came together after 9-11 and there was all the American flags.
SPEAKER_0:  That was beautiful to see, but then you have to transfer that.
SPEAKER_0:  And I wish all of us
SPEAKER_0:  Americans could go and see.
SPEAKER_0:  the daughters that would lose their parents, the parents that would lose their daughters and sons because bombs dropped.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  the thousands, the tens of thousands of civilians that died.
SPEAKER_0:  in Afghanistan and in Iraq because of the decisions made.
SPEAKER_0:  in the name of politics, like if we just met those families.
SPEAKER_0:  And if we empathize with them.
SPEAKER_0:  and just put ourselves in their place.
SPEAKER_0:  It's impossible not to feel hate.
SPEAKER_0:  for America for Everybody.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I visited Ukraine and spoke to a lot of Ukrainians and.
SPEAKER_0:  They said, um...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there's...
SPEAKER_0:  There's loved ones that are Russians before the war.
SPEAKER_0:  But now...
SPEAKER_0:  All they have is hate.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you ask many of them, will they ever forgive? Not not.
SPEAKER_0:  Not the regime.
SPEAKER_0:  not the soldiers who will ever forgive Russians.
SPEAKER_0:  Many of them say never.
SPEAKER_0:  and that never...
SPEAKER_0:  feels like it's a generational.
SPEAKER_0:  Never.
SPEAKER_1:  Hmm.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, look.
SPEAKER_1:  You think about this.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, if your grandparents were wiped out in a drone attack, your parents...
SPEAKER_1:  your brothers, your sisters, all of your loved ones, and you're missing a leg and an eye.
SPEAKER_1:  and the world does not take you into consideration, you'll never be seen or considered in the halls of Congress are discussed.
SPEAKER_1:  What are you gonna grow up with?
SPEAKER_1:  But the thing is, is that we should not be speaking about this only from the standpoint of, oh shoot, they're going to grow up and hate us.
SPEAKER_1:  we should be thinking about what was done to them.
SPEAKER_1:  and hate that.
SPEAKER_1:  despise that.
SPEAKER_1:  that it's ugly.
SPEAKER_1:  you see when people carry out a terrorist attack.
SPEAKER_1:  They're not considering.
SPEAKER_1:  lives of the civilians in these places. So those that perpetrate the 9-11 attacks are not seen.
SPEAKER_1:  the thousands of people that they killed.
SPEAKER_1:  the human beings, the lives, many of whom are Muslim by the way.
SPEAKER_1:  actually no.
SPEAKER_1:  One of them was a very active Muslim.
SPEAKER_1:  Islamic Circle of North America.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean.
SPEAKER_1:  They didn't see those stories, right?
SPEAKER_1:  when you drop a bomb.
SPEAKER_1:  on this many people, when you drone people.
SPEAKER_1:  and you say, oops, collateral damage.
SPEAKER_1:  We were looking for one person.
SPEAKER_1:  killed 40 people.
SPEAKER_1:  and there's no count.
SPEAKER_1:  No names.
SPEAKER_1:  Nothing that can be recalled in the American memory.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a problem.
SPEAKER_1:  a fundamental issue with how we treat the rest of the world.
SPEAKER_1:  Right?
SPEAKER_1:  I'm an American. I've.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that I'm responsible.
SPEAKER_1:  to the extent that I have to critique these policies.
SPEAKER_1:  And I have to try to challenge.
SPEAKER_1:  America to deal with the world differently.
SPEAKER_1:  And when I go overseas...
SPEAKER_1:  when I'm around Muslims in the Muslim world, right? in the Middle East and in the Muslim world.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I have to, I'm speaking as a Palestinian.
SPEAKER_1:  American Muslim who grew up in South Louisiana. I've got a
SPEAKER_1:  complex.
SPEAKER_1:  background here, right? A lot of experiences here that I'm grateful for because they all contribute.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  who i who i am and who what i know when and what i've been i think they're all enriching
SPEAKER_1:  I wouldn't relinquish the Palestinian part.
SPEAKER_1:  I wouldn't relinquish.
SPEAKER_1:  the American part and I certainly wouldn't relinquish the Muslim part.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's...
SPEAKER_1:  helping people consider.
SPEAKER_1:  what they're not seeing.
SPEAKER_1:  and when you can dehumanize entire groups of people.
SPEAKER_1:  to where you can.
SPEAKER_1:  reduce them to chalk.
SPEAKER_1:  Casualty counts.
SPEAKER_1:  and not be able to recall a single story.
SPEAKER_1:  then
SPEAKER_1:  You have to take a step back and ask yourself, what are we becoming?
SPEAKER_1:  What are we becoming? Not a single victim of Afghanistan or Iraq.
SPEAKER_1:  millions of people.
SPEAKER_1:  Not a single person.
SPEAKER_1:  in the average American.
SPEAKER_1:  conjuring their head.
SPEAKER_0:  If you apply...
SPEAKER_0:  this to a very difficult topic of Israel and Palestine.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of which, right?
SPEAKER_0:  You have been critical of the policies of the state of Israel, but...
SPEAKER_0:  as we've mentioned, very supportive of Jewish people.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of friends, rabbis and
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Jews in general here in Dallas and across the world.
SPEAKER_0:  What is the difference to you in that part of the world between politics and religion? Well, in this case,
SPEAKER_0:  Zionism and Judaism, both terms broadly defined.
SPEAKER_1:  Both terms broadly defined.
SPEAKER_0:  I say that because those terms...
SPEAKER_0:  There's technical definitions and there's other.
SPEAKER_0:  popularly used and so you have to be kind of just like we said with Islamophobia
SPEAKER_0:  These terms are...
SPEAKER_0:  they become politicized.
SPEAKER_0:  So just generally speaking, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Zionism.
SPEAKER_0:  has to do with politics and Judaism.
SPEAKER_1:  the best into it. Yeah. It's the great complexity like to a lot of people like, wait a minute.
SPEAKER_1:  Right. And you got to take a step back and wonder why there are so many Zionist anti-Semites in America.
SPEAKER_1:  Ha ha.
SPEAKER_1:  and there are so many.
SPEAKER_1:  anti-Zionists who are far from being.
SPEAKER_1:  anti-Semites, anti-Zionism that are opposed to the ideology that are opposed to
SPEAKER_1:  the implications of it.
SPEAKER_1:  Look, I think that it's fundamentally secular.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, when you think about it, there is an ethnosupremacism there is.
SPEAKER_1:  I am the child of-
SPEAKER_1:  of.
SPEAKER_1:  Palestinians that were forcibly displaced.
SPEAKER_1:  I've never been able to go to where my parents, my grandparents are from.
SPEAKER_1:  I've never been able to see that land. I've never been able to access that. I have cousins that I'll never be. Well, I shouldn't say never. Insha'Allah, God willing, I will meet them.
SPEAKER_1:  but that I've only been able to speak through a phone.
SPEAKER_1:  FaceTime, Zoom.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that.
SPEAKER_1:  It's important for us to separate.
SPEAKER_1:  criticism.
SPEAKER_1:  of Israel's policies.
SPEAKER_1:  from antisemitism. In fact, it's an injustice.
SPEAKER_1:  cheapens anti-Semitism.
SPEAKER_1:  when you...
SPEAKER_1:  Throw every.
SPEAKER_1:  person.
SPEAKER_1:  who is opposed to Zionism or opposed to Israel's policies.
SPEAKER_1:  in the bucket of being anti-semites.
SPEAKER_1:  It's wrong. It cheapens it. It doesn't.
SPEAKER_1:  do justice to it.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's important for us to have a meaningful conversation about.
SPEAKER_1:  America's support for Israel.
SPEAKER_1:  Listen, there are terms.
SPEAKER_1:  that are important here. I'ma throw out these big terms, right?
SPEAKER_1:  Apartheid.
SPEAKER_1:  Occupation.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Ethnic cleansing. These are terms.
SPEAKER_1:  that are legal terms.
SPEAKER_1:  There are objective thresholds here.
SPEAKER_1:  for apartheid.
SPEAKER_1:  occupation.
SPEAKER_1:  ethnic cleansing.
SPEAKER_1:  The Threshold of Apartheid
SPEAKER_1:  has been crossed according to
SPEAKER_1:  multiple, the most respectable human rights organizations in the world. These are the organizations that you will champion and that you will use.
SPEAKER_1:  and every single other conflict to justify your own policies.
SPEAKER_1:  but that threshold of apartheid has been passed. According to Human Rights Watch, according to Amnesty International, according to the Harvard Law Review.
SPEAKER_1:  The threshold of apartheid has been crossed. There's a legal terminology there.
SPEAKER_1:  sets of laws for two separate people.
SPEAKER_1:  you have a displaced people.
SPEAKER_1:  that are forcibly
SPEAKER_1:  being removed that are being treated differently that are.
SPEAKER_1:  stateless.
SPEAKER_1:  that are.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, undergoing.
SPEAKER_1:  daily humiliation.
SPEAKER_1:  that live behind an apartheid wall.
SPEAKER_1:  that live under a different set of policies that are routinely bombarded.
SPEAKER_1:  that have lost their ability to free movement, that have lost their ability to access to basic necessities of human life.
SPEAKER_1:  There are legal definitions here.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't see how any objective human being can read those reports on apartheid and the threshold crossed for apartheid and walk away from that and say that this is just Jews and Muslims that don't like each other.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a legal definition here, occupation.
SPEAKER_1:  when Israel was created in 1948.
SPEAKER_1:  you will find many Jews who are opposed to Zionism, and I think this is important.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  to talk to Jews who are opposed to Zionism, and they are many.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  that will say that we were told that it was a land without a people.
SPEAKER_1:  for a people without a land.
SPEAKER_1:  The problem with that was...
SPEAKER_1:  There were people there.
SPEAKER_1:  our ancestors.
SPEAKER_1:  750,000 Palestinians expelled in the Nakba.
SPEAKER_1:  and many Palestinians.
SPEAKER_1:  that have been removed and harassed.
SPEAKER_1:  End
SPEAKER_1:  that are treated.
SPEAKER_1:  in horrific ways and the occupation is expanding. It is an illegal occupation. Settlements are still expanding.
SPEAKER_1:  and the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  enables that occupation.
SPEAKER_1:  with its funding.
SPEAKER_1:  with its unconditional support, unwavering support of Israel.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  It does so.
SPEAKER_1:  in a way that completely undermines.
SPEAKER_1:  any of its claims.
SPEAKER_1:  being a beacon of freedom in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  because it is in plain sight now.
SPEAKER_1:  that the world can see.
SPEAKER_1:  What is happening in Sheikh Jarrah? What is happening in Jerusalem? What is happening with these expanding settlements?
SPEAKER_1:  everything that flies in the face of any claim to wanting a peaceful solution.
SPEAKER_1:  children in Gaza when I talk about dehumanization.
SPEAKER_1:  The children?
SPEAKER_1:  that were on the face of the New York Times, which is historically.
SPEAKER_1:  one of the most anti-Palestinian
SPEAKER_1:  newspapers in America.
SPEAKER_1:  the faces of the children of Gaza.
SPEAKER_1:  America
SPEAKER_1:  and many parts of the world are now seeing it.
SPEAKER_1:  We have been saying for a very long time.
SPEAKER_1:  This is apartheid. This is an occupation. This is an injustice. The world needs to check it, hold it accountable.
SPEAKER_1:  South Africa.
SPEAKER_1:  which experienced apartheid Nelson Mandela, Desmond Tutu, all of those that fought apartheid in South Africa.
SPEAKER_1:  said that.
SPEAKER_1:  Palestinians are living under apartheid.
SPEAKER_1:  and that the same strategies that check the apartheid in South Africa.
SPEAKER_1:  need to be used to hold Israel accountable.
SPEAKER_1:  for apartheid.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... with the palestinians
SPEAKER_1:  It's impossible for us.
SPEAKER_1:  as Palestinians.
SPEAKER_1:  simply say
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  We should give up on this cause.
SPEAKER_1:  because all the odds are stacked against us.
SPEAKER_1:  But when you have...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, videos coming out of the Israeli army.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  spewing skunk water.
SPEAKER_1:  skunk water.
SPEAKER_1:  sewage water on worshippers leaving Al-Aqsa.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  far-right leaders.
SPEAKER_1:  Now taking the government.
SPEAKER_1:  and the so-called only democracy in the Middle East.
SPEAKER_1:  prohibiting a Palestinian flag being raised anywhere around.
SPEAKER_1:  American reporter Serena Abouakla
SPEAKER_1:  Palestinian American Christian Reporter.
SPEAKER_1:  Palestinian-American Christian Reporter, one of the most prominent journalists in the Middle East.
SPEAKER_1:  shot in the face.
SPEAKER_1:  plain sight.
SPEAKER_1:  and all America could say was, all the American government could say was
SPEAKER_1:  If it turns out...
SPEAKER_1:  that it's indeed Israel.
SPEAKER_1:  that Israel is responsible for the death of an American journalist.
SPEAKER_1:  then we will hold them accountable.
SPEAKER_1:  Nothing.
SPEAKER_1:  It was a shame.
SPEAKER_1:  to see that happen and it just solidified.
SPEAKER_1:  to us.
SPEAKER_1:  that whether it's a democratic president.
SPEAKER_1:  or a Republican president.
SPEAKER_1:  Unfortunately, the support for Israel.
SPEAKER_1:  is enabling it.
SPEAKER_1:  to continue.
SPEAKER_1:  to wipe out the Palestinian population.
SPEAKER_1:  from.
SPEAKER_1:  its historic lands. And so.
SPEAKER_1:  We see that happening and I'll say this as well.
SPEAKER_1:  People ask me about the Abraham Accords.
SPEAKER_1:  I say, you know...
SPEAKER_1:  You are.
SPEAKER_1:  talking about faith between.
SPEAKER_1:  Are you talking about peace between communities of faith and protecting communities of faith? Why are you opposed to the Abraham Accords? I think that the name of Abraham.
SPEAKER_1:  should not be used and I wrote an article called Why I Opposed the Abraham Accords. The name of Abraham should not be used to justify arms deals.
SPEAKER_1:  that only further disenfranchised the abused population of the Palestinians.
SPEAKER_1:  where
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  You have.
SPEAKER_1:  quote unquote, Muslim regimes making peace with Israel and that's being used.
SPEAKER_1:  against.
SPEAKER_1:  the Palestinian people who are.
SPEAKER_1:  only further disenfranchised.
SPEAKER_1:  from having a voice in their own fate.
SPEAKER_1:  for the sake of American arms deals.
SPEAKER_1:  and security.
SPEAKER_1:  and economic benefits.
SPEAKER_1:  It's despicable. It's repulsive.
SPEAKER_1:  talk to the people.
SPEAKER_1:  speak to people on the ground there.
SPEAKER_1:  see what's happening with your own two eyes and think about the injustice where.
SPEAKER_1:  our taxpayer dollars are being used.
SPEAKER_1:  to suppress a people and what legally meets the definition by every objective standard of apartheid.
SPEAKER_1:  of occupation.
SPEAKER_1:  of ethnic cleansing.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's ongoing and it's happening in real time and it's becoming more blatant.
SPEAKER_1:  with.
SPEAKER_1:  a redeem now that's unapologetic of even expressing.
SPEAKER_1:  what the policies.
SPEAKER_1:  have already done.
SPEAKER_1:  And that is the removal of a people.
SPEAKER_1:  forcible removal of a people because
SPEAKER_1:  The government knows that the United States support is unconditional.
SPEAKER_1:  I hope you have hope.
SPEAKER_0:  that Jews, Muslims and Christians on this land will.
SPEAKER_0:  Live in peace one day.
SPEAKER_0:  together.
SPEAKER_0:  basic respect for each other's humanity.
SPEAKER_1:  Look.
SPEAKER_1:  This isn't a religious conflict.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that's.
SPEAKER_1:  fundamentally one of the problems.
SPEAKER_1:  So even the question is...
SPEAKER_0:  not the correct question.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not the correct question. This videos may have gotten your returns for ios black shoots or fly out of the pan...
SPEAKER_1:  Not a religious conflict. Yes, religion is invoked. Yes, there.
SPEAKER_1:  there are religious elements.
SPEAKER_1:  but
SPEAKER_1:  There are many dues.
SPEAKER_1:  that are opposed.
SPEAKER_1:  to what is happening right now towards the Palestinians, many.
SPEAKER_1:  recommend.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, serious discussion with even people whose perspectives have grown. Peter Beinert being an example.
SPEAKER_1:  Rabbi Simone Zimmerman.
SPEAKER_1:  started if not now.
SPEAKER_1:  Beta Slim.
SPEAKER_1:  an Israeli human rights organization that also classed it as apartheid recently. There are many Jews that are opposed to what is happening right now.
SPEAKER_1:  Palestinians are also not exclusively a Muslim population. Sharia number, I thought it was Christian.
SPEAKER_1:  there are many Palestinian Christians.
SPEAKER_1:  that are also being denied entry into their historic churches and that are completely
SPEAKER_1:  bewildered.
SPEAKER_1:  or or
SPEAKER_1:  uh, absolutely lost in regards to why.
SPEAKER_1:  American evangelicals have this ironclad support for.
SPEAKER_1:  the occupation and have ignored the plight of Palestinian Christians.
SPEAKER_1:  Of course, I believe Muslims, Christians and Jews can coexist.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Of course I have hope.
SPEAKER_1:  because I have to have hope as a person of faith.
SPEAKER_1:  but as much hope as I have.
SPEAKER_1:  I think there's a great sense of urgency for people to open their eyes.
SPEAKER_1:  Learn what's actually happening on the ground. Read the reports.
SPEAKER_1:  Stop letting these.
SPEAKER_1:  commentators and these companies that.
SPEAKER_1:  are able to generate propaganda.
SPEAKER_1:  own the narrative.
SPEAKER_1:  There are objective standards here. There are objective standards here.
SPEAKER_1:  Measures.
SPEAKER_1:  of oppression.
SPEAKER_1:  that need to be considered here.
SPEAKER_1:  What's happening to Gaza?
SPEAKER_1:  is one of the greatest atrocities.
SPEAKER_1:  of our time.
SPEAKER_1:  Learn about it.
SPEAKER_1:  I'd tell people to just watch.
SPEAKER_1:  The Vice documentaries, for example, the mini documentaries, I'd sent them to you as well.
SPEAKER_1:  inside the battle for Jerusalem. I mean
SPEAKER_1:  Think about it, a guy from Long Island, New York.
SPEAKER_1:  can fly.
SPEAKER_1:  to Israel.
SPEAKER_1:  Right?
SPEAKER_1:  flying to Tel Aviv.
SPEAKER_1:  and walk into a home that's been occupied by families for generations and throw the people out under the full protection of the military there.
SPEAKER_1:  and spit on them.
SPEAKER_1:  historic homes.
SPEAKER_1:  And when people come up to me and say we're opposed to Islamophobia.
SPEAKER_1:  We're opposed to Islamophobia, but they support that.
SPEAKER_1:  you're not opposed to Islamophobia. How can you be opposed to Islamophobia when you...
SPEAKER_1:  traffic in the same framings.
SPEAKER_1:  end.
SPEAKER_1:  dehumanization.
SPEAKER_1:  dot.
SPEAKER_1:  enables the viciousness towards Muslims here and Palestinians over there.
SPEAKER_1:  they do not deserve.
SPEAKER_1:  to be treated like equal human beings, like full human beings.
SPEAKER_1:  and that based on historic claims, a guy can fly from New York.
SPEAKER_1:  into a historic neighborhood in Jerusalem.
SPEAKER_1:  and kick out generational families.
SPEAKER_1:  with military guns next to them. What does that sound like? How's that?
SPEAKER_1:  How's that normal?
SPEAKER_1:  Right. And so I think that if people
SPEAKER_1:  take the time to read.
SPEAKER_1:  People take the time to investigate.
SPEAKER_1:  Then
SPEAKER_1:  They come to this conclusion.
SPEAKER_1:  themselves that this is unacceptable.
SPEAKER_1:  and that you can't put...
SPEAKER_1:  And this is one of the problems with the framing of Israel-Palestine.
SPEAKER_1:  is that you're equating occupier and occupied.
SPEAKER_1:  You're equating the two sides of the conflict.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's not a conflict, it's an occupation.
SPEAKER_1:  There is such a disparity of power here.
SPEAKER_1:  that you cannot equate the two sides.
SPEAKER_1:  how you know you can.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, Malcolm X would say you clip the bird's wing and then blame it for not flying as high as you do.
SPEAKER_1:  You can't do that to a people and just equate them.
SPEAKER_1:  with their occupier.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  It's an atrocity. It requires us to challenge it.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  I am-
SPEAKER_1:  hopeful.
SPEAKER_1:  current movement of Muslims, Christians and Jews and people of all faiths.
SPEAKER_1:  that are saying enough is enough.
SPEAKER_1:  Thresholds have been crossed here.
SPEAKER_1:  that this is an atrocity that cannot continue.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  This is very personal to me because this is happening now.
SPEAKER_1:  What I anticipate, and this is what America did, this is what Nelson Mandela actually predicted with the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  What I anticipate is that.
SPEAKER_1:  10 years from now, 20 years from now.
SPEAKER_1:  Every American will say, how could we have supported this?
SPEAKER_1:  And this was terrible.
SPEAKER_1:  and we'll pay.
SPEAKER_1:  symbolic.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, homage to the Palestinian cause.
SPEAKER_1:  But there are people now.
SPEAKER_1:  that are clinging on for dear life.
SPEAKER_1:  Access to their places of worship.
SPEAKER_1:  access to their generational homes.
SPEAKER_1:  Right now, there are children that are in detention.
SPEAKER_1:  and there's a bill in Congress.
SPEAKER_1:  to just stop, I mean.
SPEAKER_1:  Wherever you stand on this issue.
SPEAKER_1:  child detainment.
SPEAKER_1:  Tile detainment, tile detention.
SPEAKER_1:  should be a red line, right?
SPEAKER_1:  Congresswoman Betty McCollum has put this bill on the floor of Congress. She can't even get that passed.
SPEAKER_1:  All right, just to at least censure.
SPEAKER_1:  child detainment.
SPEAKER_1:  by the idea.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  People need to look into this deeper.
SPEAKER_1:  They need to.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  Consider the human element of this.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  consider the urgency of it as well with this new, with this new regime, it's only going to unfortunately get.
SPEAKER_1:  get much worse in the immediate term and so we have to do something about it.
SPEAKER_0:  If I may ask you for some advice.
SPEAKER_0:  for a reason not.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll explain maybe in a little bit.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... maybe i should just explain now which is i think
SPEAKER_0:  because you've talked about Islamophobia, because you've been at the center of Islamophobia,
SPEAKER_0:  so many catastrophic events because you sort of jump into the fire.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, to try to help people.
SPEAKER_0:  You've been attacked a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  Just in general, you've been under stress. It's just...
SPEAKER_0:  You're not immune to stress. So I'll just read some of the comments.
SPEAKER_0:  Part of me wants to ask.
SPEAKER_0:  just how psychologically difficult it's been and where you draw strength.
SPEAKER_0:  And would you advise?
SPEAKER_0:  If the opportunity is there.
SPEAKER_0:  for a person like me.
SPEAKER_0:  for silly kid in a suit.
SPEAKER_0:  to go to that part of the world and take seriously conversations.
SPEAKER_0:  I would divide it into two categories. There's leaders and there's people.
SPEAKER_0:  The leaders are sort of these.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  political entities that have their interests, they also have power.
SPEAKER_0:  and they want to hold on to power.
SPEAKER_0:  and then people are just...
SPEAKER_0:  regular people that have.
SPEAKER_0:  families that just want to
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  have basic rights and freedoms and continue to love their families and practice, and pursues
SPEAKER_0:  jobs and careers and lives that they can flourish and so on. Those are very kind of different dynamics of play.
SPEAKER_0:  and if given the opportunity to speak to leaders for me.
SPEAKER_0:  Would you advise I do it or not?
SPEAKER_0:  or not, and when I say leaders, I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  leaders that
SPEAKER_0:  would make the case.
SPEAKER_0:  pro-Zionist case?
SPEAKER_0:  and the anti-Zinus case. And in both cases, I would...
SPEAKER_0:  make it a very challenging conversations for both of them. unlike today.
SPEAKER_0:  Our conversation today, you're an inspiring, incredible person.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm a huge fan of yours.
SPEAKER_0:  You spread so much love to the Muslim community here.
SPEAKER_0:  to the Jewish community, just everybody loves you.
SPEAKER_1:  but not everybody.
SPEAKER_1:  None. Yes, that's true. Not everybody. That's true. But a lot of people love you.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, but this was kind of inspiring and a positive conversation. Wasn't very challenging.
SPEAKER_0:  Now although we did
SPEAKER_0:  tough, touch, challenging topics and he did exceptionally well there. But I would do very challenging conversation with those leaders in that part of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Is that a bad idea?
SPEAKER_1:  All right, well, let me tell you from now, first and foremost.
SPEAKER_1:  the first part because I don't want to lose the first part of your
SPEAKER_1:  your conversation. Is it?
SPEAKER_1:  psychologically.
SPEAKER_1:  stressful.
SPEAKER_1:  Very.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  But when you're
SPEAKER_1:  when you're a person of faith.
SPEAKER_1:  And you believe that.
SPEAKER_1:  Good work will always be rewarded.
SPEAKER_1:  And that doing the right thing will always be rewarded eventually.
SPEAKER_1:  you're able to.
SPEAKER_1:  weather.
SPEAKER_1:  That storm.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  quite a bit.
SPEAKER_1:  So your wife told you.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, that's the second thing. Okay. Right. That's the second thing I was going to mention is honestly supportive.
SPEAKER_1:  supportive family. You know, my dad's 80 men.
SPEAKER_1:  And he's been through a lot. He was born in 1943 before his five years before Israel was even created. He was born in Palestine.
SPEAKER_1:  He's suffered displacement. He has.
SPEAKER_1:  been around the world and somehow built himself up to be.
SPEAKER_1:  a distinguished professor of chemistry, an author and inventor.
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, grew up.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, taking on some of the most difficult challenges and was just always a man of.
SPEAKER_1:  I always admired my dad being a man of principle. And like, he just tells me, man, stay the course, stay the course, stay the course, don't be afraid, don't back down.
SPEAKER_1:  I have a supportive family. I have a supportive wife. I've got supportive kids.
SPEAKER_1:  So I have amazing people around me.
SPEAKER_1:  that keep me grounded for sure.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Ultimately, obviously, faith.
SPEAKER_1:  And also I'll say this slander doesn't stand.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you mean by that?
SPEAKER_1:  when people slander you and it kind of comes with the territory of a public mirror.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not going to stand.
SPEAKER_1:  throughout time because eventually any sincere person will find the truth.
SPEAKER_1:  And the only people that will regurgitate that will continue to do so. So when I get portrayed as.
SPEAKER_1:  and antisemite.
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  because of my strong takes on Israel and challenging Israel. And I will continue to do so.
SPEAKER_1:  It takes just.
SPEAKER_1:  people in Dallas, like we know him, what are you talking about?
SPEAKER_1:  You know?
SPEAKER_1:  So slander doesn't stand at least with the people that are important to you.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, it might reside on the internet. It might have great rankings and.
SPEAKER_1:  social media bots that give attraction.
SPEAKER_0:  but is that psychologically difficult to you to have that?
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, it is difficult.
SPEAKER_1:  It's very difficult and it's hurtful.
SPEAKER_1:  especially when it comes from quarters that you.
SPEAKER_1:  would hope that it doesn't come from.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you take a step back, you.
SPEAKER_1:  Re-evaluate.
SPEAKER_1:  You lean into your faith and you lean on the people that are closest to you and then you keep going.
SPEAKER_1:  You learned the lessons.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, could I be doing something better? Could I be doing something different? Could I be saying something better? Could I be saying something different?
SPEAKER_1:  are the noble causes that I want to achieve? Am I, am I doing justice by those causes? Uh, how do I grow out of this? Right. You become wiser.
SPEAKER_1:  through these things as well.
SPEAKER_1:  The second part of your question though about what you should do.
SPEAKER_1:  If you're going to talk to people, talk to people.
SPEAKER_1:  from a place of inquiry, I would say talk to people.
SPEAKER_1:  more so than leaders.
SPEAKER_1:  And especially some of those who have been erased from the media commentary. Benjamin Netanyahu gets a lot of airtime.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... you know here in the united states uh... he's
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Well spoken.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, he speaks perfect English, he's an American as well.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  I would challenge him.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, on, on, on some of the things that he has said and done.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, he has an ongoing corruption case. I think that.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, I think he's a fascist. I think that he's a, uh, a person who has done much evil. I think that he has a lot of blood on his hands. And I think that.
SPEAKER_1:  One day he will be prosecuted for that.
SPEAKER_1:  But I'd say talk to people on the ground.
SPEAKER_1:  and people that have been erased, talk to the families that are being displaced. I don't care about the political leadership. I'd much rather you talk to the people.
SPEAKER_1:  on the ground in East Jerusalem.
SPEAKER_1:  that have been displaced.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  the families, talk to Palestinian Christians, talk to the sister of Shalina Abu Akla, Lina Abu Akla who has been.
SPEAKER_1:  Who was.
SPEAKER_1:  extremely.
SPEAKER_1:  disappointed and let down.
SPEAKER_1:  on Joe Biden.
SPEAKER_1:  went to.
SPEAKER_1:  the region.
SPEAKER_1:  and did not take her calls, did not meet her, which was an absolutely disgraceful move. He should have met with her.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, she's the sister of an American journalist who was murdered in cold blood.
SPEAKER_1:  Talk to Lena Abouakla, talk to Mitri Rahib.
SPEAKER_1:  Mithri, interesting person for example, is a Lutheran.
SPEAKER_1:  ahead of the Lutheran Church in Palestine.
SPEAKER_1:  He comes to Dallas sometimes and talks about the plight of Palestinian Christians.
SPEAKER_1:  I think if you're talking to people in leadership.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, obviously...
SPEAKER_1:  There are some that will be able to represent themselves in English. You know, Hanan Ashrawi is a very eloquent person, for example.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if you're going to have any luck getting into Gaza, but I'll pray for you if you do. But obviously, you know, if you want to talk to everybody, you got to talk to everybody, man. So I don't know, butessa.
SPEAKER_0:  say this very important way to say
SPEAKER_0:  whitewashing because I've heard this a lot so also Ukraine and Russia
SPEAKER_0:  There's an interesting line between weight washing.
SPEAKER_0:  which is something you definitely should not do.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  a deep empathy.
SPEAKER_0:  for
SPEAKER_0:  a large number of human beings.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a really tricky line to walk. And I also disagree with you about, well, I think-
SPEAKER_0:  and an officer disagreement.
SPEAKER_0:  I think I disagree about leaders. I think I agree 100% that the most important people are the people on the ground. OK.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  I think those are extremely important people to understand.
SPEAKER_0:  not just as leaders but as human beings too.
SPEAKER_0:  and in many cases to have a challenging conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  but from a place of empathy.
SPEAKER_0:  from understanding human.
SPEAKER_1:  of being.
SPEAKER_1:  So if you plan to talk to right wing.
SPEAKER_1:  the current leadership of Israel.
SPEAKER_1:  my only request to you.
SPEAKER_1:  is
SPEAKER_1:  talk to the victims themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  Not the Palestinian authority talks to the victim. I know you want to write. So I, and I appreciate them. Talk to the victims themselves. Talk to those people that are being.
SPEAKER_1:  thrown out of their homes.
SPEAKER_1:  and subjected to the daily humiliation, go to a checkpoint.
SPEAKER_1:  and walk through the checkpoint the way that a Palestinian walks through a checkpoint and tell me that's not apartheid.
SPEAKER_1:  Walk through that checkpoint.
SPEAKER_1:  crammed in in cages and tell me it's not apartheid.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, I think you're a very sincere person. Uh, I think you're gonna, you're gonna do your best.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll be praying for you.
SPEAKER_0:  harder than others, but yes, I feel like we're in the middle of a negotiation.
SPEAKER_1:  and we've come to a point where we're both agree.
SPEAKER_1:  Everyone deserves to be everyone.
SPEAKER_1:  Not everyone deserves to be, but I think there's a great value and benefit. Let me say I agree with you in hearing.
SPEAKER_1:  people even.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, tyrants.
SPEAKER_1:  um hearing them.
SPEAKER_1:  so that you can properly deconstruct and decipher what you're hearing.
SPEAKER_1:  But just think of the voices that don't get heard. And a lot of times what's been done to the Muslim world is, and what's being done right now in the name of the Abraham Accords.
SPEAKER_1:  What's wrong with the Palestinians?
SPEAKER_1:  The other Arabs are making peace with them.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me tell you something, those regimes that are signing on to the Abraham Accords, the people are not happy, but they're terrified.
SPEAKER_1:  of challenging those regimes.
SPEAKER_1:  So if you go talk to the leaders of some of these countries that have signed on to the Abraham Accords,
SPEAKER_1:  and that are, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  in some twisted way.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  making this about religion and peace.
SPEAKER_1:  you can greatly.
SPEAKER_1:  Skew.
SPEAKER_1:  the narrative.
SPEAKER_1:  to where Palestinians are just an inherently disagreeable people that don't want peace.
SPEAKER_1:  They just want to live in their homes.
SPEAKER_1:  They just want to live as full, equal human beings.
SPEAKER_1:  They want the things that everybody wants.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  they're only being further disenfranchised. In the name of peace now.
SPEAKER_1:  because voices are being amplified.
SPEAKER_1:  in the name of peace that are suffocating voices for justice.
SPEAKER_1:  He said hope.
SPEAKER_0:  As a man of faith you have hope. What gives you hope about...
SPEAKER_0:  this part of the world and our world in general.
SPEAKER_0:  on you.
SPEAKER_0:  look across and see so much conflict, so much division happening.
SPEAKER_0:  or gives you hope.
SPEAKER_1:  I-
SPEAKER_1:  Think that if you look through history.
SPEAKER_1:  We have been through points as a world.
SPEAKER_1:  Where?
SPEAKER_1:  We almost.
SPEAKER_1:  were not going to exist anymore. If you lived in the time.
SPEAKER_1:  of the Crusades a few.
SPEAKER_1:  lived.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... in some of these darker moments of history
SPEAKER_1:  World War I, World War II, you probably thought you weren't going to come out of this as a world.
SPEAKER_1:  I have hope in God.
SPEAKER_1:  and I have hope.
SPEAKER_1:  that godly people.
SPEAKER_1:  people that are devoted to God and people of righteousness.
SPEAKER_1:  can shift things.
SPEAKER_1:  with his help.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  I also
SPEAKER_1:  I believe that younger people, I hope they'll be different.
SPEAKER_1:  I think younger people.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  Hopefully.
SPEAKER_1:  We're using the word hope a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you might hear it inshallah, God willing.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  We'll see.
SPEAKER_1:  the path that we're heading.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  will seek to disrupt.
SPEAKER_1:  this.
SPEAKER_1:  bleak trajectory.
SPEAKER_1:  and bring it back to something else.
SPEAKER_1:  So here's the thing, we live in a time of hyper-exposure.
SPEAKER_1:  that hyperexposure could paralyze you?
SPEAKER_1:  or it could empower you.
SPEAKER_1:  It could.
SPEAKER_1:  make you completely shut down and say, what's the point?
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  Even trying.
SPEAKER_1:  to help these people out. Why even talk about the Palestinians?
SPEAKER_1:  You got these people here, the Uyghurs, the Rohingya, you got...
SPEAKER_1:  What's happening in Honduras, Guatemala, El Salvador, Brazil.
SPEAKER_1:  South America, Africa, Ethiopia.
SPEAKER_1:  Somalia, it's so much and it can be overwhelming.
SPEAKER_1:  to a person who cares.
SPEAKER_1:  but you ultimately realize.
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  the difference that you can make.
SPEAKER_1:  can become.
SPEAKER_1:  a much greater difference, even if it's after your lifetime.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll tell you actually a story that.
SPEAKER_1:  I remember the first time I went to Syria.
SPEAKER_1:  Syrian refugee camps.
SPEAKER_1:  and you deal with people.
SPEAKER_1:  in this deeply human way.
SPEAKER_1:  out.
SPEAKER_1:  for me the most clarifying parts.
SPEAKER_1:  the world are the refugee camps.
SPEAKER_1:  where I feel the most clarity in life.
SPEAKER_1:  about what I'm supposed to be doing.
SPEAKER_1:  and life.
SPEAKER_1:  You go to the refugee camps and then after you're interacting with these people.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, maybe giving a few people some trailer homes and some
SPEAKER_1:  food and
SPEAKER_1:  something that sustain themselves, coats and blankets you drive out of the refugee camps.
SPEAKER_1:  Back to where you're staying.
SPEAKER_1:  And the camps get bigger and bigger and bigger and bigger and the people get smaller and smaller and smaller and smaller.
SPEAKER_1:  But then you realize...
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  It might be that that small section that I touched.
SPEAKER_1:  is going to be the change that affects all of them.
SPEAKER_1:  What's going to happen to that?
SPEAKER_1:  12 year old boy.
SPEAKER_1:  that has seen.
SPEAKER_1:  the horrors of this world.
SPEAKER_1:  And that is absolutely committed.
SPEAKER_1:  to uplifting.
SPEAKER_1:  his people.
SPEAKER_1:  and bringing about a change.
SPEAKER_1:  being responsible for the plight of his people.
SPEAKER_1:  And so when I look at any.
SPEAKER_1:  section of devastation in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  You never know which part of it that you're going to touch that's going to change everything. By the grace of God, by the help of God.
SPEAKER_1:  So you keep trying to do your part. The Prophet Muhammad peace be upon him said that the most beloved of deeds to God.
SPEAKER_1:  are the consistent ones, even if they're small.
SPEAKER_1:  small act of charity.
SPEAKER_1:  That small smile, that small act of kindness.
SPEAKER_1:  That small prayer.
SPEAKER_1:  might go a long way.
SPEAKER_1:  if he blesses it.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  Keep chipping away, chipping away, chipping away.
SPEAKER_0:  Do not be paralyzed by the scale of the division, just...
SPEAKER_0:  chip away at it.
SPEAKER_0:  chip away at it. Small step at a time. I suppose all of us can do that.
SPEAKER_0:  Young people can do that.
SPEAKER_0:  Just one person at a time, try to help. Just one person at a time, try to help.
SPEAKER_1:  Absolutely.
SPEAKER_0:  Omar, you're an incredible person, you're an inspiration.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I think you mentioned.
SPEAKER_0:  You came to Dallas for a podcast and instead you got a friend.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's an honor to be.
SPEAKER_0:  your new friend and I think it's time to go pray.
SPEAKER_0:  I hope it's okay that I join you in.
SPEAKER_0:  At least in movement.
SPEAKER_1:  Absolutely. Thank you so much. I appreciate you coming down. It's been an absolute pleasure.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  You're having to
SPEAKER_1:  Qa'taniya kitaba waj'alani nabiya waj'alani mubarakana inama hum
SPEAKER_1:  And he has guided me through prayer and zakat, as long as I am alive And he was kind to my mother, and he has not made me a tyrant or a wretched man And peace be upon me on the day I was born and on the day I die and on the day I am resurrected alive. Allah
SPEAKER_1:  Allah!
SPEAKER_1:  Allah Akbar
SPEAKER_1:  Salamu alaikum wa rahmatullah
SPEAKER_1:  Watch.
SPEAKER_1:  Sure you don't want to come back? Do a round two? Yeah!
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_0:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with Omar Suleiman.
SPEAKER_0:  To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_0:  And now.
SPEAKER_0:  Let me leave you some words.
SPEAKER_0:  from Muhammad Ali.
SPEAKER_0:  Impossible is just a big word.
SPEAKER_0:  thrown around by small men.
SPEAKER_0:  who find it easier to live in a world they've been given.
SPEAKER_0:  and to explore the power they have to change it.
SPEAKER_0:  Impossible is not a fact.
SPEAKER_0:  is an opinion.
SPEAKER_0:  Impossible is not a declaration.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a dare.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you for listening and hope to see you.
SPEAKER_0:  next time.