SPEAKER_0:  Why weren't we pushing towards economic fusion and new materials and new...
SPEAKER_0:  methods of heat extraction and so forth because everybody knew fusion was 40 years away.
SPEAKER_0:  and now it's four years away.
SPEAKER_0:  following is a conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  with Dennis White.
SPEAKER_1:  nuclear physicist at MIT.
SPEAKER_1:  and the Director of the MIT Plasma Science and Fusion Center.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the Lex Friedman Podcast.
SPEAKER_1:  to support it, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now, to your friends.
SPEAKER_1:  Here's Dennis.
SPEAKER_1:  white.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's start with a big question.
SPEAKER_0:  What is nuclear fusion? It's the underlying process that powers the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  So as the name implies.
SPEAKER_0:  It fuses together or brings together.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  different elements.
SPEAKER_0:  technically nuclei.
SPEAKER_0:  that come together.
SPEAKER_0:  and if you can...
SPEAKER_0:  push them together close enough that you can trigger essentially a reaction.
SPEAKER_0:  What happens is that the
SPEAKER_0:  The element typically changes, so this means that you change from one element to another, chemical element to another.
SPEAKER_0:  Underlying what this means is that you change the nuclear structure.
SPEAKER_0:  This rearrangement through E equals MC squared releases large amounts of energy.
SPEAKER_0:  So Fusion...
SPEAKER_0:  is the fusing together.
SPEAKER_0:  of lighter elements into heavier elements.
SPEAKER_0:  And when you go through it, you say, oh, look, so here were the initial elements.
SPEAKER_0:  Typically hydrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  They had a particular mass, rest mass.
SPEAKER_0:  which means just the mass with no kinetic energy. And when you look at the product afterwards, it has less rest mass.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you go, well, how is that possible? Because you have to keep mass, but mass and energy are the same thing.
SPEAKER_0:  which is what E equals MC squared means.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  The conversion of this comes into kinetic energy, namely energy that you can use in some way.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's what happens in the center of stars.
SPEAKER_0:  So fusion is literally the reason life is.
SPEAKER_0:  is viable in the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  So fusion.
SPEAKER_1:  It's happening in our sun.
SPEAKER_0:  And what are the elements?
SPEAKER_0:  The elements are hydrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  that are coming together.
SPEAKER_0:  It goes through a process which is probably gets a little bit.
SPEAKER_0:  too detailed but...
SPEAKER_0:  It's a somewhat-
SPEAKER_0:  complex catalyzed process that happens in the center of stars.
SPEAKER_0:  But in the end, stars are big balls of hydrogen, which is the lightest, the simplest element, the lightest element, the most abundant element, most of the universe is hydrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's essentially a sequence through which
SPEAKER_0:  these processes occur that you end up with helium.
SPEAKER_0:  So those are the primary things. And the reason for this is because...
SPEAKER_0:  helium has features as a nucleus, like the interior part of the atom.
SPEAKER_0:  that is extremely stable.
SPEAKER_0:  And the reason for this is helium has two protons and two neutrons. These are the things that make up nuclei that make up all of us.
SPEAKER_0:  along with electrons and because it has two pairs.
SPEAKER_0:  it's extremely stable.
SPEAKER_0:  And for this reason, when you convert...
SPEAKER_0:  the hydrogen into helium, it just wants to stay helium and it wants to release kinetic energy. stars are
SPEAKER_0:  basically conversion engines of hydrogen into helium.
SPEAKER_0:  And this also tells you why you love fusion. I mean-
SPEAKER_0:  because our sun will last 10 billion years approximately.
SPEAKER_0:  That's along the fuel last.
SPEAKER_1:  But to do that kind of conversion, you have to have extremely high temp-
SPEAKER_0:  temperatures.
SPEAKER_0:  It is one of the criteria for doing this, but it's the easiest one to understand. Why is this? It's because...
SPEAKER_0:  Effectively what this requires is that these
SPEAKER_0:  hydrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  ions, which is really the barenucleus. So they have a positive charge. Everything has a positive charge of those ones.
SPEAKER_0:  is that to get them to trigger this reaction, they must approach within.
SPEAKER_0:  distances which are like the size of the nucleus itself because the nature, in fact, what it's really using is something called the strong nuclear force. There's four fundamental forces in the universe. This is the strongest one.
SPEAKER_0:  But it has a strange property is that it.
SPEAKER_0:  While it's the strongest force by far, it only has impact over distances, which are the size of a nucleus. So to get-
SPEAKER_0:  put that into what does that mean? It's a...
SPEAKER_0:  millionth of a billionth of a meter.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  incredibly small distances, but because the distances are small.
SPEAKER_0:  and the particles have charge.
SPEAKER_0:  They want to push strongly apart, namely they have repulsion that wants to push them apart.
SPEAKER_0:  So it turns out when you go through the math of this.
SPEAKER_0:  the average velocity or energy of the particles must be very high.
SPEAKER_0:  to have any significant probability of the reactions happening.
SPEAKER_0:  And so the center of our sun is that.
SPEAKER_0:  about 20 million degrees Celsius.
SPEAKER_0:  And on Earth, this means it's one of the first things we teach, you know, entering graduate students. Real quick.
SPEAKER_0:  You can do a quick basically power balance and you can determine that on Earth it requires a minimum temperature.
SPEAKER_0:  of about 50 million degrees Celsius on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  to perform fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  to get enough fusion that you would be able to make, get energy gain out of it.
SPEAKER_0:  So you can trigger fusion reactions at lower energy, but they become almost vanishingly small at lower temperatures than that.
SPEAKER_1:  First of all, let me just link on some crazy ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... one the strong force just stepping out and looking at all the physics
SPEAKER_1:  Is it weird to you that there's these...
SPEAKER_1:  forces and they're very particular.
SPEAKER_1:  like it operates at a very small distance then gravity operates at a very large distance
SPEAKER_1:  and they're all very specific than the standard model describes.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... three of those forces extremely well and there's and this is one of them dis особuls
SPEAKER_1:  There's a big part of you that's...
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, an engineer.
SPEAKER_1:  Did you step back and almost look at the philosophy of physics?
SPEAKER_0:  So it's interesting because as a scientist, I see the universe through that lens of essentially the interesting things that we do are through the forces that get used around those.
SPEAKER_0:  and everything works because of that.
SPEAKER_0:  Richard Feynman had, I don't know if you've ever read Richard Feynman, it's a little bit of a tangent, but. He's never been on the podcast. He's never been on the podcast. He was unfortunately passed away, but one of, like a, like a hero to almost all, all physicists.
SPEAKER_0:  And part of it was because of what you said, he kind of looked through a different lens at these.
SPEAKER_0:  typically look like very dry like equations and relationships and he kind of
SPEAKER_0:  I think he brought out the wonder of it in some sense, right, for those.
SPEAKER_0:  he posited what would be, if you could write down a single.
SPEAKER_0:  Not even really a sentence, but a single concept.
SPEAKER_0:  That was the most important thing scientifically that we knew about. That in other words, you had only one thing that you could transmit like a future or past generation.
SPEAKER_0:  It was very interesting. It's not what you think. It wasn't like, oh, strong nuclear force or fusion or something like this.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's very profound, which was...
SPEAKER_0:  Here's.
SPEAKER_0:  the reason that matter.
SPEAKER_0:  operates the way that it does is because
SPEAKER_0:  All matter is made up of.
SPEAKER_0:  individual particles that interact each other through forces.
SPEAKER_0:  That was it.
SPEAKER_0:  So just that atomic theory, basically. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Which is like, wow, that's like so simple.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's not so simple.
SPEAKER_0:  It's because like who thinks about atoms that they're made of?
SPEAKER_0:  Like.
SPEAKER_0:  This is a good question I give to my students. How many atoms are in your body? Like almost no students can answer this. But to me that's like a fundamental thing.
SPEAKER_0:  By the way, it's about 10 to the 28.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  trillion.
SPEAKER_0:  million, trillion, trillion or something like that. Yes, yes.
SPEAKER_1:  One thing is to think about the number and the other is to start to really...
SPEAKER_1:  under the fag.
SPEAKER_1:  that it all holds together. Yeah, it all holds together and you're actually that. You're more that than you are anything else.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, exactly. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, there are people who do study such things of the fact that if you look at the...
SPEAKER_0:  For example, the ratios between those fundamental forces.
SPEAKER_0:  people have figured out, oh, if this ratio was different by some factor, like a factor of two or something, I was like, oh, this would all like not work.
SPEAKER_0:  And you look at the sun, right? So it turns out that there are key.
SPEAKER_0:  reactions that if they had slightly lower probability, no star would ever ignite.
SPEAKER_0:  and then life wouldn't be possible. It does seem like the universe set things up for us.
SPEAKER_1:  that it's possible to do some cool things.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's challenging.
SPEAKER_1:  so that it keeps it fun for us.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, yeah, that's the way I look at it. I mean the-
SPEAKER_0:  know the multiverse model is an interesting one because there are you know quantum scientists who look at it and figure it out. It's like oh yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  like quantum science perhaps tells us that there are almost an infinite variety of
SPEAKER_0:  Other universes?
SPEAKER_0:  But the way that it works probably is it's almost like a form of natural selection. It's like, well...
SPEAKER_0:  the universes that didn't have the correct
SPEAKER_0:  or interesting relationships between these forces, nothing happens in them.
SPEAKER_0:  So almost by definition, the fact that we're having this conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  means that we're in one of the interesting ones by default.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, one of the somewhat interesting, but there's probably super interesting ones where we, I tend to think of humans as incredible creatures. Our brain is an incredible creature.
SPEAKER_1:  computing device but...
SPEAKER_1:  I think we're also extremely cognitively limited, as I can imagine.
SPEAKER_1:  alien civilizations that are much, much, much, much more intelligent.
SPEAKER_1:  in ways we can't even comprehend. In terms of their ability to comprehend.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  construct models of the world, to do physics, and mathematics.
SPEAKER_0:  I would see it in a slightly different way. It's actually because we have
SPEAKER_0:  Um, we have.
SPEAKER_0:  we have creatures that live with us on the earth that have cognition.
SPEAKER_0:  that understand and move through their environment.
SPEAKER_0:  but they actually see things.
SPEAKER_0:  in a way, or they sense things in a way which is so fundamentally different, it's really hard.
SPEAKER_0:  Like the problem is the translation, not necessarily intelligence, so it's the perception of the world. I don't know if that's what zap's supposed to be called by that name.
SPEAKER_0:  And when I go and I see my dog smelling things.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a realization that I have that he...
SPEAKER_0:  Seize.
SPEAKER_0:  or senses the world in a way that I can never, like I can't understand it because I can't.
SPEAKER_0:  translate my way to this.
SPEAKER_0:  We get little glimpses of this as humans though by the way because they're
SPEAKER_0:  some parts of it, for example, optical information, which comes from light,
SPEAKER_0:  is that now because we've developed the technology, we can actually see things.
SPEAKER_0:  I get this as one of my areas of research is spectroscopy, so this means the study of light.
SPEAKER_0:  And I get to quote unquote see things or representations of them from.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, the far infrared all the way to like hard, hard X-rays, which is.
SPEAKER_0:  several orders of magnitude of the
SPEAKER_0:  of the light intensity but our own human eyes?
SPEAKER_0:  Like see, a teeny teeny little sliver of this.
SPEAKER_0:  so that even bees, for example, see a different.
SPEAKER_0:  place in video so I don't.
SPEAKER_0:  I think if you think of.
SPEAKER_0:  there's already other intelligences around us in a way, in a limited...
SPEAKER_0:  way.
SPEAKER_0:  because of the way they can communicate. But it's like, those are already baffling. In many ways, yeah. It's a, if we just.
SPEAKER_1:  focusing on the census there's already a lot of diversity.
SPEAKER_1:  but there's probably things we're not even considering unique possibilities.
SPEAKER_1:  For example,
SPEAKER_1:  whatever the heck consciousness is.
SPEAKER_1:  could actually be a door into understanding some physical phenomena we haven't even begun understanding. So just like you said, spectroscopy.
SPEAKER_1:  there could be a similar kind of spectrum for consciousness that we're just like
SPEAKER_1:  Or like these dumb
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh...
SPEAKER_1:  descendants of apes walking around, it sure feels like something to experience the color red.
SPEAKER_1:  But like we don't have...
SPEAKER_1:  It's the same as in the ancient times you experience physics, you experience light. It's like, oh, it's bright and you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, yeah. And you construct kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, semi-prolative kind of explanations. We might actually experience this faster than we thought, because we might be building.
SPEAKER_0:  another kind of intelligence.
SPEAKER_1:  and that that intelligence will explain to us.
SPEAKER_0:  How silly we are. There was an email thread going around.
SPEAKER_0:  the professors in my department already of, so what is it going to look like to figure out students have actually written their term papers?
SPEAKER_0:  or it's chat, the chat GPT.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, uh, it was.
SPEAKER_0:  So as usual, we tend to be empiricists in my field. So of course they were in there like trying to figure out if it could answer like questions for a qualifying exam to get into the PhD program at MIT, which was...
SPEAKER_0:  They didn't do that well at that point, but of course, this is just the beginning of it. So we have some interesting ones to go.
SPEAKER_1:  and eventually both the students and the professors will be replaced by Chad GPT. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Sit on the beach.
SPEAKER_0:  I really recommend, I don't know if you've ever seen them, it's called The Day the Universe Changed.
SPEAKER_0:  Is that a movie? James Burke?
SPEAKER_0:  He's a science historian based in the UK. He had a fairly famous series on...
SPEAKER_0:  public television called Connections, I think it was, but the one that I really enjoyed was the day the universe changed.
SPEAKER_0:  And the reason for the title of it was that...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  It says the universe is what we know and perceive of it.
SPEAKER_0:  So when there's a fundamental insight as to something new...
SPEAKER_0:  The universe for us changes. Of course, the universe from an objective point of view is the same as it was before, but for us it has changed.
SPEAKER_0:  So he walks through these.
SPEAKER_0:  these moments of perception in the history of humanity that changed what we were, right?
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  So as I was thinking about coming to discuss this, people see fusion, oh it's still far away or we've been...
SPEAKER_0:  It's been slow progress. It's like when my
SPEAKER_0:  when my godmother was born.
SPEAKER_0:  Like people had no idea how stars work.
SPEAKER_0:  So you talk about like that day, that insight, the universe change is like, oh.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the, I mean, and they still didn't understand all the parts of it, but you know, they basically got it. It was just like, oh.
SPEAKER_0:  because of the... because of...
SPEAKER_0:  the understanding of these processes, it's like we unveiled the reason that there can be life in the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  That's probably one of those days the universe changed, right? Yeah. And that was around the 1930s. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like technology is developing faster and faster and faster.
SPEAKER_1:  I tend to think that just like with chat GPT, I think this year might be extremely interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  just with how rapid
SPEAKER_1:  and how profitable the efforts in artificial intelligence are.
SPEAKER_1:  Just stuff will happen where our whole world is transformed like this.
SPEAKER_1:  and there's a shock and then next day you kind of go on and you adjust immediately.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... you probably won't have a similar kind of thing with uh... nuclear fusion with energy because there's
SPEAKER_1:  probably going to be an opening ceremony and stuff. It's gonna be us. And the announcement will take months. But with digital technology, you can just have a.
SPEAKER_1:  immediate transformation of society.
SPEAKER_1:  and it would be this.
SPEAKER_1:  gasp and then you kinda just, like we always do, and then you don't even remember, just like with the internet and so on, how the days were before.
SPEAKER_0:  and how it worked before, right?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean Fusion will be...
SPEAKER_0:  because its energy, its nature is that it will be, and anything that has to do with energy use tends to be a slower transition.
SPEAKER_0:  But they're the most.
SPEAKER_0:  I would argue some of the most profound. Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  transitions that we make. I mean the reason
SPEAKER_0:  that we can live like this and sit in this building and have this podcast and people around the world at its heart is energy use.
SPEAKER_0:  and its intense energy use.
SPEAKER_0:  that came from the evolution of starting to use intense energies at the beginning of the Industrial Revolution up to now.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, it's a bedrock actually of.
SPEAKER_0:  all of these, but it doesn't.
SPEAKER_0:  tend to come overnight.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  and some of the most important some of the most amazing technologies when we don't notice could we take it for granted is it enables the
SPEAKER_0:  whole thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly, which is energy, which is...
SPEAKER_0:  Amazing for how fundamental it is to our society and way of life is very poorly understood.
SPEAKER_0:  concept actually, just even energy itself, people confuse.
SPEAKER_0:  energy sources, with energy storage, with energy transmission, these are different.
SPEAKER_0:  physical phenomena.
SPEAKER_0:  which are very important. So for example,
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you buy an electric car and you go, oh good, I have an emission free car.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Ah, ah, but it's like so-
SPEAKER_0:  So why do you say that? Well, it's because if I draw the circle around the car, I have electricity and it doesn't emit anything.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, but you plug that into a grid where you follow that wire back.
SPEAKER_0:  there could be a coal power plant.
SPEAKER_0:  or a gas power plant.
SPEAKER_0:  at the end of that.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, really?
SPEAKER_0:  You mean so this isn't like carbon free? I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's not their fault, they don't.
SPEAKER_0:  Like the car isn't a source of energy. The underlying source of energy was the combustion of the fuel back somewhere.
SPEAKER_1:  Plus there's also a story of how the
SPEAKER_1:  Raw materials are mine.
SPEAKER_1:  in which parts of the world.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... with the sort of basic respect or
SPEAKER_1:  or a deep disrespect of human rights that happens in that money. So the whole supply chain, there's a story there that's deeper than just a particular electric car with a circle around it.
SPEAKER_0:  in the physics or the science of it too is the energy use.
SPEAKER_0:  that it takes to do that digging up, which is also important in all that.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, anyway, so.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. We wandered away from fusion, but yes. Oh, it's a beautiful stroll. It's very important actually in the context of this just because
SPEAKER_0:  Now those of us who work in infusion and these...
SPEAKER_0:  other kinds of disruptive energy.
SPEAKER_0:  technologies.
SPEAKER_0:  It's interesting that I do think about like what would it, what is it going to mean to society to have an energy source that is like this.
SPEAKER_0:  that would be like fusion, which has such completely different characteristics.
SPEAKER_0:  For example, free unlimited access to the fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  but it has technology implications. So what does this mean geopolitically? What does it mean?
SPEAKER_0:  for how we distribute wealth within our society.
SPEAKER_0:  It's very difficult to know.
SPEAKER_0:  but probably profound. yeah
SPEAKER_1:  have to find another reason to start wars.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... numbers instead of resources
SPEAKER_0:  We've done a pretty good job of that over the course of our history.
SPEAKER_1:  So we talked about the forces of physics and again sticking to the philosophical before we get to the specific technical stuff. E equals MC squared you mentioned. How amazing is that to you? That energy and mass are the same.
SPEAKER_1:  And what does that have to do with nuclear fusion?
SPEAKER_0:  So it has to do with everything we do. It's the fact that energy and mass are equivalent to each other. They're just.
SPEAKER_0:  The way we usually comment to it is that they're just energy just in different forms.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you intuitively?
SPEAKER_1:  Understand that?
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  But it takes a long time.
SPEAKER_0:  Hi.
SPEAKER_0:  I haven't for a while, but often I teach the...
SPEAKER_0:  the introductory class for.
SPEAKER_0:  incoming nuclear engineers and
SPEAKER_0:  And so we put this up as an equation and we go through many...
SPEAKER_0:  iterations of using this.
SPEAKER_0:  how you derive it, how you use it, and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  And then usually in the final exam, I would give, I would basically take all the equations that I've used before and I flip it around. Like basically...
SPEAKER_0:  instead of thinking about energy is equal to mass, it's sort of mass is equal to energy. I ask the question in a different way.
SPEAKER_0:  And usually about half the students don't get it. It takes a while.
SPEAKER_0:  is to get that intuition, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, so.
SPEAKER_0:  So in the end, it's interesting is that this is actually the source of all free energy because that energy that we're talking about is kinetic energy if it can be transformed for mass. So is it about even...?
SPEAKER_0:  Even though we used equals MC squared, this was burning coal.
SPEAKER_0:  and burning gas and burning wood is actually still equals MC squared.
SPEAKER_0:  The problem is that you would never know this because the relative change in the mass is incredibly small.
SPEAKER_0:  By the way, which comes back to fusion, which is that.
SPEAKER_0:  E equals MC squared. Okay, so what does this mean? It tells you that the
SPEAKER_0:  the amount of energy that is liberated in a particular reaction when you change mass.
SPEAKER_0:  has to, because C squared is that's the speed of light squared. It's a large number. It's a very large number and it's totally constant everywhere in the universe, which is. Which is another weird thing. Which is another weird thing. And in all rest frames and the, actually, the relativity stuff gets more difficult conceptually until you get through. Anyway, so you go, you go to that and.
SPEAKER_0:  And what that tells you is that it's the relative change in the mass will tell you about the relative amount of energy that's liberated.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is what makes fusion and you asked about fission as well too. This is what makes.
SPEAKER_0:  them extraordinary. It's because the relative change in the mass is very large.
SPEAKER_0:  as compared to what you get, like in a chemical reaction.
SPEAKER_0:  In fact, it's about 10 million times larger.
SPEAKER_0:  And that is at the heart of why you use something like Fusion. It's because...
SPEAKER_0:  That is a fundamental of nature. Like you can't beat that.
SPEAKER_0:  So of whatever you do, if you're thinking about, and why do I care about this? Well, because mass is like the fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  So this means gathering.
SPEAKER_0:  the resources that it takes to gather a fuel, to hold it together, to deal with it, is the environmental impact it would have.
SPEAKER_0:  and fusion will always have 20 million times.
SPEAKER_0:  the amount of energy released per reaction.
SPEAKER_0:  that you can do those. So this is why.
SPEAKER_0:  We consider it the ultimate environmentally friendly energy source, it was because of that.
SPEAKER_1:  So is it...
SPEAKER_1:  Is it correct to think of mass broadly?
SPEAKER_1:  as a kind of storage of energy. Yes problem.
SPEAKER_1:  You mentioned its environmentally friendly soil.
SPEAKER_1:  Nuclear fusion is a source of energy. It's cheap, clean, safe.
SPEAKER_1:  So easy access to fuel and virtual unlimited supply, no production of greenhouse gases.
SPEAKER_1:  little radioactive waste produced.
SPEAKER_1:  allegedly. Can you sort of elaborate?
SPEAKER_1:  why it's cheap, clean, and safe.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll start with the easiest one, cheap. It is not cheap yet.
SPEAKER_0:  because it hasn't been made at a commercial scale. Mine flies when you're having fun. Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  But yes, not yet. We'll talk about it. We'll come back to that because this is-
SPEAKER_0:  cheaper or more technically correct term that is economically interesting is
SPEAKER_0:  is really the primary challenge actually of fusion at this point.
SPEAKER_0:  But I think we can get back to that. So what were the other ones you said?
SPEAKER_1:  So actually when we're talking about cheap, we're thinking like asymptotically.
SPEAKER_1:  You take it forward.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. It's a hundred years.
SPEAKER_1:  that's sort of
SPEAKER_1:  because of
SPEAKER_1:  how much availability there is of resources to use. of the fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  the fuel. We should separate those two. The fuel is already cheap. It's basically free.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you mean by basically free?
SPEAKER_0:  If we were to be using fusion fuel sources to power.
SPEAKER_0:  your, and it's like, that's all we had was fusion power plants around and we were doing it.
SPEAKER_0:  The fuel cost per person are something like 10 cents a year.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, it's free.
SPEAKER_0:  This is why it's hard to, in some ways, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  It's hard to understand fusion because people see this and go, oh, if the fuel is free, this means the energy source is free because we're used to energy sources like this. So we, you know, we spend resources and drill to get gas or oil or we chop wood or we make coal, or these things, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So fusion, this is what makes fusion. And it's also.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not an intermittent renewable energy source like wind and solar.
SPEAKER_0:  This makes it hard to understand. So as you're saying, the fuel is free. Why isn't the-
SPEAKER_0:  Like why isn't the energy source free?
SPEAKER_0:  And it's because...
SPEAKER_0:  of the necessary technologies which must be applied.
SPEAKER_0:  to basically recreate the conditions which are in stars.
SPEAKER_0:  In the center of stars in fact. So there's only one natural place in the universe that fusion energy occurs.
SPEAKER_0:  that's in the center of stars.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's going to bring a price to it, depending on.
SPEAKER_0:  the cost and sorry, the size and complexity of the technology that's needed to recreate those things. We'll talk about the details.
SPEAKER_1:  of technologies and which parts might be expensive today and which parts might be expensive in two hundred years
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly.
SPEAKER_0:  it will have a revolution, I'm certain of it.
SPEAKER_0:  So about clean, so clean is.
SPEAKER_0:  At its heart, what it does is convert, it basically converts hydrogen into its heavier forms of hydrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  predominant one that we use on earth.
SPEAKER_0:  and converts it into helium.
SPEAKER_0:  and some other products but primarily helium is the product that's left behind. Department of Health.
SPEAKER_0:  safe inert gas, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  In fact, that's actually what our sun is doing, is eventually going to extinguish itself because it'll just make so much helium.
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't do that.
SPEAKER_0:  in that sense, clean because there's no
SPEAKER_0:  There's no emissions of...
SPEAKER_0:  of carbon or pollutants that come
SPEAKER_0:  directly from the combustion of the fuel itself.
SPEAKER_0:  and safe. Safe, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  We're talking about very high temperatures. Yeah. Yeah. So this is also the counterintuitive thing. So I told you temperatures, which like 50 million degrees or
SPEAKER_0:  It actually tends to be more like about 100 million degrees is really what we aim.
SPEAKER_0:  So how can 100 million degrees be safe?
SPEAKER_0:  And it's safe because it is.
SPEAKER_0:  This is so much hotter than anything on Earth, where everything on Earth is at around 300 Kelvin, that's around a few tens of degrees Celsius.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  What this means is that in order to get a medium to those temperatures
SPEAKER_0:  You have to completely isolate it from anything to do with terrestrial environment.
SPEAKER_0:  It can have no contact like with anything on earth basically.
SPEAKER_0:  So this means, this is the technology that I just described.
SPEAKER_0:  is it fundamentally what it does is it takes this fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  And, uh, it isolates it from any terrestrial conditions so that it has no idea it's on earth. It's not touching any object that's at room temperature in.
SPEAKER_1:  walls of the
SPEAKER_0:  Even including the walls of the containment building or containment device or even air or anything like this.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's that part.
SPEAKER_0:  that makes it safe and there's actually another aspect to it.
SPEAKER_0:  That fundamental part makes it so safe.
SPEAKER_0:  In the main lines.
SPEAKER_0:  approach diffusion is also that it's very hot.
SPEAKER_0:  where there's very, very few particles.
SPEAKER_0:  in at any time in the thing that would be the power plant. Actually the more correct way to do it is you say, there's very...
SPEAKER_0:  few particles.
SPEAKER_0:  per unit volume.
SPEAKER_0:  cubic centimeter and cubic meter, so we can do this. So right now we're.
SPEAKER_0:  Although we don't think of air really as a, there's atoms floating around us and there's a density.
SPEAKER_0:  because if I wave my hand, I can feel the air pushing against my face. That means we're in a fluid or a gas which is around us.
SPEAKER_0:  that has a particular.
SPEAKER_0:  number of atoms per cubic meter.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's about, this actually turns out to be 10 to the 25th. So this is one with 25 zeros behind it.
SPEAKER_0:  per cubic meter. So we can figure out like cubic meters about like this, the volume of this table, like the whole volume of this table.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, okay, very good. So like fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a few of those. So fusion, like the mainstream one of fusion, like what we're working on at MIT will have a hundred thousand times less particles.
SPEAKER_0:  per unit volume than that.
SPEAKER_0:  This is very interesting because it's extraordinarily hot, 100 million degrees.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's very tenuous.
SPEAKER_0:  and what matters from the engineering and safety point of view.
SPEAKER_0:  is the amount of
SPEAKER_0:  Energy which is stored.
SPEAKER_0:  per unit volume.
SPEAKER_0:  because this tells you about the
SPEAKER_0:  the scenarios and that's what you worry about because when those kinds of energies are released.
SPEAKER_0:  Suddenly, it's like what would be the consequences, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So the consequences of this are essentially zero.
SPEAKER_0:  because that's less.
SPEAKER_0:  energy content than boiling water.
SPEAKER_0:  Because of the low density. Because of the low density. So if you take.
SPEAKER_0:  water is at about a hundred million to a billion times more dense.
SPEAKER_0:  than this.
SPEAKER_0:  So even though it's at much lower.
SPEAKER_0:  temperature.
SPEAKER_0:  It's actually still, it has more energy content.
SPEAKER_0:  So if for this reason...
SPEAKER_0:  One of the ways that I explain this is that if you imagine a power plant that's like powering Cambridge, Massachusetts.
SPEAKER_0:  If you were to, which you wouldn't do this directly, but if you went like this on it, it actually extinguishes the fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  because it gets too cold.
SPEAKER_0:  immediately.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the other one. The other part is that it does not, because it works by staying hot.
SPEAKER_0:  rather than a chain reaction, it can't run out of control. That's the other part of it. So by the way, this is what-
SPEAKER_0:  very much distinguishes it from fission. It's not a process that can run away from you because it's basically thermally stable.
SPEAKER_0:  What does thermostable mean? That means is that you want to run it at the optimization in temperature such that if it deviates away from that temperature, the reactivity gets lower.
SPEAKER_0:  And the reason for this is because it's hard to keep the reactivity going. Like it's a very hard fire to keep going basically.
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't run away from you. It can't run away from you. How difficult is the control there to keep it at that?
SPEAKER_0:  It varies from concept to concept, but in general it's fairly easy to do that. And the easiest thing, it can't physically run away from you because the other part of it is that there's just...
SPEAKER_0:  at any given time there's a very, very small amount of fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  available to fuse it anyway. So this means that
SPEAKER_0:  That's always intrinsically limited to this. So even if the power consumption of the device goes up, it just kind of burns itself out immediately. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  So you are the, just to take another tangent on a tangent, you're the director of MIT's Plasma Science and Fusion Center.ánh
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  we'll talk about.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe you can mention some interesting aspects of the history of the center.
SPEAKER_1:  in the broader history.
SPEAKER_1:  of MIT and maybe brought a history of science and engineering and the history of human civilization, but also just the link on the safety aspect.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you prevent?
SPEAKER_1:  some of the amazing reactors that you're designing.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you prevent from destroying all of human civilization in the process?
SPEAKER_1:  What's the safety problem?
SPEAKER_0:  Fusion is interesting because it's not really directly weaponizable because
SPEAKER_0:  What I mean by that is that you have to work very hard to make these conditions which you can get energy gain from fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  And this means that when we design these devices with respect to application in the energy field.
SPEAKER_0:  is that they...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, you...
SPEAKER_0:  while they will...
SPEAKER_0:  Because they're producing large amounts of power and they will have hot things inside of them, this means that they have like a level of industrial hazard, which is very similar to what you would have like in a chemical processing plant.
SPEAKER_0:  anything like that and any kind of energy plant actually has these as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  but the underlying, underneath it core technology.
SPEAKER_0:  like can't be directly used in a nefarious way because of the power that's being emitted. Just basically..
SPEAKER_0:  If you try to do those things, typically it just stops working.
SPEAKER_1:  So the safety concerns have to do with just regular things that, uh, like equipment malfunctioning.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  melting of a quick like all all this kind of stuff that has nothing to do with fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  necessarily. I mean, usually what we worry about is the viability because in the end we build pretty complex objects.
SPEAKER_0:  to realize these requirements. So what we try.
SPEAKER_0:  really hard to do is like not damage those components, but those are things which are internal to the
SPEAKER_0:  to the Fusion device and this is not something that you would...
SPEAKER_0:  consider about like it would, as you say, destroy human civilization because that release of energy is just inherently limited because of the fusion process.
SPEAKER_0:  So it doesn't say that there's zero.
SPEAKER_0:  So you asked about the other feature of it that it's safe. So it is.
SPEAKER_0:  The process itself is intrinsically safe.
SPEAKER_0:  but because it's a complex technology, you still have to take into consideration aspects of the safety.
SPEAKER_0:  So it produces ionizing radiation instantaneously.
SPEAKER_0:  So you have to take care of this, which means that you shield it.
SPEAKER_0:  Think of like your dental x-rays or treatments for cancer and things like this. We always shield ourselves from this.
SPEAKER_0:  So we get the beneficial effects, but we minimize the harmful effects of those.
SPEAKER_0:  So there are all those aspects of it as well too.
SPEAKER_1:  So we'll return to MIT's Plasma Science and Field Center, but let us linger on the destruction of human civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  Which brings us to the topic of nuclear fission. What is that?
SPEAKER_1:  What are some of the process?
SPEAKER_1:  that is inside nuclear weapons.
SPEAKER_1:  and current nuclear power.
SPEAKER_0:  plants.
SPEAKER_0:  So it relies on the same underlying.
SPEAKER_0:  physical principle, but it's exactly the opposite.
SPEAKER_0:  which actually the names imply. Fusion means bringing things together. Fission means splitting things apart.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Fission requires the heaviest.
SPEAKER_0:  instead of the lightest.
SPEAKER_0:  and the most unstable versus the most stable.
SPEAKER_0:  elements. So this tends to be uranium.
SPEAKER_0:  or plutonium, primarily uranium. So take uranium.
SPEAKER_0:  So uranium-235 is one of the, this is one of the heaviest unstable elements. And what happens?
SPEAKER_0:  is that this is, and fission is triggered by the fact that one of these subatomic particles, is a neutron which has no electric charge.
SPEAKER_0:  basically gets in proximity enough to this.
SPEAKER_0:  and triggers an instability effectively inside of this.
SPEAKER_0:  on the border of instability.
SPEAKER_0:  and basically splits it apart.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's the fission, right? The fissioning.
SPEAKER_0:  And so when that happens...
SPEAKER_0:  because the products that are
SPEAKER_0:  and it roughly splits in two, but it's not even that. It's actually more complex. It splits into this whole array of lighter elements and nuclei.
SPEAKER_0:  And when that happens...
SPEAKER_0:  there's less rest mass.
SPEAKER_0:  laugh than the original one. So it's actually the same, so it's again, it's rearrangement of the strong nuclear force.
SPEAKER_0:  that's happening.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  But that's the source of energy. And so in the end, it's like, so this is a famous graph that we show everybody is basically, it turns out every
SPEAKER_0:  element that exists in the periodic table, all the things that make up everything.
SPEAKER_0:  how...
SPEAKER_0:  Remember you asked a good question. It was like, so should we think of mass as being the same as stored energy?
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  So you can make a plot that basically shows the relative amount of stored energy.
SPEAKER_0:  and all of the elements that are stable and make up basically the world, okay, and the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  And it turns out that this one has...
SPEAKER_0:  a maximum amount of stability or storage at iron.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's kind of in the middle of the periodic table because this goes from, you know, it's roughly that.
SPEAKER_0:  And so what that means is that if...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  If you take something heavier than iron, like uranium, which is more than twice as heavy than that...
SPEAKER_0:  and you split apart, somehow just magically, you just split apart as constituents when you get something that's lighter.
SPEAKER_0:  that will, because it moves to a more stable energy state, it releases kinetic energy. That's the energy that we use.
SPEAKER_0:  Kinetic energy meaning the movement of things. So it's actually an energy you can do something with.
SPEAKER_0:  And fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  It sits on the other side of that because it's also moving towards iron, but it has to do it through fusion together.
SPEAKER_0:  So this leads to some pretty profound differences. As I said, they have some underlying.
SPEAKER_0:  physics or science.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  proximity to each other, but they're literally the opposite. so fusion
SPEAKER_0:  Why is this? It actually goes into practical implications of it, which is that fission can happen at room temperature.
SPEAKER_0:  It's because this neutron has no
SPEAKER_0:  electric charge and therefore it's literally room temperature neutrons.
SPEAKER_0:  that actually trigger the reaction. So this means.
SPEAKER_0:  in order to establish.
SPEAKER_0:  what's going on with it and it works by chain reaction.
SPEAKER_0:  is that you can do this at room temperature. So Enrico Fermi did this like on a-
SPEAKER_0:  on a university campus, University of Chicago campus.
SPEAKER_0:  The first sustained.
SPEAKER_0:  you know chain reaction was done underneath a squash core.
SPEAKER_0:  with a big blocks of graphite, it was still, don't get me wrong, an incredible human achievement, right?
SPEAKER_0:  But that's, you know, and then you think about fusion, I have to build a contraption of some kind that's going to get to a hundred million degrees. Okay, wow, that's a big difference.
SPEAKER_0:  The other one is about the chain reaction that namely fission.
SPEAKER_0:  works by the fact that
SPEAKER_0:  When that fission occurs, it actually produces free neutrons.
SPEAKER_0:  free neutrons, particularly if they get slowed down to room temperature.
SPEAKER_0:  can trigger other fission reactions if there's other uranium nearby or fissometers.
SPEAKER_0:  So this means that the way that it releases energy is that you set this up in a very careful way.
SPEAKER_0:  such that every, on average, every reaction that happens.
SPEAKER_0:  exactly releases enough neutrons and slows down that they actually make another reaction, exactly one.
SPEAKER_0:  And what this means is that because each reaction releases a fixed amount of energy, you do this and then in time, this looks like just a constant power output. So that's how our fission power plant.
SPEAKER_1:  And so their control of the chain reactions is extremely difficult and extremely important.
SPEAKER_0:  It's very important. And when you intentionally design it, that it creates more than one,
SPEAKER_0:  vision reaction.
SPEAKER_0:  per starting reaction that it exponentiates away.
SPEAKER_0:  But which is what a nuclear weapon is.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so how does an atomic weapon work? How does a hydrogen bomb work? Asking for a friend.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so at its heart, what you do is you very quickly put together.
SPEAKER_0:  enough of these materials that can undergo fission with room temperature neutrons.
SPEAKER_0:  and you put them together fast enough that what happens is that the
SPEAKER_0:  this process can essentially grow mathematically like very fast.
SPEAKER_0:  And so this releases large amounts of energy. That's the underlying.
SPEAKER_0:  reason that it works.
SPEAKER_0:  So you've heard of a fusion weapon.
SPEAKER_0:  This is interesting, but it's dislike fusion energy in the sense that what happens
SPEAKER_0:  is that you're using.
SPEAKER_0:  fusion reactions, but it simply increases the gain actually of the weapon rather than it's not a pure.
SPEAKER_0:  at its heart it's still a fission.
SPEAKER_0:  You're just using fusion reactions as a sort of intermediate catalyst basically to get even more energy out of it.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's not directly applicable to be used in energy source.
SPEAKER_1:  Does it terrify you?
SPEAKER_1:  Just again, to step back at the philosophical, the humans.
SPEAKER_1:  I've been able to use physics and...
SPEAKER_1:  engineering to create.
SPEAKER_1:  such powerful.
SPEAKER_0:  weapons.
SPEAKER_0:  I wouldn't say terrify, I mean we should be...
SPEAKER_0:  This is the progress of humanity. Every time that we've gone-
SPEAKER_0:  access the day the universe changed.
SPEAKER_0:  This was really changed when we got access to new kinds of energy sources. But every time you get access, and typically what this meant was you get access.
SPEAKER_0:  to more intense energy, right? And that's what that was. And so the ability to move from burning wood.
SPEAKER_0:  to using coal, to using...
SPEAKER_0:  gasoline and petrol and then finally to use this is that
SPEAKER_0:  is that both the potency and the consequences are elevated.
SPEAKER_0:  around those things. It's just like you.
SPEAKER_1:  said the.
SPEAKER_1:  the way that fusion, nuclear fusion, would change the world.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't think.
SPEAKER_1:  Unless we think really deeply, we'll be able to anticipate some of the things we can create. There's going to be a lot of amazing stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  But then that amazing stuff is going to enable.
SPEAKER_1:  more amazing stuff and more.
SPEAKER_1:  unfortunately or
SPEAKER_1:  Depending how you see it more powerful weapons
SPEAKER_0:  Well, yeah, but see, that's the thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Fusion breaks that trend.
SPEAKER_0:  in the following way.
SPEAKER_0:  one of them so fusion doesn't work on a chain.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no chain reaction, zero.
SPEAKER_0:  So this means it cannot physically exponentiate away on you because it works.
SPEAKER_0:  And actually this is why stars, by the way, we know this already, it's why stars are so stable, why most stars and suns are so stable.
SPEAKER_0:  It's because...
SPEAKER_0:  They are regulated through their own temperature when they're heating.
SPEAKER_0:  because what's happening is not that there's some probability of this exponentiating away, is that the energy that's being released by fusion basically is keeping the fire hot.
SPEAKER_0:  And these tend to be, you know, and when it comes down to thermodynamics and things like this, there's a reason, for example, it's pretty easy to keep a constant temperature like in an oven and things like this. It's the same thing.
SPEAKER_0:  infusion.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is actually one of the features that I would argue fusion breaks the
SPEAKER_0:  What breaks the trend of this is that it's...
SPEAKER_0:  It has more energy intensity than fission on paper.
SPEAKER_0:  but it actually does not have the consequences of control and sort of rapid release of the energy because it's actually
SPEAKER_0:  The physical system just doesn't want to do that.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, we're gonna have to look else-
SPEAKER_1:  I swear.
SPEAKER_1:  the weapons with which we fight World War III.
SPEAKER_1:  Fair enough.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, so...
SPEAKER_1:  What is plasma?
SPEAKER_1:  That you may have may have not mentioned you mentioned ions and electrons and so on so what is plasma? What is the role of plasma in nuclear fusion?
SPEAKER_0:  So plasma is a phase of matter or state of matter.
SPEAKER_0:  Unfortunately, our schools don't.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, I'm not sure why this is the case, but it all-
SPEAKER_0:  children learn the three phases of matter.
SPEAKER_0:  And what does this mean? So we'll take water as an example.
SPEAKER_0:  If it's cold, it's ice, it's in a solid phase.
SPEAKER_0:  And then if you heat it up, it's the temperature that typically depends.
SPEAKER_0:  sets the phase, although it's not only temperature.
SPEAKER_0:  So you heat it up.
SPEAKER_0:  And you go to a liquid and obviously it changes its physical properties because it can, you can pour it and so forth, right?
SPEAKER_0:  And then if you heat this up enough, it turns into a gas.
SPEAKER_0:  and a gas behaves differently because
SPEAKER_0:  There's a very sudden change in the density, actually that's what's happening. So it changes by about a factor of 10,000 in density from the liquid phase into when you make it into steam at atmospheric pressure.
SPEAKER_0:  All very good.
SPEAKER_0:  except the problem is they forgot like what happens if you just keep elevating the temperature
SPEAKER_0:  You don't want to give kids ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  is. I'm gonna start experimenting and I'm gonna start...
SPEAKER_0:  heating up the gas. It's good to start doing it anyway. So you, it turns out that once you get above it's approximately five or ten thousand degrees Celsius.
SPEAKER_0:  then you hit a new phase of matter. And actually that's the phase of matter that is for all.
SPEAKER_0:  pretty much all the temperatures that are above that as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and so what does that mean? So it actually changes, so it's a different state of matter. And the reason...
SPEAKER_0:  that it becomes a different state of matter is that it's hot enough.
SPEAKER_0:  that what happens is that the atoms that make up, remember go back to Feynman, right? Everything's made up of these.
SPEAKER_0:  individual things, these atoms.
SPEAKER_0:  atoms can actually themselves be
SPEAKER_0:  which are made of.
SPEAKER_0:  nuclei which contain the positive
SPEAKER_0:  particles in the neutrons and then the electrons.
SPEAKER_0:  which are very, very light, very much less mass than the nucleus.
SPEAKER_0:  and that surrounds us. This is what makes up an atom.
SPEAKER_0:  So a plasma is what happens when you start.
SPEAKER_0:  pulling away enough of those electrons that they're free.
SPEAKER_0:  from the ions, so almost all the atoms that make us up and this water and all that, the electrons are in tightly bound states and basically they're extremely stable. Once you're at about 5,000 or 10,000 degrees, you start pulling off the electrons.
SPEAKER_0:  And what this means is that now...
SPEAKER_0:  the medium that is there.
SPEAKER_0:  its constituent particles mostly have net charge.
SPEAKER_0:  So why does that matter? It's because now-
SPEAKER_0:  This means that the particles can interact.
SPEAKER_0:  through their electric charge. In some sense they were when it was in the atom as well too. But now that they're free particles.
SPEAKER_0:  This means that they start, it fundamentally changes the behavior. It doesn't behave like a gas, it doesn't behave like a solid or a liquid, it behaves like a plasma.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  So why is it disappointing that we don't speak about this? Because 99% of the universe is in the plasma state.
SPEAKER_0:  is called stars.
SPEAKER_0:  and in fact our own son.
SPEAKER_0:  At the center of the sun is clearly a plasma.
SPEAKER_0:  But actually the surface of the sun, which is around 5500 Celsius, is also a plasma.
SPEAKER_0:  it's hot enough that is that. In fact, the things that you see, sometimes you see these pictures from the surface of the sun, amazing.
SPEAKER_0:  like satellite photographs of like those big arms of.
SPEAKER_0:  things in of light coming off of the surface of the sun and solar flares, those are plasmas.
SPEAKER_1:  What are some interesting ways that this...
SPEAKER_1:  force theta matter is different than gas.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's go to how a gas works. Right. So the reason a gas, and it goes back to Feynman's brilliance in saying that this is the most important concept.
SPEAKER_0:  The reason actually solid, liquid and gas phases work is because the nature of the interaction between the atoms changes.
SPEAKER_0:  And so in a gas...
SPEAKER_0:  You can think of this as being
SPEAKER_0:  this room and the things, although you can't see them.
SPEAKER_0:  is that the molecules are
SPEAKER_0:  flying around.
SPEAKER_0:  but then with some frequency they basically bounce into each other.
SPEAKER_0:  and when they bounce into each other, the exchange.
SPEAKER_0:  momentum and energy.
SPEAKER_0:  around on this.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it turns out that the probability and the distances and the scattering.
SPEAKER_0:  of those and what they do.
SPEAKER_0:  It's those interactions that set the, about how a gas behaves.
SPEAKER_0:  So what do you mean by this? For example, if I take a-
SPEAKER_0:  an imaginary test particle of some kind, like I spray.
SPEAKER_0:  something into the air that's got a particular color. In fact, you can do it in liquids as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  how it gradually will disperse.
SPEAKER_0:  away from you? This is
SPEAKER_0:  This is fundamentally sad.
SPEAKER_0:  because of the way that those particles are bouncing into each other.
SPEAKER_1:  more celebrities of those?"
SPEAKER_0:  The rate that they go at and the distance that they go at and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  So this was figured out by Einstein and others at the beginning of the Brownian motion, all these kinds of things.
SPEAKER_0:  These were set up at the beginning of the last century and was really like...
SPEAKER_0:  this great revelation, wow, this is why matter behaves the way that it does. like wow lively.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  So, but it's really like, and also in liquids and in solids, like what really matters is
SPEAKER_0:  is how you're interacting with your nearest neighbor.
SPEAKER_0:  So you think about that one, the gas particles are basically going around until they actually hit into each other though.
SPEAKER_0:  They don't really exchange information. And it's the same in a liquid, you're kind of beside each other, but you can kind of move around. In a solid, you're literally like stuck beside your neighbor, you can't move.
SPEAKER_0:  Plasmas are weird in the sense that it's not like that.
SPEAKER_0:  So it is because the particles have electric charge.
SPEAKER_0:  This means that they can push against each other.
SPEAKER_0:  without actually being in close proximity to each other.
SPEAKER_0:  That's not an infinitely true statement.
SPEAKER_0:  If he goes get this a little bit more technical, but basically this means that you can start having action or exchange of information at a distance.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's in fact the definition of a plasma, that it says, these have a technical name, it's called a Coulomb collision, which just means that it's dictated by this.
SPEAKER_0:  force which is being pushed between.
SPEAKER_0:  charge particles.
SPEAKER_0:  is that the definition of a plasma is a medium.
SPEAKER_0:  in which the collective behavior is dominated by these collisions at a distance.
SPEAKER_0:  So you can imagine, then this starts to give you some strange.
SPEAKER_0:  behaviors.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  which I could quickly talk about like, one of the most counterintuitive ones is
SPEAKER_0:  as plasmas get
SPEAKER_0:  More hot.
SPEAKER_0:  as they get higher in temperature.
SPEAKER_0:  then the collisions happen less frequently.
SPEAKER_0:  Like what?
SPEAKER_0:  That doesn't make any sense. When particles go faster, you think they would collide more often.
SPEAKER_0:  But because...
SPEAKER_0:  the particles are interacting through their electric field.
SPEAKER_0:  When they're going faster, they actually spend less time.
SPEAKER_0:  in the influential field of each other, and so they talk to each other less in an energy and momentum exchange point of view.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just, we're just one of the count, one of the counterintuitive aspects of plasmas, which is probably very.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  relevant for nuclear f-
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, exactly.
SPEAKER_1:  So if I can try to summarize.
SPEAKER_1:  What a nuclear fusion reactor.
SPEAKER_1:  is supposed to do.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  You have what a couple of elements.
SPEAKER_0:  what are you doing the elements using deuterium and tritium which are the heavy forms of hydrogen
SPEAKER_1:  hydrogen. You have those and you start heating it.
SPEAKER_1:  And then as you start heating it, I forgot the temperatures.
SPEAKER_0:  said, but it becomes plasma. No, first, first it becomes. Oh, first it becomes plasma. So it's a gas and then it turns into a plasma at about 10,000 degrees. And then.
SPEAKER_1:  We have a bunch of electrons and ions flying around.
SPEAKER_1:  and then you keep heating the thing.
SPEAKER_1:  And I guess as you heat the thing, the ions hit each other rarer and rarer. Yes. Oh man, that's not fun. You have to keep.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  eating it.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  such that you have to keep hitting into the probability of them colliding.
SPEAKER_1:  becomes reasonably high.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  So also on top of that and sorry to
SPEAKER_1:  interrupt.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to.
SPEAKER_1:  prevent them from hitting the walls of their
SPEAKER_0:  reactor.
SPEAKER_0:  So you asked about the root.
SPEAKER_0:  the definitions of the requirements for fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  So the most famous one, or in some sense, the most intuitive one is the temperature.
SPEAKER_0:  And the reason for that is that
SPEAKER_0:  you can make many, many kinds of plasmas that have zero fusion going on.
SPEAKER_0:  And the reason for this is that the
SPEAKER_0:  average, so you can make a plasma at around 10,000. Thank you for watching, and I'll see you next time.
SPEAKER_0:  By the way, you're welcome to come to our laboratory at the PSFC, I can show you a demonstration of a plasma that you can see with your eyes and sit at about 10,000 degrees.
SPEAKER_0:  You can put your hand up beside it and all this and it's like, and nothing, there's zero fusion going on.
SPEAKER_0:  So you have, as I will.
SPEAKER_1:  was the temperature of the plasma? About 10,000 degrees. So that means city chyba moldipSIK13 is a nuclear reaction.
SPEAKER_0:  stick your hand in? Well, you can stick your hand into it, but there's a glass tube. You can basically see this. See it right there....
SPEAKER_0:  And you can put your hand on the glass too, because it's. What's the colors?
SPEAKER_0:  It's purple.keeping it for theOOOOOOм
SPEAKER_0:  Let's move from.
SPEAKER_0:  It is kind of beautiful. Yeah, plasmas are actually quite astonishing sometimes in their beauty.
SPEAKER_0:  Actually, one of the most amazing forms of plasma is lightning, by the way, which is an instantaneous form of plasma that exists on Earth but immediately goes away because everything else around it is at room temperature.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, so there's different requirements in this. So making a plasma takes a-
SPEAKER_0:  about this, but at 10,000 degrees, even at a million degrees...
SPEAKER_0:  there's almost no probability of the fusion reactions occurring. and this is because
SPEAKER_0:  While the charged particles can hit into each other.
SPEAKER_0:  If you go back to the very beginning of this, remember I said...
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, these charged particles.
SPEAKER_0:  have to get to within distances which are like this.
SPEAKER_0:  size of a nucleus because of the strong nuclear force.
SPEAKER_0:  Well...
SPEAKER_0:  Unfortunately...
SPEAKER_0:  as the particles get closer,
SPEAKER_0:  This, the repulsion that comes from the
SPEAKER_0:  Charge the coulomb force.
SPEAKER_0:  increases like the inverse distance squared.
SPEAKER_0:  So as they get closer, they're pushing harder and harder apart.
SPEAKER_0:  Then it gets a little bit more exotic, which maybe you'll like though, that it turns out that people...
SPEAKER_0:  understood this and um
SPEAKER_0:  at the beginning of the...
SPEAKER_0:  of the age after Rutherford discovered the nucleus. It was like, oh yeah, it was like, how's this going to work, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Because how do you get anything within these distances? Inquire…
SPEAKER_0:  extraordinary energy and it does and in fact when you look at those energies they're very, very high.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  But it turns out quantum physics comes to the rescue.
SPEAKER_0:  because the particles aren't
SPEAKER_0:  aren't actually just particles, they're also waves. This is the point of quantum, right? You can treat them both as waves and as...
SPEAKER_0:  as particles.
SPEAKER_0:  And it turns out if you get
SPEAKER_0:  if they get in close enough proximity to each other.
SPEAKER_0:  Then
SPEAKER_0:  The
SPEAKER_0:  Dynasty
SPEAKER_0:  pops through.
SPEAKER_0:  basically this energy barrier through an effect called quantum tunneling.
SPEAKER_0:  which is really just the transposition of the fact that it's a wave.
SPEAKER_0:  so that it has a finite probability of this.
SPEAKER_0:  It's, it's, by the way, you talk about like, do you have a hard time like conceptualizing this? These are, this is one of them. It's quantum tunnel is one of them. Yeah. This is like throwing a ping pong ball, like at a piece of paper and then every like, you know, 100 of them just like magically show up on the other side of the paper without seemingly breaking the paper. I mean, to use a physical analogy.
SPEAKER_1:  And that phenomenon is critical for the function of nuclear fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  for all kinds of fusions so this
SPEAKER_0:  This is the reason why stars can work as well too. Like the pr-
SPEAKER_0:  Stars would have to be much, much hotter actually to be able to... In fact, it's not clear that they would actually ignite.
SPEAKER_0:  In fact, without this effect.
SPEAKER_0:  So we get to that. So this is why there's another requirement. It's not, so you must make a plasma, but you also must get it very hot.
SPEAKER_0:  in order for the reactions to have a significant probability to actually fuse.
SPEAKER_0:  and it actually falls effectively almost to zero for lower temperatures.
SPEAKER_0:  as well too.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's some nice equation that gets you to 50 million degrees.
SPEAKER_1:  or like a... Yeah,
SPEAKER_1:  The order you said practically speak.
SPEAKER_0:  making a hundred million. It's a really simple equation. It's the ideal gas law basically almost always in the end you've got a
SPEAKER_0:  certain.
SPEAKER_0:  number of these fusion particles in the plasma state. They're in the plasma state. There's a certain number of particles.
SPEAKER_0:  And if the confinement is perfect, if you put in a certain content of energy, then basically, eventually they just...
SPEAKER_0:  they come up in a temperature.
SPEAKER_0:  and they go up to high temperature.
SPEAKER_0:  This turns out to be, by the way, extraordinarily small amounts of energy.
SPEAKER_0:  And you go, what? It's like I'm getting something to like a hundred million degrees. That's going to take the biggest.
SPEAKER_0:  that I've ever seen.
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  And the reason for this is it goes back to the energy content.
SPEAKER_0:  of this.
SPEAKER_0:  So yeah, you have to get it to high average energy.
SPEAKER_0:  But there's very, very few particles.
SPEAKER_1:  low density. How do you get it to be low density?
SPEAKER_0:  in the reactor is this. So the way that you do this is primarily, again, this is not exactly true in all kinds of fusion, but
SPEAKER_0:  And the, in the primary one that we work on magnetic fusion, this is all happening in a hard vacuum, so it's like it's happening in outer space. So basically you've gotten rid of all the other particles except for these specialized. So you had them one at a time.
SPEAKER_0:  No, actually it's even easier than that. You connect a gas valve.
SPEAKER_0:  and you basically leak gas into it in a controlled fashion. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  This is beautiful. It's a gas cylinder. How do you get it from hitting the walls?
SPEAKER_0:  So now you've touched on the other necessary requirements. So it turns out it's not just temperature that's required.
SPEAKER_0:  You must also confine it.
SPEAKER_0:  So what does this mean? What does this mean?
SPEAKER_1:  And there's two types of confinement as you mentioned, you mentioned the magnetic.
SPEAKER_0:  Magnetic one.
SPEAKER_0:  There's one called inertial as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  But the general principle actually has nothing to do with
SPEAKER_0:  in particular with what the technology is that you use to confine it.
SPEAKER_0:  It's because...
SPEAKER_0:  This goes back to the fact that the requirement in this is high temperature and thermal content.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's like building a fire.
SPEAKER_0:  And what this means is that if you, when you release the energy...
SPEAKER_0:  into this or apply heat to this.
SPEAKER_0:  If it just instantly leaks out, it can never get hot, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So you're familiar with this as like, you've got something that you're, you're, you're trying to apply heat to, but you're just throwing the heat away very quickly. This is why we insulate homes by the way, and things like this, right? It's like, you don't want the heat that's coming into this room to just immediately leave because you'll just start consuming infinite amounts of heat to try to keep it hot.
SPEAKER_0:  So in the end, this is one of the requirements, and it actually has a name. We call the energy confinement time.
SPEAKER_0:  So this means if you release a certain amount of energy into this fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  how long does it take for this energy to leave the system? So you could imagine that in this room...
SPEAKER_0:  that these heaters are putting energy into the air in this room and you waited for a day, but all the heat have gone to outside. If I open up the windows, that's energy confinement time. Okay, so it's the same concept as that.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is an important one. So all fusion must have confinement.
SPEAKER_0:  There's another more esoteric reason for this, which is that
SPEAKER_0:  people often confuse temperature and energy.
SPEAKER_0:  So what I mean by that.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is literally a temperature, which means that it is a-
SPEAKER_0:  system in which all the particles, every particle...
SPEAKER_0:  has high kinetic energy and is actually in a fully relaxed state, namely that entropy has been maximized. It gets a little bit more technical, but this means that basically it is.
SPEAKER_0:  It is a thermal system. So it's like the air in this room, it's like the water, it's the water in this. These all have temperatures, which means that there's a distribution of those energies because the particles have collided so much that it's there.
SPEAKER_0:  So we.
SPEAKER_0:  This is distinguished from having high energy particles, like what we have in particle accelerators, like CERN and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  Those are...
SPEAKER_0:  high kinetic energy but it's not a temperature so it actually doesn't count as confinement.
SPEAKER_0:  So we go through all of those.
SPEAKER_0:  You have temperature and then the other requirement, not too surprising is actually that there has to be enough.
SPEAKER_0:  density of the fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  Enough, but not too much. Enough, but not too much, yes. And so.
SPEAKER_0:  in the end.
SPEAKER_0:  The way that there's a fancy name for it is called the Lawson Criterion because it was formulated by scientists in the United Kingdom.
SPEAKER_0:  about 1956 or 1957.
SPEAKER_0:  And this was essentially the realization of, oh, this is what it's going to take, regardless of the confinement method.
SPEAKER_0:  These are, this is the basic, what it is actually power balances just says
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a certain amount of heat coming in, which is coming from the fusion reaction itself.
SPEAKER_0:  because the fusion reaction heats the fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  versus how fast you would lose it.
SPEAKER_0:  and it basically summarized by those three parameters, which is fairly simple. So temperature,
SPEAKER_0:  And then the reason we say 100 million degrees is because...
SPEAKER_0:  almost always in-
SPEAKER_0:  And for this kind of fusion, deuterium tritium fusion, the minimum and the density and the confinement time product is at about a hundred million. So you almost always design your device around that minimum.
SPEAKER_0:  and then you try to get it contained well enough.
SPEAKER_0:  and you try to get enough density. So
SPEAKER_0:  You know, so that temperature thing sounds.
SPEAKER_0:  Crazy.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what we've actually achieved in the laboratory, like our experiment here.
SPEAKER_0:  at MIT when it ran its optimum configuration.
SPEAKER_0:  It was at 100 million degrees.
SPEAKER_0:  but it wasn't actually the product of the density in the confinement time.
SPEAKER_0:  wasn't sufficient that we were at a place that we were getting.
SPEAKER_0:  high net energy gain.
SPEAKER_0:  but it was making fusion reactions.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is the sequence that you go through, make a plasma.
SPEAKER_0:  then you get it hot enough.
SPEAKER_0:  and when you get it hot enough, the fusion reactions start happening so rapidly.
SPEAKER_0:  that it's overcoming the rate at which it's leaking heat to the outside world.
SPEAKER_0:  and at some point it just becomes like a star.
SPEAKER_0:  Like a sun.
SPEAKER_0:  and our own sun and a star doesn't have anything plugged into it. It's just keeping itself hot through its own fusion reactions.
SPEAKER_0:  In the end, that's really close to what a fusion power plant would look like. What does it visually look like?
SPEAKER_1:  like does it does it look like like you said like purple plasma
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, actually it's invisible to the eye because it's so hot that it's basically emitting light in frequencies that we can't detect.
SPEAKER_0:  It's literal, it's invisible.
SPEAKER_0:  Ha ha!
SPEAKER_0:  In fact, light goes through it, visible light goes through it so easy that if you were to look at it, what you would see...
SPEAKER_0:  In our own particular configuration, what we make is in the end is a donut shaped, it's a vacuum vessel to keep the air out of it.
SPEAKER_0:  And when you turn on the plasma, it gets so hot that most of it just disappears in the visible spectrum.
SPEAKER_0:  You can't see anything.
SPEAKER_0:  and there's very, very cold plasma.
SPEAKER_0:  which is between 10 and 100,000 degrees.
SPEAKER_0:  which is out in the very periphery of it, which is kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  So the very cold plasma is allowed to interact with the...
SPEAKER_0:  and kind of has to interact with something eventually at the boundary of the vacuum vessel. And this kind of makes a little halo around it and it glows this beautiful purple.
SPEAKER_0:  light basically and these are that's the that's the that's what we can sense in the human spectrum. I remember..
SPEAKER_1:  reading on the subreddit called Shower Thoughts.
SPEAKER_1:  I wish people should check out. It's just fascinating philosophical ideas that strike you while you're in the shower.
SPEAKER_1:  And one of them was
SPEAKER_1:  It's lucky that fire, when it burns...
SPEAKER_1:  communicates that it's hot using visible light. Otherwise, humans would be screwed.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if there's a deep profound truth to that, but nevertheless, I did find it in store.
SPEAKER_0:  thought subreddit. Actually, I do have the- thanks for watching
SPEAKER_0:  This goes off in a bit of, you're right, this is actually, it's interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  Because as a scientist, you also think about evolutionary functions and how we got, like why do we have the senses that we do? Yeah. Interesting question.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like why can bees see an ultraviolet and we can't?
SPEAKER_0:  then you go, well, it's natural selection. For some reason, this wasn't really particularly important to us, right? Why can't we see in the infrared and other things can? It's like, hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a fascinating question, right? Obviously there's some advantage that you have there that isn't there and even color distinguishing, right? Of something safe to ease, whatever it would be.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll actually go back to this because it's something that I tell all of my students when I'm teaching.
SPEAKER_0:  ionizing radiation and radiological safety.
SPEAKER_0:  Whatever you say, there's a cultural.
SPEAKER_0:  concern or...
SPEAKER_0:  than when people hear the word radiation. Like, what does this mean? It literally just means light.
SPEAKER_0:  is what it means, right?
SPEAKER_0:  but it's light in different parts of the spectrum.
SPEAKER_0:  All right.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it turns out besides the visible light that we can see here, we are immersed.
SPEAKER_0:  in almost the totality of the electromagnetic spectrum.
SPEAKER_0:  There's visible light, there's infrared light.
SPEAKER_0:  There is microwaves going around, as that's how our cell phone works. It's way past our detection capability.
SPEAKER_0:  but also higher energy ones, which have to do with ultraviolet light, how you get a sunburn.
SPEAKER_0:  And even x-rays and things like this at small levels are continually being like from the concrete in the walls of this hotel, there's x-rays hitting our body continuously. I can bring out a, we can go down to the lab at MIT, you can bring out a detector and show you every single room we'll have.
SPEAKER_0:  and have these by our bo-
SPEAKER_1:  Why do you mean the 10th of the 28th?
SPEAKER_0:  atoms and they're coming in and they're interacting with those things.
SPEAKER_0:  And those particularly the ones where the light is at higher average energy per light particle.
SPEAKER_0:  Those are the ones that can possibly have an effect on human health.
SPEAKER_0:  So we...
SPEAKER_0:  It's interesting humans and all animals of
SPEAKER_0:  evolved on Earth where we're immersed in that all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  There's natural source of radiation all the time, yet we have zero ability to detect it.
SPEAKER_0:  like zero.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and our ability.
SPEAKER_1:  cognitive ability to filter it all out.
SPEAKER_1:  and not
SPEAKER_0:  It would probably overwhelm us actually, if we could see all of it. But my main point is, goes back to your thing about fire and self-protection.
SPEAKER_0:  if ionizing radiation was such a critical aspect of the health of organisms on earth.
SPEAKER_0:  We would almost certainly have evolved methods to detect it, and we have none.
SPEAKER_0:  Ha ha ha!
SPEAKER_0:  And yes, the physical world.
SPEAKER_1:  that's all around is so incredible. You're blowing my mind Dr. Dennis White. Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's say you have experience with magnetic confinement. You have experience with inertial confinement. Most of your work has been in magnetic confinement.
SPEAKER_1:  but let's sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  talk about the sexy recent thing for a bit of a time. There's been a breakthrough in the news.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  that laser-based inertial confinement was used by DOEs.
SPEAKER_1:  National Ignition Facility at the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you explain this breakthrough that happened in December? 왔어
SPEAKER_0:  So it goes to the set of criteria that I talked about before about getting.
SPEAKER_0:  high energy gain.
SPEAKER_0:  So in the end...
SPEAKER_0:  What are we after in fusion is that we...
SPEAKER_0:  We basically assemble this plasma fuel in some way.
SPEAKER_0:  and we provided a starting amount of energy. Think of lighting the fire.
SPEAKER_0:  And what you want to do is get back significant excess gain from the fact that the fusion is releasing the energy.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's like the equivalent of like...
SPEAKER_0:  We want to have a match, a small match, light a fire, and then the fire keeps us hot.
SPEAKER_0:  very much like that.
SPEAKER_0:  And so as I said, we've made many of the, and what do we mean by we? It's like the fusion community has pursued.
SPEAKER_0:  aspects of this through a variety of different confinement methodologies.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, is that the.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  the key part about what happens.
SPEAKER_0:  What was the threshold we had never gotten over before was that if you only consider the plasma fuel, not the total engineering system, but just the plasma fuel itself.
SPEAKER_0:  We had not gotten to the point yet where...
SPEAKER_0:  basically the size of the match
SPEAKER_0:  was smaller than the amount of energy that we got from the future.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there a good term for...
SPEAKER_1:  when the output
SPEAKER_1:  is greater than the input.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, yes, there is. Well, there's several special definitions of this. So one of them is that
SPEAKER_0:  If you, if you like in a fire, if you laid a match.
SPEAKER_0:  and you have it there and it's an infinitesimal amount of energy compared to what you're getting out of the fire. We call this ignition.
SPEAKER_0:  Which makes sense, right? This is like what our own son is as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  So that was not ignition in that sense as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  So what we call this is scientific, the one that I just talked about, which is for some instance.
SPEAKER_0:  when I get enough fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  energy released compared to the size of the match.
SPEAKER_0:  We call this scientific break even.
SPEAKER_0:  Breakeven. Breakeven. And it's because you've gotten past the fact that this is Unity now.
SPEAKER_0:  at this point.
SPEAKER_1:  fusion gain or as using the notation Q from the paper overview of the Spark talk mark before using
SPEAKER_0:  the same kind of term. Yeah actually so that is sorry the technical term is Q.
SPEAKER_0:  capital Q.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, so people actually use Q. We actually use capital Q or somebody's is called Q. Q is taken. Q sub P or something like this. Okay, so this is.
SPEAKER_0:  Which means, what it means is that it's in the plasma.
SPEAKER_0:  So all we're considering is the energy balance or gain that comes from the plasma itself. We're not considering.
SPEAKER_0:  the technologies which are around it, which are providing the containment and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  So why the excitement and so on? Well, because for one reason, it's a rather simple threshold to get over.
SPEAKER_0:  to understand that you're getting more energy out from the fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  even the theoretical sense than you were from the, you know, from the starting match. Do you mean conceptually simple? It's conceptually simple that you get past one that everyone under, like when you're less than one.
SPEAKER_0:  That's much less interesting than getting past one. So that's a really big threshold.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah
SPEAKER_0:  but it really is a scientific threshold because what QP.
SPEAKER_0:  actually
SPEAKER_0:  the notes.
SPEAKER_0:  is the relative amount of self-heating.
SPEAKER_0:  that's happening in the plasma.
SPEAKER_0:  So what I mean by this.
SPEAKER_0:  is that in the end in these systems...
SPEAKER_0:  And what you want is...
SPEAKER_0:  Something that where the.
SPEAKER_0:  the relative amount of heating.
SPEAKER_0:  which is keeping the fuel hot is dominated by
SPEAKER_0:  from the fusion reactions themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it becomes...
SPEAKER_0:  It's sort of like thinking like a bonfire is a lot more interesting physically than just holding a blowtorch to a wet log.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a lot more dynamics, it's a lot more self-evolved and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  And what we're excited as scientists is that it's clear that in that experiment...
SPEAKER_0:  that they actually got to a point where the fusion reactions themselves
SPEAKER_0:  we're actually altering the state of the plasma.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, wow, I mean, we'd seen it in glimpses before in magnetic confinement at relatively small levels.
SPEAKER_0:  But apparently it seems like in this experiment it's likely to be a dominant.
SPEAKER_0:  dominated by self-heating. That's a very important, that's a very-
SPEAKER_1:  So that makes it a salsa style.
SPEAKER_0:  self-sustaining type of interaction. More self-sustaining, it's more self-referential system.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... in innocence
SPEAKER_0:  And it sort of self evolves in a way. Again, it's not that it's going to evolve to a dangerous state. It's just that.
SPEAKER_0:  We want to see what happens when the fusion is the dominant heating source.
SPEAKER_0:  And we'll talk about that but...
SPEAKER_1:  So there's also another element which is the inertial confinement.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... laser-based initial confinement is kind of a little bit of an underdog
SPEAKER_1:  I guess so a lot of the...
SPEAKER_1:  broad nuclear fusion community has been focused on magnetic confinement. rocks
SPEAKER_1:  just how laser based.
SPEAKER_1:  inertial confinement works. So it says, uh,
SPEAKER_1:  192 laser beams.
SPEAKER_1:  or lined.
SPEAKER_1:  on a deuterium tritium DT targets smaller than a P.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, this is like, okay, well, you know, it depends. Not all P's are made the same, but, uh, this is like, uh, throwing a perfect strike in baseball from a pitch. This is like a journalist wrote to say, I think this is like, Oh, no, it's not a journalist. DOE.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, yeah, we try to use all these analogies.
SPEAKER_1:  This is like throwing a perfect strike in baseball from a-
SPEAKER_1:  pictures mount 350 miles away from the plate.
SPEAKER_1:  There you go.
SPEAKER_1:  Department of Energy, the United States Department of Energy wrote this.
SPEAKER_0:  I can't explain it.
SPEAKER_1:  What the?
SPEAKER_0:  with the lasers. What actually happens, actually there's usually mass confusion about this.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So what's going on in this form of it? So I think what
SPEAKER_0:  The fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  is delivered in a discreet, the fusion fuel, the deuterium intradium.
SPEAKER_0:  is in a discreet spherical, it's more like a BB, let's call it a BB, so it's a small one. And all the fuel that you're gonna try to burn is basically there.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's about that size.
SPEAKER_0:  So what's hap, so how are you going to get, and it's that.
SPEAKER_0:  Literally, it's like 20 degrees above absolute zero because the deuterium and tritium are kept in
SPEAKER_0:  in a liquid and solid state.
SPEAKER_1:  the fuel is injected not as a gas as a solid
SPEAKER_0:  It's actually, and these are particular experiments they can introduce one of these, you know,
SPEAKER_0:  these targets once per day, approximately something like that. Cause it's very-
SPEAKER_0:  It's very, it's kind of amazing technology actually that I know some of the people that worked on this back in the is.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  They actually make these things at a BB size of this frozen fuel. It's actually at cryogenic temperatures.
SPEAKER_0:  and they're almost like smooth to the atom level. I mean they're amazing pieces of technology.
SPEAKER_0:  So what you do in the end is.
SPEAKER_0:  think you, what you have is a spherical.
SPEAKER_0:  assembly of this fuel like a ball.
SPEAKER_0:  And what is the purpose of the lasers? The purpose of the lasers is to provide optical energy.
SPEAKER_0:  to the very outside of this.
SPEAKER_0:  And what happens is...
SPEAKER_0:  that energy is absorbed.
SPEAKER_0:  because it's in the solid phase of matter, so it's absorbed really in the surface.
SPEAKER_0:  And then what happens is that when it's absorbed into something called the ablator, what does that mean?
SPEAKER_0:  It means it goes instantly from.
SPEAKER_0:  the solid phase to the gas phase. So it becomes like a rocket engine.
SPEAKER_0:  but you hit it like very uniformly.
SPEAKER_0:  So all, there's like rocket engines coming off the surface. Think of like an asteroid almost, there's like rockets coming off.
SPEAKER_0:  So what does that do? Well, what does a rocket do? It actually pushes...
SPEAKER_0:  by Newton's laws, right? It pushes the other thing on the other side of it, equal and opposite reaction, it pushes it in.
SPEAKER_0:  So what it does is that the laser's actually.
SPEAKER_0:  Don't heat. This is what was confusing. People think the lasers, oh, we're gonna get it to a hundred million degrees. In fact, you want the exact opposite of this. What you want to do.
SPEAKER_0:  is get essentially a rocket going out like this.
SPEAKER_0:  And then.
SPEAKER_0:  What happens is that the sphere, like, and this is happening in a billionth of a second or less actually.
SPEAKER_0:  this rapidly, that force like so rapidly.
SPEAKER_0:  compresses the fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  that what happens is that you're squeezing down on it and.
SPEAKER_0:  And, you know, it's like, what was the...
SPEAKER_0:  See BB, that's bad actually, I should have started with a basketball. Basket goes from like a basketball down to something like, like this.
SPEAKER_0:  and a billionth of a second.
SPEAKER_0:  And when that happens, I mean, scale that in your mind.
SPEAKER_0:  So when that happens, and in this comes from...
SPEAKER_0:  almost from classical physics, so there's some quantum in it as well too. But basically, if you can do this.
SPEAKER_0:  like very uniformly and so-called adiabatically, like you're not actually heating the fuel. What happens is you get adiabatic compression.
SPEAKER_0:  such that the very center of this thing all of a sudden just spikes up in temperature because it's actually done so fast.
SPEAKER_0:  So why is it called inertial fusion? It's because you're doing this on such fast time scales that the inertia of the hot fuel basically isentropic.
SPEAKER_0:  is still finite so it can't like push itself apart before the fusion happens.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh wow.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you make it so?
SPEAKER_0:  how do you make it so fast? this is why you use lasers because
SPEAKER_0:  You're applying.
SPEAKER_0:  this energy in very, very short periods of time, like under a fraction of a billionth of a second.
SPEAKER_0:  And so basically that, and then the force, which is coming from this, comes from the energy of the lasers.
SPEAKER_0:  which is basically the rocket action which does the compression. which forces the force.
SPEAKER_1:  is the inward facing force is that is that increasing the temperature
SPEAKER_0:  No, you want to keep the fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  cold.
SPEAKER_0:  and then just literally just ideally compress it.
SPEAKER_0:  and then in something which is at the very center of that compressed sphere.
SPEAKER_0:  because you've compressed it so rapidly, the laws of physics basically require
SPEAKER_0:  for it to increase in temperature. So the change in pressure. The effect is like, if you know the thing, so adiabatic cooling we're actually fairly familiar with. If you take a spray can, right, and you push the button.
SPEAKER_0:  When it rapidly expands, it cools. This is the nature of a lot of cooling technology we use actually.
SPEAKER_0:  Well the opposite is true that if you would take all of those particles and jam them together very fast back in they want to heat up.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's what happens. And then what happens?
SPEAKER_0:  is you basically have this very cold compressed.
SPEAKER_0:  set of fusion fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  And at the center of this...
SPEAKER_0:  it goes to this hundred million degrees Celsius.
SPEAKER_0:  And so if it gets to that 100 million degrees Celsius, the fusion fuel starts to burn.
SPEAKER_0:  And when that fusion fuel starts to burn, it wants to heat up the other cold fuel around it and it just basically propagates out.
SPEAKER_0:  so fast that what you would do ideally, you would actually burn in a fusion sense and most of the fuel that's in the pellet.
SPEAKER_0:  So this was very exciting because what they had done was...
SPEAKER_0:  It's clear that they propagated.
SPEAKER_0:  this, they got this what they call a hotspot.
SPEAKER_0:  And in fact that this heating had propagated out into the fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's the science behind inertial fusion.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  behind a reactor that's based on this kind of inertial.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... confinement
SPEAKER_1:  is that you would have
SPEAKER_1:  A new BB every-
SPEAKER_0:  like 10 times a second or something like that.
SPEAKER_1:  is there's some kind of, so there's a incredible device that you kind of implied that kind of has to create one of those BBs.
SPEAKER_0:  So you have to make the BBs very fast.
SPEAKER_0:  There's reports on this, but what does it mean? The starting point is can you make this game?
SPEAKER_0:  So this was a scientific achievement primarily. Right. And the rest is just engineering. No, no, no. The rest is incredibly complicated engineering. Well, in fact, there's still physics hurdles to overcome. So
SPEAKER_0:  So where does this come from? And it's actually because if you want to make an energy source out of this.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... this had a gain of around one point five that namely the fusion energy was approximately was one point five times the
SPEAKER_0:  the laser input energy. And it's a fairly significant threshold.
SPEAKER_0:  However, from the-
SPEAKER_0:  from the science of what I just told you is that there's two fundamental efficiencies which come into it which really come from physics really.
SPEAKER_0:  One of them is hydrodynamic efficiency. What I mean by this is that it's a rocket.
SPEAKER_0:  So this just has a fundamental.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... efficiency uh... built into it
SPEAKER_0:  which comes out to orders of like 10%.
SPEAKER_0:  This means that your ability to do work on the system is just limited by that.
SPEAKER_0:  And then the other one is the efficiency of laser systems themselves, which if their wall plug efficiency is 10%, you've done spectacularly well.
SPEAKER_0:  In fact, the wall plug efficiency.
SPEAKER_0:  of the ones using that experiments are like more like 1%.
SPEAKER_0:  So when you go through all of this.
SPEAKER_0:  The approximate place that you're ordering this is for a fusion power plant would be a gain of 100 not 1.5.
SPEAKER_0:  So you still, you know, and hopefully we see experiments that keep
SPEAKER_0:  climbing up towards higher and higher.
SPEAKER_0:  game.
SPEAKER_0:  But then the whole fusion power plant is a totally different thing.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not one.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not one BB and one laser pulse per day. It's like five or 10 times per second.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, like that, right? So you're doing it there.
SPEAKER_0:  And then comes the other aspect, so it's making the targets, delivering them.
SPEAKER_0:  being able to repeatedly get them to burn.
SPEAKER_0:  And then we haven't even talked about like, how do you then get the fusion energy out?
SPEAKER_0:  which is mainly because these things
SPEAKER_0:  basically micro implosions which are occurring. So this energy is coming out to some medium on the outside that you've got to figure out how to extract the energy.
SPEAKER_0:  out of this thing.
SPEAKER_1:  that energy to electricity.
SPEAKER_0:  So in the end...
SPEAKER_0:  you have to basically convert it into heat in some way. so
SPEAKER_0:  most of the, in the end what fusion makes mostly is like high, very energetic particles from the fusion reaction.
SPEAKER_0:  So you have to slow those down in some way and then make heat out of it.
SPEAKER_0:  So basically the conversion of the kinetic energy of the particles into heating some
SPEAKER_0:  engineered material that's on the outside of this.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's...
SPEAKER_1:  from a physics perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  is a somewhat solved problem but from an engineering is
SPEAKER_1:  It's still, it's still.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, physics, I can draw the, I can show you all the equations that tell you about how it slows down and converts.
SPEAKER_0:  kinetic energy into heat.
SPEAKER_0:  And then what that heat means, you can write out like an ideal thermal cycle, like a Carnot cycle. So the physics of that, yeah, great. The integrated engineering of this is a whole other thing.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll ask you to maybe talk about the difference between inertial and magnetic, but first we'll talk about magnetic. But let me just linger on this breakthrough. You know, it's nice to have exciting things, but.
SPEAKER_1:  in a deep human sense, there's no competition in science and engineering.
SPEAKER_1:  world like you said we were broad.
SPEAKER_1:  First of all, we are humanity altogether. And you talk about this, it's a bunch of countries collaborating. It's really exciting.
SPEAKER_1:  others in nuclear
SPEAKER_1:  Fusion community broadly. But then there's also MIT, there's colors and logos and it's exciting and you are.
SPEAKER_1:  You have friends and colleagues here that work extremely hard and done some incredible stuff. Is there some?
SPEAKER_1:  sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you feel seeing somebody else?
SPEAKER_1:  get a breakthrough using a different technology. Is that exciting?
SPEAKER_1:  Does the competitive fire get...
SPEAKER_0:  All of the above. I mean, the ignition. I have, so, you know, just to wave the flag a little bit. So MIT was a central player.
SPEAKER_0:  in this accomplishment.
SPEAKER_0:  Interesting, I would say it showed some of our two best traits. So one of them was that the-
SPEAKER_0:  How do you know that this happened?
SPEAKER_0:  this measurement, right?
SPEAKER_0:  One of the ways to do this is if I...
SPEAKER_0:  told you is that in DT fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  What it actually, the product that comes out is helium.
SPEAKER_0:  We call it alpha, but it's helium.
SPEAKER_0:  and a free neutron.
SPEAKER_0:  So the neutron contains 80% of the energy released by the fusion reaction.
SPEAKER_0:  And it also, because it lacks a charge, it basically tends to just escape and go flying out. So this is what we would use eventually for.
SPEAKER_0:  That's mostly what fusion energy would be.
SPEAKER_0:  So what my colleagues, my scientific colleagues at the Plasmas Science Infusion Center built were extraordinary measurement tools of
SPEAKER_0:  being able to see the exact details of not only the number of neutrons that were coming out, but actually what energy that they're at.
SPEAKER_0:  And by looking at that configuration, it reveals enormous, I'm not gonna scoop them because they need to publish the paper, but it reveals enormous amounts of scientific information about what's happening in that process that I just described.
SPEAKER_0:  so excited I mean
SPEAKER_0:  And I have, you know, I have...
SPEAKER_0:  colleagues there that have worked like for 30 years on this for that moment.
SPEAKER_0:  Of course you're excited for them. Time for a minute.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's one of those, like, there is nothing, it's hard to describe to people who aren't, it's like almost addicting to be a scientist when you get to be at the forefront of research of anything.
SPEAKER_0:  When you see like an actual discovery of some kind and you're looking at it, particularly when you're the person who did it, right?
SPEAKER_0:  And you go, no human being has ever seen this or understood this. It's like, it's pretty thrilling, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So even in proxy, it's incredibly thrilling to see this.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not, I don't know, it's rivalry or jealousy. It's like...
SPEAKER_0:  I can tell you already, fusion is really hard. So anything that keeps pushing the needle forward is a good thing.
SPEAKER_0:  But we also have to be realistic about what it means, you know, to making a fusion energy system. That's the...
SPEAKER_1:  And then, but that's the fun. I mean, these are the still the early.
SPEAKER_1:  steps you maybe you can say the early leaps.
SPEAKER_1:  So let's talk about the magnetic confinement.
SPEAKER_1:  How does magnetic confinement work? What's a takamak?
SPEAKER_1:  UGH
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, how does it all work?
SPEAKER_0:  to go back to that, so why inertial confinement works on the same principle that a star works.
SPEAKER_0:  So like what is the confinement mechanism in the star?
SPEAKER_0:  is gravity.
SPEAKER_0:  because it's its own inertia.
SPEAKER_0:  of the something the size of the sun
SPEAKER_0:  basically pushes a force by gravity against the center.
SPEAKER_0:  The center is very, very hot, 20 million degrees, and literally outside the sun it's essentially zero because it's the vacuum of space.
SPEAKER_0:  How the hell does it do that?
SPEAKER_0:  It does that.
SPEAKER_0:  Why doesn't it just leak all of its heat? It doesn't leak its heat because it all is held together by the fact that it can't escape because of its own gravity.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is why the fusion happens in the center of the star.
SPEAKER_0:  Like we think of the surface of the sun as being hot. That's the coldest part of the story.
SPEAKER_0:  So, over our own sun, this is about 5,500 degrees. Beautiful symmetry, by the way.
SPEAKER_0:  So how do we know all this? Cuz...
SPEAKER_0:  We can't of course see directly into the interior of the sun.
SPEAKER_0:  By knowing the volume and the temperature of the surface of the sun, you know exactly how much power it's putting out.
SPEAKER_0:  and by this you know that this is coming from fusion reactions occurring.
SPEAKER_0:  at exactly the same rate.
SPEAKER_0:  in the middle of the sun.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it possible as a small tangent?
SPEAKER_1:  to build.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  inertial
SPEAKER_1:  confinement system like the sun is it possible to create
SPEAKER_0:  a sun. It is of course possible to make a sun, although you wouldn't have stars.
SPEAKER_0:  but it is not impossible on earth because for the simple reason that it takes
SPEAKER_0:  The gravitational force is extremely weak and so it takes something like the size of a star to make fusion occur in the center.
SPEAKER_1:  I didn't mean on earth. I mean if you had to build like a second Sun
SPEAKER_0:  How'd you do it?
SPEAKER_0:  You can't, there's not enough hydrogen around.
SPEAKER_1:  So the delimiting factor is the...
SPEAKER_1:  just the hydrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean the forces and energy that it takes to assemble that is just...
SPEAKER_0:  Mind boggling.
SPEAKER_0:  All right. So we wouldn't do that. To be continued. Yeah, to be continued. So what are we doing it with? So in the one that I just described, it's like you say, so you have to replace this with some force, which is
SPEAKER_0:  better than that.
SPEAKER_0:  And so what I mean by that is it's stronger than that.
SPEAKER_0:  So when I talked about the laser fusion...
SPEAKER_0:  This is coming from the force which is enormous compared to gravity.
SPEAKER_0:  like from the rocket action of pushing it together.
SPEAKER_0:  So in magnetic confinement...
SPEAKER_0:  We use another force of nature, which is the electromagnetic force.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's very, it's.
SPEAKER_0:  orders and orders of magnitude stronger than the gravitational force.
SPEAKER_0:  And the key force that matters here is that if you have a charged particle, namely it's a particle that has an electric net electric charge,
SPEAKER_0:  and it's in the proximity of a magnetic field.
SPEAKER_0:  then there is a force which is exerted on that particle.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is called the Lorentz force for those who are keeping track. So that is the force that we use to replace physical containment.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  So this again, confused. How do you hold something at a hundred million degrees? It's impossible in a physical container.
SPEAKER_0:  This is not like
SPEAKER_0:  It's not this plastic bottle holding in this liquid or a gas chamber.
SPEAKER_0:  What you're doing is you're immersing the fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  in a magnetic field.
SPEAKER_0:  that basically exerts a force at a distance. This comes back again to again, like why plazas are so strange. It's the same thing here. And if it's immersed in this magnetic field, you're not actually physically touching it.
SPEAKER_0:  but you're making a force go onto it.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's the inherent feature of magnetic confinement.
SPEAKER_0:  And then magnetic confinement devices are like a Tokamak are basically.
SPEAKER_0:  are configurations which exploit the features of that magnetic containment.
SPEAKER_0:  There's several features to it. One is that the stronger the strength of the magnetic field, the stronger the force.
SPEAKER_0:  And for this reason is that if you increase the strength of magnetic fields
SPEAKER_0:  This means that the containment, because namely the force which you're pushing against it is more effective.
SPEAKER_0:  And the other feature is that there is no force.
SPEAKER_0:  So for those who remember magnetic fields, what are these things? They're also invisible. But, you know, if you think of a permanent magnets or your fridge magnet, there are, there are.
SPEAKER_0:  field lines, which we actually designate as arrows, which are going around you sometimes.
SPEAKER_0:  See this in school when you have the
SPEAKER_0:  you know, the iron filings on a thing and you see the directions of the magnetic field lines.
SPEAKER_0:  or when you use a compass.
SPEAKER_0:  That's telling you because we're living in an immersed magnetic field made by the Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  which is at very low intensity magnetic, but it's strong enough that we can actually see what direction is it. So this is the arrow that the magnetic field is pointing. It's always pointing north and for us.
SPEAKER_0:  is out.
SPEAKER_0:  So an interesting feature of this force is that there is no force along the direction of the magnetic field.
SPEAKER_0:  There's only force in the directions orthogonal to the magnet.
SPEAKER_0:  So this, by the way, is a huge deal in a whole other discipline of plasma physics, which is like the study of like our near atmosphere.
SPEAKER_0:  So the study of aurora borealis.
SPEAKER_0:  what's happening in the near atmosphere, what happens when solar flares hit the magnetic. In fact.
SPEAKER_0:  Remember I said.
SPEAKER_0:  Fusion is the reason that life is responsible.
SPEAKER_0:  In the universe?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you could also argue so is magnetic confinement because...
SPEAKER_0:  the charged particles which are being emitted from.
SPEAKER_0:  from the galaxy and from our own star.
SPEAKER_0:  would be very, very damaging on Earth. So we get two layers of protection. One is the atmosphere itself.
SPEAKER_0:  But the other one is the magnetic field which surrounds the Earth and basically traps these charged particles so they can't get away. It's the same deal.
SPEAKER_1:  How do you create a strong magnetic field? Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  With a giant magnet. Giant magnet, yeah. So it's basically true.
SPEAKER_0:  engineering is essentially essentially two ways to create a magnet so one of them is that we're familiar with like fridge magnets and so forth these are so-called permanent magnets
SPEAKER_0:  And what it means is that...
SPEAKER_0:  Within these, the atoms arrange in a particular way that it produces, the electrons basically arrange in a particular way, that it produces a permanent magnetic field that is set by the material.
SPEAKER_0:  So those have a fundamental limitation, how strong they can be and they also tend to have.
SPEAKER_0:  this.
SPEAKER_0:  like circular shape like this. So we don't typically use those.
SPEAKER_0:  So what we use are so-called electromagnets. And what is this? I don't know, I'm so sorry.
SPEAKER_0:  So the other way to make a magnetic field is to also go back to your elementary school physics.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... or science class
SPEAKER_0:  is that you take a nail and you wrap a copper wire around it and connect it to a battery, then it can pick up iron filings.
SPEAKER_0:  This is an electromagnet.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's simplest what it is, it's an electric current which is going in a pattern around and around and around.
SPEAKER_0:  And what this does is it produces a magnetic field which goes through it by the laws of electromagnetism.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's how we make the magnetic field in these configurations.
SPEAKER_0:  And the key there is that it's not limited by the magnetic property of the material.
SPEAKER_0:  the magnetic field amplitude is set by the amount of
SPEAKER_0:  the geometry of this thing and the amount of electric current that you're putting through.
SPEAKER_0:  and the more electric current that you put through, the more magnetic field that you get.
SPEAKER_0:  The closest one.
SPEAKER_0:  that people maybe see is...
SPEAKER_0:  Wanna move?
SPEAKER_0:  One of my favorite skits actually was Super Dave Osborne on, mehr raining sun on, sc'nie the
SPEAKER_0:  probably passed you is a show called Super Dave Osborne, which is a great comedian cult.
SPEAKER_0:  He was a stunt man and one of his tricks was that he was, he gets into a car and then one of those things in the junkyard comes down, you know, and picks up the car and then puts it into the, into the crusher. This was his stunt, which is pretty hilarious.
SPEAKER_0:  Anyway, but that thing that picks them up.
SPEAKER_0:  Like how does that work? That's actually not a permanent magnet. It's an, it's an electro magnet.
SPEAKER_0:  And so you can turn by turning off and on the power supply, it turns off and on the magnetic field. So this means you can pick it up and then when you switch it off,
SPEAKER_0:  magnetic field goes away and the car drops. Okay. So that's, that's what it looks like.
SPEAKER_0:  Speaking of giant magnets.
SPEAKER_1:  MIT in...
SPEAKER_1:  Commonwealth
SPEAKER_1:  Fusion Systems CFS.
SPEAKER_1:  built a.
SPEAKER_1:  Very large, high temperature, superconducting electromagnet.
SPEAKER_1:  that was ramped up to a fuel strength of 20 Tesla, the most powerful magnetic field of its kind ever created down on earth.
SPEAKER_1:  because I enjoy this kind of thing. Can you please tell me about this magnet?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, sure.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh it was.
SPEAKER_0:  It's fun, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a lot to parse there. So maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  So we already explained an electromagnet which...
SPEAKER_0:  in general is
SPEAKER_0:  What you do is you take electric current and you force it to
SPEAKER_0:  to follow a pattern of some kind, typically like a circular pattern.
SPEAKER_0:  around and around and around and around. And it goes the more time, the more current and the more times it goes around, the stronger the magnetic field that you make.
SPEAKER_0:  And as I pointed out, it's like really important in magnetic confinement because it is the force that's produced by that magnetic. In fact, technically it goes like the magnetic field squared.
SPEAKER_0:  because it's a pressure which is actually being exerted on.
SPEAKER_0:  the plasma to keep it.
SPEAKER_0:  contained.
SPEAKER_1:  Just so we know for magnetic confinement.
SPEAKER_1:  What is usually the geometry of the magnet?
SPEAKER_0:  What are we supposed to imagine? Yeah, so the geometry typically is what you do is
SPEAKER_0:  you want to produce a magnetic field that loops back on itself.
SPEAKER_0:  and the reason for this was
SPEAKER_0:  goes down to the nature of the forest that I described.
SPEAKER_0:  Which is that there's no-
SPEAKER_0:  there's no containment or force along the direction of the magnetic field.
SPEAKER_0:  So here's a magnetic field. In fact, what it's.
SPEAKER_0:  more technically or more graphically what it's doing is that
SPEAKER_0:  When the plasma is here, there's plasma particles here.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a magnetic field.
SPEAKER_0:  What it does is it forces all those, because of this, this Lorentz force.
SPEAKER_0:  It makes all of those charged particles execute circular orbits around the magnetic field. And they go around like this.
SPEAKER_0:  but they stream freely along the magnetic field.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is why the nature of the containment is that if you can get that circle smaller and smaller, it stays further away from earth, temperature materials. That's why the confinement gets better.
SPEAKER_0:  But the problem is that because it free streams along, so we just have a long straight magnetic field.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, it'll just keep leaking out the ends like really fast.
SPEAKER_0:  So you get rid of the ends. So you basically loop it.
SPEAKER_0:  So what these look like are typically donut shaped or.
SPEAKER_0:  or technically toroidal shape it.
SPEAKER_0:  donut shaped.
SPEAKER_0:  things where this collection of magnetic fields loops back on itself, and it also for reasons which are more complicated to explain.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically it also twists slowly around in this direction.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's what it looks like. That's what the plasma looks like because that's what the fuel looks like.
SPEAKER_0:  So then this means is that the.
SPEAKER_0:  the electromagnets.
SPEAKER_0:  are configured in such a way that it produces the desired magnetic fields around this. How precise does this have to be? You were probably listening to our conversation with some of my colleagues yesterday.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's actually, it depends on the configuration about how you're doing it.
SPEAKER_0:  configuration of the plasma. The configuration of the electromagnets and about how you're achieving this this requirement.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  It's, it's, it's fairly precise, but it doesn't have to be in, particularly in something like a Tokamak. What we do is we produce.
SPEAKER_0:  planar coils, which just mean they're flat.
SPEAKER_0:  and we situate them. So if you think of.
SPEAKER_0:  a circle like this.
SPEAKER_0:  What does it produce if you put current through it? It produces a magnetic field which goes through the circle like this.
SPEAKER_0:  So if you align many of them like this, this, this, this, there's things online, you can go see the picture of dude.
SPEAKER_0:  You keep arranging these around in a circle itself.
SPEAKER_0:  This forces the magnetic field lines to basically just keep executing around like this.
SPEAKER_0:  So you tend to align.
SPEAKER_0:  That one tends to, well, it requires.
SPEAKER_0:  good alignment, it's not like insane alignment because you're...
SPEAKER_0:  You're actually exploring the symmetry of the situation to help it.
SPEAKER_0:  There's another kind of configuration of this kind of magnetic confinement called a stellarator which...
SPEAKER_0:  We have these names for historic reasons. Which is different than a tokamak. It's different than a tokamak, but it actually works on the same physical principle that namely, in the end it produces a plasma which loops in magnetic fields, which loop back on themselves. parallel bodies.
SPEAKER_0:  In that case, the totality of the confining magnetic field is produced.
SPEAKER_0:  by external three dimensional magnets, so they're twisted.
SPEAKER_0:  And it turns out the precision of those is more stringent.
SPEAKER_1:  So are talkamags by far more popular for research and development currently than...
SPEAKER_0:  Stellar Raiders.
SPEAKER_0:  of the concepts which are there, the Tokamak is by far the most.
SPEAKER_0:  mature in terms of its.
SPEAKER_0:  breadth of performance and um and
SPEAKER_0:  thinking about how it would be applied in a fusion energy system.
SPEAKER_0:  The history of this was that many, in fact, you asked about this, if we go back to the history of the Piles, Science and Fusion Center.
SPEAKER_0:  The history of fusion is that
SPEAKER_0:  People.
SPEAKER_0:  scientists had started to work on this in the 1950s. It was all hush-hush and cold war and all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like, they realized, holy cow, this is like really hard. Like we actually don't really know like what we're doing in this.
SPEAKER_0:  because everything was at low temperatures, they couldn't get confinement.
SPEAKER_0:  It was interesting. And then they declassified it. And this is one of the few places that the West and the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  actually collaborated on was a science. Even during the cold war. Even during the middle of the cold war, it was really.
SPEAKER_0:  And this actually perpetuates all the way till now for, we can talk about the project that that is sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  captured it now.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... but
SPEAKER_0:  And the reason they declassified it is because like everything like
SPEAKER_0:  kind of like sucked basically, you know, about trying to make this confinement high-temperature plasma.
SPEAKER_0:  And then the Russians...
SPEAKER_0:  then the Soviets came along with this device called a Tokamak, which is a Russian acronym, which basically means
SPEAKER_0:  magnetic coils arranged in the shape of a doughnut.
SPEAKER_0:  And they said, holy cow.
SPEAKER_0:  Like everyone was stuck at like a meager, like half a million degrees.
SPEAKER_0:  half a million degrees, which is like infusion terms of zero basically.
SPEAKER_0:  And then they come along and they say, oh, we've actually achieved a temperature 20 times higher than everybody else.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's actually started to make fusion reactions and everyone just go, oh.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, no way, it's just hype from the, it's like, there's no way because we've failed at this.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  It's a great story in the history of fusion is that then, but they insisted and said, no, look, you can see this from our data. It's like this thing is really hot.
SPEAKER_0:  And it seems to be working. This is, you know, late 1960s.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  there was a...
SPEAKER_0:  There was a team that went from the United Kingdom's fusion development lab.
SPEAKER_0:  and they brought this very fancy.
SPEAKER_0:  amazing new technology called a laser.
SPEAKER_0:  and they used this laser and they shot the laser beam through the plasma.
SPEAKER_0:  And by looking at the scattered light that came from the...
SPEAKER_0:  There you go.
SPEAKER_0:  that basically the scattered light gets more.
SPEAKER_0:  broadened in its spectrum if it gets hotter.
SPEAKER_0:  So you could exactly tell the temperature of this. And even though you're not physically touching the plasma, it's like, holy cow, you're right. It is like, it is 10 million degrees.
SPEAKER_0:  And so this was one of those explosions of like.
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone in the world then wanted to build a tokamak because
SPEAKER_0:  It was clearly like, wow, this is like so far ahead of everything else that we tried.
SPEAKER_0:  So that actually has a part of the story to MIT in the Plosnice infusion center was
SPEAKER_0:  why is there a strong fusion and a major fusion program at MIT? it was because
SPEAKER_0:  we were host to the Francis Bitter Magnet Laboratory, which is also the National High Field Magnet Laboratory.
SPEAKER_0:  you can see where this goes. We're telling the stories backwards almost.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, the, the, the advent of a Tokamak.
SPEAKER_0:  along with the fact that you could make very strong magnetic fields with the technology that had been developed at that laboratory. That was the origins of sort of pushing together the physics of the plasma containment.
SPEAKER_0:  and the magnet technology and put them together.
SPEAKER_0:  in a way that I would say is a very typical MIT success story. We don't do just-
SPEAKER_0:  just pure science or pure technology, we sort of set up this intersection between them and the room.
SPEAKER_0:  several pioneers that.
SPEAKER_0:  of my of the of people at m i t like brutal copy who's a professor in the physics department and ron parker was a
SPEAKER_0:  professor of electrical engineering and nuclear engineering. It's like even the makeup of the people, right, has got this blends of science and engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  And that actually was the origin of the Plot of Science Infusion Center, was doing those things. So anyway.
SPEAKER_0:  back to this. So why, so yes, tokamaks have been.
SPEAKER_0:  have achieved the highest in magnetic fusion by far like the
SPEAKER_0:  the best amounts of these.
SPEAKER_0:  of these conditions that I talked about. And in fact,
SPEAKER_0:  pushed right up to the point where they were near QP of one.
SPEAKER_0:  They just didn't quite get over one.
SPEAKER_0:  So can we actually just linger?
SPEAKER_1:  on the collaboration across different nations. Just maybe looking at the philosophical aspect of this.
SPEAKER_1:  even in the cold war.
SPEAKER_1:  There's something hopeful to me besides the energy.
SPEAKER_1:  that these giant international projects
SPEAKER_1:  are.
SPEAKER_1:  a really powerful way to ease some of the geopolitical tension, even in military conflict across nations.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a-
SPEAKER_1:  War in Ukraine?
SPEAKER_1:  and Russia.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a brewing tension and conflict with China.
SPEAKER_1:  Just the world is still.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  seeking military conflict.
SPEAKER_1:  cold or hot.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... what can you say well sort of the lessons of the twentieth century in these giant projects
SPEAKER_1:  in their ability to eat some.
SPEAKER_0:  of this tension.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a great question. So as I said, there was a reason because it was so hard. That was one of the reasons the
SPEAKER_0:  they declassified it and actually they started working together in some sense on it as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think it was really, there was...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, an heuristic or altruistic aspect to this. It's like...
SPEAKER_0:  This is something that could-
SPEAKER_0:  change, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  the future of humanity and its nature and its relationship with energy. Isn't this something that we should work on together?
SPEAKER_0:  Right, and.
SPEAKER_0:  And that went along in those ones. And in particularly-
SPEAKER_0:  any kind of place where you can actually have an open exchange of
SPEAKER_0:  of people who are sort of at the intellectual frontiers of your society, this is a good thing, right? of the people who are sort of at the intellectual frontiers of your society, this is a good thing.
SPEAKER_0:  being able to collaborate. I've had the
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I have had an amazing career. I've worked with people from, it's like hard to throw a dart at a country on the map.
SPEAKER_0:  and not hit a country of people that I've been able to work with.
SPEAKER_0:  How amazing is that?
SPEAKER_0:  and even just getting small numbers of people to bridge the cultural...
SPEAKER_0:  and societal divides is a very important thing, even when it's a very teeny fraction.
SPEAKER_0:  of the overall populations.
SPEAKER_0:  It can be held up as an example of that.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's interesting that if you look at then that continued collaboration, which continues to this day.
SPEAKER_0:  that this actually played a major role in fact in East-West relations or like Soviet-West relations.
SPEAKER_0:  is that back in the Reagan Gorbachev days, which of course were interesting in themselves of all.
SPEAKER_0:  kinds of.
SPEAKER_0:  is happening, you know, on both sides, right?
SPEAKER_0:  but still like a desire to push down the stockpile of nuclear weapons and all that within that context.
SPEAKER_0:  There was.
SPEAKER_0:  a very fairly significant historic event that at one of the Reagan-Gorbachev summits.
SPEAKER_0:  is that they didn't get there. Like they couldn't figure out how to.
SPEAKER_0:  bargain to the point of some part of the treaty I can't remember the details of anymore.
SPEAKER_0:  but they needed some kind of a symbol.
SPEAKER_0:  Almost.
SPEAKER_0:  to say, but we're still going to keep working towards something that's important for all of us.
SPEAKER_0:  What did they pick? A fusion project.
SPEAKER_0:  And that was in the mid 1980s and actually.
SPEAKER_0:  Then after.
SPEAKER_0:  So
SPEAKER_0:  they basically signed an agreement that they would move forward to like literally collaborate on a project whose idea would be to show
SPEAKER_0:  large net energy gain infusions.
SPEAKER_0:  commercial viability and work together on that.
SPEAKER_0:  and very soon after that Japan joined, as did the European Union.
SPEAKER_0:  And now, um...
SPEAKER_0:  that project, it evolved.
SPEAKER_0:  over a long period of time and had some interesting political ramifications to it.
SPEAKER_0:  In the end, this actually also had...
SPEAKER_0:  South Korea, India.
SPEAKER_0:  in China.
SPEAKER_0:  join as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  So you're talking about like major.
SPEAKER_0:  a major fraction of, and now Russia of course, at the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_0:  And actually that coalition is holding together despite the obvious political.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, a turmoil that's going around on all those things. And that's a project called ETER.
SPEAKER_0:  which is under construction in the south of France right now.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you actually look at it before we turn the giant magnet and maybe even talk about spark and the stuff going though all amazing stuff going on at MIT.
SPEAKER_1:  What is Zeter? What is this international nuclear fusion megaproject?
SPEAKER_1:  being built in the South of
SPEAKER_0:  So its scientific purpose
SPEAKER_0:  is a worthy one than it's essentially in any fusion device.
SPEAKER_0:  The thing that you want to see is more and more relative amounts of self-heating.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is something that had not been seen, although we had made fusion reactions and we'd seen small amounts of the self heating.
SPEAKER_0:  We never got to a dominant, this actually goes to this QP business. Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  the goal of Eater.
SPEAKER_0:  And it shifted around a little bit historically, but very, you know, fairly quickly became we want to get to a large amount of self-heating. So this is why it has a
SPEAKER_0:  Its primary feature is to get to QP of around 10.
SPEAKER_0:  And through this...
SPEAKER_0:  This is a way to study this plasma that has
SPEAKER_0:  more higher levels of self-determination around on it.
SPEAKER_0:  but it also has another feature which was
SPEAKER_0:  let's produce fusion power at a relevant scale.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  And actually they're linked together, which actually makes sense. What you think about is that-
SPEAKER_0:  because the fusion power
SPEAKER_0:  is the heating source itself, this means that they're linked together. And so Eater makes
SPEAKER_0:  is projected to make about 500 million watts.
SPEAKER_0:  Fusion power?
SPEAKER_0:  So this is a significant amount like this is what you would use.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, for powering cities.
SPEAKER_1:  just the research that there really is the development of really trying to achieve scale here so self heating and scale
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  So this meant then...
SPEAKER_0:  2 is the
SPEAKER_0:  the development of an industrial base that can actually produce the technologies like the electromagnets and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  And to do it with, it is a tokamak. It is, it is.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, but very interesting. It also revealed limitations of this as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, it's interesting is that.
SPEAKER_0:  It is clearly a.
SPEAKER_0:  on paper and in fact in practice as well too, the world…
SPEAKER_0:  the world, you know, in very different political systems and you consider at least geopolitical or economic rivals or whatever you want to use.
SPEAKER_0:  like working towards a common cause.
SPEAKER_0:  and one that we all think is worthy is very satisfying.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's also interesting to see.
SPEAKER_0:  the limitations of this, it's because
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you've got seven chefs in the kitchen.
SPEAKER_0:  So what is this meant in terms of...
SPEAKER_0:  the speed of the project and the ability to govern it and so forth. It's just been a challenge, honestly, around us.
SPEAKER_0:  This is
SPEAKER_0:  I mean it's very hard technically what's occurring.
SPEAKER_0:  But when you also introduce such levels of, I mean, this isn't just me saying it. There's like GEOO reports from the US government and so on. It's hard to like...
SPEAKER_0:  steer all this around.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  And what that's tended to do is make it.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not the fastest decision making process.
SPEAKER_0:  My own personal view of it was it was interesting because you asked me, you said about the magnet and common fusion systems.
SPEAKER_0:  It was.
SPEAKER_0:  I worked most of my career on Eater because when I came into the field in the early 1990s when I-
SPEAKER_0:  completed my PhD and started to work.
SPEAKER_0:  This was one of the most, like you can't imagine being more excited about something like we're going to change the world with this project. We're going to do these things.
SPEAKER_0:  And we just like port like.
SPEAKER_0:  An entire generation and afterwards as well too, has just poured their imagination and their creativity about making this thing work.
SPEAKER_0:  Very good.
SPEAKER_0:  But also at some point though when, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  when it got to being another five years of delay or a decade of delay, you start asking yourself, well,
SPEAKER_0:  Is this what I want to do? Right. Am I going to wait for this? So it was a part of-
SPEAKER_0:  me starting to ask questions with my students.
SPEAKER_0:  I was like...
SPEAKER_0:  Is there another way that we can get to this extremely worthwhile goal that maybe
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe it's not that pathway. And the other part that was clearly frustrating to me because I.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm an advocate of fusion. You asked me about, was I, you know, I was like, well, it's laser fusion or inertial fusion or magnetic fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  I just want fusion energy, okay?
SPEAKER_0:  because I think it's so important to the world.
SPEAKER_0:  is that.
SPEAKER_0:  The other thing, if that's the case...
SPEAKER_0:  then why do we have only one?
SPEAKER_0:  attempt at it on the entire planet.
SPEAKER_0:  which was Eater.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like that makes no sense to me, right? We should have multiple attempts at this with different...
SPEAKER_0:  levels of whatever you want to think about a technical schedule, scientific risk, which are incorporated in them, and that's going to give us a better chance of actually getting to the goal line.
SPEAKER_0:  With that spirit.
SPEAKER_1:  You're leading MIT's effort to design Spark, a compact high field.
SPEAKER_1:  DT Burning Takamak.
SPEAKER_1:  How does it work?
SPEAKER_1:  What is it? What's the motivation?
SPEAKER_1:  uh... what's the design what are they do
SPEAKER_0:  behind. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  At its heart, it's exactly the same concept as ITER.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's basically a configuration of electromagnets.
SPEAKER_0:  It's arranged in the shape of a donut.
SPEAKER_0:  And within that we would do the same thing that happens in all the other token max and including an eater and in this one.
SPEAKER_0:  is that namely you put in gas, make it into a plasma, you heat it up.
SPEAKER_0:  It gets to about 100 million degrees.
SPEAKER_0:  The differentiator in Spark is that
SPEAKER_0:  We use the actual deuterium tritium fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  because of the access to very high magnetic fields.
SPEAKER_0:  It's in a very compact.
SPEAKER_0:  space. It's very-
SPEAKER_0:  very small.
SPEAKER_0:  What do I mean by small?
SPEAKER_0:  So it's...
SPEAKER_0:  40 times smaller in volume than Eater.
SPEAKER_0:  but it uses exactly the same physical principles. So this comes from the high magnetic field.
SPEAKER_0:  So in the end.
SPEAKER_0:  Like what is, why does this matter? What it does is it does those things.
SPEAKER_0:  And it should get to the point where it's producing over a hundred million watts of fusion power.
SPEAKER_0:  But remember, it's 40 times smaller. So either was 500 megawatts.
SPEAKER_0:  technically.
SPEAKER_0:  Our design is around 150 megawatts. So it's only about a factor of three difference despite being 40 times smaller.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and we see.
SPEAKER_0:  QP large.
SPEAKER_0:  order of 10 or something like this at that state.
SPEAKER_0:  is very important scientifically because this is basically matches what Eater is looking to do. The plasma is dominated by its own heating.
SPEAKER_0:  is very, very important.
SPEAKER_0:  And it does that for about 10 seconds.
SPEAKER_0:  And the reason it's for 10 seconds is that in terms of that, that basically allows everything to settle in terms of.
SPEAKER_0:  the fusion in the plasma equilibrium, everything is nice and settled.
SPEAKER_0:  So you know, you have seen the physical state at which you would expect a power plant to operate basically for a
SPEAKER_0:  for magnetic fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, wow.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's more than that.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's more than that, it's because about who's building it and why, and how it's being financed.
SPEAKER_0:  So that scientific pathway was made possible by the fact that we had access to a next generation.
SPEAKER_0:  of magnet technology.
SPEAKER_0:  So to explain this real quick.
SPEAKER_0:  Why do we call it, you said it in the words, a superconducting magnet? What does this mean?
SPEAKER_0:  Superconducting magnet means that the materials which are in the electromagnet
SPEAKER_0:  have no electrical resistance.
SPEAKER_0:  Therefore, when the electric current is put into it...
SPEAKER_0:  the current goes around unimpeded.
SPEAKER_0:  So it could basically keep going around and around, you know, technically for infinity.
SPEAKER_0:  and what that means is that the…
SPEAKER_0:  when you energize these large electromagnets, they're using basically zero electrical power to maintain them.
SPEAKER_0:  Whereas if you would do this in a normal wire, like copper,
SPEAKER_0:  You basically make an enormous toaster oven.
SPEAKER_0:  that's consuming enormous amounts of power and getting hot, which is the problem.
SPEAKER_0:  That was the technical breakthrough.
SPEAKER_0:  that was realized.
SPEAKER_0:  by myself and at the time my students and post-docs and colleagues at MIT.
SPEAKER_0:  was that we saw the advent of this.
SPEAKER_0:  new superconducting material which would allow us to access much higher magnetic fields. It's basically a next generation of the technology.
SPEAKER_0:  And, um.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was quite disruptive to fusion that namely what it would allow that if we could if we could get to this point where we can make the round 20 Tesla
SPEAKER_0:  we knew by the rules of tokimaks that this is going to allow us to vastly shrink.
SPEAKER_0:  like the sizes of these devices, so it wouldn't take.
SPEAKER_0:  Although it's a worthy goal, it wouldn't take a seven nation international treaty basically to build it.
SPEAKER_0:  You could build it with a company and a university.
SPEAKER_1:  So same kind of design, but now using the superconducting magnet.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  And if in fact, if you look at it, it's like, it's.
SPEAKER_0:  If you just expand the size of it, they're like, they look almost identical to each other because it's based on the, and actually that comes for a reason, by the way, is that it also looks like a bigger version.
SPEAKER_0:  of the tokamak that we ran at MIT for 20 years.
SPEAKER_0:  where we established
SPEAKER_0:  the scientific benefits, in fact, of these higher magnetic fields.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's the pathway that runs. So I always say, so what does this mean?
SPEAKER_0:  The context is different.
SPEAKER_0:  Because...
SPEAKER_0:  It was made because it's primarily being made by a private sector company spun out of MIT.
SPEAKER_0:  because the way that it raised money and the purpose of the entity which is there is to make commercial fusion power plants.
SPEAKER_0:  not just to make a scientific experiment.
SPEAKER_0:  This is actually why we have...
SPEAKER_0:  That's why we have a partnership, right, is that our purpose at MIT is not to commercialize directly.
SPEAKER_0:  But boy, do we want to advance the technology and the science that comes along this. And that's the reason we're sort of doing it together.
SPEAKER_1:  MIT and Commonwealth Fusion Systems. So what's interesting to say about financing? And this seems like from a scientific view.
SPEAKER_1:  perspective, maybe not an interesting topic, but it's perhaps an extremely interesting topic.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, you can just look at the texture between.
SPEAKER_1:  SpaceX and NASA, for example. It's just clear that there's different financing mechanisms that actually significantly accelerate.
SPEAKER_1:  the development of science and engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  It's great that you brought that up. We use several historic.
SPEAKER_0:  analogs and one of them is around SpaceX, which is an appropriate one because
SPEAKER_0:  Space, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  putting things into orbit has a, just to put.
SPEAKER_0:  has a minimum size to it and
SPEAKER_0:  integrated technological complexity and budget and things like this.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, our point when we were like talking about starting like a fusion commercialization, you know, company.
SPEAKER_0:  people look at you like, isn't this still really just a science experiment?
SPEAKER_0:  But one of the things that we pointed to was...
SPEAKER_0:  SpaceX to say well.
SPEAKER_0:  Tell me like 25 years ago, how many people would have voted that the leading entity on the planet to put things into orbit, it's a private company. People would have thought you were not so, right? It's like...
SPEAKER_0:  And what is interesting about SpaceX was that it proved it's more than actually just finance.
SPEAKER_0:  It's really the purpose of the organization.
SPEAKER_0:  So the purpose of a gu-
SPEAKER_0:  and I'm not against public finance or anything like that, but the purpose of a public entity like NASA.
SPEAKER_0:  correctly speaks to the political...
SPEAKER_0:  Because the cost comes from the political.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, assembly.
SPEAKER_0:  that is there and I guess from us eventually as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  but its purpose wasn't about making a commercial product.
SPEAKER_0:  It's about fundamental discovery and so forth, which is all rich is all really great.
SPEAKER_0:  Like why did, why did space X
SPEAKER_0:  It's interesting because why did SpaceX succeed so well?
SPEAKER_0:  is because the idea was it's like the the focus that comes
SPEAKER_0:  in the idea that you're going to relentlessly reduce costs.
SPEAKER_0:  and increase efficiency is a drive that comes from the commercial.
SPEAKER_0:  aspect of it, right?
SPEAKER_0:  And this also then changes...
SPEAKER_0:  the people in the teams which are doing as well too. In fact trickles throughout the whole thing because
SPEAKER_0:  The purpose isn't.
SPEAKER_0:  While you're advancing things, it's really good that we can put things in orbit a lot more cheaply. It advances science, which is an interesting synergy, right?
SPEAKER_0:  It's the same thing that we think is going to happen in fusion, that namely, this is a bootstrap effect that actually, that when you start to push yourself to think about near term.
SPEAKER_0:  commercialization.
SPEAKER_0:  It allows the science to get in hand faster, which then allows the commercialization to go faster and up we go.
SPEAKER_0:  By the way, we've seen this also in another, again, it's a.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to watch out with analogies because they only can go so far but like biotech.
SPEAKER_0:  is another one, like you look at the human genome project, which was...
SPEAKER_0:  It's sort of like, to me, that's like mapping the human genome.
SPEAKER_0:  Like that we can make net energy from fusion. Like it's one of those like.
SPEAKER_0:  in your drawer that you go, this is a significant achievement by humanity, right, in the century.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  There's the human genome project.
SPEAKER_0:  Fully government funded.
SPEAKER_0:  going to take 20, 25 years because we basically know the technology.
SPEAKER_0:  We're just going to be really diligent. Keep going da-da-da-da.
SPEAKER_0:  And then all of a sudden what comes along?
SPEAKER_0:  disruptive technology.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? You can sequence, you know, shotgun sequencing and computer, you know, recognition patterns and basically, oh,
SPEAKER_0:  I can do this 100 times faster.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, wow.
SPEAKER_0:  Right. And so, so that's really the.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, you know, to me that the story about why we started, why we launched common with fusion systems was more than
SPEAKER_0:  just about another source of funding.
SPEAKER_0:  which it is a different source of funding because it comes with... it's also a different purpose.
SPEAKER_0:  which is very important.
SPEAKER_1:  But there's also something about
SPEAKER_1:  a mechanism that creates culture.
SPEAKER_1:  So giving power to like a young student, ambitious student to have a tremendous impact on the progress of nuclear fusion.
SPEAKER_1:  creates a culture that actually makes progress target slowly.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you said, when seven nations collaborate...
SPEAKER_1:  it gives more incentive to the bureaucracy to slow things down, to kind of have, let's first have a discussion and certainly don't give voice to the young, ambitious minds that are really pushing stuff forward.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's something about.
SPEAKER_1:  like the private sector that
SPEAKER_1:  rewards, encourages, inspires.
SPEAKER_1:  Young minds.
SPEAKER_1:  to say in the most beautiful ways, F you to the.....
SPEAKER_0:  It is, it is a little... The boss!
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, just like we'll make it faster. We'll make it simpler. We'll make it better. We'll make it cheaper.
SPEAKER_0:  And sometimes that brashness doesn't bear out. You know, that's an aspect that you just take a different risk profile as well too. But you're right. This
SPEAKER_0:  You know, of the...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it was interesting, our own trajectory at the fusion center was.
SPEAKER_0:  Like we were pushed into this place by necessity as well too, because
SPEAKER_0:  I told you we had operated for a long time a tokamak.
SPEAKER_0:  at on the MIT campus achieve these world records like 100 million degree plasma and stuff like wow this is fantastic
SPEAKER_0:  you know, somewhat ironically I have to say is that it was like oh
SPEAKER_0:  But we're not, this isn't the future of fusion anymore. Like we're not, we're just going to stop with small projects because it's too small, right? So we should need, we need to really move on to these much bigger projects because that's really the future of fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it was defunded.
SPEAKER_0:  And this basically put at risk like we were going to essentially lose MIT in the ecosystem.
SPEAKER_0:  really a fusion, both from the research but also from the research.
SPEAKER_0:  clearly important from educational.
SPEAKER_0:  part of it.
SPEAKER_0:  So we, you know, we pushed back against this. We got a lifeline.
SPEAKER_0:  We were able to go and it was in this time scale that we basically came up with this idea.
SPEAKER_0:  we should do this and in the end it was
SPEAKER_0:  All of those.
SPEAKER_0:  the people who were in the C level of the company were all literally students who got caught in that. They were PhD students at the time.
SPEAKER_0:  So you talk about enabling.
SPEAKER_0:  another generation is like, yeah, there you go. Right.
SPEAKER_1:  So Spark gave...
SPEAKER_0:  A lifeline.
SPEAKER_1:  to the the future set at MIT.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's way more than that. It wasn't just about like surviving for the sake of surviving. It was like-
SPEAKER_0:  In the end for me, it became like this. I remember the moment. Do we talk about these moments as a scientist and-
SPEAKER_0:  We were just like, we were working so hard about figuring out like, does this really, will this really work? Like, and it's complex.
SPEAKER_0:  Like does the magnet work? Does the interaction with the plasmid work? Does all these things work? And it was just a grind push, push, push, push.
SPEAKER_0:  And I remember the moment because I was sitting.
SPEAKER_0:  in my office in Brookline.
SPEAKER_0:  And there was just like, I read like, and I was in, I don't know, whatever, the 20th or 40th slide or something into it.
SPEAKER_0:  And it was sort of that moment, like it just came together.
SPEAKER_0:  And I like, I got, I couldn't even sit down.
SPEAKER_0:  Because all it was just like, my wife was like, why are you walking around the apartment like this? I just couldn't, I said it's going to work.
SPEAKER_0:  like it's going to work.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, holy cow, that moment of realization is like.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of amazing, but it also brings the responsibility of making it work as well. How do you spell that?
SPEAKER_1:  So you mean like that magic?
SPEAKER_1:  Realization that you can have this this modern magnet technology and you can actually.
SPEAKER_1:  Like why do we need to work with either we can do it here?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, yeah. But it's interesting that Eater is...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  That one of the reasons that we started with a group of six of us at MIT, and then once we got some funding through the establishment of the company, it became a slightly larger.
SPEAKER_0:  But in the end we had a rather small team.
SPEAKER_0:  This was like a team of order of like 20 to 25 people line spark in
SPEAKER_0:  like about two years.
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_0:  How does that happen? Well,
SPEAKER_0:  We're clever?
SPEAKER_0:  But you have to give either it's due here as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, this is an aspect always of
SPEAKER_0:  the boot strap up, like I go back to the human genome project.
SPEAKER_0:  So modern day genomics would not be possible without the underlying basis that came from setting that up.
SPEAKER_0:  It had to be there. It had to be curiosity driven, public program. It's the same with Eader, but because we had the tools.
SPEAKER_0:  that we're there to understand Eader, we also have the tools to understand Spark.
SPEAKER_0:  So we parlayed those in an extremely powerful way.
SPEAKER_0:  to be able to tell us about what was going to happen.
SPEAKER_0:  So these things are never simple, right? It's like people look at this go, Oh, this means we should.
SPEAKER_0:  Like should we really have a public based program about Fusion or should we have it all in the private?
SPEAKER_0:  No, the answer is neither way because in all these...
SPEAKER_0:  complex technologies, you have to keep pushing on all the fronts to actually get it there.
SPEAKER_0:  So, you know, the natural question.
SPEAKER_1:  We hear breakthrough.
SPEAKER_1:  with the inertial confinement, with the magnetic confinement.
SPEAKER_1:  So when will we have commercial?
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  reactors power plants that are actually producing electricity. What's your sense?
SPEAKER_1:  Looking out into the future, what do you think you can envision in the future where we have actual electricity coming from?
SPEAKER_0:  nuclear fusion. Partly driven by us but in other places as well too. There's the advent what's so different now than three or four years.
SPEAKER_0:  like we launched around four years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  What's so different now is the advent of a very nascent but-
SPEAKER_0:  seemingly robust like commercial
SPEAKER_0:  you know, endeavor.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's not just commonwealth fusion systems, there's something like 20 plus.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, companies. There's a sector now. There's a sector. They actually, they actually have something called the fusion industry association, which if your viewers want to go see this, this describes the different.
SPEAKER_0:  and they've got this plethora of approaches. Like I haven't even described all the approaches. I've basically described the mainline approaches.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... you know
SPEAKER_0:  And they're all at varying degrees of technical and scientific maturity with.
SPEAKER_0:  very huge different balances between them.
SPEAKER_0:  What they share.
SPEAKER_0:  is that because they're going out and finding getting funding from the private sector.
SPEAKER_0:  is that their stated goals
SPEAKER_0:  or about.
SPEAKER_0:  Getting Fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  into place so that both it meets the investors demands, which are interesting, right? And the time skills of that, but also it's like, well,
SPEAKER_0:  There's going to, and why? It's because it's easy. There's this enormous push.
SPEAKER_0:  driver about getting carbon free energy sources out into the market and whoever.
SPEAKER_0:  figures those out is going to be both very, it's going to be very important geopolitically but also economically as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a different kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  bat I guess or a different kind of gamble that you're taking with fusion but it's so disruptive.
SPEAKER_0:  that it's like there's essentially a class of investors.
SPEAKER_0:  and teams that are ready to go after it as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  So what do they share in this?
SPEAKER_0:  They typically share.
SPEAKER_0:  getting after fusion on a timescale so that
SPEAKER_0:  Could it have any relevance towards?
SPEAKER_0:  Climate change, battling climate change.
SPEAKER_0:  And I would say.
SPEAKER_0:  This is difficult but-
SPEAKER_0:  It's fairly easy because it's math. So what you do is you actually go to some target like 2050 or 2060, something like this, and say, I want to be blank percent of the world's market of electricity or something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  And we know historically what it takes to...
SPEAKER_0:  Evolve.
SPEAKER_0:  and distribute these kinds of technologies. Cause every technology takes some period of time. It's so called S curve. It's basically everything follows a logarithmic curve, exponential type curve. That's a straight line of log plot.
SPEAKER_0:  And like you look at wind, solar, fission, they all follow the same thing. So it's easy. You take that curve and you go that slope and you work backwards.
SPEAKER_0:  And you go, if you don't start in the early 2030s, like.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not gonna have a...
SPEAKER_0:  It's not going to have a significant impact by that time.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  All of them share this idea. And in fact, it's not just the companies now.
SPEAKER_0:  The US federal government has a program.
SPEAKER_0:  that was started last year that said.
SPEAKER_0:  We should be looking to try to get like the first and what I mean by like, what does it mean to start that you've got something that's putting electricity on the grid, a pilot.
SPEAKER_0:  Mukul.
SPEAKER_0:  And if that can get started, like in the early 2030s.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, the idea of ramping it up, you know, makes sense. math!
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  that's the ambition, then the question is, and actually this is different because the government program
SPEAKER_0:  and they vary around in this. So for example, the United Kingdom's government idea was to get the first one on by 2040.
SPEAKER_0:  And China has ambitions probably middle.
SPEAKER_0:  2030s.
SPEAKER_0:  or maybe a little bit later and Europe, continental Europe.
SPEAKER_0:  is a little bit, I'm not exactly sure where it is, but it's like later, it's like 2050 or 2060 because it's mostly linked to the Eater timeline as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  the fusion companies, which makes sense, it's like, of course they've got the most aggressive timelines, it's like, we're gonna map the human genome faster as well too, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So it's interesting about where we are. And I think, you know, my-
SPEAKER_0:  We're not all the way there, but my intuition tells me we're probably going to have a couple of cracks at it actually on that timeline.
SPEAKER_0:  This is where we have to be careful though, you say commercial fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  What does that mean?
SPEAKER_0:  Commercial fusion to me means that you're actually...
SPEAKER_0:  Have a...
SPEAKER_0:  known quantity about what it costs, what it costs to build and what it costs to operate.
SPEAKER_0:  the reliability of putting energy on the grid. That's commercial fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  Sike.
SPEAKER_0:  So it turns out that that's not necessarily exactly the first fusion devices that put electricity on the grid because there's a learning curve to get.
SPEAKER_0:  better and better at it.
SPEAKER_0:  That's probably, I would suspect the biggest hurdle is to get to the first one.
SPEAKER_1:  The work I've done.
SPEAKER_1:  other work I continue to do with autonomous vehicles and semi-autonomous vehicles. There's an interesting parallel there were a bunch of companies.
SPEAKER_1:  announced.
SPEAKER_1:  a deadline for themselves in 2020, 2021, 2022.
SPEAKER_1:  and uh... only a small subset of those companies have actually
SPEAKER_1:  really push that forward is Google with Waymo.
SPEAKER_1:  or alphabet rather, and then there's...
SPEAKER_1:  Tesla with semi-autonomous driving in their autopilot full-cell driving mode.
SPEAKER_1:  and those are different approaches.
SPEAKER_1:  So Tesla is achieving much, much higher scale.
SPEAKER_1:  but sort of...
SPEAKER_1:  the quality of the dry is semi-autonomous.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if there's a metaphor and analogy here. And then there's Waymo that's focusing on very specific cities but achieving real.
SPEAKER_1:  full autonomy with actual passengers, but the scales are much smaller.
SPEAKER_1:  So I wonder.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, just like you said, there'll be these kinds of similar kind of really
SPEAKER_0:  pushes.
SPEAKER_0:  Absolutely. So actually this is what I, it's why I'm encouraged about fusion. So fusion's still hard. Let's let everyone be clear.
SPEAKER_0:  because of the science underneath it of achieving the right conditions for the plasma.
SPEAKER_0:  basically is a yardstick that you have to put up against all of them.
SPEAKER_0:  What's encouraging that I see in this, and it's actually what happens when you sort of
SPEAKER_0:  let loose the creativity of this is.
SPEAKER_0:  maybe I'll go back to first principles. So fusion is also a fairly strange.
SPEAKER_0:  So if you think about building a coal plant, like burning wood and coal and gas is actually not that much different from each other.
SPEAKER_0:  because they're kind of about the same physical conditions and you get the fuel and you light it.
SPEAKER_0:  Fusion is very, remember I told you that there's this condition of the temperature which is kind of universal.
SPEAKER_0:  If you take the density of the fuel between magnetic fusion and inertial fusion, they're different by about a factor of 10 billion.
SPEAKER_0:  So this.
SPEAKER_0:  and the density of fuel really matters. And actually so does the, this means energy confinement time is also different by a factor of 10 billion as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  because it's the product of those two. So one's really dense and short, not lived.
SPEAKER_0:  And the other one's really long lived and actually under dense as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  So what that means is that the way to the...
SPEAKER_0:  The way to get the underlying physical state is so different among these different approaches.
SPEAKER_0:  What it lends itself to is...
SPEAKER_0:  Does this mean that eventual commercial products
SPEAKER_0:  will actually fill different needs in the energy system. Sort of goes to your comment about
SPEAKER_0:  have to suspect this because anything that is high-tech.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's like a really important thing in our economy.
SPEAKER_0:  tends to never find its way as only one manifestation. Like, look at transportation as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  We have scooters.
SPEAKER_0:  Vespas.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, overland trucks.
SPEAKER_0:  electric cars, of course we have these because they meet different demands.
SPEAKER_0:  So what's interesting that I find fascinating now is that we have infusion is going to look like that.
SPEAKER_0:  that probably there's
SPEAKER_0:  While the near term focuses on electricity production, there might even be different kinds of markets that actually make sense in some places.
SPEAKER_0:  less in others, it comes to trade-offs.
SPEAKER_0:  Cause we haven't really talked about the engineering yet, but engineering really matters.
SPEAKER_0:  like to the operation of the device.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it could be.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, that, that, you know, I suspect what we'll end up with is several different configurations, which have different features, which are trade-offs basically in the, in the energy market.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you see as the major engineering?
SPEAKER_1:  or general hurdles.
SPEAKER_0:  that are in the way.
SPEAKER_0:  So the first one is just the cost of building a single unit.
SPEAKER_0:  So Fusion has, and it was actually interesting you talked about the different models that you have. So Fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  has um
SPEAKER_0:  One of its interesting limitations is that it's very hard.
SPEAKER_0:  almost at some point becomes physically impossible to actually make small power units.
SPEAKER_0:  like a kilowatt, a thousand watts, which is like a personal home, like this is about a thousand watts or your personal use of energy of electricity is about like a thousand watts.
SPEAKER_0:  This is basically impossible for a single unit to do this.
SPEAKER_0:  um...
SPEAKER_0:  So like you're not going to have a fusion power plant like as your furnace or your electric heater in your home.
SPEAKER_0:  And the reason for this comes from the fact that fusion relies on it being, it's not just that it's very hot, it says that the fusion power is the heating source to keep it hot. So if you, if you, if you go too small, it basically just cannot keep it hot. leap.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's interesting is that this is one of the hard parts. So this means that the individual units
SPEAKER_0:  It varies from concept to concept, but the National Academy's report that came out last year.
SPEAKER_0:  sort of put the benchmark as being.
SPEAKER_0:  Like probably the minimum size looks like around 50 million watts of electricity, which is like enough for like a small to-
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  Mid-sized city actually.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's sort of like a scale challenge. And in fact, it's one of the reasons why.
SPEAKER_0:  in commonwealth and other private sector ones like
SPEAKER_0:  They try to push this down actually of trying to get to these smaller units.
SPEAKER_0:  just because it reduces the cost of it.
SPEAKER_0:  then probably, obviously, I would say it's an obvious one like achieving the fusion state itself and high gain is
SPEAKER_0:  is a hard one, what we already talked about. What kind of hurdle, what kind of challenges? Well, that's achieving the right temperature, density and energy confinement time in the fuel itself in the plasma itself.
SPEAKER_0:  And so some of the...
SPEAKER_0:  The configurations which are being chosen have
SPEAKER_0:  are actually quite a ways to go in fact of seeing those. But.
SPEAKER_0:  what their their consideration is all yes but
SPEAKER_0:  By our particular configuration, the engineering simplicity confers like an economic advantage, even if we're behind in a, in sort of a science sense. Okay,
SPEAKER_0:  Which is fine, that's the-
SPEAKER_0:  This is also what you get when you get a.
SPEAKER_0:  an explosion in the private sector, you basically are distributing risks in different ways, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  All of that good.
SPEAKER_0:  So what I would say is that the next hurdle to really overcome is about making electricity.
SPEAKER_0:  So like we need to see.
SPEAKER_0:  a unit or several units, like put using fusion in some way to put a meaningful amount of energy on the grid.
SPEAKER_0:  because this starts giving us real...
SPEAKER_0:  answers.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, as to like what this is going to look like. The full end to end. The full end to end thing. So Commonwealth goal is that I'll
SPEAKER_0:  I'll just comment to Commonwealth because I'll take some credit for this.
SPEAKER_0:  is that.
SPEAKER_0:  the origins of commonwealth were in fact in examining that.
SPEAKER_0:  Like we could see this new technology coming forward, this new superconducting material
SPEAKER_0:  And the origins of our thought process were really around designing, effectively, the pilot plant or the commercial unit. It's called ARC.
SPEAKER_0:  which is actually the step forward after spark.
SPEAKER_0:  And that was the origins of it. So all the things that were other parts of the plan, like spark and the magnet.
SPEAKER_0:  We're actually.
SPEAKER_0:  all informed totally by building something that's going to put net electricity on the grid.
SPEAKER_0:  And the timing of that we still hope is actually the early 2030s.
SPEAKER_1:  So Spark is the design of the Takamak and Arc is the actual full intent.
SPEAKER_0:  is like a thing that actually puts the energy on the grid. So Spark is named intentionally, that it's like it's on for short.
SPEAKER_0:  period of time.
SPEAKER_0:  and it doesn't have a...
SPEAKER_0:  It has, yeah, it's the spark of the fusion revolution or something like that, I guess we could call it.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so those are sort of the programmatic challenges of doing that.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it's interesting, you asked about, you talked about SpaceX. So what is-
SPEAKER_0:  evolved even in the last year or so was in fact in March of 2022.
SPEAKER_0:  The White House announced that it was going to start a program.
SPEAKER_0:  that kind of looks like a SpaceX analogy that namely, wow.
SPEAKER_0:  We've got these things in the private sector. We should leverage the private sector and the advantages of what they obtain.
SPEAKER_0:  but also with the things like this is going to be hard and it's going to take quite a bit of financing.
SPEAKER_0:  So why don't we set up a program.
SPEAKER_0:  where we don't really get in the way of the private sector fusion companies, but we help them finance these difficult things, which is how SpaceX.
SPEAKER_0:  basically became successful through the COTS program. Fantastic.
SPEAKER_0:  Right. And that's evolving as well too. so
SPEAKER_0:  Like the fusion ecosystem is almost unrecognizable from where it was like five years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  around those things.
SPEAKER_0:  How important is it for...
SPEAKER_1:  the heads of the companies that are working on nuclear fusion to have a twitter account
SPEAKER_1:  and to be quite, you said you don't use Twitter. Paste the link to our characters!
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you very much.
SPEAKER_1:  Ha ha ha!
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, there is some element to, and I don't think this should be discounted, whatever you think about.
SPEAKER_1:  Figures like Jeff Bezos with Blue Origin or Elon Musk with SpaceX.
SPEAKER_1:  There is...
SPEAKER_1:  a science communication.
SPEAKER_1:  to put it in nice terms.
SPEAKER_1:  That's kind of required to really...
SPEAKER_1:  educate the public and get everybody excited and sell the sexiness of it. I mean, just even the videos of SpaceX, just being able to kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  get everybody excited about going out to space once again. I mean, there's all kinds of different ways of doing that, but.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I guess what the companies do well, you know, is to advertise themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  that really sell themselves. It is, yeah. Well, actually it is, like I feel like one of the reasons on this podcast.
SPEAKER_0:  Like I don't have an official role in the company.
SPEAKER_0:  And one of the reasons for this was...
SPEAKER_0:  Also that-
SPEAKER_0:  It's interesting because when you come from like you're running a company, it makes sense that they're promoting their own product and their own vision which totally makes sense.
SPEAKER_0:  But there's also a very important role for academics.
SPEAKER_0:  who have knowledge about what's going on, but are.
SPEAKER_0:  sufficiently distant from it that they're not fully only self motivated just by their own projects or so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  And for me this is...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, we see particularly the problems of the distrust in technology.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and then honestly in the scientific community.
SPEAKER_0:  as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  It will be...
SPEAKER_0:  that one of the greatest tragedies, I would say.
SPEAKER_0:  that if we go through all of this and almost pull off what looks like a miracle, like
SPEAKER_0:  technologic and scientific wise, which is to make a fusion power plant.
SPEAKER_0:  and then nobody wants to use it.
SPEAKER_0:  because they feel that they don't trust the people who are doing it or the technology.
SPEAKER_0:  So we have to get so far out ahead of this. Just like-
SPEAKER_0:  So I give lots of public lectures or things like this.
SPEAKER_0:  of accessing a larger range of people.
SPEAKER_0:  We're not trying to hide anything. You can come and see, you know, come do tours of our laboratory.
SPEAKER_0:  In fact, I want to set those up virtually as well too. You might look at our
SPEAKER_0:  plasmasized infusion center YouTube channel. So we are reaching out through those media and it's really important that we do those things.
SPEAKER_0:  but also then setting up the realistic expectations of what we need to do.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  We're not there. Like we don't have commercial fusion devices yet. You asked like, what are the challenges?
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not going to get into any deep technical questions of what the challenges are.
SPEAKER_0:  But it is.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  the pathway, not just to make.
SPEAKER_0:  work technically, but to make it economically competitive and viable so that it's actually used out in the private sector is a non-trivial task.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's because...
SPEAKER_0:  of the newness of it. Like we're simultaneously trying to evolve the technology and make it economically viable at the same time.
SPEAKER_0:  Those are two
SPEAKER_0:  difficult coupled tasks.
SPEAKER_0:  So my own research and my own drive right now.
SPEAKER_0:  is that fantastic commonwealth fusion systems is set up.
SPEAKER_0:  We have a commercialization unit of that particular kind, which is gonna drive forward a token back. In fact, I was just...
SPEAKER_0:  There's discussions, there's dialogues going on around the world with other kinds of ones like stellarators and which prefer different kinds of...
SPEAKER_0:  challenges and economic advantages.
SPEAKER_0:  But what we have to, I know what we have to have, what we have to have.
SPEAKER_0:  is a new generation.
SPEAKER_0:  of integrated scientists, technologists and engineers that understand what needs to get done to get all the way to the goal line.
SPEAKER_0:  because we don't have them.
SPEAKER_1:  like a multidisciplinary. Yeah, exactly. What's required? I mean, you've spoken about.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, you said that fusion is quote.
SPEAKER_1:  the most.
SPEAKER_1:  multidisciplinary field you can imagine. Yes. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Why is that? What are the differences? Yeah, well, because most of our discussion that we've had so far is really like a physics discussion really, so don't...
SPEAKER_0:  neglect physics is at the origin of this.
SPEAKER_0:  But already we touched on plasma physics and nuclear physics, which are.
SPEAKER_0:  basically to, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  somewhat overlap but independent disciplines.
SPEAKER_0:  then when it comes to the engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  It's almost everything. So, so why is this? Well, let's build, let's build an electromagnet together. Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  What is this going to take? It's going to take, um...
SPEAKER_0:  basically electrical engineering, computer so you understand how it goes together, what happens.
SPEAKER_0:  computational engineering to model this.
SPEAKER_0:  very complex integrated thing, materials engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  because you're pushing materials to their limit with respect to stress and so forth. Takes cryogenic engineering, which is sort of a sub-discipline, but cooling things to extremely low temperatures.
SPEAKER_0:  probably some kind of chemistry thing in there too. Well, actually, yeah, which tends to show up in the materials. And that's just one of the sub components of it.
SPEAKER_0:  almost everything gets hit in this right so you're and you're also in a very integrated environment because in the end all these things
SPEAKER_0:  while you isolate them from each other in a physics sense, in an engineering sense, they all have to work seamlessly together.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's one of those, I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  In my own career I've basically done atomic physics.
SPEAKER_0:  spectroscopy, you know, plasma physics.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  iron etching.
SPEAKER_0:  So this includes material science, something called MHD, maybe even magneto hydrodynamics.
SPEAKER_0:  And now all the way through it like.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not even sure how many different careers I've had. It's also, by the way, this is also an M.
SPEAKER_0:  a recruiting stage for like young scientists thinking to come in. Like my comment to sign is if you're bored in fusion, you're not paying attention because there's always something interesting to go.
SPEAKER_0:  and do.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's a really important part of what we're doing, which isn't new in Fusion actually, in fact is in the roots of...
SPEAKER_0:  of what we've done at MIT. But holy cow, like the proximity.
SPEAKER_0:  of possibility of commercial fusion is the new thing.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, so my catchphrases.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, you may wonder, like, why weren't we doing all these things? Like, why weren't we pushing towards economic fusion and new materials and new...
SPEAKER_0:  methods of heat extraction and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  because everybody knew Fusion was 40 years away.
SPEAKER_0:  And now it's four years away.
SPEAKER_0:  You
SPEAKER_1:  There is a history, like you said, 40, 30, whatever, the kind of old joke.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a history of Fusion projects.
SPEAKER_1:  that...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, are characterized by cost overruns and delays. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  How do you avoid this? How do you minimize the chance of this?
SPEAKER_0:  You have to build great teams.
SPEAKER_0:  um, uh, is one of them.
SPEAKER_0:  It tends to be that the smaller the
SPEAKER_0:  There's sort of an, I'm not an expert in this, but I've seen this enough integrated engineering. Is there an equation? Yeah, well, there's almost, I've seen this from enough teams. Like I've seen also the futility of lone geniuses trying to solve everything by themselves. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  but also organizations that have 10,000 people in them is just not, doesn't lend itself at all to innovation. So.
SPEAKER_0:  Like one of our original sponsors and a good friend, Vinod Khosla, I don't know if you've ever talked to Vinod Khosla, he's a venture buyer-
SPEAKER_0:  He's got.
SPEAKER_0:  fantastic ideas about the right sizes of teams and.
SPEAKER_0:  things that really innovate, right?
SPEAKER_0:  And there is an optimum place in there is that you get enough.
SPEAKER_0:  cross-discipline and ideas, but it doesn't become so overly bureaucratic that you can't execute on it.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  So one of the ways, and this was one of the challenges of fusion, is that everything was leading towards something special.
SPEAKER_0:  Like I have to have like, it's enormously large, like teams just to execute because of the scale of the project.
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that now.
SPEAKER_0:  through both technology and the argue financing innovation, we're driving to the point where it's smaller focused teams about doing those things. So that's one way to make it faster.
SPEAKER_0:  The other way to make it faster is modularize the problem or parse the problem.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is the other difficulty in fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  is that you tend to look at this as like, oh, it's really just about making the plasma into this state here that you get this energy gain.
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  because in the end, if you can...
SPEAKER_0:  out the different problems of making that and then make it as separate as possible from extracting the energy and then converting it into electricity. The more separate those are, the better they are because you get parallel paths that basically mitigate risk.
SPEAKER_0:  This is not new in Fusion by the way, this is the way that we attack.
SPEAKER_0:  most complex technological.
SPEAKER_0:  integrated technological challenges.
SPEAKER_1:  Have you by any chance seen
SPEAKER_1:  some of the application of artificial intelligence, reinforcement learning, a deep mind.
SPEAKER_1:  has a nice paper, has a nice effort.
SPEAKER_1:  on.
SPEAKER_1:  basically using reinforcement learning for a learned control algorithm for controlling nuclear fusion. Do you find those kinds of...
SPEAKER_1:  I guess you throw them under the umbrella of computational modeling.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you find those interesting promising?
SPEAKER_0:  directions. They're all interesting. So when people, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll pull back. Maybe a natural question is like, why is it different in fusion? Like, there's a long history diffusion, right? It was going on for, like I told you, like stories from the late 1960s. Like what's different now, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So I think.
SPEAKER_0:  From the technology point of view, there's two massive things which are different. So one of them, I'll be parochial, it's the advent of this new superconducting materials because
SPEAKER_0:  the most mature ways that we understand about how we're going to get to fusion power plants or magnetic fusion. And by the fact that you've got access.
SPEAKER_0:  to something which like changes the...
SPEAKER_0:  economic equation by an over an order magnitude is just a totally.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, and that.
SPEAKER_0:  That wasn't that long ago, it was only September of 2021 that we actually demonstrated the technology. That changes the prospects there.
SPEAKER_0:  and the other one is computing.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's across the whole spectrum. It's not just in control.
SPEAKER_0:  of the fusion device, it's actually in the, we actually use machine learning and things like this in the design of the magnet itself. It's an incredibly complex design space. So you use those tools.
SPEAKER_0:  the simulation of the plasma itself is actually...
SPEAKER_0:  we're at a totally different place than we were.
SPEAKER_0:  So those are the two big drivers that I see actually that make it different. And it's interesting, both those things.
SPEAKER_0:  self-enforce about what you asked about before, like how do you avoid delays and things? Well, it's by having smaller teams.
SPEAKER_0:  that can actually execute on those.
SPEAKER_0:  But now you can do this because.
SPEAKER_0:  the new magnets make the devices all smaller.
SPEAKER_0:  And computing means your human effectiveness about exploring.
SPEAKER_0:  the optimization space is way better.
SPEAKER_0:  like they're all interlinked to each other.
SPEAKER_1:  cluster modularization, like you said, and everything just kind of works together to make smaller teams more effective.
SPEAKER_0:  move faster. And it's actually, and it's through that learned experience. I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, of the things that I'm the most proud of about what came out. In fact...
SPEAKER_0:  the origins of thinking about how we would use the high temperature superconducting magnets.
SPEAKER_0:  came out of my design class.
SPEAKER_0:  at MIT.
SPEAKER_0:  And in the design class, like one of the features that I kept, I mean, it was interesting. I actually learned, I really learned along with the students about this, but like this insistence on the features, like...
SPEAKER_0:  We can't have so many
SPEAKER_0:  coupled integrated hard technology developments. We have to separate these somehow.
SPEAKER_0:  So we worked and worked and worked at this. And in fact, that's what really, in my opinion, the greatest advantage of the arc design and built into the Commonwealth Fusion System idea.
SPEAKER_0:  is like to parse out the problems. Like how can we attack these in parallel?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and so...
SPEAKER_0:  It really comes to, we talked about philosophy. It's like a design philosophy, like how do you attack these kinds of problems?
SPEAKER_0:  And you do it like that.
SPEAKER_1:  And also like you mentioned offline that there's a power to.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, as part of a class.
SPEAKER_1:  to design a nuclear fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... well it's a big uh... well then it is reality and it's it's hard to imagine a more powerful force than like fifteen m i t p h t students like working together towards solving a problem
SPEAKER_0:  And what I always-
SPEAKER_0:  In fact, we just...
SPEAKER_0:  We recently just taught the most recent, I say I teach it, I mean I guide it actually.
SPEAKER_0:  the most recent version of this where they actually designed, you know, based on this National Academies report they actually designed.
SPEAKER_0:  Like a pilot plant.
SPEAKER_0:  that has basis and similarities to what we had done before.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I kept wanting to push the envelope and where they are.
SPEAKER_0:  the creativity and the...
SPEAKER_0:  uh... and uh... the energy
SPEAKER_0:  that they bring to these things is kind of like, it keeps me going, like, I'm not gonna retire anytime soon, when I keep seeing that kind of dedication and it's wonderful.
SPEAKER_0:  around on that. Um, it almost not to overuse a, um,
SPEAKER_0:  uh, uh, or to paraphrase something right, which is
SPEAKER_0:  that the famous quote by Margaret Mead.
SPEAKER_0:  Never doubt that a-
SPEAKER_0:  small group of dedicated persons will change the world. Indeed, it's the only thing that ever has.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, that's just such a powerful and inspiring thing for an individual.
SPEAKER_1:  Find the right team, be part of that, and then you, yourself, your passion, your efforts could actually make a big change.
SPEAKER_1:  big impact. I gotta ask you...
SPEAKER_1:  So it's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a whole nother different conversation I'm sure to have, but nuclear power is the currently stands. So using fission.
SPEAKER_1:  is extremely safe despite public perception.
SPEAKER_0:  It is the safest actually.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a whole nother conversation, but almost like a human bureaucratic.
SPEAKER_1:  physics.
SPEAKER_1:  engineering.
SPEAKER_1:  question of
SPEAKER_1:  What lessons do you draw from the
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  catastrophic events where they.
SPEAKER_1:  the pop plants did fail, so Chernobyl and Three Mile Island. Chernobyl, what lessons did you learn?
SPEAKER_0:  draw. Three by Lyle wasn't really a disaster because nothing escaped from the thing but Chernobyl and Fukushima had obvious consequences in the populations.
SPEAKER_0:  live nearby.
SPEAKER_1:  What lesson do you draw from those that you can carry forward to Fusion?
SPEAKER_1:  Now I know there's
SPEAKER_1:  You can say that you're not going to have the same kind of issues, but it's possible that
SPEAKER_1:  The same folks also said they're not gonna be, have those same kind of issues. We humans, the human factor.
SPEAKER_1:  We haven't talked about that one quite as much, but it's still there.
SPEAKER_0:  So to be clear, it's not, so fusion has intrinsic safety with respect to it can't run away. Those are physics bases.
SPEAKER_0:  Technology and engineering basis of running a complex, again, anything that makes large amounts of power and heats things up is got intrinsic safety in it.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  by the fact that we actually produce very energetic particles, this doesn't mean that there's no radiation involved in, ionizing radiation.
SPEAKER_0:  be more accurate.
SPEAKER_0:  infusion, it's just that it's in a very different order of magnitude basically.
SPEAKER_0:  So what are the lessons?
SPEAKER_0:  the infusion.
SPEAKER_0:  So one of them is.
SPEAKER_0:  Make sure that you're looking at aspects of the holistic.
SPEAKER_0:  environmental
SPEAKER_0:  and societal footprint that the technology will have.
SPEAKER_0:  As technologists, we tend not to focus on these.
SPEAKER_0:  and particularly in early stages of development.
SPEAKER_0:  Like we just want something that works.
SPEAKER_0:  But if we come with just something that works but doesn't actually satisfy...
SPEAKER_0:  societal demands for safety.
SPEAKER_0:  And for, I mean, we will have materials that we have to dispose of out of fusion. Just this is.
SPEAKER_0:  But there's technological questions about what that looks like.
SPEAKER_0:  So will this look like something that you have to put in the ground for 100 years or 5 years?
SPEAKER_0:  And the consequences of those are both economic and societal acceptance and so forth.
SPEAKER_0:  but don't bury those. Like, put the- bring these up front.
SPEAKER_0:  talk to people about them and make people realize that you're actually
SPEAKER_0:  The way I would look at it is that you're making fusion more economically attractive by making it more societally acceptable as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And then realize is that, you know, I think there's a few interesting, you know, boundaries basically. So one of them, speaking of boundaries, that successful fusion devices.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm-
SPEAKER_0:  pretty sure will require that you don't have to have an evacuation plan for anybody who lives at the site.
SPEAKER_0:  So this has implications for what we build.
SPEAKER_0:  from a fusion engineering point of view.
SPEAKER_0:  but has major implications for where you can site.
SPEAKER_0:  Fusion devices.
SPEAKER_0:  So in many ways it becomes more like, well, you know, we have fences around, you know, industrial heat sources and things like this for a reason, right, for personal safety. It looks more like that.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not quite as simple as that, but that's what it should look like.
SPEAKER_0:  And in fact, we have research projects going on right now at MIT that are.
SPEAKER_0:  like trying to push the technologies to make it more look like that.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that those are key.
SPEAKER_0:  And then in the end, as I said.
SPEAKER_0:  So Chernobyl is physically impossible actually in a fusion system.
SPEAKER_0:  From a physics perspective, you can't run away like it did at Chernobyl, which was basically human error.
SPEAKER_0:  of letting the reactors run out of control, essentially.
SPEAKER_0:  Human error can still happen.
SPEAKER_1:  nuclear fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so, but in that one, if human error occurs, then it just stops.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is done.
SPEAKER_0:  and all those things this is the requirement of of us as technologists and developers of this technology.
SPEAKER_0:  to not ignore that dimension, in fact, of the design. And that's why me personally, I'm actually...
SPEAKER_0:  pouring myself more and more into that area because this is going to be
SPEAKER_0:  I actually really think it is an aspect of the economic viability of fusion because
SPEAKER_0:  It clearly...
SPEAKER_0:  differentiates ourselves and also sets us up to be about what we want fusion to be. That again on paper fusion can supply all of our energy.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, all of it.
SPEAKER_0:  So this means I want it to be like.
SPEAKER_0:  like really environmentally benign.
SPEAKER_0:  But this takes engineering ingenuity basically to do that.
SPEAKER_0:  Let me ask you some.
SPEAKER_1:  Wild Out there.
SPEAKER_0:  Sure.
SPEAKER_0:  We've been talking too much, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Simple.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... practical things in everyday life now only revolutionizing the entire energy infrastructure of human civilization yes
SPEAKER_1:  But, um...
SPEAKER_1:  So cold fusion.
SPEAKER_1:  This idea, this dream.
SPEAKER_1:  This interesting...
SPEAKER_1:  physical goals seem to be impossible.
SPEAKER_1:  But perhaps it's possible. Do you think it is possible? Do you think?
SPEAKER_1:  down the line so we're in...
SPEAKER_1:  and the far distance is possible to achieve fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  at low temperature.
SPEAKER_0:  It's very, very, very unlikely.
SPEAKER_0:  and this comes from, so this would.
SPEAKER_0:  require a pretty fundamental shift in our understanding of.
SPEAKER_0:  of physics as we know it now.
SPEAKER_0:  And we know a heck of a lot about how nuclear reactions occur.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  By the way, what's interesting is that they actually have a different name for it. They call it leaner, like low energy nuclear reactions.
SPEAKER_0:  But we do have low energy nuclear reactions. We know these, it's because these come from-
SPEAKER_0:  particularly the weak force, nuclear force.
SPEAKER_0:  And
SPEAKER_0:  So it's at this point.
SPEAKER_0:  As a scientist you always keep yourself open, but you also demand proof.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? And that's the thing.
SPEAKER_1:  It almost requires a breakthrough on the theoretical physics side.
SPEAKER_1:  So something, some deeper understanding about quantum mechanics of this. So the quantum tunneling, some weird...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, and people have looked at that, but...
SPEAKER_0:  even something like quantum tunneling has a limit as to what it can actually do. So there are people.
SPEAKER_0:  who are genuine, you know, that really want to see it make it, but...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it sort of goes to the extro... I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  We know fusion happens at these high energies.
SPEAKER_0:  when we know this extremely accurately and I can show you a plot.
SPEAKER_0:  that shows that as you go to lower and lower energy, it basically becomes immeasurable.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're going down this other pathway, it means there's really a very...
SPEAKER_0:  different physical mechanism involved.
SPEAKER_0:  All I would say is that I actually poke in my head once in a while to see what's going on.
SPEAKER_0:  in that area.
SPEAKER_0:  and as scientists we should always try to make ourselves open.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and...
SPEAKER_0:  But in this one, it's like, but show me...
SPEAKER_0:  something that I can measure and that is repeatable and then it's going to take more extraordinary effort. And to date this has not met that threshold in my opinion.
SPEAKER_1:  So I'm.
SPEAKER_1:  even more so than just mentioning.
SPEAKER_1:  or in that question, thinking about people that are claiming to have achieved cold fusion.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm more thinking even about...
SPEAKER_1:  people who are studying black holes and they're basically trying to understand.
SPEAKER_1:  function of.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, theoretical physicists.
SPEAKER_1:  They're doing the long haul.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, we're trying to investigate like, okay, what is happening at the singularity? What is the-
SPEAKER_1:  This kind of...
SPEAKER_1:  uh, holographic projections on a plate. this weird
SPEAKER_1:  freaking things that are out there in the universe and like somehow accidentally they start to figure out something we
SPEAKER_0:  Weird, yeah. And then all of a sudden- There's weirdness all over the place already, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  how that weirdness will, I think on a timescale probably of a hundred years or so, that weirdness will open. gdEo
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, it just seems like.
SPEAKER_1:  nuclear fusion and black holes and all of this are too, they're next door neighbors a little bit too much for like you'll find something.
SPEAKER_0:  interesting let me tell you storybook
SPEAKER_0:  Yes. It's a real story..
SPEAKER_0:  So they were really, really clever scientists in the end of the late 1800s.
SPEAKER_0:  in the world. You talk about like James Clerk Maxwell and you talk about Lord Kelvin.
SPEAKER_0:  And you talk about Lorentz actually who named after these other ones and
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, on and on and on and like Faraday and they discovered electromagnetism, holy cow. And it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  they figure out all these things and
SPEAKER_0:  Yet there were these weird...
SPEAKER_0:  things going on that you couldn't quite figure out. It's like, what the heck is going on with this, right?
SPEAKER_0:  But we teach this all the time in physics classes, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So what was going on? Well there's just a few.
SPEAKER_0:  There's just a few kind of things.
SPEAKER_0:  things unchecked, but basically we're at the end of discovery because we figured out how everything works.
SPEAKER_0:  because we've got basically Newtonian mechanics and we've got Maxwell's equations.
SPEAKER_0:  which describe basically how matter gets pushed around and how electromagnetism works. Holy cow, what a feat.
SPEAKER_0:  But there are these few nagging things.
SPEAKER_0:  For instance, there's certain kinds of rocks that for some reason, like if you put a photographic plate around it...
SPEAKER_0:  it like it's burned or it gets an image on it.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, where's the electromagnetism in that?
SPEAKER_0:  There's no electromagnetic properties of this rock.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yeah, and the other thing too is that if I...
SPEAKER_0:  if I take this wonderful classical derivation of something that is hot.
SPEAKER_0:  about how it releases radiation.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything looks fantastic. Perfect match.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, until I get high frequencies.
SPEAKER_0:  of the light and then it basically just, the whole thing falls apart. In fact,
SPEAKER_0:  it gives a physical explanation which is total nonsense.
SPEAKER_0:  It tells you that every object should basically be producing an infinite amount of heat.
SPEAKER_0:  And by the way...
SPEAKER_0:  Here's the sun.
SPEAKER_0:  and we can look at the sun.
SPEAKER_0:  and we can figure out it's made out of hydrogen. And Lord Kelvin actually made a very famous calculation who was basically one of the founders of thermodynamics.
SPEAKER_0:  So you look at the hydrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  Hydrogen has a certain energy content, you know the latent heat basically of hydrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  We know the mass of the sun because we knew the size of it. And he conclusively proved that basically
SPEAKER_0:  The sun could only make net energy for about 2 or 3,000 years.
SPEAKER_0:  So therefore all this nonsense about like deep, because clearly the sun can only last for two or three thousand years.
SPEAKER_0:  if you think about the chemical and this is basically the chemical energy content of hydrogen.
SPEAKER_0:  and what comes along.
SPEAKER_0:  in one decade.
SPEAKER_0:  basically one guy sitting in a postal office you know in switzerland
SPEAKER_0:  figures out that all these, you know, Einstein of course, which was like figured out all of this, took these seemingly unconnected things and it's like boom, there it is. This is what it was, it wasn't just him, but it was like there's quantum physics, like this explains this other disaster.
SPEAKER_0:  And then there's other guy, my hero.
SPEAKER_0:  Ernest Rutherford, experimentalist.
SPEAKER_0:  did the most extraordinary experiment, which is like...
SPEAKER_0:  which was that, okay, they had these funny rocks. They emitted these particles. In fact, they called them alpha particles, alpha just A in the alphabet, right? Because it was the first thing that they discovered.
SPEAKER_0:  what were they doing? So they were
SPEAKER_0:  they were taking these alpha particles and I, by the way, I do this to all my students because it's a demonstration of what you should be as a good scientist.
SPEAKER_0:  So he took these alpha things and he was a classically trained physicist, knew everything about momentum scattering and stuff like that.
SPEAKER_0:  And he took this.
SPEAKER_0:  And these alpha...
SPEAKER_0:  which clearly were some kind of energy, but they couldn't quite figure out what it was. So let's try to figure that, and we'll actually use this to try to probe the nature of matter.
SPEAKER_0:  So he took this.
SPEAKER_0:  these alpha particles
SPEAKER_0:  and a very, very thin gold foil.
SPEAKER_0:  And so what you wanted to see was that as they were going through...
SPEAKER_0:  the way that they would scatter based on classical, in fact, the coulomb collision.
SPEAKER_0:  based on classical mechanics, this will tell me reveal something.
SPEAKER_0:  about what the nature of the charge distribution is in matter because they didn't know where the hell is this stuff coming from?
SPEAKER_0:  even though they'd solved that electromagnetism.
SPEAKER_0:  They didn't know what made up charges.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, very interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  On it through it goes.
SPEAKER_0:  And so what did you set up? So it turns out in these experiments what you did was
SPEAKER_0:  because if these al- these so-called alphas
SPEAKER_0:  which actually now we know something else.
SPEAKER_0:  As they go through, they would deflect. How much they deflect tells you how strong electric field they saw.
SPEAKER_0:  So you put detectors, because if you put like a piece of glass in front of this...
SPEAKER_0:  What will happen is that when the alpha particle hits, it literally gives a little...
SPEAKER_0:  But a little bit of light like this. It's Syntellies.
SPEAKER_0:  a little blue flash.
SPEAKER_0:  So he would train his students or postdocs or whatever the heck they were at the time. You have to train yourself because you have to put yourself in the dark for like hours.
SPEAKER_0:  get your eyes adjusted and then they would start the experiment and they would sit there and literally count the things. And they could see this pattern developing which was revealing about what was going on.
SPEAKER_0:  But there was also another part to the experiment, which was that
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, here's the.
SPEAKER_0:  alphas. Here's the source.
SPEAKER_0:  they're going this way, they could tell they were going in one direction only, they're going in this direction.
SPEAKER_0:  And you put all these over here because you want to see how they deflect and bend through it.
SPEAKER_0:  but you put a control in the experiment.
SPEAKER_0:  but you basically put glass.
SPEAKER_0:  part of glass plates back here.
SPEAKER_0:  because obviously...
SPEAKER_0:  Everything should just deflect, but nothing should bounce back.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's the control of the experiment.
SPEAKER_0:  But what did they see?
SPEAKER_0:  They saw things bouncing back.
SPEAKER_0:  Like what the hell?
SPEAKER_0:  Like that fit no model of any idea.
SPEAKER_0:  But Rutherford refused to ignore.
SPEAKER_0:  What was the clearest, like they validated it.
SPEAKER_0:  and he sat down and based on classical physics, he made the most extraordinary discovery.
SPEAKER_0:  which was the nucleus.
SPEAKER_0:  which is a very, very strange discovery.
SPEAKER_0:  what I mean by that, because what he could figure out from this is that in order for these particles.
SPEAKER_0:  to bounce back.
SPEAKER_0:  and hit this plate.
SPEAKER_0:  They were hitting something that must be...
SPEAKER_0:  heavier than them.
SPEAKER_0:  and that basically something like 99.999% of the mass.
SPEAKER_0:  of the matter that was in this gold foil.
SPEAKER_0:  who was in something that contained...
SPEAKER_0:  about one trillionth of the volume.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's called the nucleus.
SPEAKER_0:  And until...
SPEAKER_0:  And you talk about, so how revealing is this? It's like...
SPEAKER_0:  This totally changes your idea of the universe because a nucleus.
SPEAKER_0:  is a very unintuitive, non-intuitive thing.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, why is all the mass?
SPEAKER_0:  in something that is like zero.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, basically it was the realization that matter is empty.
SPEAKER_0:  It's all empty space.
SPEAKER_0:  And that changes everything. And it changes everything.
SPEAKER_0:  until you had that, like you had steam engines, by the way, you had telegraph wires, you had all those things.
SPEAKER_0:  But that realization, those two realizations opened up everything.
SPEAKER_0:  Like lasers, all these things about the modern world of what we use.
SPEAKER_0:  And that set it up. So all I would point out is that there's a story already that sometimes there's these nagging things.
SPEAKER_0:  at the edge of science.
SPEAKER_0:  that we pat ourselves on the back and we think we got everything under control.
SPEAKER_0:  By the way, that was the origin of also, but.
SPEAKER_0:  that it, think about this, that was 1908. It took like another.
SPEAKER_0:  20 some years.
SPEAKER_0:  before people put that together with, that's the process that's
SPEAKER_0:  hiring stars.
SPEAKER_0:  is the rearrangement of those nuclei, not atoms. That's why Kelvin wasn't wrong, he just was working with the wrong assumptions, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So fast forward to today, like what would this mean, right? Well, there's a couple of things like this that sit out there in physics.
SPEAKER_0:  and I'll point out one of them, which is very interesting. We don't know what the hell makes up 90% of the mass in the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  So, you know, the search for dark matter, right? What is it?
SPEAKER_0:  We still haven't discovered it. 90% of the mass.
SPEAKER_0:  of the universe is undetectable.
SPEAKER_0:  Like what?
SPEAKER_1:  And then, you know, and dark energy and the again black holes are the window into this.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, sometimes black holes are way better understood than those things as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  So all it tells us is that we shouldn't have hubris about the ideas that we understand everything.
SPEAKER_0:  And when we, you know, who knows what the next...
SPEAKER_0:  major intellectual insight will be about how the universe functions.
SPEAKER_0:  And actually.
SPEAKER_1:  I think Rutherford is the one who's attributed at least that quote that physics is the only
SPEAKER_1:  Real science, everything else is stamp collecting.
SPEAKER_1:  Alright, so...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm sorry, he's my hero, but I'll slightly disagree with that. Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  lol
SPEAKER_1:  No offense to stamp collecting, that's very important too. But you have to have humility about the kind of disciplines that make progress at every stage in science. Physics did make a huge amount of progress in the 20th century, but it's possible that other disciplines start to step in.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, but Rutherford couldn't imagine, like, mapping the human genome because we didn't even know about DNA.
SPEAKER_0:  Or computers, really. Or computers, really.
SPEAKER_1:  probably didn't think deep about.
SPEAKER_0:  No, it's just like, is it?
SPEAKER_0:  Here's a wild one, what if like the next great...
SPEAKER_0:  revelation to humanity about the universe is not done by the human mind.
SPEAKER_1:  that seems increasingly more likely. And then you start to ask deep questions about what is the purpose of science. For example,
SPEAKER_1:  if
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  AI system will design.
SPEAKER_1:  a nuclear fusion reactor.
SPEAKER_1:  better than humans do, but we don't quite understand how it works.
SPEAKER_1:  and the AI can't, we know that it works.
SPEAKER_1:  contested very thoroughly, but we don't know exactly.
SPEAKER_1:  what the control mechanism is, maybe what the chemistry of the physics is.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... a i can't quite explain it they just can't it
SPEAKER_0:  It's impenetrable to our consciousness basically, trying to hold it all together.
SPEAKER_1:  And then, okay, so now we're living in that world where many of the biggest discoveries are made by AI systems. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  As if we weren't going back.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I say, you know, it's, again, I will point out like when my godmother was born, like none of this was in front of us, right? It's like we live in an amazing time.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Like my grandfather, you know, plowed fields with a horse.
SPEAKER_0:  I get to work on designing Fusion Rear.
SPEAKER_0:  Pretty amazing time.
SPEAKER_1:  but still there's humans, so we'll see. We'll see if that's around 100 years.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe it'll be outside.
SPEAKER_0:  I think we're pretty resilient actually.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I know. That's one lesson from life is it finds a way. Let me ask you a bigger question, as if those weren't big enough. Let's look out.
SPEAKER_1:  maybe a few hundred years, maybe a few thousand years out.
SPEAKER_1:  There's something called the Kardashev Scale. It's a method of measuring civilization's level of technological advancement based on the amount of energy it's able to use.
SPEAKER_1:  So type one civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  And this might be given all your work is not no longer a scale that makes quite make sense.
SPEAKER_1:  but...
SPEAKER_1:  It very much focuses on the source of fusion.
SPEAKER_1:  natural source of fusion which is for us the sun.
SPEAKER_1:  And type one civilizations are able to leverage.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... to collect
SPEAKER_1:  all the energy that hits Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  And then type two civilizations are the ones that are able to leverage.
SPEAKER_1:  the entirety of the energy that comes from the sun by maybe building something.
SPEAKER_0:  Like a Dyson Sphere? Yeah!
SPEAKER_1:  If...
SPEAKER_1:  When will we reach type 1 status?
SPEAKER_1:  is get to the level which we're, I think, maybe a few orders of magnitude away from currently.
SPEAKER_1:  And in general, do you think about this kind of stuff is where energy is so fundamental to.
SPEAKER_1:  this like of life on earth.
SPEAKER_1:  but also the expansion of life into the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yeah, so what-
SPEAKER_0:  One of the fun, on a weekend when I sat down and figured out what would it mean for interstellar travel, like to have a DT.
SPEAKER_0:  In fact, one of the-
SPEAKER_0:  I talked about my design class. One of my design classes was how you use.
SPEAKER_0:  essentially a special configuration of a fusion device for not only traveling to but colonizing Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  So because what we're we're.
SPEAKER_0:  You talk about energy use being at the heart of civilizations like-
SPEAKER_0:  What if you want to go to Mars not to just visit it but actually leave people there and make it something happen?
SPEAKER_0:  these massive amounts of energy.
SPEAKER_0:  So what would that look like? And it actually transforms how you're thinking about doing that as well too. Oh yeah, so we do those kinds of fun.
SPEAKER_0:  And actually it was a fairly, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Quasi-realistic actually.
SPEAKER_1:  think.
SPEAKER_1:  It'll be nuclear fusion that powers this.
SPEAKER_0:  civilization on Mars?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, what we considered was something, so it turns out that there's thorium.
SPEAKER_0:  which is a heavy element.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's a so-called fertile element.
SPEAKER_0:  that we still know fairly little about the geology of Mars in a deep sense.
SPEAKER_0:  and we know that there's a lot of this on the surface of Mars. So one of the things we considered was what would happen
SPEAKER_0:  that it's basically a combination of a fusion
SPEAKER_0:  device that actually makes fuel from the thorium.
SPEAKER_0:  But the underlying energy one was vision itself as well too. This is one of the examples of trying to be clever.
SPEAKER_0:  around those things or what is it you know
SPEAKER_0:  This also means that in interstellar travel it's like, oh yeah, that looks almost like impossible basically from an energy balance point of view. It's just like the energy required that you have to transport to get there. The only things that would work are DT fusion and basically...
SPEAKER_0:  annihilation.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like Star Trek, right?
SPEAKER_1:  Interstellar travel will require.
SPEAKER_0:  fusion.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, it's almost even impossible with fusion power actually. So hard.
SPEAKER_0:  It's so hard because you have to carry the fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  with you and the rocket equation tells you about how much fuel you use.
SPEAKER_0:  to take, so what you end up with is like, how long does it take to go to these places? And it's like...
SPEAKER_0:  staggering, you know, periods of time.
SPEAKER_0:  So I tend to believe.
SPEAKER_1:  that there's alien civilizations dispersed.
SPEAKER_0:  all throughout the universe. Yeah, but we might be totally isolated from it.
SPEAKER_1:  So you think we're not, there's none in this galaxy.
SPEAKER_1:  like.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess, and the question I also have is what kind of, do you think they have nuclear fusion?
SPEAKER_1:  Is it all?Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  The physics is all the same? Yeah. Oh, the physics is all the same. Yeah. Right. So this is the, and this is the Fermi paradox. Like, where the hell is everybody?
SPEAKER_0:  the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, the scariest one of those is that
SPEAKER_0:  I would point out that there's been, you know, there's, you know, order of many tens of millions of species on the planet Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  and only one ever got to the point of sophisticated tool use.
SPEAKER_0:  that we could actually start.
SPEAKER_0:  essentially leveraging.
SPEAKER_0:  The power of...
SPEAKER_0:  what's in nature.
SPEAKER_0:  our own will.
SPEAKER_0:  Does this mean that basically this means? So almost look.
SPEAKER_0:  There is almost certainly life or-
SPEAKER_0:  DNA equivalence or whatever would be somewhere. I mean, just because you just need a soup and you need energy and
SPEAKER_0:  You get it.
SPEAKER_0:  organics and whatever the equivalent of amino acids are.
SPEAKER_0:  But most of the life on earth has been that those, still amazing, but it's still, it's not very interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  Are we, are we actually the accident of history? This is a very interesting one. Super, super rare. Super rare.
SPEAKER_0:  And then of course the other part is that also just
SPEAKER_0:  The other scary part of it, which if you look at the fairy paradoxes.
SPEAKER_0:  Good, good, we got to this point.
SPEAKER_0:  How long has it been?
SPEAKER_0:  in humans. So humans, homo sapien has been around for a long time.
SPEAKER_0:  100,000 years, 200,000 years or something.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  our ability in that timeline to actually make an imprint on the universe by emitting radio waves or by modifying nature in a significant way has only been for about a hundred of those hundred thousand years
SPEAKER_0:  And, you know, are we, it's a good question. So-
SPEAKER_0:  Is it by definition, by the fact that when you are able to reach that level?
SPEAKER_0:  of being able to manipulate nature and for example, discover.
SPEAKER_0:  discover like fission.
SPEAKER_0:  or burning fossil fuels and all this.
SPEAKER_0:  is that what it says, oh, you're doomed, because...
SPEAKER_0:  By definition, any species that gets to a point that can modify their environment like that, they'll actually push themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, past, that's one of the most depressing scenarios that I can imagine. Yeah, so the... So basically, we will never line up in time.
SPEAKER_0:  because you get this little teeny window in time over.
SPEAKER_0:  civilization might occur and you can never see it because you never...
SPEAKER_0:  these sort of like scatter like fireflies around the galaxy.
SPEAKER_1:  is up is up is up is up and then explodes destroys itself because
SPEAKER_0:  of the exponential. And when we say destroy ourselves, all we would have to do is that we basically go, if you
SPEAKER_0:  Humans are all left and we're still living on the planet.
SPEAKER_0:  But all we have to do is go to...
SPEAKER_0:  the technology of like, you know, 1800. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  and were invisible in the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  So, when I listened to the podcast, I thought I wanted to talk about this as well too, because it comes from a science point of view actually of what it means.
SPEAKER_0:  But also to me, it's like another compelling driver of telling us, like, why we should try.
SPEAKER_0:  Really hard not to screw this up.
SPEAKER_0:  Like we're in this unique place of our ability to discover and make it.
SPEAKER_0:  I just don't want to give up about thinking that we can get through.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I tend to see that there is some kind of game theoretic force like with mutual assured destruction that ultimately in each human being there's a
SPEAKER_1:  desire to survive and a willingness to cooperate.
SPEAKER_1:  to have compassion for each other in order to survive. I think that's
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, maybe not in humans.
SPEAKER_1:  but I can imagine the nearly infinite number of species in which...
SPEAKER_1:  that overpowers.
SPEAKER_1:  Any, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  technological advancement that can destroy.
SPEAKER_1:  or rewind this piece. So I think...
SPEAKER_1:  If humans fail.
SPEAKER_1:  I hope they don't.
SPEAKER_1:  I see a lot of evidence for them not.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like somebody will survive. And there you start to ask questions about why, why we haven't met yet.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe it's just the spaces.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, spaces, it's...
SPEAKER_0:  I think in logarithms and I can't even.
SPEAKER_0:  fathom space. This is extraordinary, right? Yes. It's extraordinarily large.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, there's so many places on Earth. I just recently visited Paris for the first time.
SPEAKER_1:  and there's so many other places.
SPEAKER_0:  There's so many other places. Well, I like to.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it's interesting that we have this fascination with alien life.
SPEAKER_0:  We have
SPEAKER_0:  What is essentially alien life on earth already? Like you think about the organisms that.
SPEAKER_0:  develop around deep sea thermal vents. One of my favorite books of all time from Stephen Jay Gould.
SPEAKER_0:  If you've never read that book, it kind of blows your mind. It's about the Cambrian explosion.
SPEAKER_0:  of life and it's like, oh you look at these things and it's like
SPEAKER_0:  are the chance of us existing as a species.
SPEAKER_0:  the genetic diversity was larger.
SPEAKER_0:  This is about 500 million years ago or something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  It is a mind altering trip of thinking about our place in the universe, I have to say.
SPEAKER_1:  itself.
SPEAKER_1:  is a kind of alien with almost...
SPEAKER_1:  almost a mystery to ourselves. We still don't understand it. The very mechanism that...
SPEAKER_1:  helps us explore the world is still a mystery.
SPEAKER_1:  That.
SPEAKER_1:  Like understanding that will also unlock
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  it quite quite possibly unlock.
SPEAKER_1:  our ability to understand the world and maybe build machines that help us understand the world, build tools that...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean it already has, I mean our ability to understand the world is...
SPEAKER_0:  is ridiculous almost actually.
SPEAKER_0:  My voice, bye000s!!!
SPEAKER_0:  And, and post the bot on. It's almost unbelievable. Where we've gotten all this to. so
SPEAKER_1:  What advice would you give?
SPEAKER_1:  to young folks.
SPEAKER_1:  or folks of all ages who are lost in this world looking for a way, looking for a career they can be proud of or looking.
SPEAKER_1:  to have a life that can be proud.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Oh, the first thing I would say is don't give up.
SPEAKER_0:  I get to see multiple sides of this and you know there is...
SPEAKER_0:  There seems to be a level of despair.
SPEAKER_0:  in a young generation.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, no, it's...
SPEAKER_0:  And it's almost like the Monty Python skit, like I'm not dead yet. Right. I mean, like we're not there. We're in a place that, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  And don't say the world's going to end in 300 days or something. It's not, okay?
SPEAKER_0:  And what we mean by this is that...
SPEAKER_0:  We have a robust society that's figured out how to do like amazing things, and we're going to keep doing amazing things.
SPEAKER_0:  but that shouldn't be complacency.
SPEAKER_0:  about what our future is and the future for their children as well too.
SPEAKER_0:  And in the end...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's a very, it's a staggering legacy to think of what we've built up.
SPEAKER_0:  Primarily by basically using carbon fuels. Like people almost tend to think of this as an evil thing that we've done.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's an amazing thing that we've done.
SPEAKER_0:  But we owe it to ourselves and to this thing that we've built. I mean, we're talking about the end of the world, which is just nonsense.
SPEAKER_0:  What it is is it's the end of this kind of lifestyle.
SPEAKER_0:  and civilization at this scale and the ability to execute on these kinds of things that we are talking about today.
SPEAKER_0:  Like we are extraordinarily privileged.
SPEAKER_0:  We're in a place where it's just, it's...
SPEAKER_0:  It's almost unfathomable compared to most of the misery that humans have lived in for our history.
SPEAKER_0:  So don't give up about this, okay?
SPEAKER_0:  but also roll up your sleeves.
SPEAKER_0:  and let's get going at getting real solutions to the problems that are in front of us.
SPEAKER_0:  which are significant.
SPEAKER_0:  I would argue most of them are linked to what we use in energy, but it's not just that. It's around all the aspects of like, what does it mean?
SPEAKER_0:  What does it mean to have a distributed energy source that lifts billions of people out of poverty?
SPEAKER_0:  you know, particularly outside of like the Western nations, right?
SPEAKER_0:  That seems to me a pretty-
SPEAKER_0:  compelling.
SPEAKER_0:  in a moral goal.
SPEAKER_0:  for all of us.
SPEAKER_0:  but particularly for this upcoming
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  And then the other part is that we've got possible solutions in front of us.
SPEAKER_0:  Apply your talents.
SPEAKER_0:  In a way.
SPEAKER_0:  that you're passionate about and...
SPEAKER_0:  is gonna make a difference.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's only possible.
SPEAKER_1:  with optimism, hope and hard work.
SPEAKER_1:  What, uh, easy question.
SPEAKER_1:  It's certainly easier than nuclear fusion.
SPEAKER_1:  What's the meaning of life?
SPEAKER_0:  Why are we here? 42. Is it 42?
SPEAKER_1:  No.
SPEAKER_1:  And...
SPEAKER_1:  We already discussed about the beauty of physics that there's almost a desire to ask a why question about why the parameters have these values Yeah
SPEAKER_0:  It's very tempting, yeah. It's-
SPEAKER_0:  It's an interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  hole to go down as a scientist because we're
SPEAKER_0:  A part of what
SPEAKER_0:  people.
SPEAKER_0:  have a hard time people who aren't scientists have a hard time understanding what scientists do to themselves
SPEAKER_0:  and a great scientist.
SPEAKER_0:  does a very non-
SPEAKER_0:  intuitive or non-human thing.
SPEAKER_0:  What we do is we train ourselves to doubt ourselves. Like how? Like that's a great scientist. We doubt everything we see.
SPEAKER_0:  We doubt everything that we think.
SPEAKER_0:  because
SPEAKER_0:  We.
SPEAKER_0:  We basically try to turn off the belief.
SPEAKER_0:  right, that humans just naturally have.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  So when it comes to these things, I can make my own comments to this. It's like personally.
SPEAKER_0:  You see these things about the ratios of life. And I made a comment where I said, well, you know, a wrap, my
SPEAKER_0:  Some part of my brain that just goes...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, well, yeah, cause we're the only interesting, you know, multiverse because by definition it has to look like this, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  But I have to say there's other times, I can say in the history of the whole-
SPEAKER_0:  of what has happened over the last 10 years.
SPEAKER_0:  There have been some pretty weird coincidences, like coincidences
SPEAKER_0:  that like you look at it and just go, is that really, was that really a coincidence? Was that tauh.
SPEAKER_0:  is something like
SPEAKER_0:  pushing us towards these things.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's a natural, it's a human instinct because, you know, since the beginnings of humanity, we've always assigned
SPEAKER_0:  You know?
SPEAKER_0:  you know, human motivation and needs.
SPEAKER_0:  to these somewhat empirical observations.
SPEAKER_1:  some sense the stories.
SPEAKER_1:  before we understand the real explanations.
SPEAKER_1:  The stories, the myths.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, service as a
SPEAKER_1:  as a good approximation for the thing that we're yet to understand. Absolutely. In a net sense.
SPEAKER_1:  You said the antithesis to sort of scientific Tao is having a faith.
SPEAKER_1:  In this.
SPEAKER_1:  stories they're almost
SPEAKER_1:  silly when looked at from a scientific perspective, but just even the feelings of
SPEAKER_1:  It seems that love is a fundamental fabric of human condition.
SPEAKER_1:  And what the hell is that?
SPEAKER_0:  Billها
SPEAKER_0:  Why are we so connected to each other? As a physicist I go it's you know
SPEAKER_0:  This is a repeatable thing that's due to a set of synapses that fire in a particular pattern and all this. That's kind of like, okay man, what a drag that is to think of it this way.
SPEAKER_1:  and you can have an evolutionary biology explanation but there's still a magic to it.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I see scientists, some of my colleagues, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  do this as well too, like where?
SPEAKER_0:  What is spirituality compared to science and so forth?
SPEAKER_0:  My own feeling in this is that...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, as a scientist, cause I've had the pleasure of being able to like.
SPEAKER_0:  both understand what my predecessors did, but I also had the privilege of being able to discover things, right as a scientist and
SPEAKER_0:  And I see that in just the range of our conversations.
SPEAKER_0:  That is my, in a weird way, it's the awe.
SPEAKER_0:  that comes.
SPEAKER_0:  From looking at that.
SPEAKER_0:  That is...
SPEAKER_0:  if you're not in awe.
SPEAKER_0:  of the universe and nature. You haven't been paying attention. I mean my own personal feeling is that-
SPEAKER_0:  I feel.
SPEAKER_0:  If I go snorkeling on a coral reef.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel more awe than I could ever feel like in a church.
SPEAKER_1:  you kind of notice some kind of magic there.
SPEAKER_0:  There's something about the way the whole...
SPEAKER_0:  darn thing holds together that just
SPEAKER_0:  sort of escapes your imagination and that's.
SPEAKER_0:  to me that this thing of
SPEAKER_0:  And then we have different words, we call them holistic or.
SPEAKER_0:  spiritual, the way that it all hangs together. In fact, one of the issues you asked about, like what I think about.
SPEAKER_0:  One of the craziest things that I think that how does it hold together is like our society.
SPEAKER_0:  How does-
SPEAKER_0:  What? Yeah. How ou-
SPEAKER_0:  Because there's no way, like just think of the United States, there's 330 million people.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of working like this engine.
SPEAKER_0:  about going towards making all these things happen.
SPEAKER_0:  But there's like no one in charge of this, really. Not really, yeah. How the heck does this happen?
SPEAKER_0:  It's kind of like, it's...
SPEAKER_0:  So these things, these are the kinds of things mathematically and organization wise.
SPEAKER_0:  that I think of just because they're awe-inspiring.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's different.
SPEAKER_1:  ideas that we come up together and we share them and then there's
SPEAKER_1:  There's teams of people that share different ideas and those ideas compete like there was the ideas themselves are these kinds of different Organisms and ultimately somehow we build bridges and nuclear reactors
SPEAKER_0:  and do those things.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I have to give a shout out to my daughter, by the way, who's an applied math major and she's amazing at math and over the break she was showing me she's doing research. It's basically about how – – Fin –
SPEAKER_0:  ideas and ethos are transmitted within a society. Nice. So she's building an applied math model.
SPEAKER_0:  I was explaining like...
SPEAKER_0:  She was showing me in this simulation, she goes, Oh, look, look at this. And I said, oh.
SPEAKER_0:  That's like how political parties like evolve.
SPEAKER_0:  And even though it was a rather, you know, quote unquote simple mathematical model, it wasn't really. It's like.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  What maybe
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe she has a chance to derive mathematically the answer to what's the meaning of life. There we go. And maybe it is indeed 42. Sega is absolutely fearless.
SPEAKER_1:  Dennis, thank you so much for just...
SPEAKER_1:  doing.
SPEAKER_1:  creating tools, creating systems, exploring.
SPEAKER_1:  This idea.
SPEAKER_1:  That's one of the most amazing magical ideas in all of human endeavor, which is
SPEAKER_1:  nuclear fusion. I mean that's so-
SPEAKER_0:  interesting. You know it's almost like my...
SPEAKER_0:  One of my lifelong goals is like to make it, it's like, it's not magic. It's like, it's boring as all heck. And this means we're using it everywhere. Right? Yeah. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  And the magic is then built on top of it. Well, thank you for everything you do. Thank you for talking to me. It's a huge honor. This was a fascinating and amazing conversation. Thank you.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with Dennis White.
SPEAKER_1:  To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now...
SPEAKER_1:  Let me leave you with some words from Albert Einstein.
SPEAKER_1:  There are two ways to live your life.
SPEAKER_1:  One is as though nothing is a miracle.
SPEAKER_1:  The other.
SPEAKER_1:  as though everything's a miracle.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for listening.
SPEAKER_1:  I hope to see you.
SPEAKER_1:  next time.