SPEAKER_1:  I think it's actually not that hard to imagine we are the only civilization in the galaxy right now.
SPEAKER_1:  living.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, that's this kernel extent.
SPEAKER_1:  But there may be very many extinct civilizations. If each civilization has a typical lifetime comparable to, let's say AI is the demise of our own.
SPEAKER_1:  That's only a few hundred years of technological development or maybe 10,000 years if you go back to the Neolithic Revolution.
SPEAKER_1:  the dawn of agriculture.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, hardly anything can cosmic time span.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  That's nothing, that's the blink of an eye.
SPEAKER_1:  And so it's not surprising at all that we would happen not to co-exist with anyone else.
SPEAKER_1:  That doesn't mean nobody else was ever here.
SPEAKER_1:  And if other civilizations come to that same conclusion and realization, maybe they scour the galaxy around them, but find any evidence for intelligence.
SPEAKER_1:  Then
SPEAKER_1:  They have two options, they can either give up on communication.
SPEAKER_1:  and just say, well, it's never going to happen.
SPEAKER_1:  We just may as well just, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  worry about what's happening here on our own planet.
SPEAKER_1:  Or they could attempt communication, but communication through time.
SPEAKER_1:  The following is a conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  with David Kipping.
SPEAKER_0:  an astronomer and astrophysicist at Columbia University.
SPEAKER_0:  Director of the Cool Worlds Lab.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  He's an amazing educator.
SPEAKER_0:  about.
SPEAKER_0:  the most fascinating scientific phenomena in our universe.
SPEAKER_0:  I highly recommend you check out his videos on the Cool Worlds YouTube channel.
SPEAKER_0:  David.
SPEAKER_0:  quickly became one of my favorite human beings.
SPEAKER_0:  I hope to talk to him.
SPEAKER_0:  many more times in the future.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the Lex Friedman podcast.
SPEAKER_0:  support it.
SPEAKER_0:  Please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_0:  And now, dear friends.
SPEAKER_0:  Here's David.
SPEAKER_0:  Kipping.
SPEAKER_0:  Your research at Columbia is in part focused on what you call cool worlds or
SPEAKER_0:  worlds outside our solar system or temperature.
SPEAKER_0:  It's sufficiently cool to allow for moons, rings, and life to form, and for us humans to observe it.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you tell me?
SPEAKER_0:  More about.
SPEAKER_0:  this idea, this place of cool worlds.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, the history of discovering planets outside our solar system was
SPEAKER_1:  really dominated by these hot planets.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's just because of the fact they're easier to find.
SPEAKER_1:  When the very first methods came online, these were primarily the Doppler spectroscopy method, looking for wobbling stars.
SPEAKER_1:  and also the transit method. And these two both have a really strong bias towards finding these hot planets.
SPEAKER_1:  Now.
SPEAKER_1:  planets are interesting. The chemistry in the atmosphere is fascinating. It's very alien.
SPEAKER_1:  An example of one that's particularly close to my heart is Trace 2B.
SPEAKER_1:  whose atmosphere is so dark it's less reflective than coal.
SPEAKER_1:  And so they have.
SPEAKER_1:  really bizarre.
SPEAKER_1:  Photometric properties.
SPEAKER_1:  yet at the same time.
SPEAKER_1:  They resemble nothing like our own home.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  It said there's two types of astrophysicists, the astrophysicists who care about how the universe works.
SPEAKER_1:  They want to understand the mechanics of.
SPEAKER_1:  the machinery of this universe, why did the big bang happen, why is the universe expanding, how are galaxies formed?
SPEAKER_1:  And there's another type of astrophysicist which perhaps...
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  speaks to me a little bit more, it whispers into your ear, and that is why we hear.
SPEAKER_1:  Are we alone? Are there others out there?
SPEAKER_1:  And ultimately, along this journey, the hotplates aren't going to get us there.
SPEAKER_1:  when we're looking for life in the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  seems to make perfect sense that there should be planets like our own out there.
SPEAKER_1:  maybe even moons like our own planet around gas giants that could be habitable.
SPEAKER_1:  And so my research has been driven by trying to find these more miraculous globes that might
SPEAKER_1:  resemble our own planet.
SPEAKER_0:  So they're the ones that lurk more in the shadows in terms of how difficult it is to detect.
SPEAKER_1:  They're much harder. They're harder for several reasons. The method we primarily use is the transit method. So this is really eclipses.
SPEAKER_1:  As the planet passes in front of the star, it blocks out some starlight.
SPEAKER_1:  The problem with that is that not all planets pass in front of their star. They have to be aligned correctly from your line of sight.
SPEAKER_1:  And so the further away the planet is from the star, the cooler it is.
SPEAKER_1:  the less likely it is that you're gonna get that geometric alignment.
SPEAKER_1:  So whereas a hot Jupiter, about 1% of hot Jupiters will transit in front of their star,
SPEAKER_1:  only about
SPEAKER_1:  0.5%, maybe even a quarter of a percent of Earth-like planets will have the right geometry.
SPEAKER_1:  to transit.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that makes it much, much harder for us.
SPEAKER_0:  What's the connection between temperature of the planet and geometric alignment?
SPEAKER_0:  Probability of geometric alignment. There's no-
SPEAKER_1:  direct connection, but they're connected via an intermediate parameter, which is their separation from the star.
SPEAKER_1:  So the planet will be cooler if it's further away from the star.
SPEAKER_1:  Which in turn means that the probability of getting that alignment correct is going to be less.
SPEAKER_1:  On top of that, they also transit their star less frequently.
SPEAKER_1:  So if you go to the telescope and you want to discover a hot Jupiter.
SPEAKER_1:  You could probably do it in a week or so, because the orbital periods are of order of one, two, three days. So you can actually get the full orbit two or three times over.
SPEAKER_1:  whereas if you wanted to set an Earth-like planet.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to observe that star for 3-4 years.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's actually one of the problems with.
SPEAKER_1:  Kepler. Kepler.
SPEAKER_1:  was this very successful mission that NASA launched.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm over a decade ago now, I think, and...
SPEAKER_1:  It discovered thousands of planets. It's still the dominant source of exoplanets that we know about.
SPEAKER_1:  But unfortunately, it didn't last as long as we would have liked it to.
SPEAKER_1:  It died after about 4.35 years, I think it was. And so...
SPEAKER_1:  for an Earth-like planet, that's just enough to catch four transits.
SPEAKER_1:  and full transits was kind of seen as the minimum.
SPEAKER_1:  But of course, the more transits you see, the easier it is to detect it because you build up signal to noise.
SPEAKER_1:  If you see the same thing, tick, tick, tick, tick, tick, the more ticks you get.
SPEAKER_1:  the easier is to find it.
SPEAKER_1:  And so it was really a shame that...
SPEAKER_1:  Kepler was just at the limit of where we were expecting it to start to see Earth-like planets.
SPEAKER_1:  And in fact, it really found zero.
SPEAKER_1:  zero planets that are around stars like the Sun.
SPEAKER_1:  orbits similar to the Earth around the Sun.
SPEAKER_1:  and could potentially be.
SPEAKER_1:  similar to our own planet in terms of its composition.
SPEAKER_1:  And so it's a great shame, but that's why it gives astronomers.
SPEAKER_1:  more to do in the future.
SPEAKER_1:  Just to clarify.
SPEAKER_0:  The transit method.
SPEAKER_0:  is
SPEAKER_0:  primary way of detecting these things.
SPEAKER_0:  And what it is is, uh,
SPEAKER_0:  when the object.
SPEAKER_0:  passes, occludes.
SPEAKER_0:  The source of light, just a tiny bit.
SPEAKER_0:  a few pixels.
SPEAKER_0:  And from that we can infer something about its mass and size and distance and geometry and all of that.
SPEAKER_0:  That's like.
SPEAKER_0:  trying to tell.
SPEAKER_0:  What?
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  at a party, you can't see anything about a person, but you can just see by the way they occlude others.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is the method.
SPEAKER_0:  but this is super far away.
SPEAKER_0:  How many pixels of information do we have?
SPEAKER_0:  basically how high resolution is the signal that we.
SPEAKER_0:  that we can get about these occlusions.
SPEAKER_1:  You're right in your description. I think just to build upon that a little bit more, it might be almost like...
SPEAKER_1:  your vision is completely blurry. Like you have an extreme.
SPEAKER_1:  in a high prescription.
SPEAKER_1:  and say you can't.
SPEAKER_1:  resolve anything. Everything's just blurs.
SPEAKER_1:  And but you can tell that something was there because it just got fainter for a short amount of time. Someone passed in front of a light. And so that light in your eyes would just dim for a short moment.
SPEAKER_1:  Now the reason we have that problem with blown as a resolution.
SPEAKER_1:  is just because the stars are so far away.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, these are the closest stars are four light years away, but most of the stars Kepa looked at with thousands of light years away.
SPEAKER_1:  And so there's absolutely no chance that the telescope can physically resolve.
SPEAKER_1:  the star?
SPEAKER_1:  or even.
SPEAKER_1:  the separation between the planet and the star is too small, especially for a telescope like Kepler, it's only a meter across.
SPEAKER_1:  In principle, you can make those detections, but...
SPEAKER_1:  you need a different kind of telescope. We call that direct imaging. And direct imaging is a very exciting.
SPEAKER_1:  distinct way of detecting planets.
SPEAKER_1:  But it, as you can imagine, is going to be.
SPEAKER_1:  far easier to detect plants which are really far away from their star to do that, because that's going to make that separation really big.
SPEAKER_1:  And then you also want the star to be really close to us, to the nearest stars.
SPEAKER_1:  Not only that, but you would prefer that planet to be really hot.
SPEAKER_1:  because the hotter it is, the brighter it is.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that tends to bias direct imaging towards plants which are in the process of forming.
SPEAKER_1:  So things which have just formed the planet still got all of its
SPEAKER_1:  primordial heat embedded within it.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's glowing, we can see those quite easily.
SPEAKER_1:  But for the planets more like the Earth, of course, they've cooled down, and so we can't see that the light is pitiful compared to a newly formed planet.
SPEAKER_1:  We would like to get there.
SPEAKER_1:  with direct imaging. The dream is to have.
SPEAKER_1:  the pale blue dot, an actual photograph of it, maybe even just a one pixel photograph of it.
SPEAKER_1:  But for now, the entire solar system.
SPEAKER_1:  is one pixel, certainly with the transit method most other telescopes.
SPEAKER_1:  And so all you can do is see where that one pixel.
SPEAKER_1:  which contains potentially dozens of planets.
SPEAKER_1:  and the star, maybe even multiple stars.
SPEAKER_1:  dims for a short amount of time.
SPEAKER_1:  The dims just a little.
SPEAKER_0:  bit and from that
SPEAKER_1:  you can infer something.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean, it's like being a detective.
SPEAKER_1:  and the scene, right? It's very, it's indirect clues of the existence of the planet.
SPEAKER_0:  It's amazing that humans can do that.
SPEAKER_0:  I was just looking out in these immense distances.
SPEAKER_0:  and looking...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, if there's alien civilizations out there, let's say one exactly like our own.
SPEAKER_0:  or like.
SPEAKER_0:  Would we even be able to see an Earth that passes?
SPEAKER_0:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  in the way of its sun and slightly dims. And that's the only sign we have.
SPEAKER_0:  of that.
SPEAKER_0:  of the alien.
SPEAKER_0:  human-like civilization out there. Is it just a little bit of a dimming?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, it depends on the type of star we're talking about. If it is a star, truly like the sun.
SPEAKER_1:  The dip that causes is 84 parts per million. I mean, that's just, it's like the same as a.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, it's like a firefly flying in front of like a giant floodlight at a stadium or something. That's the kind of the brightness contrast that you're trying to.
SPEAKER_1:  compared to, so it's extremely difficult detection.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  in the very, very best cases we can get down to that. But as I said, we don't really have any true earth analogs that have been in the exoplanet candidate yet.
SPEAKER_1:  Unless you relax that definition, you say.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not just doesn't have to be a star just like the sun. It could be a star that's smaller than the sun. It could be.
SPEAKER_1:  these orange dwarfs or even the red dwarf stars.
SPEAKER_1:  and the fact those stars are smaller means that for the same size planet passing in front of it
SPEAKER_1:  More light is blocked out.
SPEAKER_1:  So a very exciting system.
SPEAKER_1:  For example, as Trappist 1.
SPEAKER_1:  which has seven planets, which are.
SPEAKER_1:  smaller than the Earth?
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  those are quite easily detectable, not with a space-based telescope, even from the ground, that's just because the star is so much smaller.
SPEAKER_1:  that the relative increase in or decrease in brightness is enhanced significantly.
SPEAKER_1:  because that's smaller size.
SPEAKER_1:  So TRAPP is one E. It's a planet which is in the right distance for liquid water.
SPEAKER_1:  It has a slightly smaller size than the Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  It's about 90% the size of the Earth, about 80% the mass.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's one of the top targets right now for potentially having life.
SPEAKER_1:  And yet...
SPEAKER_1:  It raises.
SPEAKER_1:  many questions about.
SPEAKER_1:  What would that environment be like? This is a star which is 1 eighth the mass of the sun.
SPEAKER_1:  It's um...
SPEAKER_1:  Stars like that take a long time to...
SPEAKER_1:  Come off that adolescence.
SPEAKER_1:  When stars first form, like the sun, it takes them maybe 10, 100 million years to sort of settle in to that main sequence lifetime.
SPEAKER_1:  But for stars like these lights.
SPEAKER_1:  M-Dwarfs as we call them.
SPEAKER_1:  They can take up to a billion years or more.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  Calm down.
SPEAKER_1:  And during that period, they're producing huge amounts of X-rays, ultraviolet radiation.
SPEAKER_1:  potentially rip off the entire atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  it may desiccate the plants in the system.
SPEAKER_1:  And so even if water arrived by comets or something.
SPEAKER_1:  It may have lost all that water due to this prolonged period of high activity.
SPEAKER_1:  So we have lots of...
SPEAKER_1:  open-ended questions about these m-dwarf planets.
SPEAKER_1:  but they are the most accessible.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  In the near term, if we detect anything in terms of...
SPEAKER_1:  by our signatures.
SPEAKER_1:  it's going to be for one of these red dwarf stars.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not going to be a true.
SPEAKER_1:  Earth Twin, as we would recognise it as having a yellow star.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, let me ask you, I mean, there's a million...
SPEAKER_0:  Waste assets question I'm sure Alaska about.
SPEAKER_0:  habitable worlds.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's just go to our own solar system. What can we learn about?
SPEAKER_0:  The planets and moons.
SPEAKER_0:  in our solar system that.
SPEAKER_0:  might contain life.
SPEAKER_0:  whether it's Mars or some of them.
SPEAKER_0:  Moons of Jupiter.
SPEAKER_0:  and Saturn.
SPEAKER_0:  What kind of characteristics? Because you said it might not need to be Earth-like. What kind of characteristics might be?
SPEAKER_0:  we'd be looking for.
SPEAKER_1:  when we look for life.
SPEAKER_1:  It's hard to define even what life is.
SPEAKER_1:  but we can maybe do a better job in defining the sorts of things that life does.
SPEAKER_1:  And that provides some aspects to some avenue for looking for them.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  any
SPEAKER_1:  Classically, conventionally, I think we thought the way to look for life was to look for oxygen.
SPEAKER_1:  Oxygen is a byproduct of its synthesis on this planet.
SPEAKER_1:  We didn't always have it. Certainly if you go back to the Icaean period.
SPEAKER_1:  You have this period called the Great Oxidation Event where the Earth floats with oxygen for the first time and so that's to saturate the oceans and then the atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  that oxygen if we detect it on another planet whether it be
SPEAKER_1:  Mars, Venus or an exoplanet, whatever it is.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  that was long thought to be evidence for something doing fetch synthesis.
SPEAKER_1:  because if you took away all the plant life on the earth...
SPEAKER_1:  The oxygen, one just hang around here, there's a highly reactive molecule.
SPEAKER_1:  it would oxidize things and so within about a million years you would probably lose all the oxygen on planet Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  So that was a...
SPEAKER_1:  conventionally how we thought we could look for life.
SPEAKER_1:  And then we start to realize that it's not so simple because A, there might be other things that life does apart from fetch synthesis.
SPEAKER_1:  Certainly the vast majority of the Earth's history had no oxygen, and yet there was living things on it, so that doesn't seem like a complete test.
SPEAKER_1:  And secondly,
SPEAKER_1:  Could there be other things that produce oxygen besides from life?
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  a growing concern has been.
SPEAKER_1:  these false positives in biosignature work. And so one example of that would be phtholysis that happens in the atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  when ultraviolet write.
SPEAKER_1:  hits the upper atmosphere, can break up water vapour.
SPEAKER_1:  the hydrogen spits off to the oxygen.
SPEAKER_1:  The hydrogen is a much lighter atomic species and so it can actually escape certainly planets like the Earth's gravity
SPEAKER_1:  That's why we don't have any hydrogen or very little helium.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  that leaves you with the oxygen, which then oxidizes the surface. And so there could be a residual oxygen signature just due to this photolysis process.
SPEAKER_1:  So we've been trying to generalize.
SPEAKER_1:  And, um...
SPEAKER_1:  Certainly in recent years there have been other suggestions of things we could look for in the solar system and beyond.
SPEAKER_1:  nitrous oxide.
SPEAKER_1:  Basically, laughing gas is a product of microbes.
SPEAKER_1:  That's something that we're starting to get more interested in looking for. Methane gas in combination.
SPEAKER_1:  with other gases can be an important biosignature.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, phosphine.
SPEAKER_1:  well and phosphine is particularly relevant to the solar system because there was a lot of interest for venus recently
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  may have heard that there was a claim of.
SPEAKER_1:  a biosignature in Venus's atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it was like two years ago now.
SPEAKER_1:  And the judge and jury are still out on that.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  There was a...
SPEAKER_1:  Very provocative.
SPEAKER_1:  claim and signature of a phosphine-like spectral absorption.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  but it could have also have been some of the molecule in particular, sulfur dioxide.
SPEAKER_1:  which is not a biosignature.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is a detection of a gas in the atmosphere.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, Venus.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  It might be controversial, so...
SPEAKER_0:  dimensions so
SPEAKER_0:  One, how to interpret that.
SPEAKER_0:  Two, is this the right gas? And three, is this even the right detection? Is there an error in the detection?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean, how much do we believe the detection in the first place?
SPEAKER_1:  If you do believe it.
SPEAKER_1:  does that necessarily mean there's life there?
SPEAKER_1:  And what gives, how can you have life in the Venus's atmosphere in the first place? Because that's-
SPEAKER_1:  You know, been seen as like a hellhole place for imagining life. But I guess the counter to that has been that, okay, yes, the surface is.
SPEAKER_1:  a horrendous place to imagine life thriving.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  But as you go up in altitude.
SPEAKER_1:  The very dense atmosphere means that there is a cloud layer.
SPEAKER_1:  where the temperature.
SPEAKER_1:  and the pressure become actually fairly similar to the surface of the Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  And so it may be there are microbes stirring around in the clouds which are producing phosphine.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  At the moment, this is.
SPEAKER_1:  Fascinating, it's got a lot of us.
SPEAKER_1:  reinvigorated about the prospects of
SPEAKER_1:  going back to Venus and doing another mission there. In fact, there's now...
SPEAKER_1:  Two NASA missions, very task.
SPEAKER_1:  and DaVinci, which are going to be going back and before 2030, the 2030s.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  And then we have a European mission I think that's slated now and even a Chinese mission.
SPEAKER_1:  might be coming along the way as well. So we might have multiple missions going to Venus, which has
SPEAKER_1:  long been overlooked. I mean, apart from the Soviets, there really has been very little in the way of exploration of Venus. Certainly as compared to Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  Mars has enjoyed most of the activity from NASA's.
SPEAKER_1:  rovers and surveys.
SPEAKER_1:  Mars is certainly fascinating. There's this signature of methane that has been seen there before.
SPEAKER_1:  time.
SPEAKER_1:  Again, there the discussion is whether that methane is a product of biology, which
SPEAKER_1:  is possible, something that happens on the Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  or whether it's some geological process that...
SPEAKER_1:  We are.
SPEAKER_1:  yet to fully understand could be, for example, a reservoir of methane that's trapped under the surface and is leaking out seasonally.
SPEAKER_0:  So the nice thing about Venus is if there's...
SPEAKER_0:  a giant living civilization there, it'll be.
SPEAKER_0:  airborne so you can just fly through.
SPEAKER_0:  and collect samples with Mars and.
SPEAKER_0:  moons of
SPEAKER_0:  Saturn and Jupiter you're gonna have to dig it
SPEAKER_0:  dig under to find the civilizations, dead or living.
SPEAKER_1:  Right. And so yeah, maybe it's easier than for Venus because certainly you can imagine just a balloon floating through the atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  or a drone or something that would have the capability of just scooping up and sampling
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  To dig into the surface of Mars is maybe...
SPEAKER_1:  feasible-ish with, you know, especially with something like Starship that could
SPEAKER_1:  launch a huge digger basically to the surface and you could just excavate away at the surface.
SPEAKER_1:  but for something like Europa
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  We really are still.
SPEAKER_1:  unclear about how thick the ice layer is.
SPEAKER_1:  how you would melt through that huge thick layer to get to the ocean.
SPEAKER_1:  and then potentially also discussions about contamination.
SPEAKER_1:  The problem with looking for life in the solar system, which is different from looking for life with exoplanets.
SPEAKER_1:  is that you always run the risk of.
SPEAKER_1:  especially if you visit there, of introducing the life yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  It's very difficult to completely exterminate.
SPEAKER_1:  every single microbe and spore on the surface.
SPEAKER_1:  of your rover or the surface of your lander.
SPEAKER_1:  And so there's always a risk of introducing something. I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  To some extent, there is continuous exchange of material between these planets naturally on top of that as well. And now we're sort of accelerating that process to some degree.
SPEAKER_1:  And so if you.
SPEAKER_1:  dig into Europa's surface, which probably is completely pristine, it's very unlikely there has been much exchange with the outside world.
SPEAKER_1:  for its subsurface ocean.
SPEAKER_1:  You are for the first time.
SPEAKER_1:  potentially introducing.
SPEAKER_1:  bacteria spores into that environment that
SPEAKER_1:  may compete or may introduce spurious signatures for the life you're looking for.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  It's almost an ethical question as to how to proceed with.
SPEAKER_1:  looking for life on those subsurface oceans.
SPEAKER_1:  And I don't think one, we've really.
SPEAKER_1:  have a good resolution for this. dialed up
SPEAKER_0:  So you mean ethical in terms of concern.
SPEAKER_0:  for the...
SPEAKER_0:  like for preserving life elsewhere, not to murder it as opposed to scientific.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, we always worry about a space virus, right? Coming here or some kind of external source. And we would be the source of that.
SPEAKER_1:  potential contamination or the other direction.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah
SPEAKER_0:  I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  They.
SPEAKER_0:  that whatever survives in such harsh conditions.
SPEAKER_0:  I'd be pretty good at.
SPEAKER_0:  surviving in all conditions. It might be a little bit more resilient and robust, so I might actually.
SPEAKER_0:  Take a ride on us.
SPEAKER_0:  back home.
SPEAKER_1:  Possibly, I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm sure that some people would be concerned about that. I think-
SPEAKER_1:  We would hopefully have some containment procedures if we did sample return. Or you mean you don't even really need a sample return. These days you can-
SPEAKER_1:  pretty much sounded like a little micro laboratory.
SPEAKER_1:  to the planet to do all the experiments in situ and then just send them back to your planet.
SPEAKER_1:  the data.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I don't think this is necessary, especially for a case like that where you might have contamination concerns that you have to bring samples back.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Although probably if you brought back Europe and sushi, it would probably sell for quite a bit with the billionaires in New York City. Sushi. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  I would love from an engineering perspective just to...
SPEAKER_0:  see all the different candidates and designs for like the scooper for Venus and the scooper for
SPEAKER_0:  Europa in
SPEAKER_0:  and Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  I haven't really looked deeply into how they actually, like the actual engineering of collecting the samples because
SPEAKER_0:  That's the engineering of that.
SPEAKER_0:  is probably essential for not either destroying life or
SPEAKER_0:  or polluting it with our own microbes and so on.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's an interesting engineering challenge. I usually for rovers and stuff focus on the robot on the
SPEAKER_0:  sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  mobility aspect of it on the robotics, the perception.
SPEAKER_0:  and the movement and the planning and the control.
SPEAKER_0:  There's probably the scooper is probably where the action is. Yeah. The microscopic.
SPEAKER_0:  Sample Collection.
SPEAKER_0:  So basically you have to first clean.
SPEAKER_0:  your vehicle. Make sure it doesn't have any earth-like things on it.
SPEAKER_0:  And then...
SPEAKER_0:  You have to put it into some kind of thing that's perfectly sealed from the environment so if we bring it back or we analyze it it's not
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  It's not going to bring anything else externally. Yeah, I don't know. It would be that be an interesting engineering design there.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean, Kirstie has been...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  leaving these little.
SPEAKER_1:  pods on the surface quite recently.
SPEAKER_1:  Neat photos you can find online.
SPEAKER_1:  and they kind of look like lightsaber hilts.
SPEAKER_1: ...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, to me, I think I tweeted something like, you know, this weapon is your life. Like don't lose your curiosity because it's just dumping these little vials everywhere.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's, yeah, it is scooping up these things and the intention is that in the future.
SPEAKER_1:  there will be a sample return mission that will come and pick these up.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, the engineering behind those things is so impressive. The thing that blows me away the most has been the landings.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Especially I'm trying to be a pilot at the moment. So that's the sort of, you know, watching landings has become like my pet hobby on YouTube at the moment.
SPEAKER_1:  how not to do it, how to do it with different levels of.
SPEAKER_1:  conditions and things.
SPEAKER_1:  with the, you know, when you.
SPEAKER_1:  Think about landing on Mars, just the light travel time effect means that there's no
SPEAKER_1:  possibility of a human controlling that descent. And so you have to put all of your faith.
SPEAKER_1:  and your trust in the.
SPEAKER_1:  computer code or the AI or whatever it is that you've put on board that thing to make the correct descent.
SPEAKER_1:  And so there's this famous.
SPEAKER_1:  period called seven minutes of hell where you're basically waiting for that light travel time to come back to know whether your vehicle successfully landed on the surface of nought.
SPEAKER_1:  And during that period...
SPEAKER_1:  You know in your mind simultaneously that it is doing these multi-stages of
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  deploying its parachute, deploying the crane.
SPEAKER_1:  activating its jets to come down and controlling its descent to the surface.
SPEAKER_1:  And then the crane has to fly away so it doesn't accidentally hit the rover.
SPEAKER_1:  And so there's a series of multi-stage points where any of them go wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, the whole mission could, could go awry.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, and so the fact that
SPEAKER_1:  We.
SPEAKER_1:  are fairly consistently able to
SPEAKER_1:  build these machines that can do this autonomously.
SPEAKER_1:  is to me.
SPEAKER_1:  one of the most impressive acts of engineering that NASA have achieved.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, the unfortunate fact about physics is the takeoff is easier than the landing. Yes, yes, and you mentioned Starship one of the.
SPEAKER_0:  incredible engineering feats that you get to see as the reusable rockets that take off, they land and they land.
SPEAKER_0:  using control and they do so perfectly. And sometimes when it's synchronous, it's just, it's beautiful to see. And then with Starship, you see the chopsticks that catch the ship. I mean, there's just so much incredible engineer, but you mentioned.
SPEAKER_0:  Starships is somehow helpful here. So what's your hope with Starship?
SPEAKER_0:  what kind of science might enable.
SPEAKER_1:  Possibly
SPEAKER_1:  There's two things. I mean, it's the launch cost itself, which is hopefully going to mean per kilogram. It's going to dramatically reduce the cost of it. It's the sort of the level, even if it's a factor of 10 higher than what Elon originally.
SPEAKER_1:  I promise this is going to be a revolution for the Costa launch.
SPEAKER_1:  That means you could do all sorts of things. You could launch.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  large telescopes which could be...
SPEAKER_1:  Basically like JWST, but you don't even have to fold them up. JWST had this whole...
SPEAKER_1:  issue with its design that
SPEAKER_1:  it's six and a half meters across. And so you have to, there's no fuselage, which is that large at the time. There is four wasn't large enough for that.
SPEAKER_1:  And so they had to fold it up in this kind of complicated origami.
SPEAKER_1:  And so a large part of the cost was.
SPEAKER_1:  figuring out how to fold it up, testing that it unfolded correctly, repeated testing and you know, there was something like 130 fail points or something during this unfolding mechanism.
SPEAKER_1:  And so all of us were holding our breath during that process.
SPEAKER_1:  But if you have the ability to just launch arbitrarily large masses.
SPEAKER_1:  at least comparatively compared to JVST.
SPEAKER_1:  and very large mirrors into space.
SPEAKER_1:  you can more or less repurpose ground-based mirrors.
SPEAKER_1:  The Hubble Space Telescope mirror and the JVST mirrors are designed to be
SPEAKER_1:  extremely lightweight.
SPEAKER_1:  and that increased their cost significantly.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, they have this kind of honeycomb design on the back to try and minimize the weight.
SPEAKER_1:  If you...
SPEAKER_1:  really care about weight because it's so cheap, then you could just literally grab many of the existing ground-based mirrors across task as across the world, four meter, five meter mirrors
SPEAKER_1:  and just pretty much attach them to a chassis and have your own space-based telescope.
SPEAKER_1:  I think the Breakthrough Foundation, for instance, is an entity that
SPEAKER_1:  has been interested in doing this sort of thing.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  That raises the prospects of having not just one WST that just, you know, WST is a fantastic resource but it's split between all of us.
SPEAKER_1:  cosmologists.
SPEAKER_1:  star formation, astronomers.
SPEAKER_1:  those of us studying exoplanets, those of us wanting to study the ultra deep fields and the origin of the first galaxies, the expansionary of the universe, everyone has to share this resource.
SPEAKER_1:  but
SPEAKER_1:  we could potentially each have one.
SPEAKER_1:  JDST each that is maybe just studying a handful of the brightest exoplanet stars.
SPEAKER_1:  and measuring their atmospheres.
SPEAKER_1:  This is important because if you.
SPEAKER_1:  We talked about this planet Trappist-1e earlier.
SPEAKER_1:  that planet.
SPEAKER_1:  If JDBC started it and tried to look for biosignatures, by which I mean, Oxygen.
SPEAKER_1:  nitrous oxide, methane.
SPEAKER_1:  It would take it of order of 200.
SPEAKER_1:  transits.
SPEAKER_1:  to get even.
SPEAKER_1:  very marginal, what we would call 2.5 sigma detection.
SPEAKER_1:  of those, which basically nobody would believe with that.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  A hundred transits, I mean, this thing transits once every six days. So you're talking about sort of four years of staring at the same star.
SPEAKER_1:  with one telescope. The Bees am.
SPEAKER_1:  breaks, but it'd be hard to schedule much else because you'll have to continuously catch each one of these transits to build up your signal to noise.
SPEAKER_1:  And so, J2ST is never gonna do that. In principle, technically, J2ST could technically have the capability of just about detecting a biosignature.
SPEAKER_1:  on an Earth-like planet around a non-sun-like star.
SPEAKER_1:  But still, impressively, we have basically the technology to do that.
SPEAKER_1:  but we simply cannot dedicate all of its time practically.
SPEAKER_1:  that one resource. And so Starship opens up opportunities like that of mass producing.
SPEAKER_1:  these kinds of telescopes.
SPEAKER_1:  which will allow us to survey.
SPEAKER_1:  life in the universe which of course is one of the grand goals of astronomy.
SPEAKER_0:  I wonder if you can speak to the.
SPEAKER_0:  the bureaucracy, the political battles, the scientific battles for time on the James Webb telescope.
SPEAKER_0:  Listen, there must be a fascinating.
SPEAKER_0:  process of scheduling that.
SPEAKER_0:  All scientists are trying to collaborate and figure out what the most important problems are.
SPEAKER_0:  and there's an interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  network.
SPEAKER_0:  of interfering scientific experiments probably somehow
SPEAKER_1:  over.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a really difficult process. I don't.
SPEAKER_1:  envy the TAC that are going to have to make this decision. We call it the TAC, the Time Allocation Committee.
SPEAKER_1:  that make this decision.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, and I've served on these before and it's very difficult. I mean, typically for hubble, we were seeing at least 10, sometimes 20 times the number of
SPEAKER_1:  Proposals for telescope time versus available telescope time.
SPEAKER_1:  For GDustT,
SPEAKER_1:  There has been one call already that has gone out.
SPEAKER_1:  We call it cycle one.
SPEAKER_1:  And that was oversubscribed by, I think something like six to one, seven to one.
SPEAKER_1:  and the cycle two, which has just been announced fairly recently and the deadline is actually the end of this month, so my team.
SPEAKER_1:  totally laser focused on writing our proposals right now.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  That is expected to be much more competitive, probably more comparable to what Hub of Saw.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  It's hard. It's hard.
SPEAKER_0:  than the second one you said already
SPEAKER_1:  Because that's already more competitive than the first cycle. So I said the first cycle of James Webb was about six to one. Um, and this will probably be more like.
SPEAKER_1:  20 to 1. I would expect.
SPEAKER_0:  proposals by sadists and so on and it's not like...
SPEAKER_0:  You can schedule at any time because if you're looking for transit times. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  You have, you have a time critical element. Yes. Time critical element.
SPEAKER_0:  And they're conflicting and non like not obvious ways because the frequency is different. The duration is different. Right. There's a cut. It's probably computational needs that are different.
SPEAKER_0:  the type of sensors, the direction.
SPEAKER_1:  pointing all that.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's hard and...
SPEAKER_1:  There are certain programs like doing a deep field.
SPEAKER_1:  study where you just more or less point the telescope.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's pretty open. I mean, you're just accumulating photons. You can just point at that patch of the sky.
SPEAKER_1:  whenever the telescope is not doing anything else and just get to your month, let's say a month of integration time is your goal over the lifetime of JVST. So that's maybe a little bit easier to schedule. It's harder, especially for us looking at cool worlds.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, because as I said earlier, these
SPEAKER_1:  plants transit very infrequently.
SPEAKER_1:  So we have to wait if you're looking at the Earth transiting the Sun and alien watching us.
SPEAKER_1:  they would only get one opportunity per year to do that observation.
SPEAKER_1:  the transit lasts for about 12 hours.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  And so if they don't...
SPEAKER_1:  Get that time.
SPEAKER_1:  It's hard. That's it.
SPEAKER_1:  if it conflicted with another proposal that wants to use another time critical element.
SPEAKER_1:  It's much easier for plants like these hot plants for these close-in plants.
SPEAKER_1:  because they transit so frequently.
SPEAKER_1:  there's maybe a hundred opportunities. And so then the tap can say.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay they want 10 transits, there's 100.
SPEAKER_1:  opportunities here.
SPEAKER_1:  It's easier for us to give us time.
SPEAKER_1:  to give them time.
SPEAKER_1:  We're almost in the worst case scenario. We're proposing to look for X and means around to
SPEAKER_1:  cool planets.
SPEAKER_1:  And so we really only have.
SPEAKER_1:  one bite of the cherry.
SPEAKER_1:  for each one.
SPEAKER_1:  And so our sales pitch has been that these are extremely precious events.
SPEAKER_1:  End.
SPEAKER_1:  more importantly, JWST.
SPEAKER_1:  is the only telescope, the only machine humanity has ever constructed.
SPEAKER_1:  which is capable of finding moons.
SPEAKER_1:  akin to the Moon's night solar system.
SPEAKER_1:  Capper can't do it, even Hubble can't do it.
SPEAKER_1:  Genesys the first one.
SPEAKER_1:  And so there is a new window to the universe because we know these moons exist. They're all over the place in the solar system. You have the moon, you have...
SPEAKER_1:  Io, Callisto, Europa, Ganymede, Titan, lots of moons are fairly similar size, sort of 30% the size of the Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  This telescope is the first one that can find them.
SPEAKER_1:  And so we're very excited about the profound implications of
SPEAKER_1:  Ultimately solving this journey we're on in astronomy, which is to understand our uniqueness. We want to understand how common is the solar system. Are we?
SPEAKER_1:  the way, are we the architecture that frequently
SPEAKER_1:  emerges naturally.
SPEAKER_1:  Or is there something special about what happened here?
SPEAKER_0:  I think this is not the worst case, the best case. It's obvious. It's super rare. So you have to like, I would, so I'm, I love scheduling from a computer science perspective, that's my background.
SPEAKER_0:  So algorithmically, to solve a schedule problem, I'll schedule the rarest things first.
SPEAKER_0:  And obviously this is the, the JLST is the first thing that can actually detect a cool world.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is a big new thing. You can show off that new thing. Happens rarely.
SPEAKER_0:  Schedule it first. Schedule it first.
SPEAKER_1:  You should be in the tack. This is perfect. You should be in the tack.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll file my application after we're done with this. I, you know, this part of me is the OCD, part of me is the computational aspect. I love scheduling.
SPEAKER_0:  a computing device because you have that kind of scheduling.
SPEAKER_0:  on supercomputers, on...
SPEAKER_0:  That scheduling problem is fascinating, how you prioritize.
SPEAKER_0:  computational high-duty prioritized science.
SPEAKER_0:  data collection.
SPEAKER_0:  Sample collection all that kind of stuff. It's actually kind of
SPEAKER_0:  kind of fascinating because data.
SPEAKER_0:  in ways you expect and don't expect will unlock a lot of.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  some fascinating mysteries. And so collecting the data and doing so.
SPEAKER_0:  in a way that maximizes the possibility of discovery is really interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  like from a computational perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  I agree. There's a real satisfaction in extracting the maximum science per unit time out of your telescope. That's the tax job.
SPEAKER_1:  The, the tack are not.
SPEAKER_1:  machines, they're not a piece of computer code. They will make their selections based off human judgment.
SPEAKER_1:  and um
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of the telescope is certainly within the field of exoplanets because it's different fields of astronomy but within the field of exoplanets.
SPEAKER_1:  I think a good expectation is that most of the telescope time...
SPEAKER_1:  that James was he have.
SPEAKER_1:  will go towards atmospheric retrieval.
SPEAKER_1:  which is sort of alluded to earlier, you know, like detecting molecules in the atmospheres.
SPEAKER_1:  Not.
SPEAKER_1:  biosignatures because as I said, it's really not designed to do that. It's pushing GDST probably too far to expect to do that.
SPEAKER_1:  but it could detect, for example,
SPEAKER_1:  a carbon dioxide rich atmosphere on TRAPPIST-1e. That's not a bias signature.
SPEAKER_1:  But you could prove it's like a Venus in that case, or maybe like a Mars in that case. Both those have carbon dioxide rich atmospheres.
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't.
SPEAKER_1:  or disprove the existence of life. Either way...
SPEAKER_1:  but it is our first characterization of the nature.
SPEAKER_1:  of those atmospheres. Maybe we can even tell the pressure level of the temperature of those atmospheres.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's very exciting.
SPEAKER_1:  But um
SPEAKER_1:  There's, we are competing with that. And that, I think that science is completely mind blowing and fantastic. We have a completely different objective, which is in our case, to try and look for the first evidence of these small moons around these planets.
SPEAKER_1:  potentially even moons, which could be habitable, of course.
SPEAKER_1:  very exciting goal.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Attack has to make a human judgement.
SPEAKER_1:  essentially about which science are they most.
SPEAKER_1:  excited by.
SPEAKER_1:  which one has the highest promise of return.
SPEAKER_1:  the most highest chance of return. And so that's hard because if you look at a
SPEAKER_1:  a planetary atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, you know, most of the time the plant has an atmosphere already.
SPEAKER_1:  And so there's almost a guaranteed success that you're going to learn something about the atmosphere by pointing to the UST at it
SPEAKER_1:  Whereas...
SPEAKER_1:  In that case, there's a harder sell.
SPEAKER_1:  We are looking for something that we...
SPEAKER_1:  do not know for sure exists yet or not.
SPEAKER_1:  And so we are.
SPEAKER_1:  pushing the telescope to do something which is inherently more risky.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, but...
SPEAKER_0:  The existence is shown.
SPEAKER_0:  already gives a deep.
SPEAKER_0:  lesson.
SPEAKER_0:  about what's out there in the universe. That means that other stars have similar types of variety as we have in our solar system.
SPEAKER_0:  They have an eye or they have a...
SPEAKER_0:  Europa and so on.
SPEAKER_0:  which means like there's a lot of possibility.
SPEAKER_0:  for icy planets, for water.
SPEAKER_0:  for planets and moons. I mean, that's super exciting.
SPEAKER_0:  because that means.
SPEAKER_0:  everywhere through our galaxy and beyond.
SPEAKER_0:  There is.
SPEAKER_0:  Just.
SPEAKER_0:  innumerable possibility for weird creatures.
SPEAKER_1:  I agree. You don't have to convince me. I mean NASA has been on this quest.
SPEAKER_1:  for a long time.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's sometimes called Eater Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  It's the frequency of Earth-like.
SPEAKER_1:  Usually they say planets.
SPEAKER_1:  in the universe. How common.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah.
SPEAKER_1:  similar to our Earth in terms of
SPEAKER_1:  Ultimately, we'd like to know everything about these plants in terms of the amount of water they have, how much atmosphere they have, but for now it's kind of focused just on the size.
SPEAKER_1:  and the distance from the star essentially. How often do you get similar conditions to that?
SPEAKER_1:  That was Kepler's primary mission and it-
SPEAKER_1:  really just kind of flirted with the answer, didn't quite get to a definitive answer.
SPEAKER_1:  But I would say, look, if that's our primary goal.
SPEAKER_1:  to look for.
SPEAKER_1:  Earth-like.
SPEAKER_1:  I would say worlds.
SPEAKER_1:  then Moons has to be a part of that.
SPEAKER_1:  because we know that.
SPEAKER_1:  Earth-like from the capital day to the preliminary result is that Earth-like planets around sun-like stars is not
SPEAKER_1:  inevitable outcome. It seems to be something like a one to 10% outcome.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's not.
SPEAKER_1:  particularly inevitable that happens.
SPEAKER_1:  But we do often see about half of all Sunlight stars
SPEAKER_1:  have either a mini Neptune, a Neptune or a Jupiter in the habitable zone of their stars.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a very, very common occurrence that we see.
SPEAKER_1:  yet we have no idea how often they have moons around them.
SPEAKER_1:  which could also be habitable.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  that may very well be.
SPEAKER_1:  If even...
SPEAKER_1:  One in five of them.
SPEAKER_1:  has.
SPEAKER_1:  an Earth-like moon or even a Mars-like moon around them.
SPEAKER_1:  then there would be more habitable real estate in terms of exomoons.
SPEAKER_1:  The next hope that's in the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  Essentially...
SPEAKER_0:  2X, 3X, 5X, maybe 10X, the number of habitable worlds out there in the universe. Our current estimate.
SPEAKER_0:  Like the Drake equation. Absolutely. Yeah. This is a one way to increase the confidence.
SPEAKER_0:  and increase the value of that parameter.
SPEAKER_1:  And just know where to look. I mean, we-
SPEAKER_1:  We would like to know where should we listen for techno signatures? Where should we be looking for biosignatures?
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  And not only that, but what role does the-
SPEAKER_1:  does the moon have in terms of its influence on the planet?
SPEAKER_1:  We talked about these directly imaged telescopes earlier, these missions that want to take a photo.
SPEAKER_1:  quote Carl Sagan the pale blue dot of our planet but the pale blue dot of an exoplanet
SPEAKER_1:  And that's the dream to one day capture that.
SPEAKER_1:  But as impressive as the resolution is that we are
SPEAKER_1:  planning and conspiring to design for the future generation of telescopes to achieve that.
SPEAKER_1:  Even those telescopes.
SPEAKER_1:  will not have the capability of resolving the Earth and the Moon within that. It'll be a pale blue dot pixel.
SPEAKER_1:  but the moon's gray, grayness will be intermixed.
SPEAKER_1:  with that pixel.
SPEAKER_1:  And so this is a big problem because one of the ways that we are claiming to look for life in the universe
SPEAKER_1:  is a chemical DC equilibrium.
SPEAKER_1:  So you see two molecules that just shouldn't be there. They normally react with each other.
SPEAKER_1:  or even one molecule that's just too reactive to be hanging around the atmosphere by itself.
SPEAKER_1:  So if you had.
SPEAKER_1:  oxygen and methane hanging out together.
SPEAKER_1:  those would normally react fairly easily.
SPEAKER_1:  And so if you detected those two molecules in your pale blue dot spectra,
SPEAKER_1:  But okay, we have evidence for life. Something's metabolizing on this planet.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  However, the challenge is what if that moon was Titan?
SPEAKER_1:  Titan has a methane rich atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  And what if the pale blue dot?
SPEAKER_1:  was in fact a plant devoid of life.
SPEAKER_1:  but it had oxygen.
SPEAKER_1:  because of water.
SPEAKER_1:  undergoing this photolysis reaction splitting into oxygen hydrogen separately
SPEAKER_1:  So then you have all of the...
SPEAKER_1:  hallmarks of what we would claim to be life.
SPEAKER_1:  Through it all you attract.
SPEAKER_1:  It was just a moon that was deceiving you.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  We are never going to, we never going to, I would claim really understand.
SPEAKER_1:  THE END
SPEAKER_1:  or complete this quest of looking for life by signatures in the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  Unless we...
SPEAKER_1:  have a deep knowledge of the prevalence and role that moons have.
SPEAKER_1:  They may even affect the habitability of the planets themselves, because I rain moon.
SPEAKER_1:  Frequently large.
SPEAKER_1:  By mass ratio, it's the largest moon in the solar system. It's a 1% mass moon.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like at Jupiter's moons I like 10 to the power of minus 4, much smaller.
SPEAKER_1:  So our own moon seems to stabilize the obliquity of our planet.
SPEAKER_1:  It gives rise to tides.
SPEAKER_1:  Especially early on when the moon was closer those ties would have covered entire continents.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's those.
SPEAKER_1:  rock pools that would have been scattered across the entire plateau may have been the origin of life on our planet.
SPEAKER_1:  the moon forming impact may have stripped a significant fraction lithosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  of the Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  which without a plate tectonics may not have been possible. It would have had a stagnant lid.
SPEAKER_1:  because there was just too much lithosphere stuck on the top of the planet.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  There are-
SPEAKER_1:  speculative reasons, but intriguing reasons as to why
SPEAKER_1:  A large moon?
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe.
SPEAKER_1:  Not just important, but central to the question of having the conditions necessary.
SPEAKER_1:  for life. So.
SPEAKER_1:  Moons can be habitable in their own right?
SPEAKER_1:  but they can also...
SPEAKER_1:  play significant influence.
SPEAKER_1:  on the habitability of the planets they orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  And further.
SPEAKER_1:  They will.
SPEAKER_1:  surely interfere with our attempts to detect life.
SPEAKER_1:  remotely from afar.
SPEAKER_0:  So taking a tangent upon a tangent, you've written about binary planets.
SPEAKER_0:  What's...
SPEAKER_0:  and that they're surprisingly common.
SPEAKER_0:  or they might be surprisingly common.
SPEAKER_0:  What's the difference between a large moon and binary planets? What are binary planets?
SPEAKER_0:  What's interesting to say here about giant rocks flying to space and orbiting each other.
SPEAKER_1:  The thing that's interesting about binary...
SPEAKER_1:  Objects is that they're very common in the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  Binary stars are everywhere.
SPEAKER_1:  the majority of stars seem to live in binary systems.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  When we look at the outer edges of the solar system, we see binary Kuiper belt objects all the time, asteroids basically bound to one another.
SPEAKER_1:  Pluto-Sharon is kind of an example of that. It's a 10% mass ratio system.
SPEAKER_1:  It almost is by many definitions a binary planet, but now it's a...
SPEAKER_1:  Dwarf Pirates so.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. I don't know when you call that now.
SPEAKER_1:  But we know that the universe likes to make things in pairs.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So you're saying our son.
SPEAKER_0:  is an in cell.
SPEAKER_0:  It's looking. So most things are dating, they're in relationships and ours is alone.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not a complete-
SPEAKER_1:  Freak of the universe to be alone, but it is.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  It's more common for Sun-like stars. If you count up all the Sun-like stars in the universe, about half of the Sun-like star systems are in binary or trinary systems.
SPEAKER_1:  and the other half a single.
SPEAKER_1:  But because those binaries are two or three stars...
SPEAKER_1:  then cumulatively.
SPEAKER_1:  maybe like a third of all Sunlight Stars are single. I'm trying hard.
SPEAKER_0:  to not anthropomorphize the relationship.
SPEAKER_1:  start off with each other. Yeah. The triplets. The triplets. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I've met those folks also.
SPEAKER_0:  So is there something interesting to learn about the habitability, the how that affects the probability of.
SPEAKER_0:  habitable worlds.
SPEAKER_0:  when they kind of couple up like that in those different ways
SPEAKER_1:  It depends what we're talking about the stars and planets. Sunny.
SPEAKER_1:  If stars couple up, that has a big influence on the habitability.
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  Of course, this is very famous from Star Wars, Tatooine in Star Wars is a binary star system and you have Luke Skywalker looking at the sunset and seeing two stars come down.
SPEAKER_1:  And for years we thought that was.
SPEAKER_1:  purely a product of George Lucas's incredibly creative mind.
SPEAKER_1:  and we
SPEAKER_1:  didn't think that planets would exist around binary star systems. It seems like too tumultuous an environment.
SPEAKER_1:  for.
SPEAKER_1:  a quiescent planetary disk, circumstellar disk, to form planets.
SPEAKER_1:  from.
SPEAKER_1:  And yet...
SPEAKER_1:  One of the.
SPEAKER_1:  astounding discoveries from Kepler.
SPEAKER_1:  was that these appear to be quite common.
SPEAKER_1:  In fact, as far as we can tell, they're just as common around binary stars as singular stars.
SPEAKER_1:  The only caveat to that is that you don't get plants close into binary stars.
SPEAKER_1:  they have like a clearance region in on the inside.
SPEAKER_1:  Webhaz.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe they form there, but they don't last.
SPEAKER_1:  they are dynamically unstable.
SPEAKER_1:  in that zone.
SPEAKER_1:  But once you get out to about the distance that the Earth orbits the sun, we're even a little bit closer in.
SPEAKER_1:  you start to find planets emerging.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that's the right distance for liquid water, that's the right distance for potentially life on those parts.
SPEAKER_1:  And so there may very well be plenty of habitable planets around the binary stars.
SPEAKER_1:  Binary planets is a little bit different. Binary planets, I don't think we have, um,
SPEAKER_1:  any serious connection?
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  to client banarity to habitability.
SPEAKER_1:  Certainly when we investigated it, that wasn't our drive, that this is somehow the solution to life in the universe or anything.
SPEAKER_1:  It was really just a, like all good science questions, a curiosity driven.
SPEAKER_1:  question.
SPEAKER_0:  What's the dynamic? Are they legit orbiting each other?
SPEAKER_0:  as they orbit the...
SPEAKER_1:  the star. So the formation mechanism proposed here.
SPEAKER_1:  because it is very difficult to form.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  protoplanets close to each other like this. They would generally merge within the disk, and so that's why you normally get single planets.
SPEAKER_1:  But you could have something like Jupiter and Saturn form at separate distances.
SPEAKER_1:  they could dynamically be scattered in towards one another.
SPEAKER_1:  and basically not quite collide, but have a very close on encounter.
SPEAKER_1:  Now because uh...
SPEAKER_1:  the tidal forces increase dramatically.
SPEAKER_1:  as the distance decreases between two objects.
SPEAKER_1:  the tides can actually dissipate the kinetic energy.
SPEAKER_1:  and bring them bound into one another.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  That seems...
SPEAKER_1:  When you first hear that, you think, well, that seems fairly contrived that you'd have the conditions just right to get these ties to cause a capture.
SPEAKER_1:  Numerical simulations have shown that about 10% of planet-planet encounters
SPEAKER_1:  are shown to produce something like binoplanets, which is a startling prediction.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  And so that seems at odds with naively the exoplanet catalog for which we know of.
SPEAKER_1:  So far, no binoplasts.
SPEAKER_1:  And we propose one of the resolutions to this might be that the binary planets are just incredibly difficult to detect.
SPEAKER_1:  which is also counterintuitive.
SPEAKER_1:  because
SPEAKER_1:  Remember how they form is through this title mechanism. And so they form extremely close to each other.
SPEAKER_1:  So the distance that Io is away from Jupiter, just a few planetary radii, they're almost touching one another.
SPEAKER_1:  and they're just tightly locked facing each other for eternity.
SPEAKER_1:  And so in that configuration...
SPEAKER_1:  as it transits across the star, it kind of looks like...
SPEAKER_1:  You can't really resolve this two planets. It just looks like one planet to you that's going across the star.
SPEAKER_1:  The temporal resolution of the data is rarely good enough to distinguish that.
SPEAKER_1:  And so you'd see one transit.
SPEAKER_1:  but in fact it's two planets very close together.
SPEAKER_1:  which are transiting at once.
SPEAKER_1:  And so yeah, we wrote a paper just recently where we developed.
SPEAKER_1:  some techniques to try and get around this problem and hopefully provide a tool.
SPEAKER_1:  where we could finally look for these plants.
SPEAKER_0:  of detection of these finds when they're so close.
SPEAKER_1:  our focus was how do you
SPEAKER_1:  How do you get around this merging problem? So be like, welcome to the tyres Molly, so you're getting it.
SPEAKER_1:  whether they're out there or not.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, we don't know. We were planning to do a search for them.
SPEAKER_1:  But it remains an open question. And I think just one of those fun astrophysics curiosities questions, whether
SPEAKER_1:  binary planets exist in the universe. Cause then you know, you have binary earths, you could have binary Neptune, all sorts of wild stuff that
SPEAKER_1:  would you know float the sci-fi imagination
SPEAKER_0:  I wonder what the physics...
SPEAKER_0:  Binary Planet feels like.
SPEAKER_0:  It might be trivial.
SPEAKER_0:  I have to think about that.
SPEAKER_0:  I wonder if there's some interesting dynamics. Make it feel multiple.
SPEAKER_0:  or would gravity feel different at different parts of the surface of the sphere when there's another large sphere?
SPEAKER_1:  That's it. Yeah. I think that the.
SPEAKER_1:  force would be.
SPEAKER_1:  fairly similar because the shape of the object would deform.
SPEAKER_1:  to a flat geopotential, essentially a uniform geopotential, but it would lead to a...
SPEAKER_1:  distorted.
SPEAKER_1:  shape for the two objects. I think they'd become ellipsoids.
SPEAKER_1:  facing one another.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, so it would be pretty wild.
SPEAKER_1:  When you, you know, people like flat earth or spherical earth, you fly from space and you see a football-shaped earth. Yeah. That's your own planet.
SPEAKER_0:  Finally, there's proof and I wonder how difficult it'd be to travel from one to the other.
SPEAKER_0:  because you have to overcome the one.
SPEAKER_0:  No, it might be kind of easy.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean, they're so close to each other that helps and I think the most critical factor would be how massive is the planet?
SPEAKER_1:  That's always, I mean, one of the challenges with escaping paths, there was a fun paper when my colleagues wrote.
SPEAKER_1:  that suggested that super-earth planets may be inescapable. If you're a civilization that were born on a super-earth,
SPEAKER_1:  The surface gravity is so high.
SPEAKER_1:  that the chemical potential energy
SPEAKER_1:  of hydrogen or methane, whatever fuel you're using.
SPEAKER_1:  Simply.
SPEAKER_1:  is at odds with the gravity of the planet itself.
SPEAKER_1:  And so you would, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Current rockets, I'm not sure with the fraction, but maybe like 90% of the rocket is fuel or something by mass. These things would have to be...
SPEAKER_1:  Um, like the size of the, the geezer pyramids of fuel with just a tiny.
SPEAKER_1:  tip on the top in order just to escape that planetary atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  And so it has been argued that if you live on a super earth.
SPEAKER_1:  You may be forced to live there forever. There may be no escape unless you invent a space elevator or something, but then...
SPEAKER_1:  How do we even build the infrastructure and space to do something like that in the absence of...
SPEAKER_1:  successful rocket program.
SPEAKER_1:  And so the more and more we look at our earth and think about
SPEAKER_1:  the sorts of problems we're facing.
SPEAKER_1:  the more you see things about the earth which make it.
SPEAKER_1:  ideally suited in so many regards. It's almost spooky, right? That we...
SPEAKER_1:  not only live on a planet which has the right conditions for life
SPEAKER_1:  for intelligent life, for sustained.
SPEAKER_1:  fossil fuel industry just happens to be in the ground. We have plenty of fossil fuels to get our industrial revolution going.
SPEAKER_1:  but also the chemical energy contained within those fossil fuels.
SPEAKER_1:  and hydrogen and other fuels is sufficient that we have the ability to escape our plant tree.
SPEAKER_1:  atmosphere and plantar gravity.
SPEAKER_1:  to have a space program.
SPEAKER_1:  And we also happen to have a celestial body.
SPEAKER_1:  which is just within reach.
SPEAKER_1:  The Moon.
SPEAKER_1:  which doesn't also necessarily have to be true. Were the moon not there?
SPEAKER_1:  what effect would that have had on a...
SPEAKER_1:  aspirations of a space program.
SPEAKER_1:  In the 1960s, would there have ever been a space race to Mars or to Venus?
SPEAKER_1:  It's a much harder, certainly for a human program, that seems almost impossible with 1960s technology to imagine.
SPEAKER_1:  Have a come to fruition.
SPEAKER_0:  is if somebody constructed a set of.
SPEAKER_0:  challenging obstacles before us.
SPEAKER_0:  challenging problems to solve.
SPEAKER_0:  They're challenging.
SPEAKER_0:  but they're doable.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's a sequence of them.
SPEAKER_0:  Gravity is very difficult to overcome.
SPEAKER_0:  but we have given the size of Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not so bad that we can still actually.
SPEAKER_0:  construct propulsion systems that can escape it.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  And the same with climate change, perhaps. I mean-
SPEAKER_1:  climate change is the next major problem facing our civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  But we know.
SPEAKER_1:  It is technically surmountable.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's a...
SPEAKER_1:  It does seem sometimes like there has been a series of challenges laid out.
SPEAKER_1:  to
SPEAKER_1:  progress towards a mature civilization that can one day.
SPEAKER_1:  perhaps expand to the stars.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm a little more concerned about nuclear weapons, AI and
SPEAKER_0:  uh... uh... natural or artificial pandemics but yes
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, plenty of milestones that we need to cross. And we can argue about the severity of each of them, but there is no doubt that we live in a world that has serious challenges that-
SPEAKER_1:  are pushing our intellects in our will.
SPEAKER_1:  to the limit of.
SPEAKER_1:  whether we're really ready to progress to the next stage of our development.
SPEAKER_0:  So thank you for taking the tangent and there'll be a million more, but can we step back to Kepler?
SPEAKER_0:  1625B.
SPEAKER_0:  What is it? End
SPEAKER_0:  You've talked about this kind of journey, this.
SPEAKER_0:  effort to.
SPEAKER_0:  Discover.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... exo moons
SPEAKER_0:  So moons out there or small.
SPEAKER_0:  cool objects out there.
SPEAKER_0:  Where does that effort stand and what is coupler 1625B?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean, I.
SPEAKER_1:  been searching for maximum means for most of my professional career. And I think.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of my colleagues think I'm...
SPEAKER_1:  kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  it crazy to still be doing it, you know, after.
SPEAKER_1:  After five years of not finding anything, I think most people would probably try doing something else. I even had people say that to me. They said,
SPEAKER_1:  professors and I remember a cocktail party took me to the side, an MIT professor, and he said
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you should just look, look for hot Jupiters. They're everywhere. It's really, you can write PAPUS. That's so easy to find. I was like, yeah, but hot Jupiters just.
SPEAKER_1:  They're not interesting to me. I want to do something that I feel.
SPEAKER_1:  intellectually.
SPEAKER_1:  pushes me to the edge and is maybe a contribution that not no one else could do, but
SPEAKER_1:  maybe a little bit, maybe or maybe a little bit maybe more to add to as a
SPEAKER_1:  is not certainly the thing that anybody could do. I don't wanna just be the first to something for the sake of being first. I wanna do something that feels like meaningful.
SPEAKER_1:  intellectual contribution to our society. And so...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, this exomemon problem has been haunting me for years to try and solve this.
SPEAKER_1:  Now.
SPEAKER_1:  As I said, we looked for years and years using Kepler.
SPEAKER_1:  and the closest we ever got was just a hint.
SPEAKER_1:  for this one star, Kepler-1625, has a Jupiter-like planet in orbit of it.
SPEAKER_1:  and that Jupiter-like planet is on a 287 day period. So it's almost the same distance as the Earth around the Sun.
SPEAKER_1:  but for Jupiter.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  So that was already unusual. I don't think people realize that jupiter-like planets are quite rare in the universe. Certainly many nap tunes and nap tunes are extremely common.
SPEAKER_1:  But Jupiter's only about 10% of Sun-like stars have Jupiters around them as far as we can tell. When you say Jupiter,
SPEAKER_0:  which aspect.
SPEAKER_1:  of Jupiter. So, it's mass.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's a major access. So anything beyond about.
SPEAKER_1:  half an AU, so half the distance of the Earth and the Sun.
SPEAKER_1:  and something of order of a tenth of a Jupiter mass, so that's the mass of Saturn.
SPEAKER_1:  up to say 10 Jupiter masses, which is basically where you start to get to brown dwarfs.
SPEAKER_1:  those types of objects appear to be somewhat unusual. Most solar systems do not have Jupiters, which
SPEAKER_1:  is really interesting because
SPEAKER_1:  Jupiter again, like the moon, seems to have been.
SPEAKER_1:  a pivotal character in the story of the development of our solar system.
SPEAKER_1:  perhaps especially having a large influence on the development of
SPEAKER_1:  the late heavy bombardment and the rate of asteroid impacts that we receive and things like this.
SPEAKER_1:  Anyway, to come back to 1625, this juped-like planet...
SPEAKER_1:  Um, had a hint of, of something in the data. But what I mean by that is when we looked at the transit.
SPEAKER_1:  We got the familiar.
SPEAKER_1:  decrease in light that we always see when a plant truss in front of the star.
SPEAKER_1:  But we saw something extra just on the edges. We saw some extra.
SPEAKER_1:  dips around the outside.
SPEAKER_1:  It was right at the hairy edge of detectability.
SPEAKER_1:  We didn't believe it.
SPEAKER_1:  because...
SPEAKER_1:  I think one of the challenges of
SPEAKER_1:  looking for something for 10 years.
SPEAKER_1:  is that you become your own greatest skeptic. And no matter what you're shown, you're always.
SPEAKER_1:  thinking I've been.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like falling in love so many times and it not working out.
SPEAKER_1:  You.
SPEAKER_1:  convince yourself it's never gonna be.
SPEAKER_1:  It's never going to happen.
SPEAKER_1:  Not for me, you know, this just isn't, this isn't going to happen. And so I saw that and I didn't really believe it because I didn't dare let myself believe it.
SPEAKER_1:  but being a good scientist.
SPEAKER_1:  We knew we had an obligation to.
SPEAKER_1:  publish it.
SPEAKER_1:  to talk about the result and to follow it up and to try and resolve what was going on.
SPEAKER_1:  So we asked for Hubble Space Telescript time, which was...
SPEAKER_1:  awarded in that case that we were one of those lucky 20 that got telescope time.
SPEAKER_1:  and we stared at it for about 40 hours continuously.
SPEAKER_1:  And...
SPEAKER_1:  provide some context, the dip that we saw on the Capidator corresponding to a Neptune sized moon around a Jupiter sized planet which
SPEAKER_1:  was another reason why I was sceptical, that-
SPEAKER_1:  We don't have that in the solar system. That seems so strange.
SPEAKER_1:  And then when we got the Hubble data.
SPEAKER_1:  Seem to confirm exactly that there was.
SPEAKER_1:  two really striking pieces of evidence in the data that suggested this moon was there.
SPEAKER_1:  Another wizard.
SPEAKER_1:  fairly clear second dip in light, pretty clearly resolved by Hubble.
SPEAKER_1:  It was about a five sigma detection.
SPEAKER_1:  And on top of that, we could see the planet.
SPEAKER_1:  didn't transit when it should have done. It actually transited earlier than we expected it to, about 20 minutes or so.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that's a hallmark of a gravitational interaction between the planet and the moon. We actually expected that.
SPEAKER_1:  You can also expect that if the moon transits after the planet...
SPEAKER_1:  then the planet should come in earlier than expected.
SPEAKER_1:  because the barycenter, the center of mass, lives between the two of them. Kind of like another
SPEAKER_1:  balancing arm between them.
SPEAKER_1:  And so we saw that as well. So the face signature matched up.
SPEAKER_1:  The mass of the Moon was measured to be Neptune mass.
SPEAKER_1:  and the size of the moon was measured to be Neptune radius. And so everything just.
SPEAKER_1:  Really?
SPEAKER_1:  lined up.
SPEAKER_1:  And, um...
SPEAKER_1:  We spent months and months trying to kill it.
SPEAKER_1:  This is my strategy for anything interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  We just try to throw the kitchen sink at it and say, we must be tricked by something.
SPEAKER_1:  And so we tried looking at the centroid motion of the telescope, but the different wavelength channels have been observed, the pixel level information.
SPEAKER_1:  And no matter what we did, we just couldn't get rid of it.
SPEAKER_1:  And so we...
SPEAKER_1:  submit it to science. And I think at the time, science, which is one of the top journals said to us, would you mind calling your paper, discovery of an exomoon?
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  I had to push back and we said no.
SPEAKER_1:  We're not calling it that.
SPEAKER_1:  Allez!
SPEAKER_1:  even despite everything we've done, we're not calling it a discovery.
SPEAKER_1:  We're calling it evidence for an exo moon.
SPEAKER_1:  because for me I'd want to see this repeat.
SPEAKER_1:  two times, three times, four times.
SPEAKER_1:  before I really would.
SPEAKER_1:  Bet my house.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the real deal. And I do worry.
SPEAKER_1:  As I said, perhaps that's my own scepticism.
SPEAKER_1:  self skepticism going too far.
SPEAKER_1:  But I think it was the right decision. And since that paper came out,
SPEAKER_1:  There has been continuous interest in the subject. Another team independently analyzed that star.
SPEAKER_1:  and recovered actually pretty much exactly the same results as us, the same dip.
SPEAKER_1:  The same.
SPEAKER_1:  the same wobble of the planet.
SPEAKER_1:  And a third team looked at it and they actually got something different. They saw the dip was diminished compared to what we saw. They saw a little hint of a dip, but not as pronounced as what we saw.
SPEAKER_1:  and they saw.
SPEAKER_1:  The Wobble as well.
SPEAKER_1:  So this been...
SPEAKER_1:  a little bit of tension about
SPEAKER_1:  analyzing the reduction of the Hubble data.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  And so the only way my mind to resolve this is just to look again. We actually did propose to Hubble straight after that.
SPEAKER_1:  And we said, look.
SPEAKER_1:  if our model is right.
SPEAKER_1:  If the moon is there.
SPEAKER_1:  It came in late last time. It transited after the planet.
SPEAKER_1:  Because of the orbit, we can calculate that it should transit before the planet next time.
SPEAKER_1:  If it's not there, if it doesn't transit before, and even if we see a dip afterwards, we know that's not our moon. It's obviously some instrumental effect with the data.
SPEAKER_1:  We had a causal prediction as to where the moon should be.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  I was really excited about that, but we didn't get the telescope time.
SPEAKER_1:  And fortunately, if you go further into the future...
SPEAKER_1:  we no longer have the predictive capability because it's like predicting the weather. You might be able to predict the weather next week.
SPEAKER_1:  to some level of accuracy, but predicting the weather next year.
SPEAKER_1:  becomes incredibly hard.
SPEAKER_1:  Uncertainties just grow and compound as you go forward into the future more and more.
SPEAKER_0:  were you able to know where the moon would be positioned?
SPEAKER_0:  So you're able to.
SPEAKER_0:  told.
SPEAKER_0:  D-D-D-Duh.
SPEAKER_0:  orbiting
SPEAKER_0:  Like, geometry and-
SPEAKER_1:  And frequency. Yeah. So from the basically from the wobbles of the planet itself,
SPEAKER_1:  that tells us the orbital motion.
SPEAKER_1:  of the moon, it's the reflex motion of the moon.
SPEAKER_0:  Isn't it just an estimate to where
SPEAKER_0:  Like I'm concerned about you making a strong prediction here because like if you don't get
SPEAKER_0:  If you don't get the moon where the moon leads on the next time around, if you did get in the Hubble time, couldn't that mean something else if you didn't see that?
SPEAKER_0:  Because you said it would be an instrumental.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel...
SPEAKER_0:  the strong urge to disprove your, which is a really good imperative. It's a good way to do science, but like.
SPEAKER_0:  This is such a noisy signal, right? Or blurry signal maybe, low resolutions.
SPEAKER_1:  maybe that's the better answer. I mean it's a five sigma signal.
SPEAKER_1:  That's at the slightly uncomfortable edge. I mean.
SPEAKER_1:  It's often said that for any detection of a first new phenomena...
SPEAKER_1:  You really want like a 20, 25 sigma detection. Then there's just no doubt that.
SPEAKER_1:  what you're seeing is real.
SPEAKER_1:  This was at that edge. I mean, I guess it's comparable to the Higgs boson, but the Higgs boson was slightly different because there was so much theoretical impetus as to expect.
SPEAKER_1:  a signal.
SPEAKER_1:  at that precise location.
SPEAKER_1:  A Neptune-sized moon was not predicted by anyone. No one, there was no papers you can find that expect Neptune-sized moons around Jupiter-sized planets. So there was, I think we were inherently skeptical about its reality for that reason.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  but this is Science in Action and
SPEAKER_1:  When we fit the wobbles, we fit the dips, and we have this 3G geometric model for the motion of the orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  And projecting that forward, we found that about 80% of our projections led to the Moon.
SPEAKER_1:  to be before, so it's not 100%.
SPEAKER_1:  There is maybe.
SPEAKER_1:  20% of the cases it was over here.
SPEAKER_1:  But to me, that was a hard enough...
SPEAKER_1:  A hard enough projection.
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  We felt confident that we could refute the exit, which was what I really wanted. I wanted a refutable exit.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the basis of science, a falsifiable hypothesis.
SPEAKER_1:  How can you make progress in science if you don't have a falsifiable testable hypothesis? So that was the beauty of this particular case.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's a numerical simulation with a moon.
SPEAKER_0:  that fits the data that we observed, and then you can now make predictions based on that simulation.
SPEAKER_0:  This is so cool.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, it's fun. These are like little...
SPEAKER_1:  solar systems that we can simulate on the computer and re-enact the system.
SPEAKER_1:  but
SPEAKER_1:  We are, we are pushing things to the very limits of what's possible. And that's double-edged sword. It's both incredibly exciting intellectually, but.
SPEAKER_1:  Euroways.
SPEAKER_1:  you're always risking to some degree the pushing too far.
SPEAKER_0:  So I'd like to ask you about the recent paper you co-authored.
SPEAKER_0:  an exomoon survey of 70 cool giant exoplanets.
SPEAKER_0:  and the new candidate coupler 1708 PI.
SPEAKER_1:  I would say there's like three or four candidates at this point.
SPEAKER_1:  Of which we have published two of them. And to me.
SPEAKER_1:  to a quote.
SPEAKER_1:  compelling.
SPEAKER_1:  and deserve full up observations.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  direct
SPEAKER_1:  To get a confirmed detection, at least in our case, we would need to see it repeat, for sure.
SPEAKER_1:  One of the problems with some of the other methods that have been proposed is that you don't get that repeatability.
SPEAKER_1:  So for instance, an example of a technique that would lack that would be gravitational microlensing.
SPEAKER_1:  so it is possible with a new telescope coming up in the future.
SPEAKER_1:  called the Roman space telescope, which is basically a repurposed by satellite. That's the size of
SPEAKER_1:  The Hubble Mirror.
SPEAKER_1:  Getting a pint of space.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, it will stare at millions of stars simultaneously.
SPEAKER_1:  And it will look to see instead of whether any of those stars.
SPEAKER_1:  dimmer for a short amount of time.
SPEAKER_1:  which would be a transit.
SPEAKER_1:  It'll look for the opposite. It'll look to see if anything can get brighter.
SPEAKER_1:  and that brightness increase is caused by another planetary system.
SPEAKER_1:  Passing in front.
SPEAKER_1:  and then gravitationally lensing light around it to close the brightening
SPEAKER_1:  And so this is a method of.
SPEAKER_1:  discovering an entire.
SPEAKER_1:  solar system, but only.
SPEAKER_1:  only for a glimpse.
SPEAKER_1:  You just get a short glimpse of it passing like a ship sailing through the night. Just that one photo of it.
SPEAKER_1:  Now the problem with that is that...
SPEAKER_1:  It's very difficult.
SPEAKER_1:  The physics of.
SPEAKER_1:  gravitational lenses are not surprisingly quite complicated.
SPEAKER_1:  And so there's many, many possible solutions. So you might have a solution which is this could be.
SPEAKER_1:  A Red Wolf Star
SPEAKER_1:  with a Jupiter-like planet around it. That's one solution.
SPEAKER_1:  But another solution is that it's a free-floating planet, a rogue planet like Jupiter.
SPEAKER_1:  with an Earth-like moon around it.
SPEAKER_1:  And those two solutions are almost indistinguishable.
SPEAKER_1:  Now, ideally, we would be able to repeat the observation. We'd be able to go back and see, well, if the moon really is there, then we could predict its mass, its predicted motion and expect it to be maybe over here next time or something.
SPEAKER_1:  With microlensing it's a one.
SPEAKER_1:  snapshot event.
SPEAKER_1:  And so for me.
SPEAKER_1:  It's intriguing as a way of revealing something about the exome population.
SPEAKER_1:  But I always come back to transits because it's the only method we really have that's
SPEAKER_1:  absolutely repeatable that we'll be able to come back and prove to everyone that look
SPEAKER_1:  On the 17th of October, the moon will be over here and the moon will look like this and we can actually capture that image. And that's what we see with, of course, many exoplanets. So we want to get to that same point of...
SPEAKER_1:  Full confidence, full confirmation, the slam dunk detection.
SPEAKER_1:  of these xm moons but...
SPEAKER_1:  Um, yeah, it's, it's been a
SPEAKER_1:  hell of a journey.
SPEAKER_1:  to try and push.
SPEAKER_1:  the field into that direction and
SPEAKER_1:  uh... is that summer
SPEAKER_0:  Resistance to the transit method.
SPEAKER_1:  Not to the transit method, I just say to exomeons. So the transit method is by far the most popular method for looking for exoplanets.
SPEAKER_1:  But um...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, as I've alluded to, exo-moons is kind of a niche topic within the discipline of exoplanets.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's largely because there are.
SPEAKER_1:  people I think are waiting for those slam dunks.
SPEAKER_1:  And it was like the.
SPEAKER_1:  If you go back to the first exoplanet discovery...
SPEAKER_1:  that was made in 1995 by Michel Mayor and Didier Calloz.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's true at the time that they were seen as mavericks, that the idea of looking for planets around stars was considered fringe science.
SPEAKER_1:  And I'm sure many colleagues told them, why don't you do something more safe, like study eclipsing stars?
SPEAKER_1:  to binary star systems, we know those exist. So why are you wasting your time looking for planets? You're gonna get this.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Alien moniker or something, you'll be seen as a fringe maverick scientist.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I think it was quite difficult for those early planet hunters.
SPEAKER_1:  to get legitimacy and be taken seriously.
SPEAKER_1:  And so very few people risked their careers to do it, except for those that were either emboldened to try.
SPEAKER_1:  or had maybe the career.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  maybe like tenure or something so they didn't have to necessarily worry about the implications of failure.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  Once that happened, once they made the first discoveries...
SPEAKER_1:  Overnight.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, everyone and their dog was gunning into exoplanets and all of a sudden the whole, you know, the whole astronomy community shifted and...
SPEAKER_1:  huge numbers of people that were.
SPEAKER_1:  once upon a time studying eclipsing binaries, a change to becoming exoplanet scientists.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that was the first wave of exoplanet scientists.
SPEAKER_1:  We're now in a kind of a second wave or in the third wave.
SPEAKER_1:  where
SPEAKER_1:  People like me to some degree kind of grew up with the idea of exoplanets as being normal. I was 11 years old I guess when the first exoplanet was discovered.
SPEAKER_1:  And so to me, it was a fairly.
SPEAKER_1:  a normal idea to grow up with.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, and so we've been.
SPEAKER_1:  Schreienden.
SPEAKER_1:  in exoplanets from the very beginning.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that brings...
SPEAKER_1:  different perspective to those who have maybe transitioned from a different career path.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  I suspect with Exo Moons and
SPEAKER_1:  probably technosignatures.
SPEAKER_1:  astrobiology, many of the
SPEAKER_1:  topics which I've seen at the.
SPEAKER_1:  the fringes of...
SPEAKER_1:  What's possible?
SPEAKER_1:  They will all open up into becoming mainstream one day.
SPEAKER_1:  but there's a lot of people who are just waiting.
SPEAKER_1:  waiting for that.
SPEAKER_1:  assuredness.
SPEAKER_1:  that there is a
SPEAKER_1:  secure career net ahead of them before they commit.
SPEAKER_0:  It does seem to me that Exo-Moon's...
SPEAKER_0:  Open.
SPEAKER_0:  wider or open for the first time the door to to aliens.
SPEAKER_0:  more seriously academically studying, all right, let's look at like alien worlds. So I think it's still pretty fringe.
SPEAKER_0:  to talk about alien life, even on like on Mars and the moons and so on. You're kinda like...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it'll be nice, but imagine the first time you discover a living organism.
SPEAKER_0:  That's gonna change.
SPEAKER_0:  then everybody would look like an idiot for not-
SPEAKER_0:  focusing everything on this.
SPEAKER_0:  because the possibility of the things will, it's possible it might be super boring.
SPEAKER_0:  It might be very boring bacteria, but even the existence of life elsewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean that changes everything. That means life is everywhere.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. If you knew now that in five years, 10 years...
SPEAKER_1:  the first life would be discovered elsewhere. you knew that in advance.
SPEAKER_1:  It would surely.
SPEAKER_1:  affect the way you approach your entire career as a, especially someone junior in astronomy, you would surely be like, well, this is clearly going to be the direction I have to dedicate my classes and my training and my education towards that direction.
SPEAKER_0:  textbooks all the
SPEAKER_1:  That's right.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, and I think there's a lot of value to hedging.
SPEAKER_0:  like allocating some of the time.
SPEAKER_0:  to that possibility because the kind of discovery will.
SPEAKER_0:  the kind of discoveries we might get in the next few decades.
SPEAKER_0:  It feels like we're on the verge of a lot of...
SPEAKER_0:  getting a lot of really good data and
SPEAKER_0:  having better and better tools that can process that data. So there's just going to be a continuous increase of the kind of discoveries that will open. Like, but a slam dunk.
SPEAKER_0:  That's hard to come by.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I think a lot of us are anticipating.
SPEAKER_1:  We're already seeing it to some degree with venus and the phosphine incident.
SPEAKER_1:  But we've seen it before with Bill Clinton and the White House lawn announcing life.
SPEAKER_1:  from Mars and there are inevitably going to be spurious claims or at least claims which are
SPEAKER_1:  ambiguous to some degree.
SPEAKER_1:  There will be for sure a...
SPEAKER_1:  high profile journal like Nature of Science that will one day publish a paper saying
SPEAKER_1:  by a signature discovered or something like that on.
SPEAKER_1:  Trappist 1 or some other planet.
SPEAKER_1:  And then there will be years of back and forth in the literature.
SPEAKER_1:  And that might seem frustrating, but that's how science works. That's the mechanism of science at play of people.
SPEAKER_1:  scrutinizing the results to intense skepticism.
SPEAKER_1:  and.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like a crucible, you know, you burn away all the relevance is until whatever is left is the truth.
SPEAKER_1:  And so you're left with this.
SPEAKER_1:  this product.
SPEAKER_1:  which is that, okay, we either believe or don't believe that Biosynchros are there. So there's inevitably going to be a lot of.
SPEAKER_1:  controversy and debate and argument about it. We just have to anticipate that.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I think.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to basically have a thick skin to some degree academically to dive into that world.
SPEAKER_1:  And you're seeing that with phosphine.
SPEAKER_1:  It's been.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  It's been...
SPEAKER_1:  Uncomfortable to watch from the outside?
SPEAKER_1:  the kind of dialogue that some of the scientists have been having with each other.
SPEAKER_1:  about that because...
SPEAKER_1:  Um, they get a little aggressive.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, you can understand.
SPEAKER_1:  You can understand why, because...
SPEAKER_1:  Jealousy? I don't know. That's me saying, not you. That's me talking. I'm sure there's some envy and jealousy involved.
SPEAKER_1:  on the on the
SPEAKER_1:  behalf of those who are not part of the visual discovery.
SPEAKER_1:  But there's also in any case, just leave the particular people involved in Venus alone in any case of making it a claim of that magnitude.
SPEAKER_1:  Especially life.
SPEAKER_1:  Because life is pretty much...
SPEAKER_1:  One of the biggest discoveries of all time, you can imagine scientifically.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  You can see, and I'm so conscious of this in myself when I get close to, as I said, even the much smaller goal of setting an exomoon.
SPEAKER_1:  The ego creepin'.
SPEAKER_1:  And so as a scientist, we have to be so guarded against our own egos.
SPEAKER_1:  You see.
SPEAKER_1:  the lights in your eyes of a Nobel Prize or the fame and fortune and being remembered in the history books and we all...
SPEAKER_1:  Grew up in our training learning about Newton and Einstein, these giants of the field Feynman-Maxwell.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  You get the idea of these individual contributions, which.
SPEAKER_1:  get immortalized for all time. And that's seductive.
SPEAKER_1:  It's why many of us with the skill set to go into maybe banking instead decided
SPEAKER_1:  Actually, there's something about.
SPEAKER_1:  idea of being immortalized and contributing towards society in a permanent way that is more attractive than the financial reward.
SPEAKER_1:  of applying my skills elsewhere.
SPEAKER_1:  So to some degree that ego can be a benefit.
SPEAKER_1:  brings in skillful people into our field who might otherwise be tempted by money elsewhere.
SPEAKER_1:  But.
SPEAKER_1:  On the other hand, it
SPEAKER_1:  the closer you get towards.
SPEAKER_1:  when you start flirting with that.
SPEAKER_1:  Nobel prize in your, in your eyes, or you think you're on the, on the verge of seeing something you can lose objectivity.
SPEAKER_1:  A very famous example of this is...
SPEAKER_1:  uh, Barnard's Star.
SPEAKER_1:  there was a planet claimed there by Peter van der Kamp, I think it was in 1968-69.
SPEAKER_1:  And at the time it would have been the first ever exoplanet ever claimed.
SPEAKER_1:  And, um...
SPEAKER_1:  He-
SPEAKER_1:  felt assured that this planet was there. He was actually using the wobbling star method, but using the positions of the stars to see them, to claim this exoplanet.
SPEAKER_1:  It turned out that this planet was.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's not there
SPEAKER_1:  subsequent analyses by both dynamicists and theorists and those looking at the instrumental data.
SPEAKER_1:  established fairly.
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  unanimously that
SPEAKER_1:  There was no way this planet was really there.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  Peter van der Kamp insisted it was there despite-
SPEAKER_1:  overwhelming evidence that was accruing.
SPEAKER_1:  against him.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, and even to the day he died, which was
SPEAKER_1:  I think in the early 90s.
SPEAKER_1:  he was still insisting this planet was there, even when we were starting to make the first genuine exoplanet discoveries.
SPEAKER_1:  And even at that point, I think Hubble had even looked at that star.
SPEAKER_1:  and had totally ruled out.
SPEAKER_1:  any possibility of what he was talking about.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  That's the problem, how do you get to a point as a scientist where...
SPEAKER_1:  You just can't accept.
SPEAKER_1:  anything that comes otherwise, because you're, it starts out with.
SPEAKER_1:  the dream of fame.
SPEAKER_1:  And then it ends in a stubborn refusal to ever back down.
SPEAKER_0:  Of course the flip side of that.
SPEAKER_0:  Sometimes you need that.
SPEAKER_0:  to have the strength.
SPEAKER_0:  to carry a belief against the entire scientific community that resists your beliefs.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it's a double edged sword.
SPEAKER_1:  That can happen, but I guess the distinction here is evidence. Yes. So in this case.
SPEAKER_1:  that the evidence was so overwhelming. It wasn't really a matter of interpretation. It was, you had to collect, you'd observe this start with the same.
SPEAKER_1:  the same star, but with maybe 10, even a hundred times greater precision.
SPEAKER_1:  for prolonged much longer periods of time. And there was just no doubt at this point this planet was a mirage.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  And so that's why you have to be very careful. I always say don't ever name, you know, my wife, my daughter, name this planet after me that you discover.
SPEAKER_1:  I can't.
SPEAKER_1:  I can't ever name a planet after you.
SPEAKER_1:  because I'll be...
SPEAKER_1:  I won't be objective anymore.
SPEAKER_1:  How could I ever turn around to you and say that planet wasn't real that I named after you?
SPEAKER_0:  So you're somebody that talks about and is clear in your eyes and in your way of being.
SPEAKER_0:  that you love the process of discovery, that joy, the magic of just...
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  seeing something, a new observation, a new idea.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, but I guess.
SPEAKER_0:  The point is when you have that great feeling.
SPEAKER_0:  is to then switch on the skepticism.
SPEAKER_0:  like to start like testing.
SPEAKER_0:  What does this actually mean?
SPEAKER_0:  Is this real? What are the possible?
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, different interpretations that could make this a lot less grand than I first imagined. And so both have the wander and the skepticism on one brain.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I think the-
SPEAKER_1:  Generally the more I want something to be true.
SPEAKER_1:  the more I inherently doubt it.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think that just comes from, you know, I...
SPEAKER_1:  I grew up.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  with a religious family and...
SPEAKER_1:  was just sort of indoctrinated to some degree, like many children are, that, okay, this is normal, you know, there's a garden.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the way the world is.
SPEAKER_1:  God created the earth. And then as I became more...
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  well-read and literate of what was happening in the world scientifically.
SPEAKER_1:  I started to doubt.
SPEAKER_1:  and it really just struck me.
SPEAKER_1:  that the hardest thing to let go of
SPEAKER_1:  when you do decide not to be religious anymore.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's not really like a light bulb moment, but it just kind of happens over my over 11 to 13. I think for me it was happening.
SPEAKER_1:  But
SPEAKER_1:  It's that sadness of letting go of this beautiful...
SPEAKER_1:  dream which you had in your mind of eternal life for behaving yourself on Earth, you would have this beautiful heaven that you could go to and live forever.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's very attractive.
SPEAKER_1:  And for me personally...
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  That was one of the things that pulled me against it was this. It's like, it's too good to be true and it's very convenient.
SPEAKER_1:  that this could be so.
SPEAKER_1:  and I have no evidence directly in terms of a scientific sense to support this hypothesis.
SPEAKER_1:  and it just became...
SPEAKER_1:  really difficult to reconcile.
SPEAKER_1:  um, my growth as a scientist. And I know some people find that reconciliation.
SPEAKER_1:  I have not.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe I will one day.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  as a general.
SPEAKER_1:  guiding principle, which I think I...
SPEAKER_1:  I obtained from that experience.
SPEAKER_1:  was that I have to be extremely guarded.
SPEAKER_1:  about what I want to be true because
SPEAKER_1:  it's going to sway me to say things which...
SPEAKER_1:  which are not true if I'm not careful. And that's not what we're trying to do as scientists.
SPEAKER_0:  So you felt from a religious perspective that there was a...
SPEAKER_0:  a little bit of a gravitational field in terms of your opinions, like it was affecting how you could be as a scientist.
SPEAKER_0:  Like as a scientific thinker, obviously we're young.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I think...
SPEAKER_1:  I think that's, that's true that whenever you're.
SPEAKER_1:  whenever there's something you want to be true.
SPEAKER_1:  It's...
SPEAKER_1:  It's the ultimate seduction, intellectually.
SPEAKER_1:  And I worry about this a lot with...
SPEAKER_1:  UFOs with
SPEAKER_1:  It's true already with things like Venus, Phosphine and...
SPEAKER_1:  searching for astrobiological signals.
SPEAKER_1:  We have to guard against this all the way through from however we're looking for life, however we're looking for whatever this big question is.
SPEAKER_1:  there is a part of us, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  I would love that to be life in the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  I hope there is life in the universe, but-
SPEAKER_1:  I'm somewhat.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  been on record several times as being fairly
SPEAKER_1:  about trying to remain.
SPEAKER_1:  consciously agnostic about that question.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't want to make up my mind about what the answer is.
SPEAKER_1:  before I've collected evidence to inform that decision. And that's how.
SPEAKER_1:  That should work. If I only know...
SPEAKER_1:  What the answer is.
SPEAKER_1:  then what am I doing? And that's not a scientific experiment anymore. You've already decided. So what are you trying to learn? What's the point of
SPEAKER_1:  doing the experiment if you already know what the answer is. There's no point.
SPEAKER_0:  It's so complicated because so far I'm being arseful myself.
SPEAKER_0:  when I imagine the universe. So first thing I imagine.
SPEAKER_0:  about our world is that
SPEAKER_0:  We humans and me certainly as one.
SPEAKER_0:  human.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... no very...
SPEAKER_0:  First assumption is I know almost nothing.
SPEAKER_0:  about how anything works.
SPEAKER_0:  So first of all, that actually applies for.
SPEAKER_0:  for things that humans do know.
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  the quantum mechanics, all the things that there's different expertises that I just have not dedicated to. So even that starting point. If we take all of knowledge.
SPEAKER_0:  As human civilization, we know almost nothing. That's kind of an assumption I have.
SPEAKER_0:  because it seems like we keep discovering mysteries and it seems like
SPEAKER_0:  history.
SPEAKER_0:  human history is defined by moments when we said, okay, we pretty much figured it all out. And then you realize a century later, you've, when you said that you didn't figure out anything. Okay, so that's like a starting point.
SPEAKER_0:  The second thing I have is...
SPEAKER_0:  I feel like...
SPEAKER_0:  the entirety of the universe is just filled with alien civilizations.
SPEAKER_0:  statistically.
SPEAKER_0:  There's
SPEAKER_0:  The important...
SPEAKER_0:  thing that enables that belief for me is that they don't have to be human like. It could be anything.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's just the fact that life exists and just seeing the way life is on earth.
SPEAKER_0:  that it just finds a way.
SPEAKER_0:  It finds a way in so many different complicated environments.
SPEAKER_0:  It finds a way, whatever that force is.
SPEAKER_0:  That same force has to find a way elsewhere also.
SPEAKER_0:  But then if I'm also being honest,
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know how many hours in a day I spend.
SPEAKER_0:  seriously considering the possibility that we're alone.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know what I'm-
SPEAKER_0:  Good night.
SPEAKER_0:  When my heart is in mind or filled with wonder, I think about all the different...
SPEAKER_0:  life that's out there.
SPEAKER_0:  but to really imagine that we're alone?
SPEAKER_0:  Like really imagine all the vastness that's out there. We're alone.
SPEAKER_0:  Not even bacteria?
SPEAKER_1:  I would say you don't have to believe that we are alone.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  that you have to.
SPEAKER_1:  admit it's a possibility of our ignorance of the universe so far.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  You can have a belief about something in the absence of evidence.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Carl Sagan famously described that as the definition of faith.
SPEAKER_1:  if you believe something when there's no evidence.
SPEAKER_1:  You have faith that there's life in the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  But you can't.
SPEAKER_1:  You can't demonstrate, you can't prove it mathematically, you can't show me evidence of that.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  But is there some, so mathematically math is a funny thing. Is there, I mean the way physicists think, like intuition.
SPEAKER_0:  So, so basic reasoning.
SPEAKER_0:  Is there some value to that?
SPEAKER_0:  Bye!
SPEAKER_1:  I'd say we're all there. Certainly you can certainly make a very good argument. I think you've kind of already made one.
SPEAKER_1:  Just the vastness of the universe is the default argument people often turn to.
SPEAKER_1:  that surely there should be others out there. It's hard to imagine.
SPEAKER_1:  There are a order of...
SPEAKER_1:  10 to the 22 stars in our observable universe.
SPEAKER_1:  And so really the question comes down to what is the probability of one of those 10 to 22.
SPEAKER_1:  planets let's say, Earth like planets if they all have Earth like planets.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, going on.
SPEAKER_1:  to form life.
SPEAKER_1:  spontaneously.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the process of abiogenesis, the spontaneous emergence of life.
SPEAKER_0:  Also the word spontaneous is a funny
SPEAKER_1:  Well, maybe we won't use spontaneous, but.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Not being, so to say, seeded by some other civilization or something like this. It naturally emerges.
SPEAKER_0:  because even the word spontaneous.
SPEAKER_0:  makes it seem less likely?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Like this, there's just this chemistry and extremely random.
SPEAKER_1:  It could be a very gradual process over millions of years of growing complexity in chemical networks.
SPEAKER_0:  force in the universe that
SPEAKER_0:  pushes it towards interesting complexity pockets of complexity.
SPEAKER_0:  Ultimately.
SPEAKER_0:  create something like life which we can't possibly define yet.
SPEAKER_0:  and sometimes it manifests itself into something that looks like humans, but it can be a totally different kind of computational information processing system.
SPEAKER_0:  that were too dumb to even visualize.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean, certainly, I mean, it's kind of weird that complexity develops at all, right? Because
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like the-
SPEAKER_1:  opposite to our physical intuition, if you're training in physics of entropy, that thing should
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, complexity is hard to spontaneously, I shouldn't say spontaneously, but hard to emerge in general.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that's an interesting problem. I think there's been, certainly from an evolutionary perspective, you do see growing complexity.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's a nice argument I think it's by God.
SPEAKER_1:  Who?
SPEAKER_1:  who shows that if you have a certain amount of complexity.
SPEAKER_1:  It can either become less complex or more complex through random mutation.
SPEAKER_1:  And the less complex things are stripping away something, something that was necessary potentially to their survival.
SPEAKER_1:  And so in general, that's going to be.
SPEAKER_1:  not particularly useful in its survival. And so it's going to be detrimental to strip away a significant amount of its useful traits.
SPEAKER_1:  Whereas if you add something...
SPEAKER_1:  the most typical.
SPEAKER_1:  that you add is probably not useful at all. It's probably just...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't really affect its survival negatively, but neither does it provide any significant benefit.
SPEAKER_1:  But sometimes on rare occasions, of course, it will be of benefit. So.
SPEAKER_1:  If you have a certain level of complexity, it's hard to go back in complexity, but it's fairly easy to do.
SPEAKER_1:  easy to go forward with enough.
SPEAKER_1:  bites at the cherry, you will eventually build up in complexity and that tends to be why we see complexity.
SPEAKER_1:  growing in.
SPEAKER_1:  in certainly in an evolutionary sense.
SPEAKER_1:  but also perhaps it's operating in chemical networks that led to the emergence of life.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess the real...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh
SPEAKER_1:  problem I have with it with the numbers games come back to that is that.
SPEAKER_1:  we are talking about a certain probability of that occurring.
SPEAKER_1:  It may be to go from...
SPEAKER_1:  the primordial soup, however you want to call it, the ingredients that the earth started with, the organic molecules.
SPEAKER_1:  the probability of going from that.
SPEAKER_1:  Initial condition.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  something that was capable of Darwinian natural selection that maybe we could define as life.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  The probability that is maybe 1% of the time that happens, in which case you're right, the universe will be f***ed.
SPEAKER_1:  Absolutely teeming with life.
SPEAKER_1:  but across a big.
SPEAKER_1:  10 to the power minus 10, in which case it's 1 per galaxy.
SPEAKER_1:  or 10 to the power of minus 100, in which case the vast majority of universes even do not have life within it.
SPEAKER_0:  or
SPEAKER_0:  90%
SPEAKER_0:  Or 90% you said 1% it could be 90% if the conditions, the chemical conditions of a planet are correct or a moon are correct.
SPEAKER_1:  I admit that. It could be any of those numbers.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  The challenge is we just have no.
SPEAKER_1:  rigorous reason to expect why 90% is any, because we're talking about a probability for probability.
SPEAKER_1:  Worst.
SPEAKER_1:  Is, is 90% more a priori likely.
SPEAKER_1:  then 10 to the power minus.
SPEAKER_1:  Well the thing is...
SPEAKER_0:  We do have an observation, N of 1.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's difficult to know what to do with that, what kind of intuition you build.
SPEAKER_0:  On top of that.
SPEAKER_0:  because on Earth...
SPEAKER_0:  It seems like life finds a way.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay. In all kinds of conditions.
SPEAKER_0:  in all kinds of crazy conditions. And it's able to build up from the basic chemistry. You could say, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe it takes a little bit of time to develop some complicated technology like mitochondria. I don't know like photosynthesis
SPEAKER_0:  fine but it seems to figure it out.
SPEAKER_0:  and like.
SPEAKER_0:  do it extremely well.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, but I would say you're describing a different process. I mean.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe I'm, I'm at fault for separating these two processes, but to me, you're describing.
SPEAKER_1:  Basically natural selection evolution at that point.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, whereas I'm really describing ABO genesis, which is to me, a separate, distinct process.
SPEAKER_0:  to you limited to human scientists, yes, but why would it be a separate process?
SPEAKER_0:  Why is the birth of life a separate process from the process of life?
SPEAKER_0:  Why is the f-
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, we're uncomfortable with the, we're comfortable with the big bang.
SPEAKER_0:  Or I'm comfortable with the first thing, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  Like where did this come from? Right, so I think-
SPEAKER_1:  I would say I just twist that question around and say what
SPEAKER_1:  You're saying why is it a different process?
SPEAKER_1:  Um, why, and I would say why shouldn't it be a different process, which isn't really a good defense, except to say that we have.
SPEAKER_1:  We have knowledge of how.
SPEAKER_1:  natural selection evolution works.
SPEAKER_1:  think we understand that process.
SPEAKER_1:  almost no information about the earliest stages of how life emerged on our planet.
SPEAKER_1:  It may be that you're right and it is a part of a continuum.
SPEAKER_1:  It may be that it is also a distinct.
SPEAKER_1:  improbable set of circumstances that led to the emergence of life.
SPEAKER_1:  As a scientist, I'm just trying to be open-minded.
SPEAKER_1:  to both possibilities. If I assert that life must be everywhere,
SPEAKER_1:  To me, you run the risk of experiment as bias.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, if you think, you know what the answer is, if you look at an Earth like planet and you, and you are preconditioned.
SPEAKER_1:  to think there's a 90% chance of life on this planet.
SPEAKER_1:  It's going to.
SPEAKER_1:  at some level affect your interpretation of that data.
SPEAKER_1:  Whereas if I...
SPEAKER_1:  However critical you might be of the agnosticism that I impose upon myself.
SPEAKER_1:  Remain open.
SPEAKER_1:  to both possibilities.
SPEAKER_1:  then I trusted myself to make a fair assessment as to the reality of that evidence for life.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, but I wonder sort of scientifically and that's really beautiful to hear and inspiring to hear.
SPEAKER_0:  I wonder...
SPEAKER_0:  scientifically how many firsts
SPEAKER_0:  we truly know of.
SPEAKER_0:  Ike.
SPEAKER_0:  and then we don't eventually explain.
SPEAKER_0:  as actually.
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  a step number one million in a long process.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think
SPEAKER_0:  That's a really interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  if there's truly first in this universe.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, for us, whatever happened at the Big Bang is a kind of first, the origin of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's just, again.
SPEAKER_0:  It seems like history shows that we'll figure out that it's actually a continuation of something. But then physicists say that time is emergent and there are causality in times.
SPEAKER_0:  is a very human kind of construct that is very possible that all of this
SPEAKER_0:  So there could be really first.
SPEAKER_0:  of a thing to which we attach a name.
SPEAKER_0:  So whatever we call life.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe there is an or-
SPEAKER_1:  of it.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. And I would also say I'm open to that idea of it being part of a continuation.
SPEAKER_1:  but the continuation maybe is more broader and it's a continuation of
SPEAKER_1:  chemical systems and chemical networks.
SPEAKER_1:  And what we call this one particular type of chemistry in this behavior of chemistry life.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  but it is just one manifestation of all the.
SPEAKER_1:  trillions of possible permutations in which chemical reactions can occur.
SPEAKER_1:  And we assert specialness to it because that's what we are.
SPEAKER_1:  And so this is, it's also true of intelligence. You could extend the same thing and say, you know, we're, we're looking for.
SPEAKER_1:  intelligent life in the universe and then you started
SPEAKER_1:  Where does, where do you define intelligence? Where, where's that?
SPEAKER_1:  continuum of something that's really like us, are we alone?
SPEAKER_1:  There may be a continuum of chemical systems, a continuum of intelligences out there.
SPEAKER_1:  end.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  We have to be.
SPEAKER_1:  careful of our own arrogance, of assuming specialness about what we are, that we are some distinct category.
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  Phenomena
SPEAKER_1:  whereas the universe doesn't really care about what
SPEAKER_1:  category we are, it's just doing what it's doing and doing everything in infinite diversity and infinite combinations is essentially what it's doing. And so we are taking this one slice.
SPEAKER_1:  and saying
SPEAKER_1:  No, this has to be treated separately.
SPEAKER_1:  And I...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm open to the idea that it could be a truly separate phenomenon, but it may just be.
SPEAKER_1:  like a snowflake, every snowflake's different.
SPEAKER_1:  and maybe just be that this one particular.
SPEAKER_1:  iteration is another variant of the vast continuum.
SPEAKER_0:  And maybe the algorithm of natural selection itself is an invention of Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  I kind of also tend to suspect that this.
SPEAKER_0:  this, whatever the algorithm is, it kind of operates.
SPEAKER_0:  at all levels throughout the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  But maybe this is a very kind of peculiar thing.
SPEAKER_0:  That's...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  where there's a bunch of chemical.
SPEAKER_0:  systems.
SPEAKER_0:  that compete against each other.
SPEAKER_0:  somehow for survival under limited resources.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's a very earth like thing. Mm hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  There's.
SPEAKER_0:  a large number of resources enough.
SPEAKER_0:  to have a bunch of different kinds of systems competing, but not so many that...
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  They get lazy.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. And maybe that's why bacteria were very lazy for a long time. Maybe they had...
SPEAKER_0:  They didn't have much competition.
SPEAKER_1:  Quite possibly. I mean, I tried to.
SPEAKER_1:  As, as fun as it is to get into the speculation about.
SPEAKER_1:  the definitions of life and what life does and this gross network of possibilities.
SPEAKER_1:  Honestly, for me, the strongest argument.
SPEAKER_1:  remaining agnostic.
SPEAKER_1:  is to avoid that bias in assessing data. And we've seen it, I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  Pestful lol I talked about on my channel.
SPEAKER_1:  maybe last year or two years ago, you know, who's a very famous astronomer.
SPEAKER_1:  who in the 19th century was claiming the evidence of canals on Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  from him, from his perspective, and even at the time, culturally, it was widely accepted that Mars would, of course, have life. I mean, I think it seems silly to us, but it was kind of similar arguments to what we're using now about exoplanets that, well, of course, there must be.
SPEAKER_1:  life in the universe, how could it just be here? And so it seemed obvious to people that when you looked at Mars with its polar caps,
SPEAKER_1:  even if you know its atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  had seasons.
SPEAKER_1:  It seemed obvious to them that that too would be a place where life not only was present, but had emerged to a civilization, which actually was fairly comparable in technology to our own, because it was building canal systems.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, of course, the canal system seems a bizarre, technosignature to us, but it was a product of their time to them. And that was the cutting edge in technology.
SPEAKER_1:  It should be a warning shot actually a little bit for us that if we think.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, solar panels or building star links or...
SPEAKER_1:  whatever space mining is like an inevitable technosignature.
SPEAKER_1:  That may be laughably.
SPEAKER_1:  antiquated.
SPEAKER_1:  compared to what other civilizations far more advanced than this may be doing.
SPEAKER_1:  And so anyway, Percival Lowell, he was, he, I think was a product of his time that he thought life was there. But inevitably he even wrote about it extensively.
SPEAKER_1:  And so when he saw...
SPEAKER_1:  these lines, these lineae on the surface of Mars, to him it was just obvious they were canals.
SPEAKER_1:  And he was, he, that was experimented by us playing out. He was told for one that he had basically the greatest eyesight.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, out of any of his peers and ophthalmologists had told him that in Boston, that his eyesight was absolutely spectacular. So he just was convinced everything he saw was real.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  And secondly, he was convinced there was life there. And so it
SPEAKER_1:  to him, it just added up and then that kind of wasted.
SPEAKER_1:  decades of research of treating the idea.
SPEAKER_1:  of Mars being inhabited by this canal civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  But on the other hand, it's maybe not a waste because it is a lesson in history of.
SPEAKER_1:  how we should be always on guard.
SPEAKER_1:  against our own preconceptions and biases about what...
SPEAKER_1:  whether life is out there and furthermore, what types of things life might do if it is there.
SPEAKER_0:  If I were running this simulation, which we'll also talk about because you make the case against it.
SPEAKER_0:  But if I were running a simulation, I would definitely put you in a room with an alien.
SPEAKER_0:  and just to see you mentally freak out for hours at a time.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, you for sure would have thought...
SPEAKER_0:  You will be.
SPEAKER_0:  Convince that you've lost your mind.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, no, not that, but I mean, like, if we discover...
SPEAKER_0:  life we discovered interesting new physical phenomena.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the right approach is definitely to be extremely skeptical and be very, very careful about things you want to be true.
SPEAKER_1:  That's, that's, I'm not like some extreme denialist of evidence. If there was, if there was compelling evidence for life on another planet, I would.
SPEAKER_1:  be the first one to be celebrating that and be shaking hands with the alien on the White House lawn. Whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I grew up with Star Trek and that was my fantasy was to, you know, be Captain Kirk and fly across the stars, meeting at the civilization. So there's nothing more I'd want to be true as I've said, but, um.
SPEAKER_1:  We just have to guard against it when we're assessing data.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh
SPEAKER_1:  I have to say I'm very skeptical that we will ever have that.
SPEAKER_1:  Star Trek moment, even if, even if there are other civilizations out there.
SPEAKER_1:  They're never gonna be.
SPEAKER_1:  at a point which is in technological lockstep with us.
SPEAKER_1:  similar development.
SPEAKER_1:  Even
SPEAKER_1:  intellectually the idea that they could.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  have a conversation with us even through a translator.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, we can't communicate with Humback whales. We can't communicate with dolphins in a meaningful way. We can sort of bark orders at them, but we can't.
SPEAKER_1:  have abstract conversations with them about things.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, and so.
SPEAKER_1:  the idea that we will ever have that.
SPEAKER_1:  fulfilling.
SPEAKER_1:  conversation I'm deeply skeptical of. But I think...
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of us are drawn to that, it is maybe a replacement.
SPEAKER_1:  for God to some degree, that that father figure civilization that might step in.
SPEAKER_1:  teach us there of our ways and.
SPEAKER_1:  bestow wisdom upon our civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  they could equally be a giant fungus.
SPEAKER_1:  that has.
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't even understand the idea of social, socialization because it's the only entity on its planet. It just.
SPEAKER_1:  swells over the entire surface.
SPEAKER_1:  And it doesn't, it's incredibly intelligent because maybe each node communicates with each other to create essentially a giant neural net.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  It has no sense of what communication even is. So...
SPEAKER_1:  alien life is out there is surely going to be extremely diverse. I'm pretty skeptical that we'll ever get.
SPEAKER_1:  fantasy moment I always had as a kid of
SPEAKER_1:  having a dialogue within the civilization.
SPEAKER_0:  So dialogue.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, what about noticing them? What about noticing signals?
SPEAKER_0:  Do you hope?
SPEAKER_0:  So one thing we've been talking about is getting signatures, biosignatures, techno signatures about other planets.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  I feel extremely lucky in our lifetime to be able to meet
SPEAKER_0:  life forms.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... get evidence of living or dead life forms on mars or the moons of jupiter and saturn what about getting signals from outer space interstellar signals
SPEAKER_0:  What would those signals potentially look like?
SPEAKER_1:  That's a hard question to answer because we are essentially engaging in Xeno-psychology to some degree. What are the activities of another civilization?
SPEAKER_1:  But a lot of that...
SPEAKER_0:  What is the word xeno-psychology? What is the word xeno-psychology?
SPEAKER_1:  interrupt mean.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, maybe I'm just fabricating that word really, but they're trying to guess at the, um, the machinations and motivations of.
SPEAKER_1:  another intelligent being that
SPEAKER_1:  was completely evolutionary divorced from us.
SPEAKER_1:  for sick.
SPEAKER_0:  Like you said, exomoons, it's exopsychology.
SPEAKER_1:  Extrasolar. Yeah. Psychology. Yeah. Uh, alien psychology is another way of maybe making it more grounded, but.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  The
SPEAKER_1:  We can't really guess at their motivations too well, but we can look at the sorts of behaviours we engage in.
SPEAKER_1:  and at least look for them.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, we're always guilty that when we look for bio signatures, we're really looking for, and even when we look for planets, we're looking for templates of earth. When we look for bio signatures, we're looking for templates of earth based life.
SPEAKER_1:  When we look for tetanus signatures, we tend to be looking for templates of our own behaviors or extrapolations of our behaviors.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, so there's a very long list of tennis signatures that
SPEAKER_1:  people have suggested we could look for the.
SPEAKER_1:  The earliest ones were of course Radio Beacons.
SPEAKER_1:  That was sort of Project Osmo that Frank Drake was involved in.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm trying to look for radio signatures.
SPEAKER_1:  which could either be.
SPEAKER_1:  just like.
SPEAKER_1:  blurting out high power radio signals saying, hey, we're here, or could even have encoded within them.
SPEAKER_1:  galactic encyclopedias for us to unlock, which has always been the allure of the radio technique.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  but there could also be unintentional signatures.
SPEAKER_1:  For example, you can have something like the satellite system that we've produced on the Earth's artificial satellite system, Starlink.
SPEAKER_1:  type systems we mentioned.
SPEAKER_1:  You could detect the glint of light across those satellites as they orbit around the planet.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  You could set a geostationary satellite belt which would block out some light as the planet transited across the star.
SPEAKER_1:  You could detect solar panels potentially spectrally on the surface of the planet.
SPEAKER_1:  Heat Island effects, New York is hotter than New York state.
SPEAKER_1:  by a couple of degrees because the heat island effect of the city and so you could thermally map
SPEAKER_1:  different planets and detect these. So.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a large array.
SPEAKER_1:  of things that we do.
SPEAKER_1:  that we can go out and hypothesize we could look for.
SPEAKER_1:  And then on the furthest end of the scale, we have things which go far beyond our capabilities.
SPEAKER_1:  such as warp drive signatures, which have been proposed. You get these bright flashes of light or even gravitational wave detections from LIGO could be detected.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  You could have Dyson spheres.
SPEAKER_1:  the idea of covering a star is completely covered by some kind of structure which collects all the light from the star to power the civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  And that would be pretty easily detectable to some degree.
SPEAKER_1:  transferring all of the
SPEAKER_1:  visible light.
SPEAKER_1:  Thermodynamically it has to be re-emitted so it would come out as infrared light.
SPEAKER_1:  so you'd have an incredibly bright infrared star.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, one that was visibly...
SPEAKER_1:  not present at all, and so there would be...
SPEAKER_1:  pretty intriguing signature to look for.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there effort?
SPEAKER_0:  to look for something like that for different Dyson spheres out there for with the with the strong infrared
SPEAKER_1:  signal. There has been. Yeah, there has been and there's been, I think in the literature, there was one with the IRAS satellite, which is an infrared satellite.
SPEAKER_1:  They targeted, I think, a vote of 100,000 stars.
SPEAKER_1:  nearby stars and found no
SPEAKER_1:  convincing examples of what looked like a Dyson Sphere Star.
SPEAKER_1:  And then Jason Wright and his team extended this, I think, using Wwise.
SPEAKER_1:  which is another infrared satellite.
SPEAKER_1:  to look around galaxies.
SPEAKER_1:  could an entire galaxy have been converted into Dyson spheres?
SPEAKER_1:  or a significant fraction of the galaxy, which is basically the, the kind of share of type three, right? This is the.
SPEAKER_1:  when you've basically mastered the entire galactic pool of resources.
SPEAKER_1:  And again, out of 100,000 nearby galaxies, there appears to be no compelling examples of what looks like a Dyson galaxy, if you want to call it that.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, so.
SPEAKER_1:  That by no means...
SPEAKER_1:  proves that.
SPEAKER_1:  day.
SPEAKER_1:  don't exist or don't happen, but it seems like it's an unusual behaviour.
SPEAKER_1:  for a civilization to get to that stage of development and start harvesting the entire stellar output.
SPEAKER_0:  Unusually, yes, I and I mean like oh it's super interesting with gravitational waves
SPEAKER_0:  if that kind of experiment could start seeing some weirdness, some weird signals.
SPEAKER_0:  some
SPEAKER_0:  that compare to the-
SPEAKER_0:  to the power of.
SPEAKER_0:  cosmic phenomena.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean, it's a whole new window to the universe, not just in terms of astrophysics, but
SPEAKER_1:  potentially for 10 inches as well. I have to say with the warp drives, I am skeptical that warp drives are possible because
SPEAKER_1:  You can.
SPEAKER_1:  you have kind of fundamental problem relativity, you can either really have relativity.
SPEAKER_1:  Fast and light travel or causality. You can only choose two of those three things. You really can't have all three in a coherent universe.
SPEAKER_1:  If you have all three, you basically end up with a possibility of these kind of temporal paradoxes and time loops and grandfather paradoxes.
SPEAKER_0:  Or can't there be pockets of causality?
SPEAKER_0:  Something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  like where there's like pockets of consistent.
SPEAKER_1:  You could design it in that way. You could be, you know, if you had a warp drive or a time machine, essentially, you could be.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  You can be very conscious and careful of the way you use it so as to not to cause paradoxes or just do it in a local area or something.
SPEAKER_1:  But the real fundamental problem is...
SPEAKER_1:  You always have the...
SPEAKER_1:  ability to do it.
SPEAKER_1:  And so in a vast cosmic universe, if...
SPEAKER_1:  Time machines are all over the place.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  there's too much risk of someone doing it, right? Of somebody having the option of essentially breaking the universe with it. So this is...
SPEAKER_1:  A fundamental problem Hawking has this chronology protection conjecture where he said that essentially
SPEAKER_1:  It's this just can't be allowed because it breaks. It breaks all our laws of physics. If time travel is possible, current laws of physics. Yes. Correct. Yeah. Um, and so.
SPEAKER_1:  We need to rip up relativity. I mean, that's the point is the current law is physics. So you'd have to rip up our current law of relativity to make sense of how FTL.
SPEAKER_1:  could live in that universe, because you can't have relativity, FTL and causality sit nicely and play nicely together.
SPEAKER_0:  but we're currently.
SPEAKER_0:  don't have quantum mechanics and relativity playing nice together anyway, so it's not like everything is all
SPEAKER_1:  and that's a little fat. It's certainly not the full picture. It's probably not the determined picture that it must be,
SPEAKER_1:  More to go. Thank you. Baek still looks really used to hands.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, so it's already.
SPEAKER_0:  ripped up so might as well rip it up a little more.
SPEAKER_0:  And in the process, I actually try to connect the two things.
SPEAKER_0:  because maybe in the unification of...
SPEAKER_0:  of the standard model and general relativity may be their lies.
SPEAKER_0:  some kind of new wisdom.
SPEAKER_0:  about
SPEAKER_0:  of about war drives. So by the way, war drives is somehow...
SPEAKER_0:  Messing with the fabric.
SPEAKER_0:  of the universe to be able to travel faster than the speed of light.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, you're basically bending space time. You could also do it with a wormhole.
SPEAKER_1:  talking about some of the
SPEAKER_1:  hypothetical FTL system. It doesn't have to necessarily be the Alcubair drive, the warp drive. It could be any faster than light system, as long as it...
SPEAKER_1:  travel superluminally it will violate causality.
SPEAKER_0:  Presumably that will be observable.
SPEAKER_1:  with LEGO.
SPEAKER_1:  Potentially, yeah, potentially. It depends on, I think, you know, the properties of whatever the spacecraft is.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, one problem with warp drives is there's all sorts of problems with warp drives.
SPEAKER_1:  When I started this.
SPEAKER_0:  It
SPEAKER_1:  One problem. There's just this one minor problem that we have to get around.
SPEAKER_1:  When it arrives at its destination, it basically collects.
SPEAKER_1:  This vast, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  It has like an event horizon almost at the front of it. And so it collects all this radiation at the front as it goes.
SPEAKER_1:  And when it arrives, all that radiation gets dumped on its destination.
SPEAKER_1:  basically completely exterminate the planet it arrives at.
SPEAKER_1:  That radiation is also incident within the shell itself, there's Hawking radiation occurring within the shell, which is pretty dangerous.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  And then it also raises all sorts of...
SPEAKER_1:  exacerbations of the Fermi paradox, of course, as well. So you might be able to explain why.
SPEAKER_1:  we don't see.
SPEAKER_1:  a galactic empire.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, even here it's hard. You might be able to explain why we don't see Galactic Empire if everybody's limited to Voyager 2.
SPEAKER_1:  rocket speeds of like 20 kilometers per second or something.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's a lot harder to explain.
SPEAKER_1:  why we don't see.
SPEAKER_1:  the stars populated by Galactic Empires.
SPEAKER_1:  when warp drive is eminently possible because it makes...
SPEAKER_1:  expansion so much more trivial that
SPEAKER_1:  It's it.
SPEAKER_1:  It makes our life harder. Um, there was, there's some wonderful simulation work being done out of Rochester where they actually simulate all the stars in the galaxy.
SPEAKER_1:  or a fraction of them.
SPEAKER_1:  and they spawn a civilization and one of them.
SPEAKER_1:  and they let it spread out at sublight speeds.
SPEAKER_1:  And actually the very...
SPEAKER_1:  mixing of the stars themselves, because the stars are not static, they're in orbit of the galactic centre and they
SPEAKER_1:  have crossing paths with each other.
SPEAKER_1:  If you just have a range of even like five light years.
SPEAKER_1:  and your speed is of order of a few percent the speed of light is the maximum you can muster.
SPEAKER_1:  you can populate the entire galaxy within something like 100,000, to about a million years or so.
SPEAKER_1:  So in a fraction of the lifetime of the galaxy itself.
SPEAKER_1:  And so this raises some.
SPEAKER_1:  fairly serious problems because
SPEAKER_1:  If.
SPEAKER_1:  any civilization in the entire history of the galaxy decided to do that.
SPEAKER_1:  then either we shouldn't be here or we happen to live in this kind of rare pocket where they chose not to.
SPEAKER_1:  populate to.
SPEAKER_1:  And so this is sometimes called.
SPEAKER_1:  Fact A, hearts fact A.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  as the fact is that.
SPEAKER_1:  a civilization is not here now, an alien civilization has not.
SPEAKER_1:  is not in present occupation of the earth.
SPEAKER_1:  and that's difficult to...
SPEAKER_1:  resolve with the apparent ease at which even
SPEAKER_1:  a small extrapolation of our own technology could potentially populate a galaxy.
SPEAKER_1:  in far faster than.
SPEAKER_1:  history.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  to me.
SPEAKER_0:  By the way.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, the firm paradox is truly a paradox for me.
SPEAKER_0:  I suspect that if alien visited Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  I suspect if they do.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  if they are everywhere.
SPEAKER_0:  I think they're already here.
SPEAKER_0:  and we're too dumb to see it.
SPEAKER_0:  but leaving that aside.
SPEAKER_0:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  I think we should be able to in that case.
SPEAKER_0:  have very strong.
SPEAKER_0:  obvious signals when we look up at the stars.
SPEAKER_0:  at the emanation of energy.
SPEAKER_0:  required. We will see. We will see.
SPEAKER_0:  We'll see some weirdness.
SPEAKER_0:  that like where these are these kinds of stars and these are these kinds of stars that are being messed with. Like leveraging the nuclear fusion of stars.
SPEAKER_0:  to do something useful. The fact that we don't really see that.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe you can correct me. Wouldn't we be able to, if there is like alien civilizations running galaxies.
SPEAKER_0:  Wouldn't we see weirdnesses from an astronomy perspective with the way the stars are behaving?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean, it depends exactly what they're doing, but I mean, the Dyson Sphere example is one that we already discussed where a survey of 100,000 nearby galaxies find that they are not, have all been transformed into Dyson Sphere collectors.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  You could also imagine them doing things like, we wrote a paper about this recently of starlifting, where you can extend the life of your star by scooping mass off the star. So you'd be with, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  doing stellar engineering essentially.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  space if you're doing a huge amount of asteroid mining.
SPEAKER_1:  you would have a spectral signature because you're basically filling the solar system with dust. By doing that there'd be debris from that activity.
SPEAKER_1:  And so there are...
SPEAKER_1:  some limits on this.
SPEAKER_1:  Certainly we don't see...
SPEAKER_1:  uh, you know, bright flashes, which would be, you know, one of these consequences of what drivers have said is as they decelerate, they produce these bright flashes of light.
SPEAKER_1:  We don't seem to see evidence of those kind of things.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  We don't see anything obvious around the nearby stars or the stars that we've severed in detail beyond that.
SPEAKER_1:  indicate any kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  artificial civilization, the closest maybe we had was Boyajin Star, there was a lot of interest in
SPEAKER_1:  Who was a star?
SPEAKER_1:  that was just very peculiarly dipping in and out as brightness.
SPEAKER_1:  And it was hypothesized for a time that that may indeed be some kind of Dyson-like structure. So maybe a Dyson sphere that's...
SPEAKER_1:  half built.
SPEAKER_1:  And so as it comes in and out, it's blocking out huge swaths of the star.
SPEAKER_1:  It was very difficult to explain it.
SPEAKER_1:  really with any kind of planet model at the time.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  But an easier hypothesis that was proposed was it could just be a large number of comets or dust or something, or maybe a planet that had broken apart and as its fragments orbit around it blocks out starlight.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  It turned out with subsequent observations of that star, which especially the amateur astronomy community made a big contribution to as well.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  that the dips were chromatic, which was a...
SPEAKER_1:  a real important clue that that probably wasn't.
SPEAKER_1:  solid structure then that was going around it, it was more likely to be dust. Dust is chromatic.
SPEAKER_1:  By chromatic I mean, it looks different in different colours.
SPEAKER_1:  so it blocks out more red light than blue light. It was a solid structure.
SPEAKER_1:  shouldn't do that. It should be opaque, right? A solid metal structure or something.
SPEAKER_1:  So that was one of the clear indications and the...
SPEAKER_1:  behavior.
SPEAKER_1:  of in the way the light changed or the dips changed across wavelengths was fully consistent with the expectations of what small particulates would do.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  And so that's, that's very hard. I mean, the real problem with.
SPEAKER_1:  Alien hunting?
SPEAKER_1:  And the real problem, this is the real problem.
SPEAKER_0:  The one problem with the warp drive and the one problem.
SPEAKER_0:  Alien hunting.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes. Actually, I'd say this.
SPEAKER_1:  big problems for me with any search for life which includes UFOs.
SPEAKER_1:  all the way to fossils and Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  is that aliens have three
SPEAKER_1:  unique properties as a hypothesis.
SPEAKER_1:  One is they have essentially unbounded explanatory capability.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  There's almost no phenomenon I can show you that you couldn't explain with aliens to some degree. You could say well the aliens just have some super high tech.
SPEAKER_1:  way of creating that illusion.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  The second one would be.
SPEAKER_1:  unbounded avoidance capacity.
SPEAKER_1:  So I might see a UFO tomorrow and then the next day and then the next day and then predict I should see it.
SPEAKER_1:  on Thursday at the end of the week.
SPEAKER_1:  But then I don't see it, but I could always get out of that and say, well.
SPEAKER_1:  That's just because they chose not to come here. You know, they have this.
SPEAKER_1:  They can always avoid future observations fairly easily.
SPEAKER_1:  Um
SPEAKER_1:  If you...
SPEAKER_1:  survey an exoplanet for biosignatures and you don't see oxygen, you don't see methane, that doesn't mean there's no one living there.
SPEAKER_1:  They could always be either tricking their atmosphere, engineering it. We actually wrote a paper about that, how you can use lasers to hide your biosignatures as advanced civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Or you could just be living underground or under water or something where there's no signage
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  You can never...
SPEAKER_1:  really disproved his life on another planet or another star. It has infinite avoidance.
SPEAKER_1:  And then finally, the third one is that we have incomplete physical understanding of the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  So if I see a new phenomena, which Boyaj and Star was a good example of that, we saw this new phenomena of these strange dips we'd never seen before.
SPEAKER_1:  was hypothesized immediately this could be aliens. Like a God of the gaps.
SPEAKER_1:  but it turned out to be incomplete physical understanding.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that happens all the time in the first pulsar that was discovered.
SPEAKER_1:  Same story.
SPEAKER_1:  um, just limbo.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  somewhat tongue-in-cheek called it Little Green Man 1 because it looked a lot like the radio signature that was expected from an alien civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  But of course it turned out to be a completely new type of star that we had never seen before, which was a neutron star.
SPEAKER_1:  with these two jets coming out the top of it. And so.
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  That's a challenge. Those three things are really...
SPEAKER_1:  really difficult.
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of experimental design for a scientist to work around. Something that can explain anything.
SPEAKER_1:  avoid anything so it's almost un-falsifiable.
SPEAKER_1:  and could always just be.
SPEAKER_1:  some degree, as you said, we have this very limited knowledge of the infinite possibilities of physical law.
SPEAKER_1:  and we're probably only scratching the surface.
SPEAKER_1:  each time and we've seen it so often in history.
SPEAKER_1:  we may just be detecting some new phenomena.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, that last one.
SPEAKER_0:  I think I'm a little more okay with making mistakes on.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, which is exciting still. It's because no matter what.
SPEAKER_0:  So you might exaggerate the importance of the discovery, but the whole point.
SPEAKER_0:  Is to try to find stuff in this world that's weird and try to characterize that weirdness. Sure. You can throw a little green man as a label on it.
SPEAKER_0:  But eventually...
SPEAKER_0:  it like
SPEAKER_0:  It's as mysterious and as beautiful as interesting as little agreement that we tend to think that there's some kind of
SPEAKER_0:  Threshold.
SPEAKER_0:  but like there's all kinds of weird organisms on this earth that operate very differently than humans that are super interesting. The human mind is super interesting. I mean like uh-
SPEAKER_0:  Weirdness.
SPEAKER_0:  and complexity.
SPEAKER_0:  Is.
SPEAKER_0:  is as interesting in any of its forms as what we might think from Hollywood what aliens are
SPEAKER_0:  So like that's okay, looking for weirdnesses on Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay. That's one of the best sales pitches to do technical work.
SPEAKER_1:  is that we always have that as our fallback, that we're going to look for alien signatures.
SPEAKER_1:  If we fail, we're going to...
SPEAKER_1:  discover some awesome new physics along the way.
SPEAKER_1:  And even a
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, if any kind of signature that we detect is always going to be interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that.
SPEAKER_1:  that compels us to.
SPEAKER_1:  have not only the question of looking for life in the universe, but it gives us a strong sense of meaning.
SPEAKER_1:  scientific grounding as to why this sort of research should be funded and should be executed because it always pushes the frontiers knowledge
SPEAKER_0:  I wonder if we'll be able to discover and be open enough.
SPEAKER_0:  to a broad definition of aliens, where we see some kind of techno signature.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically like a touring test, like this thing is intelligent.
SPEAKER_0:  Hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  Like it's processing information in a very interesting way.
SPEAKER_0:  But you can say that about chemistry, you can say that about physics.
SPEAKER_0:  maybe not physics chemistry they can't just think
SPEAKER_0:  complex chemistry.
SPEAKER_0:  say that this is processing, this is storing information.
SPEAKER_0:  This is propagating information over time.
SPEAKER_0:  I want, I-
SPEAKER_0:  It's a gray area between a living organism.
SPEAKER_0:  we'll call an alien.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think that's super interesting. It's able to carry some kind of a-
SPEAKER_1:  intelligence.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, information is...
SPEAKER_1:  A really.
SPEAKER_1:  useful way to frame what we're looking for though because it
SPEAKER_1:  then you're divorced from.
SPEAKER_1:  making assumptions about even
SPEAKER_1:  civilization necessarily or anything like that.
SPEAKER_1:  any kind of information rig signature. Indeed.
SPEAKER_1:  you can take things like the light curve from Biogenstar and ask what is the minimum number of free parameters or
SPEAKER_1:  the minimum information content that must be encoded within this light curve.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  The hope is that maybe from, you know, a good example would be from a radio signature, you detect something.
SPEAKER_1:  has a thousand megabytes of parameters essentially contained within it.
SPEAKER_1:  That's.
SPEAKER_1:  pretty clearly at that point, not the product of a natural process, but at least any natural process that we could possibly...
SPEAKER_1:  Imagine without current understanding the universe
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  Thinking, even if we can't decode, which actually I'm skeptical would be able to ever decode in our lifetimes, it would probably take decades to fully.
SPEAKER_1:  ever figure out what they're trying to tell us.
SPEAKER_1:  But if there was a message there, we could at least know that there is a high information content.
SPEAKER_1:  and there is complexity and that this is a attempt.
SPEAKER_1:  communication information transfer.
SPEAKER_1:  and leave it to her.
SPEAKER_1:  subsequent generations to figure out what exactly it is they're trying to say.
SPEAKER_1:  What?
SPEAKER_0:  Again, wild question and thank you for.
SPEAKER_0:  entertaining them. I really really appreciate that.
SPEAKER_0:  but what kind of signal in our lifetime, what kind of thing do you think might happen?
SPEAKER_0:  could possibly happen.
SPEAKER_0:  where the scientific community would be convinced that.
SPEAKER_0:  There's.
SPEAKER_0:  alien civilizations out there.
SPEAKER_0:  Like what?
SPEAKER_0:  So you already said maybe a strong infrared signature for something like a Dyson Sphere.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, that's possibly that that's also in some degree a little bit ambiguous.
SPEAKER_1:  because that's.
SPEAKER_0:  challenge. So interrupt this.
SPEAKER_0:  where
SPEAKER_0:  Your brain would be like you as a scientist would be like.
SPEAKER_0:  I know it's ambiguous, but this is really weird. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  If you had some, I can imagine something like a prime number sequence.
SPEAKER_1:  or a mathematical sequence like the Fibonacci series, something being broadcast. Mathematically.
SPEAKER_0:  Proveable that this is not a physical phenomenon
SPEAKER_1:  Right, I mean, yeah, prime numbers is a pretty good case because there's no natural phenomena that produces prime number sequences. It seems to be a purely an abstract mathematical concept as far as I'm aware.
SPEAKER_1:  And so if we detected.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, you know, a series of radio blips.
SPEAKER_1:  that were following that sequence, it would-
SPEAKER_1:  pretty clear to me or it could even be in a car scene again.
SPEAKER_1:  suggested that pi could be encoded and that or you might use the hydrogen line but multiplied by pi like some very specific
SPEAKER_1:  a frequency of the universe, like a hydrogen line.
SPEAKER_1:  but multiply it by an abstract mathematical constant that would imply strongly that there was someone.
SPEAKER_1:  behind the scenes operating that.
SPEAKER_1:  amount of work at
SPEAKER_0:  I stored in which phenomena though.
SPEAKER_1:  So in that case, I think of a radio wave, but the information, I mean, we kind of toyed with us.
SPEAKER_1:  idea in a video I did about hypothetical civilization on my channel.
SPEAKER_1:  But one kind of fun way, I do want to bring this conversation towards time a little bit and thinking about not just looking for...
SPEAKER_1:  life and intelligence.
SPEAKER_1:  around us right now, but looking into the past and even into the future.
SPEAKER_1:  to some degree or communicating with the future.
SPEAKER_1:  And so we had this fun experiment of imagining a civilization that was born.
SPEAKER_1:  at the beginning of the history of the galaxy.
SPEAKER_1:  and being the first and what it would be like for them. And they would part.
SPEAKER_1:  desperately searching for evidence of life but couldn't find it.
SPEAKER_1:  And so they decided to try and leave something behind.
SPEAKER_1:  for future civilizations to discover, tell them about themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  But of course a radio signature is not gonna work there because it has a power source and that's a piece of machinery it's gonna eventually break down, it's gonna be hard to maintain that.
SPEAKER_1:  for billions of years time scale.
SPEAKER_1:  And so you wanted something that was kind of passive.
SPEAKER_1:  that doesn't require an energy source but can somehow transmit.
SPEAKER_1:  Information.
SPEAKER_1:  which is hard to think about something that satisfies those criteria.
SPEAKER_1:  But there was a proposal by one of my colleagues, Luke Arnold.
SPEAKER_1:  which inspired a lot of us in Techno Signatures.
SPEAKER_1:  And he suggested that you could build artificial transitors.
SPEAKER_1:  So you could build sheets of material that transit in front of the star.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe one.
SPEAKER_1:  thin sheet passes across first, then two, then three, then five, and seven, so you could follow the prime number sequence of these.
SPEAKER_1:  and so there'd be a clear indication.
SPEAKER_1:  that someone had manufactured those.
SPEAKER_1:  They don't require any energy source because they're just sheets of material in order of the star. They would eventually degrade from micrometeorites, maybe they would always become destabilised, but...
SPEAKER_1:  They should have lifetimes far exceeding.
SPEAKER_1:  the lifetime of any...
SPEAKER_1:  battery or mechanical electronic system that we could, at least with our technology, conceive building.
SPEAKER_1:  And so you can imagine an extending that and how could you
SPEAKER_1:  in code, not just a prime number sequence, but maybe in the spatial pattern.
SPEAKER_1:  of this very complex light curve we see.
SPEAKER_1:  you could encode more and more information through 2D shapes and
SPEAKER_1:  the way those odd quotations happen.
SPEAKER_1:  and maybe...
SPEAKER_1:  You could even encode.
SPEAKER_1:  messages and in-depth information from that. You could even imagine it being like a
SPEAKER_1:  a lower layer of information, which is just the prime number sequence, but then you look closely and you see a second layer of data.
SPEAKER_1:  the smaller.
SPEAKER_1:  Divids embedded within those that have a deeper layer of information to extract.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  And so to me, something like that would be.
SPEAKER_1:  really compelling that that was somebody who would mind if in essence just a
SPEAKER_1:  very impressive hoax.
SPEAKER_1:  That would be a pretty compelling evidence for civilization.
SPEAKER_0:  the methods.
SPEAKER_0:  of uh...
SPEAKER_0:  astronomy right now.
SPEAKER_0:  are kind of marching towards.
SPEAKER_0:  being able to better and better detect this.
SPEAKER_1:  like that.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  To some degree, it's just building bigger aperture in space, the bigger the telescope.
SPEAKER_1:  the finer.
SPEAKER_1:  ability to detect those minute signals.
SPEAKER_0:  What is the current scientific community?
SPEAKER_0:  but just the observations that are happening now.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you think they're ready for her?
SPEAKER_0:  prime number sequence.
SPEAKER_0:  in the
SPEAKER_0:  So if we're using the current method, the transit timing.
SPEAKER_0:  variation method.
SPEAKER_0:  Like.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you think?
SPEAKER_0:  You're ready. Do you have the tools?
SPEAKER_0:  to detect the prime number sequence.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  for sure. I mean, there's...
SPEAKER_1:  200,000 stars that Kepler monitored and it monitored them all the time. It took a photo of each one of them every 30 minutes, measured their brightness.
SPEAKER_1:  and it did that for four and a half years.
SPEAKER_1:  And so you have already, and Tess is doing it right now, another mission.
SPEAKER_1:  And so you have already an existing catalog and people are.
SPEAKER_1:  Genuinely scouring through each of those light curves with automated machine learning techniques. We even developed some in our own team.
SPEAKER_1:  that can look for weird behaviour.
SPEAKER_1:  We wrote a code called the weird detector for instance, that was just the most generic thing possible.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's-
SPEAKER_1:  Don't assume anything about the signal shape. Just look for anything that repeats. The signal shape can be anything. Can we kind of learn the template of the signal from the data itself? And then it's like a template matching filter to see if that repeats many, many times in the data.
SPEAKER_1:  And so we actually applied that and found.
SPEAKER_1:  A bunch of interesting stuff, but we didn't see.
SPEAKER_1:  anything that was the prime number sequence, at least in the capital data.
SPEAKER_1:  That's 200,000 stars.
SPEAKER_1:  Which sounds like a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  But compared to 200 billion stars in the Milky Way, it's really just scratching the surface.
SPEAKER_1:  So one.
SPEAKER_0:  because there could be something much more generalizable than the prime number sequence.
SPEAKER_0:  It's ultimately the question of...
SPEAKER_0:  signal that's very difficult to compress.
SPEAKER_0:  in the general.
SPEAKER_0:  sensible compress means. So maybe as we get better and better machine learning methods.
SPEAKER_0:  that automatically figure out.
SPEAKER_0:  analyze the data to understand how to compress it.
SPEAKER_0:  You'll be able to discover data that's for some reason not compressible.
SPEAKER_0:  But then, you know, compression really...
SPEAKER_0:  is a bottomless pit because like.
SPEAKER_0:  That's really what intelligence is, is being able to compress and
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. And to some degree the more you.
SPEAKER_1:  I would imagine, I don't work in compression algorithms, but I would imagine the more you compress your signal, the more you compress your signal.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  The...
SPEAKER_1:  The more assumptions that kind of go on behalf of the decoder, the more skilled they really have to be.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, some of the
SPEAKER_1:  a prime number sequence is completely...
SPEAKER_1:  unencoded information, essentially.
SPEAKER_1:  But if you look at the Arecibo message.
SPEAKER_1:  they were fairly careful with their pixelation of this simple image they sent.
SPEAKER_1:  to try and...
SPEAKER_1:  make it as interpretable as possible to be.
SPEAKER_1:  even a dumb alien would be able to figure out what we're trying to show them here because
SPEAKER_1:  There's all sorts of.
SPEAKER_1:  conventions and rules that are built in that we tend to presume when we design our messages.
SPEAKER_1:  And so if your messages.
SPEAKER_1:  assuming they know how to do an MP3.
SPEAKER_1:  Decoder.
SPEAKER_1:  particular compression algorithm.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm sure they could eventually reverse engineer it and figure it out, but you're, you're making it.
SPEAKER_1:  harder for them to get to that.
SPEAKER_1:  So maybe I always think you probably would have a two tier system, right? You'd probably have some lower tier key.
SPEAKER_1:  system and then maybe beneath that you'd have a deeper compressed layer of more in-depth information.
SPEAKER_1:  What about maybe...
SPEAKER_0:  observing
SPEAKER_0:  physical actual physical objects. So first let me go to your tweet as a source of inspiration.
SPEAKER_0:  You tweeted that it's interesting to ponder that if Oort clouds...
SPEAKER_0:  or ever mind.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  the systems of alien civilizations.
SPEAKER_0:  mining equipment from billions of years ago could be in our ore cloud since the ore clouds.
SPEAKER_0:  they extend really, really, really, really far outside the actual star.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  that mining equipment, just like basic boring.
SPEAKER_0:  mining equipment out there. I don't know if there's something interesting to say about ore claws themselves that
SPEAKER_0:  that are interesting to you and about possible.
SPEAKER_0:  Non-shiny.
SPEAKER_0:  light emitting mining equipment from alien civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean, that's what I mean, that's kind of the beauty of.
SPEAKER_1:  the field of technosignatures and looking for life.
SPEAKER_1:  is.
SPEAKER_1:  You can find inspiration and intellectual joy in just the smallest little thing that starts a whole thread of
SPEAKER_1:  building upon it and wondering about the implications.
SPEAKER_1:  And so in this case, I was just really struck by.
SPEAKER_1:  We kind of mentioned this a little bit earlier, the idea that...
SPEAKER_1:  Stars are not static, we tend to think of the galaxy...
SPEAKER_1:  as having stars in a certain location from the center of the galaxy, and they kind of live there, but...
SPEAKER_1:  In truth, the stars are not any.
SPEAKER_1:  orbiting around the center of the galaxy
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  But those orbits are themselves changing over time they're processing.
SPEAKER_1:  And so in fact, the orbits look more like a spirograph if you've ever done those as a kid. Ca
SPEAKER_1:  whirl around and trace out all sorts of strange patterns.
SPEAKER_1:  And so the stars intersect with one another.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  The current closest star to us is Proxima Centauri.
SPEAKER_1:  which is about 4.2 light years away, but it will not always be the closest star and over millions of years it will be supplanted by other stars.
SPEAKER_1:  In fact, stars will come even closer than Proxima within just a couple of light years.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's been happening, not just we can project that will happen over the next few million years.
SPEAKER_1:  But that's been happening presumably throughout the entire history of the galaxy for billions of years.
SPEAKER_1:  And so if you went back in time, there would have been all sorts of different nearest stars at different stages of the Earth's history.
SPEAKER_1:  and those stars are so close.
SPEAKER_1:  that they're Ork Clouds.
SPEAKER_1:  do intermix with one another so the Oort Cloud can extend out to even a light year or two around the earth.
SPEAKER_1:  debate about exactly where it ends. It probably doesn't really have a definitive end, but kind of more just kind of peters out more and more and more.
SPEAKER_1:  as you go further away.
SPEAKER_0:  By the way, for people who don't know, NorCloud, I don't know what the technical definition is, but a bunch of rocks that kind of, no.
SPEAKER_0:  Objects.
SPEAKER_0:  that orbit the star, and they can extend really, really far.
SPEAKER_1:  These are objects that probably are mostly icy rich.
SPEAKER_1:  They were probably formed fairly similar distances to Jupiter and Saturn.
SPEAKER_1:  but were scattered out through the interactions of those giant planets.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  We see a circular disk of objects around us.
SPEAKER_1:  which kind of looks like the asteroid belt, but just further away called the Kuiper belt.
SPEAKER_1:  And then further beyond that, you get the orc cloud.
SPEAKER_1:  And the all cloud is not a disk, it's just a sphere, it kind of surrounds us in all directions.
SPEAKER_1:  So these are objects that were scattered out.
SPEAKER_1:  through three dimensionally in all different directions.
SPEAKER_1:  And so those objects are potentially.
SPEAKER_1:  resources for us, especially if you were planning.
SPEAKER_1:  to do an interstellar mission one day.
SPEAKER_1:  you might want to mine the water that's embedded within those and use that as either oxygen or fuel for your rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  And so it's quite possible.
SPEAKER_1:  There's also some rare earth metals and things like that as well, but it's quite possible that a civilization might use or cloud objects as a jumping off point.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  or
SPEAKER_1:  Or in the Kuiper Belt, you have things like Planet 9 evens. There might even be objects beyond in the Oort cloud, which are actually planet-like that we just cannot detect.
SPEAKER_1:  These objects are very, very faint, so that's why they're so hard to see. I mean, even Planet 9.
SPEAKER_1:  it's hypothesized to exist, but we've not been able to confirm its existence because
SPEAKER_1:  It's at something like a thousand AU away from us, a thousand times the distance of the Earth from the Sun.
SPEAKER_1:  And so even though it's probably larger than the Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  the amount of light it reflects from the sun. The sun is what just looks like a star at that point, so far away from it.
SPEAKER_1:  it barely reflects anything back. It's extremely difficult to detect.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's all sorts of wonders that may be lurking out in the outer solar system.
SPEAKER_1:  And so this leads you to wonder.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  in the Ork Cloud.
SPEAKER_1:  That Oort cloud must have intermixed with other Oort clouds in the past.
SPEAKER_1:  And so what fraction of the cloud is...
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  belongs to us, belongs to what was scattered from Jupiter and Saturn.
SPEAKER_1:  What fraction of it?
SPEAKER_1:  could in fact be.
SPEAKER_1:  interstellar visitors.
SPEAKER_1:  And of course, we've got excited about this recently because of Oumuamua, this interstellar asteroid.
SPEAKER_1:  which seemed to be at the time the first evidence of an interstellar.
SPEAKER_1:  object.
SPEAKER_1:  But.
SPEAKER_1:  When you think about the Alt Cloud intermixing.
SPEAKER_1:  It may be that a large fraction of comets, comets are seeded from the Oort cloud.
SPEAKER_1:  eventually come in.
SPEAKER_1:  Some of those comments may indeed.
SPEAKER_1:  have been interstellar in the first place that we just didn't know about.
SPEAKER_1:  through this process.
SPEAKER_1:  There even is an example, I can't remember the name, there's an example of a comet that has a very peculiar spectral signature that has been hypothesized.
SPEAKER_1:  to have actually been.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's not a visitor, but one that was.
SPEAKER_1:  essentially sourced through this Ork Cloud mixing.
SPEAKER_1:  And so this is kind of intriguing.
SPEAKER_1:  It also, you know, the outer solar system is just such a.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like at the bottom of the ocean, we know so little about what's on the bottom of our own planet's ocean.
SPEAKER_1:  And we know next to nothing about what's in the outskirts of our own solar system. It's all darkness.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So like.
SPEAKER_0:  That's one of the things is...
SPEAKER_0:  To understand the phenomena, we need light.
SPEAKER_0:  and we need to see how light interacts with it or would light emanate from it
SPEAKER_0:  with most of our universe is darkness. So it's...
SPEAKER_0:  There could be a lot of interesting stuff. I mean, this is where your interest is with the cool worlds.
SPEAKER_0:  interesting stuff lurks in the darkness, right?
SPEAKER_1:  Basically all of us, you know, 400 years of astronomy, our only window into the universe has been light.
SPEAKER_1:  And that has only changed quite recently with the discovery of gravitational waves.
SPEAKER_1:  That's now a new window.
SPEAKER_1:  And hopefully, well, to some degree, I guess, solar neutrinos we've been detecting for our but they come from the Sun, not interstellar space.
SPEAKER_1:  but we may be able to soon detect neutrino messages as even been hypothesized as a way of communicating between civilizations as well, or just do neutrino telescopes to study the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  And so there's a growing interest in what we call multi-messenger.
SPEAKER_1:  astronomy now, so not just messages from light but messages from these.
SPEAKER_1:  other.
SPEAKER_1:  physical
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  packets of information that are coming our way.
SPEAKER_1:  But when it comes to the outer solar system...
SPEAKER_1:  Light really is our only window. There's two.
SPEAKER_1:  There's two ways of doing that. One is you detect the light from the Aort Cloud object itself, which as I just said is very, very difficult.
SPEAKER_1:  There's another trick.
SPEAKER_1:  which we do in the Kuiper belt.
SPEAKER_1:  especially
SPEAKER_1:  and that's called an occultation. And so sometimes those objects will just...
SPEAKER_1:  pass in front of a distant star just coincidentally.
SPEAKER_1:  These are very, very brief moments. They last for less than a second.
SPEAKER_1:  and so you have to have a very fast camera to detect them.
SPEAKER_1:  Which conventionally astronomers don't usually build fast cameras. Most of the phenomena we observe occurs on hours, minutes, days even.
SPEAKER_1:  but now we're developing cameras which can take thousands of images per second.
SPEAKER_1:  and yet do it at the kind of astronomical fidelity that we need for this kind of precise measurement.
SPEAKER_1:  And so you can see.
SPEAKER_1:  these very fast dips, you even get these kind of diffraction patterns that come around, which are really cool to look at.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's
SPEAKER_1:  I kind of love it because it's almost like passive radar.
SPEAKER_1:  You have these pinpricks of light. Imagine having to do really weird stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  that you live in a giant black sphere.
SPEAKER_1:  but there's these little pinholes that have been poked.
SPEAKER_1:  and through those pinholes almost laser light is shining through.
SPEAKER_1:  and inside this black sphere.
SPEAKER_1:  There are unknown things wandering around, drifting around that we are trying to discover.
SPEAKER_1:  and sometimes they will pass in front of those little pencil thin laser beams.
SPEAKER_1:  block something out so we can tell that it's there.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's not an active radar, because we didn't actually...
SPEAKER_1:  beam anything out and get a reflection off, which is what the sun does. The sun's light comes off and comes back. That's how I can activate our system.
SPEAKER_1:  It's more like a passive radar system where.
SPEAKER_1:  We are just listening very intently.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm kind of so fascinated by that, the idea that we could.
SPEAKER_1:  Map out.
SPEAKER_1:  D.
SPEAKER_1:  rich architecture of the outer solar system.
SPEAKER_1:  just by doing something that we could have done potentially for a long time, okay, which is just listening in the right way, just...
SPEAKER_1:  just tuning our instrumentation to the correct.
SPEAKER_1:  way of not listening but
SPEAKER_1:  viewing the universe to catch those objects.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, it's really fascinating. It seems almost obvious that your efforts.
SPEAKER_0:  when projected out in over like 100, 200 years.
SPEAKER_0:  We'll have a really good map.
SPEAKER_0:  through even methods like basically transit timing, high resolution transit timing.
SPEAKER_0:  but basically the planetary and the...
SPEAKER_0:  planet's satellite movements.
SPEAKER_0:  of all the different.
SPEAKER_1:  star systems out there.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and it could revolutionize the way we think about the solar system. I mean.
SPEAKER_1:  That revolution has happened several times in the past when we discovered Vesta in the 19th century.
SPEAKER_1:  That was, I think, the-
SPEAKER_1:  the seventh planet for a while or the eighth planet when it was first discovered and then we discovered Ceres and...
SPEAKER_1:  There was a bunch of asteroid objects, JNES.
SPEAKER_1:  And so for a while the textbooks had.
SPEAKER_1:  There was something like 13 planets in the solar system.
SPEAKER_1:  And then that was just a new capability that was emerging to test those small objects.
SPEAKER_1:  And then we ripped that up and said, no, no, we're gonna.
SPEAKER_1:  change the definition of a planet.
SPEAKER_1:  And then the same thing happened when we started looking at the outer skirts of the solar system. And again, we found Eris, we found Sedna.
SPEAKER_1:  these objects which.
SPEAKER_1:  resembled Pluto.
SPEAKER_1:  and the more and more of them we found, make make.
SPEAKER_1:  And eventually we again had to rethink.
SPEAKER_1:  the way we even contextualize what a planet is.
SPEAKER_1:  what the nature of the outer solar system is.
SPEAKER_1:  So regardless as to what you think about the debate about whether Pluto should be devoted or not which I know often evokes a lot of strong feelings it is an incredible
SPEAKER_1:  achievement.
SPEAKER_1:  that we.
SPEAKER_1:  were able to.
SPEAKER_1:  transform.
SPEAKER_1:  view of the solar system in a matter of years just by basically, you know, charge coupled.
SPEAKER_1:  devices, the things that's in cameras.
SPEAKER_1:  Though the invention of that device allowed us to detect objects which were much further away, much fainter.
SPEAKER_1:  and revealed all of this stuff that was there all along. And so that's the beauty of astronomy. It's just.
SPEAKER_1:  so much to discover.
SPEAKER_1:  and even in our own backyard.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you ever think about this? What are the things that you can't even imagine?
SPEAKER_0:  that will completely change astronomy over the next 100 years.
SPEAKER_0:  Like if you transport yourself forward.
SPEAKER_0:  100 years, what are the things?
SPEAKER_0:  that will blow your mind when you look at, wait, what?
SPEAKER_0:  Would it be?
SPEAKER_0:  just a very high resolution mapping of things like.
SPEAKER_0:  Holy crap, like one surprising thing might be.
SPEAKER_0:  Holy crap, there's...
SPEAKER_0:  Earth-like moons everywhere.
SPEAKER_0:  Another one could be just totally different devices for sensing.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I think usually astronomy moves forward dramatically and science in general.
SPEAKER_1:  when you have a new technological capability come online for the first time.
SPEAKER_1:  And we kind of just gave examples of that there with the solar system.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  what kind of new capabilities might emerge the next 100 years. The capability I'd love to see.
SPEAKER_1:  is not just, I mean, in the next 10, 20 years, we're hoping to take these pale blue dot images we spoke about.
SPEAKER_1:  That requires building something like JVST, but on an even larger scale.
SPEAKER_1:  and optimize for direct imaging, you don't have to have either coronagraph.
SPEAKER_1:  or a star shade or something to block out the starlight.
SPEAKER_1:  and reveal those pale blue dots.
SPEAKER_1:  So in the next sort of decades, I think that's the...
SPEAKER_1:  achievement that we can look forward to in our lifetimes is to see photos of.
SPEAKER_1:  Earths?
SPEAKER_1:  going beyond that maybe in our lifetimes, towards the end of our lifetimes perhaps. I'd love it if we-
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's technically possible as Breakthrough Starshot are giving us a lot of encouragement with.
SPEAKER_1:  to maybe send a small probe to the nearest stars and start actually taking high resolution images of these objects.
SPEAKER_1:  There's only so much you can do from far away.
SPEAKER_1:  if you want to have.
SPEAKER_1:  And we can see it in the solar system. I mean, there's only so much you can learn about Europa by pointing Hubble Space Telescope at it, but if you really want to understand that.
SPEAKER_1:  that moon, you're going to have to send something to orbit it.
SPEAKER_1:  hopefully land on it and drill down to the surface.
SPEAKER_1:  And so the idea of even taking a flyby and doing a snapshot photo that gets beam back.
SPEAKER_1:  that could be.
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't even have to be more than 100 pixels by 100 pixels. Even that would be a completely game-changing capability to be able to truly image these objects.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe.
SPEAKER_1:  at home in our own solar system.
SPEAKER_1:  we can certainly get to a point where we produce crude maps of exoplanets.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  one of the kind of the ultimate limit of what a telescope could do.
SPEAKER_1:  is given by its size.
SPEAKER_1:  And so the largest telescope you could probably ever build would be one that was the size of the sun.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a clever trick for doing this without physically building a telescope that's the size of the sun.
SPEAKER_1:  and that's to use the sun as a gravitational lens.
SPEAKER_1:  This was proposed, I think, by Von Eschlaman in like 1979, but it builds upon Einstein's.
SPEAKER_1:  The year of general relativity of course there is
SPEAKER_1:  a warping of light.
SPEAKER_1:  a bending of light from the Sun's gravitational field.
SPEAKER_1:  And so a distant starlight, it's like a magnifying glass, anything that bends light.
SPEAKER_1:  is basically can be used as a telescope.
SPEAKER_1:  it's going to bend light to a point.
SPEAKER_1:  Now it turns out the sun's gravity is not.
SPEAKER_1:  strong enough to create a
SPEAKER_1:  particularly great telescope here because the focus point...
SPEAKER_1:  is really out in the Kuiper belt. It's at 550 astronomical units away.
SPEAKER_1:  the Earth, so 550 times further away from the Sun than we are.
SPEAKER_1:  And we've, you know, that's beyond any of our spacecraft we've ever gone.
SPEAKER_1:  So you have to send a spacecraft to that distance, which would take...
SPEAKER_1:  30, 40 years.
SPEAKER_1:  even optimistically improving our chemical propulsion system significantly.
SPEAKER_1:  you'd have to bound it into that orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  But then...
SPEAKER_1:  You could use the entire sun as your telescope.
SPEAKER_1:  And with that kind of capability, you could image planets to
SPEAKER_1:  kilometer scale resolution from afar.
SPEAKER_1:  That really makes you wonder, I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  If we can conceive, maybe we can't engineer it.
SPEAKER_1:  But if we can conceive of such a device...
SPEAKER_1:  what might other civilizations be currently observing about our own planet?
SPEAKER_1:  NUMB
SPEAKER_1:  End.
SPEAKER_1:  Perhaps that is a...
SPEAKER_1:  why nobody is visiting us because there is so much you can do from afar.
SPEAKER_1:  them that's enough. Maybe they can get to the point where they can detect our radio leakage.
SPEAKER_1:  They can touch restaurant in television signals.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, they can.
SPEAKER_1:  map out our surfaces, they can tell we have cities, they can even do infrared mapping of the heat island effect and this kind of stuff they can tell.
SPEAKER_1:  the chemical composition of our planet.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that might be enough. Maybe they don't need to come down to the surface and study anthropology and see what our civilization is like.
SPEAKER_1:  But there's certainly...
SPEAKER_1:  a huge amount you can do, which is significantly cheaper to some degree than flying there.
SPEAKER_1:  just by exploiting cleverly the physics of the universe itself.
SPEAKER_1:  So your intuition is...
SPEAKER_0:  and that's very well made to be true, the observation.
SPEAKER_0:  might be way easier than travel.
SPEAKER_0:  from our perspective, from an alien perspective. Like we could-
SPEAKER_0:  get very high resolution.
SPEAKER_0:  imaging.
SPEAKER_1:  before we can ever get there. It depends on what-
SPEAKER_1:  information you want. If you want to know the chemical composition
SPEAKER_1:  and you want to know kilometer scale maps of the planet.
SPEAKER_1:  then you could do that from afar with some...
SPEAKER_1:  version of these kind of gravitational lenses.
SPEAKER_1:  If you want to do better than that, if you want to image a newspaper, selling the porch of somebody's house, you're going to have to fly there. There's no way unless you had.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, a touch get the size of such serious a star or something. You just simply cannot.
SPEAKER_1:  collect enough light to do that from many light years away.
SPEAKER_1:  So there is certainly...
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  reasons why visiting will always have its place depending on what kind of information you want.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  We've proposed in my team actually that
SPEAKER_1:  The Sun is...
SPEAKER_1:  is a
SPEAKER_1:  is the ultimate pinnacle of telescope design.
SPEAKER_1:  But flying to 1000 AU is a real pain in the butt because it's just going to take so long.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  A more practical way of achieving this might be to use the Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  Now the Earth doesn't have anywhere near enough gravity to create a substantial gravitational lens.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, but it has an atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  and that atmosphere refracts light, it bends light. So whenever you see a sunset.
SPEAKER_1:  just as the sun setting below her horizon.
SPEAKER_1:  It's actually already.
SPEAKER_1:  beneath the horizon, it's just that the light is bending.
SPEAKER_1:  through the atmosphere, it's actually already about half a degree down beneath, and what you're seeing is that.
SPEAKER_1:  is that curvature of the light path.
SPEAKER_1:  And your brain interprets it of course to be following a straight line because your brain always thinks that.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  And so you can use that bending whenever you have bending, you have a telescope. And so we've proposed to my team that you could use this refraction.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  Similarly, create an Earth-sized telescope.
SPEAKER_1:  called the Terrascope. The Terrascope. Yeah. Great video on that. Yeah. Good mid year to straight from like kind of like offici away on re- advance strfil in da
SPEAKER_1:  Do you have a paper on the telescope? I do. Yeah. Great. Um, sometimes get confused this because they've heard of an earth sized telescope because of the, may have heard of the event horizon telescope, which took an image of, um, what's the taken image right now at the center of our black hole.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's very impressive.
SPEAKER_1:  previously did Messier 87.
SPEAKER_1:  and nearby supermassive black hole.
SPEAKER_1:  And so those images were interferometric. So they were small telescopes scattered across the earth.
SPEAKER_1:  and they combine the light paths together interferometrically.
SPEAKER_1:  to create effectively an earth-sized.
SPEAKER_1:  angle resolution.
SPEAKER_1:  Telescopes always have two properties. There's the angular resolution, which is how small of a thing you can see.
SPEAKER_1:  on the surface and then there's the magnification.
SPEAKER_1:  How much brighter does that object get versus just your eye versus some small object?
SPEAKER_1:  not what
SPEAKER_1:  what the Event Horizon Telescope did.
SPEAKER_1:  It traded off.
SPEAKER_1:  amplification or magnification.
SPEAKER_1:  4
SPEAKER_1:  for the angular resolution. That's what it wanted. It wanted that high angular resolution, but it doesn't really have much photon collecting power because each telescope individually is very small.
SPEAKER_1:  The telescope is different because
SPEAKER_1:  It is literally collecting light with a...
SPEAKER_1:  light bucket, which is essentially the size of the
SPEAKER_1:  And so that gives you both benefits potentially, not only the high angular resolution.
SPEAKER_1:  that a large aperture promises you, but also actually physically collects all those photons so you can detect light from very, very far away, through outer edges of the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  We propose this as a possible.
SPEAKER_1:  future.
SPEAKER_1:  a technological way of achieving these extreme.
SPEAKER_1:  Goals, ambitious goals we have in astronomy.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's a very difficult system to test because you essentially have to fly out to these focus points.
SPEAKER_1:  and these focus points lie beyond the moon, so you have to have...
SPEAKER_1:  someone who was willing to fly beyond the moon and hitchhike an experimental telescope onto it and do that cheaply. If it was something doing low earth orbit, it'd be easy. You could just attach a CubeSat to the next Falcon 9 rocket or something.
SPEAKER_1:  test it out, it'll probably only cost you.
SPEAKER_1:  few tens of thousands of dollars, maybe hundreds of thousand dollars, but to...
SPEAKER_1:  There's basically no one who flies out that far.
SPEAKER_1:  except for bespoke missions such as a mission that's going to Mars or something that would pass through that.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of space and they.
SPEAKER_1:  typically don't have a lot of.
SPEAKER_1:  leeway in excess payload that they're willing to strap on for.
SPEAKER_1:  radical experiments.
SPEAKER_1:  That's been the problem with it. In theory, it should work beautifully, but it's a very difficult idea to experimentally test.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you elaborate why the focal point is that far away?
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  You get about half a degree bend from the Earth's atmosphere when you're looking at the sun at the horizon, and you get that.
SPEAKER_1:  times over if you're outside of the planet's atmosphere because it comes, you know, the star is half a bend to you still on the horizon and half a degree
SPEAKER_1:  back out the other way so you get about a one degree bend.
SPEAKER_1:  Check the rates of the Earth, which is about 7,000 kilometers.
SPEAKER_1:  and do your arctan function, you'll end up with a distance that's about, it's actually the inner focal point is about two thirds the distance of the Earth-Moon system.
SPEAKER_1:  The problem with that inner focal point is not useful.
SPEAKER_1:  because that light ray path had to basically scrape the surface of the Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  So it passes through the clouds, it passes through all the thick atmosphere, and it gets a lot of extinction along the way.
SPEAKER_1:  If you go higher up in altitude...
SPEAKER_1:  you get less extinction. In fact, you can even go above the clouds. And so that's even better because the clouds obviously are gonna be a pain in the neck if you're doing anything optical.
SPEAKER_1:  But the problem with that is that the atmosphere, because it gets thinner at higher altitude...
SPEAKER_1:  it bends like less.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that pushes the focal point out.
SPEAKER_1:  So the most useful focal point is actually about three or four times the distance of the Earth-Moon separation.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that's what we call one of the Lagrange points, essentially.
SPEAKER_1:  And so there was a stable orbit, kind of the outermost stable orbit you could have around the Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  So the atmosphere.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  does bad things to the signal.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's absorbing light.
SPEAKER_0:  possible to reconstruct.
SPEAKER_0:  3, 2, 2.
SPEAKER_0:  to remove the noise, whatever. So it's just strength. It's not nothing else.
SPEAKER_1:  It's possible to reconstruct, I mean to some degree we do this as a technology called adaptive optics.
SPEAKER_1:  that can correct for what's called wavefront errors that happen through the Earth's atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  The Earth's atmosphere is turbulent. It is not a-
SPEAKER_1:  single plane of air of the same density. There's all kind of wiggles and currents in the air.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  Each little layer is bending light in slightly different ways. So the light actually kind of follows a wiggly path on its way down.
SPEAKER_1:  What that means is that...
SPEAKER_1:  two light rays which are traveling at slightly different.
SPEAKER_1:  spatial separations from each other.
SPEAKER_1:  will arrive at the detector at different times, because one maybe goes on more or less a straight path and the one wiggles down a bit more before it arrives. So you have an incoherent.
SPEAKER_1:  um, light source.
SPEAKER_1:  And when you're trying to image reconstruction, you always want a coherent light source. So the way they correct for this is that this
SPEAKER_1:  If this path had to travel a little bit faster.
SPEAKER_1:  the straight one goes faster and the wiggly one takes longer.
SPEAKER_1:  The mirror is deformable. And so you actually bend the mirror on this, on the, on the straight one down a little bit to make it an equivalent light path distance.
SPEAKER_1:  So the mirror itself has all these little actuators.
SPEAKER_1:  It's actually made up of like thousands of little elements, almost looks like a liquid mirror.
SPEAKER_1:  because they can manipulate it in real time.
SPEAKER_1:  And so they scan the atmosphere with a laser beam to tell what the deformations are in the atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  and then make the corrections to the mirror to account for it. That's amazing. So you could, you could do something like this for the terrorist group, but it would be.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  It's cheaper and easier to go above the atmosphere.
SPEAKER_0:  I just fly out.
SPEAKER_1:  I think so. It would be very, it's a very, that's a very challenging thing to do. And normally when you do adaptive optics, as it's called, you're looking straight up. So you're very close to straight up.
SPEAKER_1:  If you look at the horizon, we basically never do astronomical observations on the horizon.
SPEAKER_1:  because you're looking through more atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  If you go straight up, you're looking at the thinnest portion atmosphere possible. But as you go closer and closer towards the horizon, you're increasing what we call the air mass, the amount of air you have to travel through.
SPEAKER_1:  So here it's kind of the worst case because you're going through the entire atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  In and out again with a pteroscope.
SPEAKER_1:  So you'd need a very impressive adaptive optics system to create for that. objects flight lime
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I would say it's probably simpler, at least for test proof of principle.
SPEAKER_1:  just to test it with.
SPEAKER_1:  with having some satellite that was at a much wider orbit.
SPEAKER_0:  Now, speaking of traveling.
SPEAKER_0:  out into deep space. You already mentioned this a little bit.
SPEAKER_0:  You are...
SPEAKER_0:  made a beautiful video called The Journey to the End of the Universe.
SPEAKER_0:  And sort of at the start of that, you're talking about office and Tari.
SPEAKER_0:  So what would it take for humans?
SPEAKER_0:  of four.
SPEAKER_0:  human-like creatures to travel out.
SPEAKER_1:  to Alpha Centauri.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a few different ways of doing it, I suppose.
SPEAKER_1:  One is it depends on how fast your ship is. That's always going to be the determining factor.
SPEAKER_1:  If we devised some.
SPEAKER_1:  inter-side proportion system that could travel a fraction of the speed of light.
SPEAKER_1:  than we could do in our lifetimes.
SPEAKER_1:  Which is, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  But people normally...
SPEAKER_1:  dream of when I think about instilled propulsion and travel.
SPEAKER_1:  that you could literally.
SPEAKER_1:  Step onto the spacecraft, maybe a few years later, you step off and have a Centauri B.
SPEAKER_1:  you walk around the surface and come back and visit your family. There would be of course a lot of relativistic time dilation as a result of that trip.
SPEAKER_1:  you would have aged a lot less than people back on earth by traveling close to the speed of light for some fraction of time
SPEAKER_1:  hum.
SPEAKER_1:  The challenge of this of course is that we have no such propulsion system that can achieve this.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_0:  But you think it's possible, like, so you, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... you have a paper called the hill drive
SPEAKER_0:  fuel-free relativistic propulsion of large masses via recycled boomerang photons.
SPEAKER_0:  So do you think, first of all, what is that? And second of all,
SPEAKER_0:  how difficult are alternate propulsion systems.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so.
SPEAKER_1:  The.
SPEAKER_1:  Before I took in the Hayley drive, there was...
SPEAKER_1:  There was an idea, because I think the Halo Drive...
SPEAKER_1:  is not gonna solve this problem.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll talk about the Halo drive in a moment, but the Halo drive is useful for a civilization, which is a bit more advanced than that that has spread across the stars.
SPEAKER_1:  and is looking for a cheap highway system.
SPEAKER_1:  to get across the galaxy.
SPEAKER_1:  for that first step.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Cause just to context that.
SPEAKER_1:  the halo drive requires a black hole. So that's why you're not gonna be able to do this on the earth right now.
SPEAKER_1:  But there are lots of black cars in the Milky Way, so that's the good news. So we'll come to that in a moment. But if you're trying to travel to Afsintory...
SPEAKER_1:  Without a black hole.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  than the most.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, there were some ideas out there. There was a project Daedalus and project Icarus that were two projects at the.
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  British Interplanetary Society conjured up on a 20-30 year timescale.
SPEAKER_1:  and they ask themselves if we.
SPEAKER_1:  took existing and speculatively.
SPEAKER_1:  but realistic attempts at future technology that are emerging over the next few decades.
SPEAKER_1:  How far could we push instead of...
SPEAKER_1: ordo.blogspot.com
SPEAKER_1:  Ahem, no Settledon.
SPEAKER_1:  fusion drives in that. So if we had the ability to essentially...
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  either detonate, you can always imagine that kind of nuclear fission or nuclear fusion bombs going off behind the spacecraft and propelling it that way.
SPEAKER_1:  or having some kind of successful nuclear fusion reaction.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  which obviously we haven't really demonstrated yet as a propulsion system.
SPEAKER_1:  then you could achieve something like 10% the speed of light in their systems. But these are...
SPEAKER_1:  huge spacecrafts. I think you need a huge spacecraft if you're going to take people along.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, the conversation recently has actually switched and that's, that idea is kind of antiquated now.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Most of us have kind of given up an idea of
SPEAKER_1:  people physically, biologically.
SPEAKER_1:  stepping on board the spacecraft.
SPEAKER_1:  And maybe we'll be sending something that's more like a micro probe that maybe just weighs a gram or two.
SPEAKER_1:  and that's much easier to accelerate. You could push that with a laser system to very high speed.
SPEAKER_1:  get it to maybe 20% of the speed of light.
SPEAKER_1:  It has to survive the journey, probably a large fraction of them won't survive the journey, but they're cheap enough that you could maybe manufacture millions of them.
SPEAKER_1:  and some of them do arrive and able to send back an image or
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe even if you wanted to have a person there.
SPEAKER_1:  We might have some.
SPEAKER_1:  where you're doing like a telepresence or some kind of delayed telepresence or
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  some kind of reconstruction of the planet, which is sent back. So you can digitally interact with that environment in a way which is
SPEAKER_1:  not real time, but representative of what that planet would be like to be on the surface. So we might be more like digital visitors to these planets.
SPEAKER_1:  Certainly far.
SPEAKER_1:  easier practically to do that than physically.
SPEAKER_1:  forcing this.
SPEAKER_1:  wet.
SPEAKER_1:  chunk of meat to fly across space to do that.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  And so that's maybe.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, something we can imagine down the road.
SPEAKER_1:  The Halo drive as I said is thinking even further ahead.
SPEAKER_1:  And if you did want to...
SPEAKER_1:  launch large masses.
SPEAKER_1:  large masses could even be.
SPEAKER_1:  planet-sized things in the case of the halo drive.
SPEAKER_1:  You can use black holes.
SPEAKER_1:  So this is kind of...
SPEAKER_1:  a trick of physics. You know, I often think of...
SPEAKER_1:  the universe is like a big computer game.
SPEAKER_1:  and you're trying to find.
SPEAKER_1:  cheat codes, hacks, exploits, the...
SPEAKER_1:  the universe didn't intend for you to use, but once you find them you can
SPEAKER_1:  address all sorts of interesting capabilities that you didn't previously have.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  and um...
SPEAKER_1:  The Halo Drive does that with black holes. So if you have two black holes, which is a very common situation, a binary black hole.
SPEAKER_1:  And they're inspiring towards each other. LIGOs detected, I think, dozens of these things, moving over 100 at this point.
SPEAKER_1:  and these things as they merge together.
SPEAKER_1:  They.
SPEAKER_1:  the pre-merger phase, they're orbiting very, very fast, even close to the speed of light.
SPEAKER_1:  And so Freeman Dyson, before he passed away, I think in the 70s,
SPEAKER_1:  provocative paper called gravitational machines and he suggested that you could use neutron stars as a interstellar propulsion system
SPEAKER_1:  And Neutron Stars are sort of the...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  the lower mass version of a binary black hole system essentially.
SPEAKER_1:  In this case, he suggested just doing gravitational slingshot, just fly your spacecraft.
SPEAKER_1:  into this.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  very
SPEAKER_1:  Compact.
SPEAKER_1:  and relativistic binary system. And you do need neutron stars because if there were two stars, they'd be physically touching each other.
SPEAKER_1:  So the neutron stars are so small, like 10 kilometers across, they can get really close to each other and have these very, very fast orbits with respect to each other.
SPEAKER_1:  You shoot your spacecraft through, right through the mineralite, right through the eye of a needle.
SPEAKER_1:  and you do a slingshot around one of them.
SPEAKER_1:  and you do it around the one that's coming towards you. So one will be coming away, one will be coming towards you at any one point.
SPEAKER_1:  And then you could basically steal some of the kinetic energy in the slingshot. In principle, you can set up to twice the...
SPEAKER_1:  speed.
SPEAKER_1:  You can take your speed.
SPEAKER_1:  and it becomes.
SPEAKER_1:  Your speed plus twice the speed of the Neutron Star in this case. And that will be your new speed after the slingshot.
SPEAKER_1:  This seems great because it's just free energy basically you're not
SPEAKER_1:  doing it, you know, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  generate, you don't have a nuclear power reactor or anything to generate this, you're just stealing it.
SPEAKER_1:  And indeed you can get to relativistic speeds this way. So I loved that paper.
SPEAKER_1:  But I had a criticism.
SPEAKER_1:  And the criticism was that this is like trying to fly your ship into a blender, right? This is this is two neutron stars.
SPEAKER_1:  which have huge tidal forces.
SPEAKER_1:  and they're whipping around each other once every second or even less than a second.
SPEAKER_1:  and you're trying to fly your spaceship and do this maneuver that is pretty precarious.
SPEAKER_1:  And so it just didn't seem practical to me to do this, but I loved it.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I took that idea and this is how science is. It's iterative. It's, it's, you take a previous great man's idea and you just sort of maybe slightly tweak and improve it.
SPEAKER_1:  That's how I see the Hello Drive.
SPEAKER_1:  And I just suggested, why not replace those out for black holes?
SPEAKER_1:  which is certainly very common.
SPEAKER_1:  and rather than flying your ship into that.
SPEAKER_1:  that hellhole of a blender system, you just stand back and you fire a laser beam.
SPEAKER_1:  Now because black holes have such intense gravitational fields, they can bend light into complete 180s. They can actually become mirrors.
SPEAKER_1:  So, you know, the sun bends light by maybe a fraction of a degree.
SPEAKER_1:  through gravitational lensing but
SPEAKER_1:  you know, a compact object like a black hole can do a full 180. In fact, if you obviously, if you.
SPEAKER_1:  If you went too close, if you put the laser beam too close, the black hole would just fall into it and never come back out.
SPEAKER_1:  So you just kind of push it out, push it out, push it out until you get to a point where it's just skirting the event horizon.
SPEAKER_1:  and then that laser beam skirts around and it comes back.
SPEAKER_1:  Now the laser beam wants to do a grav- I mean it is doing a gravitational slingshot.
SPEAKER_1:  but laser, I mean light photons can't speed up unlike.
SPEAKER_1:  in like the spaceship case.
SPEAKER_1:  So instead of speeding up, the way they steal energy is they increase their frequency.
SPEAKER_1:  so they become higher energy photon packets essentially, they get blueshifted.
SPEAKER_1:  so that you send maybe a red laser beam that comes back blue, it's got more energy in it.
SPEAKER_1:  And because photons carry momentum...
SPEAKER_1:  which is somewhat unintuitive in everyday experience, but they do, that's how solar cells work, they carry momentum, they push things.
SPEAKER_1:  You can even use them as laser tweezers and things to pick things up.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  because they push.
SPEAKER_1:  It comes back with more momentum than it left.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  you get an acceleration force from this.
SPEAKER_1:  And again, you're just seeing energy from the black hole to do this. So you can get up to the same speed.
SPEAKER_1:  Basically the same idea as Freeman Dyson, but doing it from a safer distance.
SPEAKER_1:  And there should be a border of a million or so or 10 million black holes in the Milky Way galaxy.
SPEAKER_1:  Some of them.
SPEAKER_1:  would be even as close as sort of 10 to 20 light years when you do that.
SPEAKER_1:  occurrence rate statistics of how close you might expect a feasibly one to be.
SPEAKER_1:  They're of course difficult to detect because they're black, so they're inherently hard to see.
SPEAKER_1:  But statistically, there should be plenty out there in the Milky Way. And so these objects would be natural waypoint stations. You could use them to both accelerate away.
SPEAKER_1:  and to break and slow down.
SPEAKER_0:  And on top of all this, you know, there's, we've been talking about astronomy and cosmology. There's been a lot of exciting.
SPEAKER_0:  breakthroughs in detection and exploration of
SPEAKER_0:  black holes.
SPEAKER_0:  So the boomerang photons that you're talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  There's been a lot of work on.
SPEAKER_0:  photon rings and just...
SPEAKER_0:  All the fun stuff going on outside.
SPEAKER_0:  black holes.
SPEAKER_0:  The garbage outside is actually might be the thing that.
SPEAKER_0:  holds.
SPEAKER_0:  a key to understanding what's going on inside. And there's the Hawking radiation, there's all kinds of fascinating stuff like a
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, there's trippy stuff about black holes that most people don't understand.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean the holographic.
SPEAKER_0:  principle with the plate and the information being stored.
SPEAKER_0:  potentially outside of the black hole.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't even, I can't even comprehend.
SPEAKER_0:  how you can project a three dimensional object onto a 2D and some hostile information where it doesn't destroy it
SPEAKER_0:  And if it does destroy it, challenging all of physics, all of this is very-
SPEAKER_0:  interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  especially for kind of more practical applications of how the black hole can be used for propulsion.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean.
SPEAKER_1:  It may be that black cards are used in all sorts of ways.
SPEAKER_1:  advanced civilizations
SPEAKER_1:  I think...
SPEAKER_1:  Again, it's been a popular idea in science fiction or science fiction tropes that Sagittarius A star, the supermassive black hole in the center of our galaxy could be the best place to look for intelligent life in the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  Because it is a giant.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Engine in a way.
SPEAKER_1:  and it was unique.
SPEAKER_1:  capability of a black hole is you can basically throw matter into it and you can get these jets that come out the accretion discs and the jets that fly out.
SPEAKER_1:  And so you can more or less.
SPEAKER_1:  use them to convert matter into energy V equals MC squared. And there's pretty much nothing else.
SPEAKER_1:  except for annihilation with its own antiparticle as a way of doing that.
SPEAKER_1:  So they have some unique properties. You could perhaps power a civilization by just throwing garbage into a black hole.
SPEAKER_1:  Right. Just throwing asteroids in and how your civilization with as much energy as you really would ever possibly need.
SPEAKER_1:  and you could also use them to accelerate away across the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  And you can even imagine using small artificial black holes as thermal generators, right? So the Hawking radiation from them.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of exponentially increases as they get smaller and smaller in size.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm so.
SPEAKER_1:  a very small black hole, one that you can almost imagine like holding in your hand.
SPEAKER_1:  would be a fairly significant heat source.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that raises all sorts of.
SPEAKER_1:  prospects about how you might.
SPEAKER_1:  use that in an engineering context to power your civilization as well.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  You have a video of becoming a Kardashev type 1 civilization. What's our hope?
SPEAKER_0:  for doing that, or a few orders of magnification.
SPEAKER_1:  you away from that.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it is surprising. I think people tend to think that we're...
SPEAKER_1:  close to this, this scale that the Kharishchev type one is defined as a civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  which is using as much energy as is essentially insulin upon the planet from the star.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Sets of water I think for the Earth of something like 10 to the 5 TeraWatts or 10 to the 7 TeraWatts is a gigantic amount of energy.
SPEAKER_1:  And we're using a tiny, tiny, tiny fraction of that right now.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  If you became a Kalashev type one civilization, which is seen not necessarily as a goal into itself, I think people think, well, why?
SPEAKER_1:  Why are we aspiring to become?
SPEAKER_1:  this energy hungry civilization, you know, surely.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  our energy needs might become, you know, might improve our efficiency or something as time goes on.
SPEAKER_1:  But ultimately the more energy you have access to.
SPEAKER_1:  the greater your capabilities will be. If you want to lift.
SPEAKER_1:  Mount Everest into space.
SPEAKER_1:  there is just a calculable amount of potential energy change that's going to take in order to accomplish that.
SPEAKER_1:  then the more energy you have access to as a civilization, then clearly the easier that energy achievement is going to be.
SPEAKER_1:  So depends on what your aspirations are as a civilization. Might not be something you want to ever do, but-
SPEAKER_0:  Well, but we should make clear that lifting heavy things isn't the only thing, it's just doing work. So it could be computation. Right, right.
SPEAKER_0:  It could be more and more and more and more sophisticated and larger and larger and larger computation, which is
SPEAKER_0:  It does seem where we're headed.
SPEAKER_0:  with the very fast increase.
SPEAKER_0:  in, um...
SPEAKER_0:  the scale and the quality of our computation outside the human brain.
SPEAKER_0:  artificial computation.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean.
SPEAKER_1:  Competition is a great example of.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean already I think some like 10% of US power electricity use is going towards the supercomputing centers, so there's a...
SPEAKER_1:  There's a vast amount of current engine needs which are already going towards computing surely.
SPEAKER_1:  only increase over time.
SPEAKER_1:  If we start ever doing anything like mind uploading or creating.
SPEAKER_1:  simulated realities that
SPEAKER_1:  that cost will surely become almost a dominant source of our energy requirements at that point if civilization
SPEAKER_1:  completely.
SPEAKER_1:  moves over to this kind of post-humanism stage.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  It's not unreasonable that our energy needs would continue to grow, certainly historically they always have at about 2% per year.
SPEAKER_1:  And so if that continues, there is going to be a certain point.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  where you're running up against the amount of energy which you can harvest because it's you're using every even if you cover the entire planet in solar panels
SPEAKER_1:  there's no more energy to be had.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  And so this is a, you know, there's a few ways of achieving this. I sort of talked about in the video how.
SPEAKER_1:  There were several renewable energy sources that we're excited about like geothermal.
SPEAKER_1:  wind power waves but...
SPEAKER_1:  Prim it all of those.
SPEAKER_1:  don't really scratch the surface or don't really scratch the itch of getting into a Kardashev type 1 civilization. They're meaningful now I would never tell anybody don't do.
SPEAKER_1:  wind power now because it's clearly useful for our current stage of civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's not.
SPEAKER_1:  it's going to be a pretty negligible fraction of our energy requirements if we got to that stage of development.
SPEAKER_1:  And so there has to be a breakthrough.
SPEAKER_1:  in either our ability to harvest solar energy.
SPEAKER_1:  which would require maybe something like a space array of solar panels to beaming the energy back down.
SPEAKER_1:  or some.
SPEAKER_1:  developments and innovations in nuclear fusion that will allow us to essentially reproduce the same process of
SPEAKER_1:  what's producing the solar photons.
SPEAKER_1:  but here on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  But even that comes with some consequences. If you're generating the energy here on earth and you're doing work on it on earth
SPEAKER_1:  then that work is going to produce waste heat and that waste heat is going to increase the ambient temperature of the planet.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  you whether even if this isn't really a greenhouse effect that you're increasing the temperature of the planet, this is just the amount of computers that are churning. You can feel the warmth coming off them.
SPEAKER_1:  if you do that much work.
SPEAKER_1:  of literally the entire instant energy of the planet is doing that work.
SPEAKER_1:  the planet is going to warm up significantly as a result of that.
SPEAKER_1:  And so, you know, that's a...
SPEAKER_1:  that clearly...
SPEAKER_1:  indicates that this is not a sustainable path, that civilizations as they approach color shift type one are gonna have to leave planet Earth, which is really the point of that video to show that.
SPEAKER_1:  It's.
SPEAKER_1:  Akashive.
SPEAKER_1:  Type 1 civilization even though it's defined as instant energy upon a planet.
SPEAKER_1:  That is not a species.
SPEAKER_1:  that is going to still be living on their planet.
SPEAKER_1:  erliest.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, in isolation, they will have to be harvesting energy from afar. They will have to be.
SPEAKER_1:  You doing work on that energy outside of that planet because
SPEAKER_1:  Otherwise you're going to dramatically change the environment in which you live.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, yeah, so that's a.
SPEAKER_0:  The more energy you create, the more energy you use.
SPEAKER_0:  the higher the imperative to expand out into the universe, but also not just the imperative but the capabilities.
SPEAKER_0:  and you're...
SPEAKER_0:  You've kind of as a side.
SPEAKER_0:  on your lab page mentioned that you're sometimes interested in astro engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  So what kind of space architectures do you think we can build?
SPEAKER_0:  house.
SPEAKER_0:  humans or interesting things outside of Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot of fun ideas here. One of the classic ideas is an O'Neill cylinder or a Stanford Taurus. These are like two.
SPEAKER_1:  rotating structures that were devised in space. And that was the 3rd basicly
SPEAKER_1:  using the centrifugal force as artificial gravity. And so these are structures which tend to be...
SPEAKER_1:  many kilometers across that you're building in space, but could potentially.
SPEAKER_1:  habitat, millions of people in orbit of the Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  And of course you could imagine putting them if you know the expanse does a pretty good job I think of exploring the idea of
SPEAKER_1:  human exploration of the solar system and having
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  many objects, many of the small near-earth objects and asteroids inhabited by mining colonies.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  One of the ideas we've played around with our group is this technology called a quasi.
SPEAKER_1:  A quasi is.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  An extension, again, we always tend to extend previous ideas, ideas built upon ideas.
SPEAKER_1:  an extension idea called a statite.
SPEAKER_1:  A statite was an idea proposed, I think by Ron Forward in the 1970s. 1970 seemed to have all sorts of wacky ideas. I don't know what was going on then. We had the Stanford, I think the Stanford Taurus, the O'Neill departures has stopped, beautiful, to the believe or believe in new land
SPEAKER_1:  The gravitational lens, people were really having fun with dreaming about space in the 70s.
SPEAKER_1:  The Stata is basically.
SPEAKER_1:  A solar sail.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's such an efficient solar sail that the outward force of radiation pressure equals the inward force of gravity from the Sun.
SPEAKER_1:  and so it doesn't need to orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  Normally you avoid, the sun is pulling us right now through force of gravity.
SPEAKER_1:  but we're not.
SPEAKER_1:  We are not.
SPEAKER_1:  getting closer towards the sun.
SPEAKER_1:  even though we are falling towards the sun because we're in orbit, which means our translational speed is just enough to keep us at the same altitude essentially from the sun.
SPEAKER_1:  And so you're in orbit and that's how you maintain distance. A Stato doesn't need to do that. It can be basically.
SPEAKER_1:  completely static and inertial space.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's just balancing the two forces of radiation pressure and inward gravitational pressure.
SPEAKER_1:  A quasi is the in between of those two states.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's...
SPEAKER_1:  has some significant outward pressure, but not enough.
SPEAKER_1:  to resist fully falling into the star. And so it compensates for that by having some translational motion.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's in between.
SPEAKER_1:  an orbit and a statite.
SPEAKER_1:  And so what that allows you to do is maintain artificial orbits.
SPEAKER_1:  So normally, if you want to calculate your orbital speed of something that's say half an AU,
SPEAKER_1:  you would use Kepler's third law and go through that and you say okay, if it's set.
SPEAKER_1:  Half an AU I can calculate the period by p squared proportional to a cubed and go through that.
SPEAKER_1:  but for a
SPEAKER_1:  Um, a quasi you can basically have any speed you want.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just a matter of how much.
SPEAKER_1:  How much of the gravitational force are you balancing out?
SPEAKER_1:  You effectively enter an orbit where you're making the mass of the star be less massive than it really is.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's as if you're orbiting a 0.1 solar mass star or a 0.2 solar mass star, whatever you want.
SPEAKER_1:  I say that means that...
SPEAKER_1:  Mercury orbits with a pretty fast orbital speed.
SPEAKER_1:  Around the sun.
SPEAKER_1:  because it's closer to the sun than we are.
SPEAKER_1:  but we could put something in Mercury's orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  that would have a slower speed and so it would co-track with the earth.
SPEAKER_1:  And so we would always be aligned with them at all times.
SPEAKER_1:  And so this could be useful.
SPEAKER_1:  if you wanted to have a...
SPEAKER_1:  either a chain of colonies or something that we're able to easily communicate and
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  and move between one another between these different bases.
SPEAKER_1:  you'd probably use something like this to maintain that.
SPEAKER_1:  Easy.
SPEAKER_1:  transferability.
SPEAKER_1:  Or you could even use it as a space weather monitoring system, which we actually propose in the paper.
SPEAKER_1:  We know that...
SPEAKER_1:  major events like the Carrington event that happened, you know, it can knock out all of our electromagnetic systems quite easily, a major solar flare could do that.
SPEAKER_1:  a G-man manic storm.
SPEAKER_1:  if we had the ability to detect.
SPEAKER_1:  those.
SPEAKER_1:  higher elevated activity cycles.
SPEAKER_1:  in advance.
SPEAKER_1:  The problem is they travel obviously pretty fast and so it's hard to get ahead of them.
SPEAKER_1:  but you could have a station which is basically sampling solar flares very close to the surface of the Earth as soon as it detects anything.
SPEAKER_1:  Suspicious.
SPEAKER_1:  magnetically it could then send that information straight back at the speed light to your earth and give you
SPEAKER_1:  maybe.
SPEAKER_1:  a half an hour warning or something that something bad was coming, you should shut off all your
SPEAKER_1:  systems or get in your Faraday cage now and protect yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, and so these, these cries are kind of a cool.
SPEAKER_1:  trick of again kind of hacking the laws of physics.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like another one of these exploits that the universe seems to allow us to do.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  potentially manifest these artificial systems that would otherwise be difficult to
SPEAKER_1:  to produce.
SPEAKER_1:  leveraging natural phenomena.
SPEAKER_1:  That's always the key.
SPEAKER_1:  is to work.
SPEAKER_1:  In my mind it's to work with nature. That's how I see astro engineering.
SPEAKER_1:  rather than against it. You're not trying to...
SPEAKER_1:  force it to do something. That's why we always think solar energy is so powerful because
SPEAKER_1:  in the battle against nuclear fusion nuclear fusion you're really fighting a battle where you're trying to confine plasma into this extremely tight space or
SPEAKER_1:  Um, it's...
SPEAKER_1:  The sun does this for free. It has gravitation.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  the earth in essence what a solar panel does it is a nuclear fusion reactive.
SPEAKER_1:  Cured.
SPEAKER_1:  Energy System
SPEAKER_1:  but it's just using gravitation for the confinement and having a huge standoff distance for his energy collection.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  Um, there are.
SPEAKER_1:  tricks like that, it's a very naive simple trick in that case, where we can
SPEAKER_1:  rather having to reinvent the wheel.
SPEAKER_1:  we can use the space infrastructure if you like.
SPEAKER_1:  astrophysical infrastructure that's already there to our benefit.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think in the long arc of human history.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably natural phenomena is the right solution.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the simple, that's the elegant solution because all the power is already there. That's why I dice in the sphere in the long.
SPEAKER_0:  Serve.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't know what a death sphere would look like, but some kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  thing that leverages the power, the energy that's already in the sun is better than.
SPEAKER_0:  creating artificial nuclear.
SPEAKER_0:  fusion reaction but then again
SPEAKER_0:  that
SPEAKER_0:  brings us to the topic of AI.
SPEAKER_0:  How much of this?
SPEAKER_0:  If we're traveling...
SPEAKER_0:  out there.
SPEAKER_0:  Interstellar travel or
SPEAKER_0:  doing some of the interesting things we'll be talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  How much?
SPEAKER_0:  of those ships would be occupied by AI systems, do you think?
SPEAKER_0:  What would the...
SPEAKER_0:  What would be the living organisms occupying those ships?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it-
SPEAKER_1:  It's depressing to think about AI in the search for life because
SPEAKER_1:  I've been thinking about this a lot over the last few weeks with playing around with chat gbt3 like many of us and being astonished with its capabilities.
SPEAKER_1:  and you see.
SPEAKER_1:  the NASA society.
SPEAKER_1:  is
SPEAKER_1:  undergoing a change.
SPEAKER_1:  seems significant in terms of the development of artificial intelligence. We've been...
SPEAKER_1:  Promise this.
SPEAKER_1:  revolution to singularity for a long time.
SPEAKER_1:  but it really seems to be...
SPEAKER_1:  stepping up.
SPEAKER_1:  its pace of development at this point.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  That's interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  because...
SPEAKER_1:  as someone who looks radiant live.
SPEAKER_1:  out there in the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  It sort of implies that...
SPEAKER_1:  our current stage of development.
SPEAKER_1:  is highly transitional.
SPEAKER_1:  And that.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, you go back for the last four and a half billion years, the planet was done, essentially.
SPEAKER_1:  if you go back.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a few thousand years of civilization, but it wasn't reproducing any technosignatures
SPEAKER_1:  And then over the last maybe 100 years, there's been something that might be detectable from afar.
SPEAKER_1:  But we're approaching this cusp where we might imagine it. Get to the end of this bold test.
SPEAKER_1:  We're thinking of like maybe years and decades with AI development.
SPEAKER_1:  typically when we talk about this.
SPEAKER_1:  But as an astronomer, I have to think about much longer timescales of centuries.
SPEAKER_1:  millennia
SPEAKER_1:  millions of years.
SPEAKER_1:  And so if this...
SPEAKER_1:  if this wave continues over that time scale.
SPEAKER_1:  Which is still the blink of an eye on a cosmic timescale.
SPEAKER_1:  That implies that
SPEAKER_1:  everything will be AI essentially out there if this is a common
SPEAKER_1:  behavior. And so that's intriguing because it sort of implies that we are
SPEAKER_1:  special.
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of our moment in time as a civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  which normally is...
SPEAKER_1:  something we're averse to as astronomers. We normally like this mediocrity principle. We're not special, we're a typical part of the universe. We're not the cosmological principle.
SPEAKER_1:  but in a temporal sense we may be.
SPEAKER_1:  in a unique location.
SPEAKER_1:  And perhaps that is part of the solution to the Fermi paradox, in fact, that if it is true that
SPEAKER_1:  planets tend to go through basically three phases.
SPEAKER_1:  dumb life for the vast majority.
SPEAKER_1:  a brief period of biological intelligence.
SPEAKER_1:  and then an extended period of artificial intelligence that they transition to.
SPEAKER_1:  then
SPEAKER_1:  We would be.
SPEAKER_1:  in a unique and special moment in galactic history that would be of particular interest for any.
SPEAKER_1:  anthropologists out there in the galaxy, right? This would be the time.
SPEAKER_1:  that you would want to study a civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  very carefully, you wouldn't want to interfere with it.
SPEAKER_1:  You would just want to see how it plays out.
SPEAKER_1:  Kind of similar to the ancestor simulations, but sometimes switched over to the same national argument.
SPEAKER_1:  that you are able to observe perhaps your own origins and study how the transformation happens.
SPEAKER_1:  And so yeah, that has for me recently been destroying the Fermi paradox a bit on its head.
SPEAKER_1:  and this idea of the zoo hypothesis that we may be monitored, which has for a long time been sort of
SPEAKER_1:  seen as a fringe idea even amongst the SETI community.
SPEAKER_1:  if we live in this truly.
SPEAKER_1:  transitional period.
SPEAKER_1:  It adds a lot of impetus to that idea, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  or even AI itself.
SPEAKER_0:  by its very nature would be observing us.
SPEAKER_0:  by
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it's like a.
SPEAKER_0:  There used to be this concept of human computation, which is actually exactly what's feeding the current chat.
SPEAKER_0:  language models.
SPEAKER_0:  which is leveraging all the busy stuff we're doing.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  do the hard work of learning so like the language models are trained on.
SPEAKER_0:  human.
SPEAKER_0:  Interaction in Human Language on the Internet.
SPEAKER_0:  And so it would
SPEAKER_0:  AI.
SPEAKER_0:  feeds.
SPEAKER_0:  and the...
SPEAKER_0:  I'll put a brain power from humans.
SPEAKER_0:  And so like it would be observing observing.
SPEAKER_0:  and it gets stronger as it observes. So it actually gets extremely good at observing humans.
SPEAKER_0:  And one of the interesting philosophical questions that starts.
SPEAKER_0:  percolating is what makes this.
SPEAKER_0:  What is the interesting thing that makes us human?
SPEAKER_0:  We tend to think of it...
SPEAKER_0:  And you said like there's three phases. What's the thing that's hard to come by in phase three?
SPEAKER_0:  Is it?
SPEAKER_0:  something like scarcity, which is limited resources.
SPEAKER_0:  Is it something like consciousness? Is that the thing that's very-
SPEAKER_0:  What do?
SPEAKER_0:  uh... that emerged the evolutionary process
SPEAKER_0:  in biological systems.
SPEAKER_0:  that are opening under
SPEAKER_0:  constrained resources.
SPEAKER_0:  this thing that feels, that it feels like something to experience the world, which we think of as consciousness.
SPEAKER_0:  Is that really difficult to replicate in artificial systems? Is that the thing that makes us fundamentally human?
SPEAKER_0:  Or is it just a side effect?
SPEAKER_0:  that we attribute way too much importance to.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you have a sense?
SPEAKER_0:  If you look out into the future and AI systems are the ones that are traveling out there.
SPEAKER_0:  12th Century and beyond.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you think they have to carry the flame of consciousness with them?
SPEAKER_1:  No, not necessarily.
SPEAKER_1:  They may do, but they may, it may not be.
SPEAKER_1:  unnecessarily.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, there's, I guess we're talking about the difference here between sort of an AGI.
SPEAKER_1:  Artificial German Ent
SPEAKER_1:  consciousness which
SPEAKER_1:  a distinct.
SPEAKER_1:  ideas and you can certainly have one without the other. So I could imagine.
SPEAKER_0:  I would disagree with this certainly in that state.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, I think it's very possible in order to have intelligence you have to have.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, well, I mean to a certain degree...
SPEAKER_1:  chat gbt3 has a level of intelligence already it's not a general intelligence but
SPEAKER_1:  It displays properties of intelligence with no.
SPEAKER_1:  consciousness so
SPEAKER_1:  Again, I would disagree. Okay. Kidsulsive is the name of your situation.
SPEAKER_1:  Whoa.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't, I don't, I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  It's very nice that you said it displays properties of intelligence.
SPEAKER_0:  in the same way it displays properties of intelligence, I would say.
SPEAKER_0:  it's starting to display properties of consciousness.
SPEAKER_0:  It certainly could fool you.
SPEAKER_1:  It is conscious.
SPEAKER_1:  Correct, yeah, I guess I get it.
SPEAKER_1:  a Turing test problem like.
SPEAKER_1:  if it's.
SPEAKER_1:  displaying all those properties.
SPEAKER_1:  If it, if it cracks like a parrot, looks like a parrot or cracks like a duck, isn't it, isn't it basically a duck at that point? So yeah, I can see that argument.
SPEAKER_1:  It probably...
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, certainly as an, I tried to think about it from.
SPEAKER_1:  The observer's point of view as an astronomer, what am I looking for?
SPEAKER_1:  whether that
SPEAKER_1:  intelligence is conscious or not.
SPEAKER_1:  has little.
SPEAKER_1:  Daring my thinkers too.
SPEAKER_1:  what I should be looking for when I'm trying to detect evidence of them.
SPEAKER_1:  It would.
SPEAKER_1:  maybe affect their...
SPEAKER_1:  behavior in ways that I can't.
SPEAKER_1:  Predict?
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  but
SPEAKER_1:  That's again getting into the game of what I would call xenopsychology of trying to make projections about the motivations of an alien species is incredibly difficult.
SPEAKER_1:  And similarly, for any kind of artificial intelligence, it's...
SPEAKER_1:  and Fathmo what its intentions may be.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  I would sort of question whether it would even be interested in.
SPEAKER_1:  traveling between the stars at all.
SPEAKER_1:  if it's primary goal.
SPEAKER_1:  is computation.
SPEAKER_1:  computation for the sake of computation.
SPEAKER_1:  Then.
SPEAKER_1:  probably going to have a different.
SPEAKER_1:  way of, you know, it's going to be engineering its solar system and the nearby material around it for a different goal.
SPEAKER_1:  if it's just simply trying to increase.
SPEAKER_1:  computer substrate across the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  And that of course, if that is its principal intention to just essentially convert dumb matter into smart matter as it goes.
SPEAKER_1:  then
SPEAKER_1:  I think that would come into conflict with our observations of the universe, right? Because...
SPEAKER_1:  the
SPEAKER_1:  The Earth shouldn't be here if that were true.
SPEAKER_1:  the Earth should have been transformed into computer substrate by this point.
SPEAKER_1:  There has been plenty of time in the history of the galaxy for that to have happened.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  So I'm skeptical.
SPEAKER_1:  that we can.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm skeptical in the part that that's a behavior that AI or any civilization really engages in.
SPEAKER_1:  but I also find it difficult to find a way out of it.
SPEAKER_1:  I have to explain why.
SPEAKER_1:  that would never happen in the entire history of the galaxy amongst potentially if life is common.
SPEAKER_1:  millions, maybe even billions of
SPEAKER_1:  instant instantiations of AI could have occurred across the galaxy.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, and so that seems to be a knock against.
SPEAKER_1:  the idea that.
SPEAKER_1:  there is life else or intelligent life else in the galaxy
SPEAKER_1:  the fact that that hasn't occurred.
SPEAKER_1:  in our history.
SPEAKER_1:  is maybe the only solid data point we really have about.
SPEAKER_1:  the activities of other civilizations.
SPEAKER_0:  Of course, the scary one could be that.
SPEAKER_0:  or just at this stage.
SPEAKER_0:  intelligent alien civilizations to start destroying themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  I guess it becomes too powerful.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything's just too many weapons, too many nuclear weapons, too many nuclear weapons style systems.
SPEAKER_0:  that just.
SPEAKER_0:  from mistake to aggression.
SPEAKER_0:  Like the probability of self-destruction is too high.
SPEAKER_0:  relative to the challenge of...
SPEAKER_0:  of avoiding.
SPEAKER_0:  the technological challenges of avoiding self-destruction.
SPEAKER_1:  You mean the AI?
SPEAKER_1:  destroys itself.
SPEAKER_1:  or we just write ours prior to the
SPEAKER_1:  Ad-ferne cookies!
SPEAKER_0:  as we get smarter and smarter AI.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, either AI destroys us or other, there could be just a million, like AI is correlated, the development of AI is correlated with all this other technological innovation.
SPEAKER_0:  genetic engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  all kinds of engineering at the nanoscale.
SPEAKER_0:  mass manufacture of things that could destroy us or cracking physics enough to have.
SPEAKER_0:  very powerful weapons.
SPEAKER_0:  nuclear weapons.
SPEAKER_0:  All of it, just.
SPEAKER_0:  too much.
SPEAKER_0:  Physics enables way too many things that can destroy us.
SPEAKER_0:  before it enables the.
SPEAKER_0:  the propulsion systems that allow us to fly far enough away before we destroy ourselves.
SPEAKER_0:  So maybe that's what happens to the other aliens.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that your resolution? Because I mean, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  us in the Techno Signature community and the astronomy community aren't.
SPEAKER_1:  thinking about this problem seriously enough.
SPEAKER_1:  in my opinion. We should.
SPEAKER_1:  we should be thinking about.
SPEAKER_1:  The...
SPEAKER_1:  What AI is.
SPEAKER_1:  doing to our society and the implications of what we're looking for.
SPEAKER_1:  And so the only, I think.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  thinking has to involve people like yourself who are
SPEAKER_1:  more intimate with the machine learning and artificial intelligence world.
SPEAKER_1:  is your how do you reconcile in your mind?
SPEAKER_1:  You said earlier that you think.
SPEAKER_1:  You can't imagine a galaxy where life and intelligence is not.
SPEAKER_1:  all over the place.
SPEAKER_1:  And if artificial intelligence is a natural progression for civilizations...
SPEAKER_1:  How do you reconcile that with?
SPEAKER_1:  with the absence of any information around us or any...
SPEAKER_1:  clues or hints of artificial behavior, artificial engineered stars.
SPEAKER_1:  or colonization, computer substrate, transform planets,
SPEAKER_0:  It's extremely difficult for me.
SPEAKER_0:  It's exciting.
SPEAKER_0:  The Fermi paradox broadly defined is extremely difficult for me.
SPEAKER_0:  And the terrifying thing is.
SPEAKER_0:  One thing I suspect.
SPEAKER_0:  is that we keep destroying ourselves. The probability of self-destruction with advanced technology is just extremely high.
SPEAKER_0:  That's why we're not seeing it.
SPEAKER_0:  but then again my intuition about why we haven't blown ourselves up with nuclear weapons.
SPEAKER_0:  It's very surprising to me from a scientific perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  Given all the cruelty I've seen in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  given
SPEAKER_0:  The
SPEAKER_0:  power that nuclear weapons place in the hands of a very small number of individuals.
SPEAKER_0:  It's very surprising to me we went to destroy ourselves.
SPEAKER_0:  and it seems to be a very low probability situation we have happening here.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  But, and then the other explanation is the zoo, here's the observation.
SPEAKER_0:  that were just being observed.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the only other thing. It's just, it's so difficult for me.
SPEAKER_0:  Of course, all of science, everything is very humbling. It would be very humbling for me.
SPEAKER_0:  to learn.
SPEAKER_0:  that we're alone in the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  It would change.
SPEAKER_0:  You know what?
SPEAKER_0:  maybe I do want that to be true because you want us to be special. That's why I'm resisting that thought maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no way we're that special.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no way we're that special. That's where my resistance comes from.
SPEAKER_1:  I would just say, you know
SPEAKER_1:  The specialness is something we...
SPEAKER_1:  In implicitly in that statement, there's kind of an assumption that we are something positive, like we're a gift to this planet or something, and that makes a special bit.
SPEAKER_1:  Hey!
SPEAKER_1:  It may be that intelligence is more of an, it's like we like rats or cockroaches. We're an infestation of this planet. We're not.
SPEAKER_1:  We're not some...
SPEAKER_1:  benevolent property that the planet would.
SPEAKER_1:  a plant would ideally like to have if you can even say such a thing.
SPEAKER_1:  But we may be.
SPEAKER_1:  not only a generally a negative force for a planet's biosphere and its own survivability, which I think you can make a strong argument about.
SPEAKER_1:  but we may also be.
SPEAKER_1:  very persistent.
SPEAKER_1:  infestation that may even in, you know, interesting thoughts in the wake of a nuclear war.
SPEAKER_1:  Would that be an absolute eradication of every human being, which would be?
SPEAKER_1:  a fairly extreme event.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh
SPEAKER_1:  Would the canal of consciousness, as you might call it, the flame of consciousness, continue with some small pockets?
SPEAKER_1:  that would maybe in 10,000 years, 100,000 years.
SPEAKER_1:  we see civilization re-emerge and play out the same thing over again.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that certainly, but nuclear weapons aren't powerful enough.
SPEAKER_0:  But yes, the...
SPEAKER_0:  to sort of push back on the infestation, sure, but the word special.
SPEAKER_0:  doesn't have to be positive.
SPEAKER_0:  I just mean...
SPEAKER_1:  I think it tends to imply, but I take your point. Yeah, but maybe.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Just maybe extremely rare, might be.
SPEAKER_0:  And that to me, it just...
SPEAKER_0:  It's very strange.
SPEAKER_0:  for me.
SPEAKER_0:  to be.
SPEAKER_0:  cosmically unique.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just very strange.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean that word.
SPEAKER_0:  The only.
SPEAKER_0:  thing.
SPEAKER_0:  of this level of complexity in the galaxy just seems very strange to me.
SPEAKER_0:  That was...
SPEAKER_1:  I would just, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  As I do think it depends on this classification, I think there is sort of, again, it's kind of buried within there as a subtext, but there is a
SPEAKER_1:  A classification that we're doing here that.
SPEAKER_1:  what we are is a distinct category of life, let's say in this case, when we're talking about intelligence we are something.
SPEAKER_1:  that can be separated.
SPEAKER_1:  But of course we see intelligence across the animal kingdom in, you know,
SPEAKER_1:  Dolphins, Humback whales.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  octopuses, crows, ravens, and so it's-
SPEAKER_1:  possible that
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  These are all manifestations of the same thing. And we are not.
SPEAKER_1:  We are not a particularly.
SPEAKER_1:  distinct class except for the fact we make technology that's really the only difference to our intelligence.
SPEAKER_1:  and we classify that separately.
SPEAKER_1:  But from a biological perspective, to some degree, it's really just all part of a continuum. And so that's why I...
SPEAKER_1:  When we talk about unique, you are.
SPEAKER_1:  putting yourself in a box which is distinct and saying this is the only example of things that fall into this box.
SPEAKER_1:  But the walls of that box may themselves be.
SPEAKER_1:  a construct of our own.
SPEAKER_1:  arrogance that we are something distinct.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  uh... but i was also speaking broadly
SPEAKER_0:  Us, meaning all life on earth.
SPEAKER_0:  that, but then it's possible that there's all kinds of
SPEAKER_0:  Living.
SPEAKER_0:  ecosystems and another planets and other moons.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just.
SPEAKER_0:  don't have interest in technological development.
SPEAKER_0:  And maybe, maybe technological development is the.
SPEAKER_0:  the parasitic thing, it destroys the organism broadly.
SPEAKER_0:  And then.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe that's actually one of the fundamentals.
SPEAKER_0:  realities, whatever broad way to categorize technological development, that's just the parasitic thing.
SPEAKER_0:  that just destroys itself. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  We're flirting around this idea of the great filter a little bit here.
SPEAKER_1:  asking where is this, does it lie ahead of us?
SPEAKER_1:  nuclear war, maybe imminent, that would be a filter that's ahead of us.
SPEAKER_1:  Or could it be behind us and that it's the advent of technology that is genuinely
SPEAKER_1:  a rare occurrence in the universe and that explains.
SPEAKER_1:  the Fermi paradox.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that's, that's something that.
SPEAKER_1:  Obviously people are.
SPEAKER_1:  debated and argued about in SETI for decades and decades.
SPEAKER_1:  It remains a...
SPEAKER_1:  a persistent.
SPEAKER_1:  People argue whether should be really quite a paradox or not, but it remains a consistent.
SPEAKER_1:  Apparent contradiction.
SPEAKER_1:  you can make a very cogent argument as to why you expect life and intelligence to be common in the universe and yet
SPEAKER_1:  Everything.
SPEAKER_1:  Everything we know about the universe is fully compatible.
SPEAKER_1:  with.
SPEAKER_1:  just us being here. & that's
SPEAKER_1:  A haunting.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  but
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not.
SPEAKER_1:  I have no-
SPEAKER_1:  preference or desire for that to be true. I'm not trying to
SPEAKER_1:  impose that view on anyone.
SPEAKER_1:  but I...
SPEAKER_1:  Do ask that we remain open-minded until evidence has been collected either way.
SPEAKER_1:  The thing is...
SPEAKER_0:  It's...
SPEAKER_0:  One of, if not the, probably I would argue is the most important question facing human civilization or the most interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Scientifically speaking, like what question is more important?
SPEAKER_0:  then um
SPEAKER_0:  somehow....
SPEAKER_0:  You know, the, there could be other ways to sneak.
SPEAKER_0:  up to it but it gets to the essence of
SPEAKER_0:  what we are.
SPEAKER_0:  what these living organisms are.
SPEAKER_0:  is somehow.
SPEAKER_0:  seeing another kind.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. Helps us understand. It speaks to the human condition, helps us understand.
SPEAKER_1:  what it is to be human to some degree.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  I think, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  I have tried to remain very agnostic about the idea of life and intelligence. One thing I try to be more optimistic about.
SPEAKER_1:  and I've been.
SPEAKER_1:  thinking a lot with our searches for life in the universe is life in the past.
SPEAKER_1:  You can-
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's actually not that hard to imagine we are the only civilization in the galaxy right now, living.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, this this kernel extent.
SPEAKER_1:  But there may be v-
SPEAKER_1:  very many extinct civilizations. If each civilization has a typical lifetime comparable to, let's say AI is the demise of our own.
SPEAKER_1:  That's only a few hundred years of technological development or maybe 10,000 years if you go back in the electric revolution.
SPEAKER_1:  the dawn of agriculture.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, hardly anything can cosmic time span.
SPEAKER_1:  Um
SPEAKER_1:  That's nothing, that's the blink of an eye.
SPEAKER_1:  And so it's not surprising at all that we would happen not to co-exist with anyone else.
SPEAKER_1:  That doesn't mean nobody else was ever here.
SPEAKER_1:  And if other civilizations come to that same conclusion and realization, maybe their scour the galaxy around them don't find any evidence for intelligence.
SPEAKER_1:  Then
SPEAKER_1:  They have two options, they can either give up on communication.
SPEAKER_1:  and just say, well, it's never going to happen.
SPEAKER_1:  We just may as well just worry about what's happening here on our own planet.
SPEAKER_1:  Or they could attempt communication, but communication through time.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's, that's almost, um.
SPEAKER_1:  the most.
SPEAKER_1:  selfless act.
SPEAKER_1:  of communication because there's no hope of
SPEAKER_1:  with getting anything back.
SPEAKER_1:  It's um...
SPEAKER_1:  a philanthropic gift almost to that other civilization that you can.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe.
SPEAKER_1:  maybe might just be nothing more than a monument, which the pyramids essentially are, a monument of their existence that these are.
SPEAKER_1:  the things they achieved, the things they believed in.
SPEAKER_1:  their language, their culture.
SPEAKER_1:  or, um...
SPEAKER_1:  It could be maybe something more than that. It could be sort of lessons from what they learned and their own history. And so.
SPEAKER_1:  I've been thinking a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  recently about.
SPEAKER_1:  How would we send a message?
SPEAKER_1:  to other civilizations in the future.
SPEAKER_1:  Because that
SPEAKER_1:  active
SPEAKER_1:  thinking seriously about the engineering of how you're designed at
SPEAKER_1:  would inform us about what we should be looking for.
SPEAKER_1:  and also perhaps be...
SPEAKER_1:  Our best chance, quite frankly.
SPEAKER_1:  I've ever making contact.
SPEAKER_1:  They might not be the contact we dream of.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's still contact, there would still be a record of our existence as pitiful as it might be compared to a two-way communication.
SPEAKER_1:  And I love the humility.
SPEAKER_0:  behind.
SPEAKER_0:  project, the Universal Project.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. It's a sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  It's humble in the f-
SPEAKER_0:  it humbles you to the...
SPEAKER_0:  fast.
SPEAKER_0:  temporal.
SPEAKER_0:  Landscape of the Universe.
SPEAKER_0:  just realizing our like...
SPEAKER_0:  Day to day lives, they, all of us will be forgotten. It's nice to think about something.
SPEAKER_0:  that sends a signal out to other.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  It was almost like a humility of acceptance as well.
SPEAKER_1:  of like knowing that you have a terminal disease.
SPEAKER_1:  But
SPEAKER_1:  your impact on the earth doesn't have to end with your death, that it could go on beyond with what you leave behind for others to discover with maybe the books you write or what you leave.
SPEAKER_1:  in the literature.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you think launching the Roadster vehicle?
SPEAKER_0:  out in space with a dog.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, the roadster.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not sure what someone would make of that if they found out. Yeah, that's true.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, there have been quasi attempts at it beyond the roadster. I mean, there's like plaques on, there's the pioneer plaques.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the Voyager 2 golden record.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  It's pretty unlikely anybody's going to discover those.
SPEAKER_1:  because they're just adrift in space and they will eventually mechanically die and not produce any signal for anyone to spot so you'd have to be extremely lucky to come across them.
SPEAKER_1:  I've often said to my colleagues that I think the best place is the moon.
SPEAKER_1:  The Moon.
SPEAKER_1:  unlike the earth has no significant weathering.
SPEAKER_1:  the, you know, the
SPEAKER_1:  How long will the Apollo descent stages, which is still sun on the lunar surface, last for?
SPEAKER_1:  The only real effect is micrometrize, which are slowly...
SPEAKER_1:  Like dust.
SPEAKER_1:  smashing against them pretty much.
SPEAKER_1:  But that's going to take millions, potentially billions of years to erode that.
SPEAKER_1:  down.
SPEAKER_1:  And so we have an opportunity, and that's on the surface.
SPEAKER_1:  If you put something just a few metres beneath the surface, it would have even greater protection.
SPEAKER_1:  And so it raises the prospect of that if we wanted to.
SPEAKER_1:  send something a significant amount of information.
SPEAKER_1:  to a future galactic spanning civilization that maybe cracks the interstellar proportion problem.
SPEAKER_1:  The moon's gonna be there for five billion years.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a long time for somebody to come by.
SPEAKER_1:  and detect maybe a strange pattern that we draw on the sand.
SPEAKER_1:  for them to, you know, big arrow, big cross, like look into here.
SPEAKER_1:  and we could have a tomb of knowledge of some record of our civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I think it's.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  When you think like that, what that implies to us, well...
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, the galaxy is 13 billion years old, the moon is already 4 billion years old. There may be places.
SPEAKER_1:  familiar to us, nearby to us, that we should be.
SPEAKER_1:  Seriously considering.
SPEAKER_1:  as
SPEAKER_1:  places we should look for life and intelligent life or evidence of relics that they might leave behind for us.
SPEAKER_0:  So that thinking like that will help us find such relics.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like a...
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  like a beneficial cycle that happens. Yes. Yeah, exactly. That enables the science of, of CID better, like of, of searching for bios.
SPEAKER_0:  tech signatures and so on.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. And it's inspiring.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's...
SPEAKER_0:  It's also inspiring in that we want to leave.
SPEAKER_0:  A legacy behind.
SPEAKER_0:  as an entire civilization.
SPEAKER_0:  Not just in the cymbals, but...
SPEAKER_0:  Broadly speaking.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. That's the last thing somehow.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. And I'm part of a team that's trying to.
SPEAKER_1:  Reeve.
SPEAKER_1:  repeat the golden record experiment.
SPEAKER_1:  We're trying to create like an open source version of the golden record that future spacecraft are able to download.
SPEAKER_1:  basically put a little hard drive that they can carry around with them and
SPEAKER_1:  you know, get these distributed hopefully across the solar system eventually.
SPEAKER_1:  That's going to be called...
SPEAKER_0:  The H-Trackers go to the galaxy.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it could be. That's a good name for it.
SPEAKER_1:  We've been toying a little bit with them, but I think probably just be golden record at this point or something, but um,
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  I think, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I think I-
SPEAKER_1:  Another-
SPEAKER_1:  benefit that I see of this activity.
SPEAKER_1:  is that it forces us as a species.
SPEAKER_1:  to ask those questions about what it is that we want.
SPEAKER_1:  another civilization to know about us.
SPEAKER_1:  The Gone Recorder was kind of funny because...
SPEAKER_1:  It had photos on it, and it had photos of people eating, for instance.
SPEAKER_1:  but had no photos of people defecating.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I always thought that was kind of funny.
SPEAKER_1:  Fire's an alien.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, if I was studying in alien, if I saw...
SPEAKER_1:  Images, I wouldn't...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not trying to be like a pervert or anything, but I would want to see the full, I want to understand the biology of that alien.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  We-
SPEAKER_1:  We always censor what we show.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, and we should show the whole act.
SPEAKER_0:  natural process and then also say we humans tend to censor these things.
SPEAKER_0:  We tend to not like to walk around naked. We tend to not to talk about.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, some of the natural biological phenomena and talk a lot about others.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. And actually just be very.
SPEAKER_0:  like the way you would be to a therapist or something, very transparent about the way...
SPEAKER_1:  we actually operate. Yeah. I mean, and Sagan had that with the Gordon record. I think he, he originally.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a male and a female figure to pitch on the golden record.
SPEAKER_1:  And the, the woman had a genitalia originally drawn and
SPEAKER_1:  There was a lot of pushback from, I think, a lot of Christian groups who were not happy about the idea of throwing this into space.
SPEAKER_1:  And so eventually they had to remove that.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  It would be confusing biologically.
SPEAKER_1:  you're trying to study xenobiology of this alien that apparently has no genitalia or the mandus, but for some reason the woman doesn't.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, and that's how...
SPEAKER_1:  That's our own societal and cultural.
SPEAKER_1:  imprint happening into that information.
SPEAKER_1:  That's to be fair.
SPEAKER_0:  just even having...
SPEAKER_0:  sexes.
SPEAKER_0:  and predators and prey, just a whole, that could be just a very unique Earth-like thing, so that might be confused about.
SPEAKER_0:  Why there's like pairs of things? Like why are you like, why, why is there.
SPEAKER_0:  a man and a woman in general, like they.
SPEAKER_0:  They could be, I mean, they could be confused about a lot of things in general. I don't think that.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't even know which way to hold the picture.
SPEAKER_0:  Or there's a picture, they might have very different sensory devices.
SPEAKER_1:  interpret this as a......sounds as their only way of navigating the world.
SPEAKER_1:  It's curve.
SPEAKER_1:  lost to send any kind of, you know, there's been a lot of conversation about sending video.
SPEAKER_1:  and audio and video and pictures and I've
SPEAKER_1:  That's one of the things I've been.
SPEAKER_1:  a little bit resistant about in the team that I've.
SPEAKER_1:  than thinking, well...
SPEAKER_1:  they might not have eyes and so...
SPEAKER_1:  if you lived in the Europa surface.
SPEAKER_1:  having eyes wouldn't be very useful.
SPEAKER_1:  If you lived on a very dark planet on the tightly locked night side of an exoplanet, having eyes wouldn't be particularly useful. So it's kind of a presumption of us to think that video is a useful form of communication.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you hope we become a multi-planetary species? So we almost sneaking up to that, but, um.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, the efforts of SpaceX, of Elon.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe in general what your thoughts are about those efforts.
SPEAKER_0:  You already mentioned Starship will be very interesting for astronomy, for science in general.
SPEAKER_0:  She's getting stuff out into space.
SPEAKER_0:  But what about the longer term goal of actually colonizing?
SPEAKER_0:  of building civilizations on other surfaces, on moons, on...
SPEAKER_1:  planets.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like an...
SPEAKER_1:  A fairly obvious thing to do for our survival, right? This...
SPEAKER_1:  a high risk.
SPEAKER_1:  If we are.
SPEAKER_1:  committed to trying to keep this human experiment going.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  putting all of our eggs in one basket is.
SPEAKER_1:  always going to be a risky strategy to pursue. It's a nice basket though. But yeah, it is a beautiful basket. I wouldn't want to, I personally have no interest in living on Mars or the moon. I would like to visit.
SPEAKER_1:  but I would definitely not want to spend the rest of my life and die on Mars. It's a-
SPEAKER_1:  It means a hell hole. Mars is a very, very diff... I think the idea that this is going to happen...
SPEAKER_1:  in the next 10, 20 years is.
SPEAKER_1:  seems to be very optimistic.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, not that it's insurmountable, but.
SPEAKER_1:  The.
SPEAKER_1:  The challenges are extreme to survive on a planet like Mars, which is like a dry frozen desert.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  with a high radiation environment. it's
SPEAKER_1:  It's a challenge of a type we've never faced before. So it's, I'm sure human ingenuity can tackle it, but.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm skeptical that we will have thousands of people living on Mars in my life.
SPEAKER_1:  But I would...
SPEAKER_1:  VELISH DA-
SPEAKER_1:  opportunity to maybe one day.
SPEAKER_1:  visit such a settlement and you know...
SPEAKER_1:  do scientific experiments on Mars or experience Mars, do astronomy from Mars, and all sorts of cool stuff you could do.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Sometimes you see these dreams of outer solar system exploration and you can like...
SPEAKER_1:  fly through the clouds of Venus, or you could...
SPEAKER_1:  just do these enormous jumps on these small moons where you can essentially jump as high as a skyscraper.
SPEAKER_1:  traverse them. So there's all sorts of you know wonderful ice skating on your rope it might be fun.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  Don't get me wrong, I love the idea of us becoming a planet tree.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's...
SPEAKER_1:  It's just a question of.
SPEAKER_1:  time around.
SPEAKER_1:  her own destructive tendencies.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  As you said earlier, add odds.
SPEAKER_1:  with a...
SPEAKER_1:  emerging capabilities.
SPEAKER_1:  to become interpenetrate.
SPEAKER_1:  And the question is, will we get out of the nest before we burn it down?
SPEAKER_1:  And I don't know. Obviously, I hope.
SPEAKER_1:  that we do.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't have any special insight that...
SPEAKER_1:  There is a problem, there is somewhat of a...
SPEAKER_1:  a gnawing intellectual itch I have with the so-called doomsday argument, which
SPEAKER_1:  Um, I try not to treat.
SPEAKER_1:  too seriously, but there is some element of it that bothers me.
SPEAKER_1:  The Doom segment.
SPEAKER_1:  Basically...
SPEAKER_1:  suggests that.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you're typically the mediocrity principle, you're not special.
SPEAKER_1:  that you're probably going to be born somewhere in the middle of all human beings who will ever be born.
SPEAKER_1:  You're unlikely to be
SPEAKER_1:  one of the first 1% of human beings that ever lived and similarly the last 1% of human beings to a level F
SPEAKER_1:  because it'd be very unique and special if that were true.
SPEAKER_1:  And so by this logic.
SPEAKER_1:  you can sort of calculate how many generations of humans you might expect. is something that the water, sowie and the biological
SPEAKER_1:  let's say 100 billion human beings that have ever lived on this planet.
SPEAKER_1:  then you could say to 95% confidence, so you divide by 5%.
SPEAKER_1:  So 100 billion divided by 0.05 would give you 2 trillion human beings that would ever live.
SPEAKER_1:  you'd expect by this argument.
SPEAKER_1:  And so if each.
SPEAKER_1:  If let's say each.
SPEAKER_1:  Each planet in general, the planet has a 10 billion population.
SPEAKER_1:  So that would be.
SPEAKER_1:  200 generations of humans we would expect ahead of us?
SPEAKER_1:  And if each one has an average lifetime of say 100 years.
SPEAKER_1:  then that would be about 20,000 years. So there's 20,000 years left in the clock. That's like a typical doomsday argument type.
SPEAKER_1:  Hell.
SPEAKER_1:  That's how they typically lay it out.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, now you can argue that a lot of the criticisms that do so argument come down to what are you really counting? You're counting humans there.
SPEAKER_1:  But maybe you should be counting years.
SPEAKER_1:  Or maybe you should be counting human hours. You know, what are you?
SPEAKER_1:  Because what you count makes a big difference to what you get out on the other end. This is called the reference class.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that's one of the big criticisms that do say like.
SPEAKER_1:  I do think it has a compelling point that it would be surprising.
SPEAKER_1:  If our future is to one day.
SPEAKER_1:  blossom and become a galactic spanning empire.
SPEAKER_1:  trillions upon trillions upon trillions of human beings will one day live across the stars for essentially
SPEAKER_1:  as long as the galaxy exists and the stars burn.
SPEAKER_1:  We would live at an incredibly special point in that story.
SPEAKER_1:  we would be right at the very, very, very beginning.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's not.
SPEAKER_1:  impossible, but it's just somewhat improbable.
SPEAKER_1:  And so there's part of that sort of irks against me.
SPEAKER_1:  but it also almost feels like a philosophical argument because you're sort of talking about...
SPEAKER_1:  soul was being drawn from this cosmic pool.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's not an argument that I lose sleep about for our fate of the doomsday, but it is.
SPEAKER_1:  somewhat.
SPEAKER_1:  intellectually annoying that
SPEAKER_1:  that there is a slight contradiction now, it feels like with the idea of a galactic spanning empire.
SPEAKER_0:  But of course there's so many unknowns.
SPEAKER_0:  I for one would-
SPEAKER_0:  Love to visit even space but
SPEAKER_0:  Mars just imagine standing on Mars and looking.
SPEAKER_0:  back at Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. So so could one my
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  incredible site.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll give you such a...
SPEAKER_1:  fresh perspective as to your entire existence and what it meant to be human.
SPEAKER_0:  and then come back to earth and it would give you.
SPEAKER_0:  give you a heck of a perspective. Plus the sunset on Mars is supposed to be nice.
SPEAKER_1:  I loved what William Shatner said after his flight.
SPEAKER_1:  His words really moved me when he came down. And I think-
SPEAKER_1:  It really captured the idea that we shouldn't really be sending engineers, our scientists into space. We should be sending out poets.
SPEAKER_1:  because those are the people when they come down who can.
SPEAKER_1:  who can truly make a difference when they describe their experiences in space.
SPEAKER_1:  I found it very moving reading what he said.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, when you talk to astronauts, when they describe what they see, it's like this.
SPEAKER_0:  Like they discovered a whole new thing that they can't possibly convert back into words. Yeah. Uh, yeah, it's.
SPEAKER_0:  It's beautiful to see just as a quick.
SPEAKER_0:  Before I forget, I have to ask you.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you summarize your argument against the hypothesis that we live in a simulation?
SPEAKER_0:  Is it similar to our discussion about the...
SPEAKER_0:  Tuesday clock.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, no, it's actually pretty more similar to my.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  agnosticism about life in the universe, and it's just sort of remaining agnostic about all possibilities.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Dissemination Argument
SPEAKER_1:  Sometimes it gets...
SPEAKER_1:  It mix this kind of two.
SPEAKER_1:  distinct things that we need to consider. One is the probability that we live in so-called base reality that we're not living in a simulated reality itself.
SPEAKER_1:  And another problem to consider is the probability that...
SPEAKER_1:  that technology is viable or possible and something we will ultimately choose to one day do.
SPEAKER_1:  Those are two distinct things. They're probably quite similar numbers to each other.
SPEAKER_1:  but they are distinct probabilities.
SPEAKER_1:  semi
SPEAKER_1:  In my paper, I...
SPEAKER_1:  I write about this.
SPEAKER_1:  I just tried to work through the problem. I teach astrocystics. I was actually teaching it this morning.
SPEAKER_1:  And so it just seemed like a fun...
SPEAKER_1:  case study of working through a Bayesian calculation for it.
SPEAKER_1:  Basing calculations work on conditionals.
SPEAKER_1:  And so when you hear any, what kind of inspired this project was when I heard Musk said was like a billion to one chance that we don't live in a simulation.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  He's right.
SPEAKER_1:  If you add.
SPEAKER_1:  The Basing Conditional.
SPEAKER_1:  and the basic condition is conditioned upon the fact that we eventually develop that technology and choose to use it.
SPEAKER_1:  or it's chosen to be used by such species.
SPEAKER_1:  by such civilizations.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the conditional.
SPEAKER_1:  And you have to add that in because that conditional isn't guaranteed.
SPEAKER_1:  And so in a Bayesian framework, you can kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  Make that explicit. You see mathematically explicitly that's a condition on your equation.
SPEAKER_1:  And the opposite side of the coin is basically in the trilemma that Bostrom originally put forward as options 1 and 2.
SPEAKER_1:  So option one is that you basically never develop the ability to do that. Option two is you never choose to execute that.
SPEAKER_1:  So we kind of group those together as sort of the.
SPEAKER_1:  the non-simulation.
SPEAKER_1:  scenario, let's call it.
SPEAKER_1:  And so you've got non-simulation scenario and simulation scenario.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Agnostically, we really...
SPEAKER_1:  have to give though, you know, how do you assess the model?
SPEAKER_1:  the a priori model probability of those two scenarios.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  It's very difficult and we can...
SPEAKER_1:  I think people would probably argue about how you assign those priors.
SPEAKER_1:  In the paper we just assigned 50-50, we just said, this hasn't been demonstrated yet.
SPEAKER_1:  There's no evidence that this is actually technically possible.
SPEAKER_1:  but nor is it that it's not technically possible, so we're just going to assign 50-50 probability these two hypotheses.
SPEAKER_1:  And then in the hypothesis where you have a simulated reality, you have a base reality set at the top.
SPEAKER_1:  So there is even in the simulated hypothesis, there's a probability you still live in base reality. There's a whole myriad of...
SPEAKER_1:  universes beneath that which are all simulated.
SPEAKER_1:  And so you have a very slim probability of being in base reality, if this is true.
SPEAKER_1:  and you have a 100% probability of living in base reality. On the other hand, if it's not true and we never develop...
SPEAKER_1:  that ability or choose never to use it.
SPEAKER_1:  And so then you apply this technique called basic model averaging, which is where you...
SPEAKER_1:  propagate the uncertainty of your two models to get a final estimate.
SPEAKER_1:  And because of that one base reality that lives in the simulated scenario.
SPEAKER_1:  you end up counting this up.
SPEAKER_1:  and getting that it always has to be less than 50%. The probability limits in
SPEAKER_1:  in a simulated reality versus a based reality has to be slightly less than 50%
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Now that really comes down to that statement of giving it 50-50 odds.
SPEAKER_1:  To begin with...
SPEAKER_1:  And on the one hand, you might say, look, David, I'm, you know, I work in artificial intelligence. I'm very confident that this is going to happen.
SPEAKER_1:  just of extrapolating of current trends.
SPEAKER_1:  Or on the other hand, a statistician would say...
SPEAKER_1:  You're giving way too much weight to the simulation hypothesis because it's an intrinsically highly complicated model.
SPEAKER_1:  You have a whole...
SPEAKER_1:  hierarchy of realities within realities within realities. Like the inception style thing, right?
SPEAKER_1:  And so this requires.
SPEAKER_1:  hundreds thousands millions of parameter is to describe.
SPEAKER_1:  And by Occam's razor, we would always normally penalize inherently complicated models as being disfavored.
SPEAKER_1:  So I think you could.
SPEAKER_1:  I argue on being too generous or too kind with that, but I sort of want to develop the rigorous mathematical tools to explore it.
SPEAKER_1:  and ultimately it's up to you to decide what you think that 50-50 odds should be.
SPEAKER_1:  But you can use my
SPEAKER_1:  formula to plug in whatever you want and get the answer. And I use 50-50. So, but...
SPEAKER_0:  when in that first pile with the first two parts of the
SPEAKER_0:  that the boss room talks about, it seems like.
SPEAKER_0:  Connected to that is the question we've been talking about which is the number of times at bat you get
SPEAKER_0:  just the number of intelligent civilizations that are out there that can
SPEAKER_0:  build such simulations.
SPEAKER_0:  very closely connected because if we're the only ones that are here.
SPEAKER_0:  and can build such things that...
SPEAKER_0:  changes things.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, yeah, I mean.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, the signature embolism has all sorts of...
SPEAKER_1:  implications like that.
SPEAKER_1:  I've always loved showing Chara points that are really interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  contradiction apparently with the simulation hypothesis that I speak about a little bit in the paper.
SPEAKER_1:  But he showed that, or pointed out that.
SPEAKER_1:  in this hierarchy of realities, which then develop their own AIs within the realities and then they are, or really ancestor simulations, I should say, rather than AI, they develop their own capability to simulate realities. You get this hierarchy.
SPEAKER_1:  And so eventually there'll be a bottom layer.
SPEAKER_1:  which I often call the sewer of reality. It's like the worst layer where it's the most pixelated it could possibly be. So, because each layer is necessarily going to have less computational power than the layer above it.
SPEAKER_1:  Because not only are you simulating that entire planet, but also some of that's being used for the computers themselves that those are simulated.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that base reality, also known as the sewer reality.
SPEAKER_1:  is a reality where they are simply unable.
SPEAKER_1:  to produce ancestor simulations because the fidelity of the simulation is not sufficient.
SPEAKER_1:  And so from their point of view, it might not be obvious that the universe is pixelated, but they would just never be able to manifest that capability. What if...
SPEAKER_0:  They're constantly simulating.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... cuz it in order to uh... appreciate the limits of the fidelity you have to have an observer
SPEAKER_0:  What if they're always simulating a dumber and dumber observer? What if the sewer has very dumb observers? They can't like scientists that are the dumbest possible scientists. So like it's very pixelated, but the scientists are too dumb to even see the pixelations.
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_0:  Like built into the universe always has to be a limitation on the cognitive capabilities of the complex systems that are within it.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so that's surreality, they would still...
SPEAKER_1:  Presumably be able to.
SPEAKER_1:  have a very impressive computational capabilities, they'll probably be able to simulate galactic formation with this kind of impressive stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  They would be just short of the ability to, however you define it, create a truly sentient conscious experience.
SPEAKER_1:  in a computer that would just be.
SPEAKER_1:  just beyond their capabilities.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  Carol pointed out that if you add up all the counter-pamely realities, there should be...
SPEAKER_1:  probabilistically, if this is true.
SPEAKER_1:  Over here, the simulation.
SPEAKER_1:  hypothesis or scenario.
SPEAKER_1:  then you're most likely to find yourself in the sewer because there's just far more of them.
SPEAKER_1:  than there are of any of the higher levels.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that sort of sets up a contradiction because then...
SPEAKER_1:  You live in a reality.
SPEAKER_1:  which is inherently incapable of ever producing ancestor simulations.
SPEAKER_1:  The premise of the entire argument is that ancestor simulations are possible.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a contradiction.
SPEAKER_0:  There's that old quote, we're all living in the sewer, but some of us are looking up at the stars.
SPEAKER_1:  This is maybe more true than we think.
SPEAKER_0:  But to me, so there's of course physics and computational fascinating questions here, but to me
SPEAKER_0:  There's a practical psychological.
SPEAKER_0:  question.
SPEAKER_0:  which is...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, how do you create?
SPEAKER_0:  A virtual reality world.
SPEAKER_0:  that is as compelling.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  None of this is even as realistic.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  Almost as realistic.
SPEAKER_0:  but as compelling or more compelling than physical reality.
SPEAKER_0:  because something tells me it's not very difficult.
SPEAKER_0:  in a in a in a.
SPEAKER_0:  full history of human civilization.
SPEAKER_0:  That...
SPEAKER_0:  is an interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of simulation to me, because that feels like it's doable in the next 100 years.
SPEAKER_0:  creating a world where we're all.
SPEAKER_0:  prefer to live in the digital world.
SPEAKER_0:  And not like a visit.
SPEAKER_0:  but like...
SPEAKER_0:  It's...
SPEAKER_0:  your scene is insane. No, like
SPEAKER_0:  You're required.
SPEAKER_0:  It's unsafe to live outside of the virtual world.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It's interesting to me from an engineering perspective how to build that.
SPEAKER_0:  Because I'm somebody that sort of loves video games and it seems like...
SPEAKER_0:  You can create incredible worlds there and stay there.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  That's a, it's a.
SPEAKER_0:  different.
SPEAKER_0:  question than creating a ultra high resolution, high fidelity.
SPEAKER_0:  Simulation of physics.
SPEAKER_0:  If that world inside a video game is
SPEAKER_0:  as consistent.
SPEAKER_0:  as the physics of our reality.
SPEAKER_0:  You can have your own scientists in that world.
SPEAKER_0:  trying to understand that physics world. They might look different.
SPEAKER_1:  and presumably they'd eventually forget, you know, give it long enough they might forget about their origins.
SPEAKER_1:  being once biological, assume this is their only reality.
SPEAKER_1:  Especially if you're now.
SPEAKER_0:  born.
SPEAKER_0:  you know uh... what certainly if you're born
SPEAKER_0:  But even if...
SPEAKER_0:  You were eight years old or something when you first started wearing the headset.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, or you have a memory wipe when you go in.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean it.
SPEAKER_1:  It also kind of maybe speaks to this issue of like Neuralink and how do we keep up with AI in our world?
SPEAKER_1:  If you want to augment your intelligence, perhaps one way of competing and the one of your impetus is for going into this digital reality.
SPEAKER_1:  would be to be competitive intellectually.
SPEAKER_1:  with artificial interchances that you could trivially augment your reality if your brain was itself artificial but
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, one, one skepticism I've always had about that is, is whether
SPEAKER_1:  It's a more philosophical question, but how much is that really you if you do a mind upload?
SPEAKER_1:  Is this just a duplicate of your memories that thinks it's you?
SPEAKER_1:  versus truly.
SPEAKER_1:  a transference of your conscious stream.
SPEAKER_1:  into that reality and I think we knew.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  It's almost like the teleportation device in Star Trek.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  with.
SPEAKER_1:  teleportation, quantum teleportation, you can kind of rigorously show that
SPEAKER_1:  Um, that.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, all as long as all of the
SPEAKER_1:  quantum numbers are exactly duplicated as you transfer over
SPEAKER_1:  It truly is from the universe's perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  in every way indistinguishable from what was there before. It really is in principle you and all the sense of being you.
SPEAKER_1:  versus creating a duplicate clone and uploading.
SPEAKER_1:  memories to that human body or a computer.
SPEAKER_1:  that would.
SPEAKER_1:  Surely be.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  a discontinuation of that conscious experience.
SPEAKER_1:  by virtue of the fact you've multiplied it. And so i
SPEAKER_1:  I would be hesitant about uploading.
SPEAKER_1:  that reason. I would see it mostly as my own.
SPEAKER_1:  killing myself and having some
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  AI duplicate of me.
SPEAKER_1:  that persists in this world, but.
SPEAKER_1:  is not truly my experience.
SPEAKER_0:  Typical.
SPEAKER_0:  20th century human.
SPEAKER_0:  with an attachment to this particular singular instantiation of brain.
SPEAKER_0:  and body.
SPEAKER_0:  how silly humans used to be. Used to have rotary phones and-
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  and other silly things.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  You're an incredible human being. You're an educator. You're a researcher.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  You have.
SPEAKER_0:  like an amazing.
SPEAKER_0:  YouTube channel
SPEAKER_0:  Looking to young people if you were to give them advice.
SPEAKER_0:  How can they have a-
SPEAKER_0:  A career?
SPEAKER_0:  that maybe is inspired by yours.
SPEAKER_0:  inspired by wandering curiosity, a career they can be proud of or a life they can be proud of.
SPEAKER_0:  What advice would you give?
SPEAKER_1:  I suddenly think in terms of it.
SPEAKER_1:  Aquarian
SPEAKER_1:  Science.
SPEAKER_1:  One thing that I may be discovered late, but has been
SPEAKER_1:  incredibly influential on me in terms of my own happiness and my own.
SPEAKER_1:  productivity.
SPEAKER_1:  has been this synergy of doing.
SPEAKER_1:  two passions at once.
SPEAKER_1:  One passion in science communication and another passion in research.
SPEAKER_1:  and not.
SPEAKER_1:  surrendering either one.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think...
SPEAKER_1:  that tends to be seen as something that's an either or, you have to completely dedicate yourself to one thing to gain mastery in it. That's a conventional way of thinking about both science and-
SPEAKER_1:  other disciplines.
SPEAKER_1:  and I have found that both have been elevated by practicing in each.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  And I think.
SPEAKER_1:  That's true in all assets of life. I mean, if you...
SPEAKER_1:  1, 2.
SPEAKER_1:  become the best researcher you possibly can.
SPEAKER_1:  You're pushing your...
SPEAKER_1:  intellect and sense your body to a high level.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  To me.
SPEAKER_1:  I've always wanted to couple that with training of my body, training of my mind and other ways besides from just what I'm doing when I'm in the lecture room or when I'm in my night watch AfD.
SPEAKER_1:  office in calculating something.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  focusing on your own.
SPEAKER_1:  development.
SPEAKER_1:  through whatever it is, meditation, for me, it's often running, working out.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  and pursuing multiple passions.
SPEAKER_1:  provides this almost synergistic bliss of all of them together.
SPEAKER_1:  so often I've had.
SPEAKER_1:  some of the best research ideas from making a YouTube video and trying to communicate an idea or interacting with my audience who've had.
SPEAKER_1:  a question that sparked a hole.
SPEAKER_1:  trail of thought that led down this wonderful intellectual rabbit hole.
SPEAKER_1:  or maybe to a new intellectual discovery.
SPEAKER_1:  can go either way sometimes with those things.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  And so thinking broadly.
SPEAKER_1:  diversely.
SPEAKER_1:  and always looking after yourself in this.
SPEAKER_1:  in this highly competitive and often extremely stressful world that we live in.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  is the best advice I can offer anybody and just try.
SPEAKER_1:  If you can, it's very cheesy, but if you can follow your passions.
SPEAKER_1:  you'll always be happy trying to.
SPEAKER_1:  Sellout.
SPEAKER_1:  for the quick.
SPEAKER_1:  cash out for the quick book out.
SPEAKER_1:  can be tempting in the short term.
SPEAKER_1:  Looking for exo means it was never easy.
SPEAKER_1:  but I made a career not out of discovering ex-amines.
SPEAKER_1:  but out of learning how to communicate the difficult problem.
SPEAKER_1:  and discovering all sorts of things along the way. We shot for the sky and we discovered all this stuff along the way. We discovered.
SPEAKER_1:  dozens of new planets using all sorts of new techniques.
SPEAKER_1:  We pushed this instrumentation to new places.
SPEAKER_1:  and I've had an extremely productive.
SPEAKER_1:  Research Career
SPEAKER_1:  in this world, I've had all sorts of ideas working on techno signatures. It's
SPEAKER_1:  you know, thinking innovatively.
SPEAKER_1:  pushes you into all sorts of exciting directions.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, so.
SPEAKER_1:  this.
SPEAKER_1:  Just try to, yeah, it's hard to find that passion, but you can.
SPEAKER_1:  Sometimes remember it when you were a kid, what your passions were and what fascinated you as a child.
SPEAKER_1:  For me, as soon as I picked up a space boat when I was five years old, that was it. I was hooked on space and...
SPEAKER_1:  I almost betrayed my passion at college. I studied physics, which I've always been fascinated by physics as well.
SPEAKER_1:  But.
SPEAKER_1:  I came back to astronomy because it was my first love and...
SPEAKER_1:  I was much happier doing research in astronomy than I was in physics because it spoke to........................................................................
SPEAKER_1:  wonder I had as a child that first was the spark of curiosity for me in science.
SPEAKER_0:  So society will try to get you to look at hot Jupiters.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  and the advice is to look for the cool world instead.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think is the meaning of this whole thing?
SPEAKER_0:  You ever ask yourself why?
SPEAKER_1:  It's just a ride.
SPEAKER_1:  That's all right. It's just a ride. We're on a roller coaster.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  We have no.
SPEAKER_1:  purpose.
SPEAKER_1:  It's an accident, am I?
SPEAKER_1:  my perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  There's no meaning to my life, there's no.
SPEAKER_1:  are very important but very important. Where's the
SPEAKER_1:  deity who is over watching what I'm doing and I have some fate or destiny.
SPEAKER_1:  It's all just riding on the roller coaster.
SPEAKER_1:  and trying to.
SPEAKER_1:  have a good time and contribute.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  to other people's enjoyment of the ride.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, try to make it a happy accident.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, yeah, I see no...
SPEAKER_1:  fundamental.
SPEAKER_1:  Providence in.
SPEAKER_1:  in my life or in the nature of the universe. And you just see this.
SPEAKER_1:  The universe is this beautiful.
SPEAKER_1:  cosmic accident of galaxies smashing together.
SPEAKER_1:  stars forging here and there and-
SPEAKER_1:  Planets occasionally spawning maybe life across the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  And we are just one of those instantiations. And we should just.
SPEAKER_1:  Enjoy this very brief.
SPEAKER_1:  episode that we have and
SPEAKER_1:  I think trying to...
SPEAKER_1:  look at it much deeper than that is...
SPEAKER_1:  is to me, it's not very soul satisfying. I just think enjoy what you've got and appreciate it.
SPEAKER_0:  It does seem noticing that beauty.
SPEAKER_0:  helps make the ride.
SPEAKER_0:  pretty fun.
SPEAKER_1:  Absolutely.
SPEAKER_0:  David, you're an incredible person. I haven't covered most of the things I wanted to talk to you about. This was an incredible conversation. I just, I'm glad you exist. I'm glad you're doing everything.
SPEAKER_0:  You're doing it, I'm a huge fan. Thank you so much for talking today, this was amazing.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you Sir Rich Lex, it's a real honour, thank you.
SPEAKER_0:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with David Kipping.
SPEAKER_0:  To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_0:  And now...
SPEAKER_0:  Let me leave you with some words from Carl Sagan.
SPEAKER_0:  Perhaps.
SPEAKER_0:  The aliens are here.
SPEAKER_0:  but are hiding.
SPEAKER_0:  because of some.
SPEAKER_0:  Lex Galactica.
SPEAKER_0:  ethic of non-interference with emerging civilizations.
SPEAKER_0:  You can imagine them.
SPEAKER_0:  curious and dispassionate.
SPEAKER_0:  observing us.
SPEAKER_0:  as we would watch a bacterial culture in a dish.
SPEAKER_0:  determine whether this year again.
SPEAKER_0:  we managed to avoid self-destruction.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you for listening.
SPEAKER_0:  hope to see you.
SPEAKER_0:  next time.