SPEAKER_0:  And the nozzle, so as you're saying, there's a bunch of different designs.
SPEAKER_0:  options.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's a critical part of this, how you do that conversion.
SPEAKER_1:  Which is basically like how much
SPEAKER_1:  Can you convert?
SPEAKER_1:  is really like the ultimate game. How much-
SPEAKER_1:  Pressure and heat.
SPEAKER_1:  can we convert into thrust?
SPEAKER_1:  Like that's really at the end of the day, that's what a rocket engine is.
SPEAKER_1:  The following is a comment.
SPEAKER_0:  Conversation with Tim Dodd.
SPEAKER_0:  Host of the Everyday Astronaut YouTube channel.
SPEAKER_0:  where he educates and inspires.
SPEAKER_0:  All of us.
SPEAKER_0:  with detailed but accessible explanations.
SPEAKER_0:  of rocket engines.
SPEAKER_0:  All things space travel.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the Lex Freedman Podcast.
SPEAKER_0:  To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_0:  And now...
SPEAKER_0:  Dear friends,
SPEAKER_0:  Here's Tim.
SPEAKER_0:  done.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you give a brief history of SpaceX rockets? So we got Falcon 1, Falcon 9.
SPEAKER_0:  There's different versions of those, Falcon Heavy.
SPEAKER_0:  Starship and also the the dragon capsules and so on
SPEAKER_1:  Well, yeah, Falcon 1 is where it all started. The original intent and the original idea of SpaceX was Elon wanted to try to
SPEAKER_1:  Get something to Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, he saw that NASA didn't have a current Mars plan.
SPEAKER_1:  and he wanted to go to Mars, so he decided how do I best do this?
SPEAKER_1:  He literally wanted it.
SPEAKER_1:  at first.
SPEAKER_1:  purchase a rocket from Russia.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Then on the after.
SPEAKER_1:  A foiled attempt at doing that, he decided he was going to try to develop his own rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  And the Falcon 1 is what came out of that process. And he developed a pretty incredible team. I don't know how exactly he stumbled upon the team that he stumbled upon that quickly.
SPEAKER_1:  But the people that he assembled were amazing.
SPEAKER_1:  and they built the Falcon 1.
SPEAKER_1:  which was a single Merlin engine followed by an upper stage engine called the Kestrel engine.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  pretty small compared to the things they're working on today, but that Merlin engine continued to evolve.
SPEAKER_1:  into being the power plant for the Falcon 9. They went from a small lift launch vehicle up into the medium class launch vehicle so they could provide services for NASA.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  That's one of the big things they first kind of hung their hat up was they got the opportunity to fly cargo to the International Space Station.
SPEAKER_1:  under originally is called the COTS program.
SPEAKER_1:  the commercial orbital transportation services.
SPEAKER_1:  for NASA which evolved into the commercial resupply contracts.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's when SpaceX developed both their Dragon capsule, which is a
SPEAKER_1:  uncrewed at first spacecraft that can dock to the ISS.
SPEAKER_1:  and the Falcon 9 rocket that can take it to the International Space Station.
SPEAKER_0:  and then Dragon rides on.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the thing up top that rides on the big.
SPEAKER_0:  booster thing that shhhhhh
SPEAKER_0:  that launches it.
SPEAKER_1:  the inter orbit. Exactly. Yep. The Falcon 9's the-
SPEAKER_1:  dead.
SPEAKER_1:  Semi truck, the dragon capsules, the payload.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's the thing being dropped off basically at assassination. In this case.
SPEAKER_1:  The destination is the International Space Station.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  and uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so they.
SPEAKER_1:  develop those relatively quickly.
SPEAKER_1:  and became a commercial success before you know it there.
SPEAKER_1:  Now the number one launch provider in the world launching more mass to orbit than anybody else launching more frequently than
SPEAKER_1:  um, countries.
SPEAKER_1:  entire
SPEAKER_1:  country of China who's going crazy right now with launches. Granted, China beat them by two launches this last in 2022, but
SPEAKER_1:  Prior year SpaceX beat the entire country of China.
SPEAKER_1:  It's nuts.
SPEAKER_0:  And just like you said, SpaceX still beats China even this year.
SPEAKER_0:  In terms of the amount of payload that was done. So all ends up.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, the mass, the orbit, right.
SPEAKER_0:  that China.
SPEAKER_0:  had like 60 something a couple more.
SPEAKER_0:  launches but there was just like small cubes that type of
SPEAKER_1:  launches exactly some of them are
SPEAKER_1:  literally like 100 kilograms or something, you know, like not large payloads.
SPEAKER_0:  And so SpaceX customers are.
SPEAKER_0:  different.
SPEAKER_0:  So whoever wants to...
SPEAKER_0:  send payloads up into space.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, but right now their biggest customer is actually themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  with Starling.
SPEAKER_1:  One of the biggest reasons they've launched so much massed orbits is because Starlink has designed
SPEAKER_1:  around the payload fairing and the payload capabilities of the Falcon 9 rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  So, you know, because they're vertically integrated, because they build their own satellites, because they're building their own rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  they can literally design a system that's, you know, another manufacturer might've made a more square.
SPEAKER_1:  satellite that was heavier or something, but SpaceX looked at it from a blank slate and said,
SPEAKER_1:  Here's our constraints.
SPEAKER_1:  our payload mass constraints or volume constraints. And they made a funky looking satellite at things like the size of a, you know, like a table folded up.
SPEAKER_1:  which isn't anything I've really ever seen before, but it's purpose built.
SPEAKER_1:  to fit.
SPEAKER_1:  as efficiently as possible inside their fairing.
SPEAKER_1:  and inside the capabilities of that rocket. So therefore,
SPEAKER_1:  because they're launching those.
SPEAKER_1:  like an insane amount, you know, a dozen, you know, 40, 50 times a year or whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, there, uh,
SPEAKER_1:  They're just putting up insane amounts of mass.
SPEAKER_1:  Like we've never seen before.
SPEAKER_0:  What about the different versions of Falcon 9? Are there some interesting memories to you of the different developments in Falcon 9?
SPEAKER_1:  The very first Falcon 9's had a square.
SPEAKER_1:  Array of engines. I had like a three by three by three grid
SPEAKER_1:  of their Merlin 1 engines, the 1Ds.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think it only lasted.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't remember if it was two or four flights.
SPEAKER_1:  before they went into this octo-wog configuration where there's eight, like a ring of eight engines with a center engine in the middle.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm still in the same diameter that the rocket was the fuselage is more or less the same 3.7 meter wide diameter
SPEAKER_1:  but the actual thrust structure changed. One of the big efficiency gains was
SPEAKER_1:  you no longer have a corner engine and then like a.
SPEAKER_1:  edge engine and then another corner engine. You can just make eight.
SPEAKER_1:  of the same.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  Part of the OctaWeb it's called.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, the same shape.
SPEAKER_1:  And then your interchangeability and your manufacturability becomes a lot simpler.
SPEAKER_1:  So that was kind of one of the bigger upgrades at first and they kept stretching it. Every time they like touch this thing, it got longer and taller and taller technically.
SPEAKER_1:  And then the next big feature that you saw.
SPEAKER_1:  and 20.
SPEAKER_1:  would have been they added landing legs.
SPEAKER_1:  to a Falcon 9 rocket, which is...
SPEAKER_1:  I was at, that was the first launch I ever went to, was actually to see.
SPEAKER_1:  It was CRS3, so Commercial Resupply Mission 3, and it was probably there.
SPEAKER_1:  God, I don't remember what that was like.
SPEAKER_1:  their 14th or 15th launch or something like pretty early on.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, and people were literally laughing at the idea of them putting landing.
SPEAKER_1:  They just thought it was stupid. They're like, why are they wasting? Why is this billionaire Elon Musk guy wasting his time trying to
SPEAKER_1:  land a rocket, it's not gonna work.
SPEAKER_0:  You said the Mars plan was there in the beginning.
SPEAKER_0:  What about the reusability of rockets?
SPEAKER_0:  Was that there in the beginning?
SPEAKER_1:  I think reusability definitely, you know, it's a
SPEAKER_1:  necessary part of.
SPEAKER_1:  making any kind of interplanetary.
SPEAKER_1:  Mission.
SPEAKER_1:  in order to actually do that, just...
SPEAKER_1:  financially you have to start reusing these things.
SPEAKER_0:  of the development of the Falcon 1 and Falcon 9.
SPEAKER_0:  How?
SPEAKER_0:  Early on did the.
SPEAKER_0:  Golov
SPEAKER_0:  reusing the rocket, having the rocket actually land.
SPEAKER_0:  How early did that gold creep in?
SPEAKER_1:  I can't speak for Elon and SpaceX, but it was pretty, you know, immediately they wanted to try to recover. I think the very first two Falcon 9 rockets in.
SPEAKER_1:  Falcon 1, I think they even wanted to try to recover.
SPEAKER_1:  using parachutes to recover the first stage.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, and now fast forward, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  almost 20 years later and Rocket Lab is actually doing a concept like that.
SPEAKER_1:  where they're pulling a parachute.
SPEAKER_1:  After the first stage is re-entering and they actually are trying to recover it with a helicopter. He's going to try to snatch it out of the air.
SPEAKER_1:  They've actually done it. They've actually done it successfully once.
SPEAKER_0:  How does the helicopter grab the rocket?
SPEAKER_1:  With this giant like drag line and a hook. Oh, and then literally just like.
SPEAKER_1:  grab snags onto the parachute.
SPEAKER_1:  Wow. And it's pretty amazing. But this is a small rocket. Their rocket's only about a metric ton.
SPEAKER_1:  that the booster is empty.
SPEAKER_0:  So the rocket releases parachutes.
SPEAKER_0:  Alexa, like
SPEAKER_0:  really high up.
SPEAKER_0:  I'd love to see this. Yeah. That's an interesting idea. Interesting, interesting idea.
SPEAKER_0:  ideas and possibilities like SpaceX.
SPEAKER_0:  basically just innovated.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of different weird ideas.
SPEAKER_0:  just in the pursuit of making things more efficient, reusable.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  So basically thinking from first principles how to solve this problem.
SPEAKER_0:  And so what you find is like, you'll get all these kinds of crazy kind of solutions.
SPEAKER_1:  And with SpaceX, they weren't even getting to the point of the booster surviving reentry long enough to be able to pull the parachutes. Yeah. You know, they're mass fractions, you know, and that varies.
SPEAKER_1:  Every single rocket's different, you know, all the...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, for instance, Rocket Lab uses carbon composite.
SPEAKER_1:  fuselage and tanks.
SPEAKER_1:  or you know same thing and that's very very lightweight has
SPEAKER_1:  really good mass fractions and therefore their drag coefficients and things like that.
SPEAKER_1:  we're able to survive reentry.
SPEAKER_1:  of the first stage, which is something that SpaceX wasn't able to do at the time.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, what's what the kind of the big, I think breakthrough for SpaceX with reusing the booster.
SPEAKER_1:  Is they uh...
SPEAKER_1:  they realized we have to basically slow down before we hit the atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  So they actually do what they used to call a reentry burn, which I still think is the correct term, because it is reentering the atmosphere. But now they call it the entry burn.
SPEAKER_1:  and they light up three of the nine Merlin engines.
SPEAKER_1:  Not only to slow it down, but actually even while those engines are firing it creates like a
SPEAKER_1:  a literal like force field as it's.
SPEAKER_1:  falling through the atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  Interesting. And, uh, but it also.
SPEAKER_1:  decreases the velocity by almost half.
SPEAKER_1:  are around half and then that therefore decreases the amount of
SPEAKER_1:  You know, the biggest thing with the atmosphere is that as it gets compressed against...
SPEAKER_1:  the front of any.
SPEAKER_1:  anything flying through the atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  the compressed atoms just get hot.
SPEAKER_1:  and they can get so hot they turn into a plasma and they get so hot they can just absolutely destroy anything.
SPEAKER_1:  So they slow down enough that the
SPEAKER_1:  Air molecules don't end up.
SPEAKER_1:  destroying the vehicle on reentry.
SPEAKER_1:  And then they realized, I think at some point it's probably a similar crossover. They're like, well, if we're lighting the engines already and it slowed down in the atmosphere, we can just use that.
SPEAKER_1:  Same engine to land.
SPEAKER_1:  And so like, well, what if we just stuck landing legs on it?
SPEAKER_1:  just landed the thing vertically and.
SPEAKER_1:  Next thing you know is December 21st, 2015. They did exactly that for the first time. I feel part of the press ocean.
SPEAKER_0:  So you were there before that then, right? Yeah, yep.
SPEAKER_1:  2014. Yep, early 2014. So that and for me, like that was so fun watching.
SPEAKER_1:  That was the peak of me just becoming obsessed with.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, with this idea I'm watching with.
SPEAKER_1:  Like in back in the day, it was like months between launches. You know, so a launch was like a big idea. Wake up at 3 a.m.
SPEAKER_1:  to watch this landing attempt or whatever, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Every, you know, there's CRS four.
SPEAKER_1:  Almost landed, CRS5.
SPEAKER_1:  Almost landed CRS6, CRS7 blew up. I was watching that on, I think it was like a Saturday morning.
SPEAKER_1:  or maybe a Sunday morning. And I remember watching that and watch it blow up. I'm sick of it.
SPEAKER_1:  Now what, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  It blew up on a scent.
SPEAKER_1:  It was their first failure. So it was their 18th flight, I believe.
SPEAKER_1:  Sierra 7, the upper stage had a...
SPEAKER_1:  one of the bottles inside the tanks that are filled with helium and one of those bottles broke off on a send.
SPEAKER_1:  and actually just completely over pressured the upper stage and the upper stage blew up and the whole rocket went kaboom.
SPEAKER_1:  in an uncontrolled manner.
SPEAKER_1:  And so, so then they came back with vengeance. When they came back, the first mission back is the first time that they landed a rocket, which was awesome.
SPEAKER_1:  So the return to flight after the anomaly was...
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it was landing a rocket.
SPEAKER_0:  I stuck the landing. Yep, nailed it. Well, actually the first time, so the first time you were there, what was that like?
SPEAKER_0:  What do you remember from that day?
SPEAKER_1:  Just, I was surprised at how much bigger the rocket was than I imagined. I was, I originally, when I was going down to Kennedy Space Center, I was disappointed that I wasn't seeing like a.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  I didn't know a ton about rockets. I knew enough to like, no.
SPEAKER_1:  what a space shuttle was, what like the Saturn V was, you know, but that was probably about the end of my knowledge. I just remember being disappointed.
SPEAKER_1:  that I wasn't seeing a big quote unquote NASA rocket flying.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I was thinking in my head like, oh, I'm gonna see this launch. It's probably gonna be like.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, three stories tall or something, you know, just some little skinny little stick and
SPEAKER_1:  little firecracker and yay, you know, and I think I'd almost been pitched that too, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  the people that I was working for at the time, I think they kind of were downplaying it. It's like, well, it's not a big rocket, it's not gonna be that exciting, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  But we get out there to the pad and I'm like.
SPEAKER_1:  This thing's huge. This is not a small rocket. Like, this is-
SPEAKER_1:  It's 70 meters tall, 220 feet tall. It's huge.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, and I think people forget like the scale of that, you know, it might look skinny and tall and all this stuff, but.
SPEAKER_1:  It's still a very, very large piece of machinery. It's physically about as large as you can ship.
SPEAKER_1:  The booster is about as big as you can ship across the country, period.
SPEAKER_1:  without like completely shutting down highways. You know, it is made within those exact specifications of.
SPEAKER_1:  of having lane privileges and bridges and everything. It's 12 feet wide.
SPEAKER_1:  3.7 meters wide and it's 45 meters long.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's like exactly what you can fit.
SPEAKER_1:  with a
SPEAKER_1:  pretty standard, you know, like before we start getting into crazy amounts of problems shipping the rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  It's huge. It's huge. And people just don't understand that. And so when I saw with my own eyes, I remember just being like,
SPEAKER_1:  This is so much cooler than I thought.
SPEAKER_0:  It's hard to believe that that thing is gonna have to lift off the ground and launch up into the air Maybe that's the most humbling aspect of it. That's something that size.
SPEAKER_0:  Humans have come up with a way to take something that size and launch it up into the air.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, there's certainly a very humbling aspect when you watch it actually leave.
SPEAKER_0:  Was there sound to it? Was there like a feeling? What were the different experiences that you first remember?
SPEAKER_1:  Well, ironically, I didn't end up getting to see that one fly.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, I went home. My camera saw it. I left my camera out there.
SPEAKER_1:  like a remote triggered camera.
SPEAKER_1:  My first images as a launch photographer at the time was CRS3, but I went home. It scrubbed too many times. Now this is back in the day. They were scrubbing like.
SPEAKER_1:  often and they'd be like a three day, five day, seven day, you just never knew.
SPEAKER_1:  So I go home and I watch the live stream of it. So I didn't even get to experience.
SPEAKER_1:  My first launch and anyone that's ever tried to, you know, go to a launch is, can probably empathize because yeah, scrubs are very common in the space flight world.
SPEAKER_1:  So that one I didn't get to see, but since then obviously I've been able to.
SPEAKER_1:  attend very many launches.
SPEAKER_0:  How much do you understand the control involved in the landing? How difficult is that problem?
SPEAKER_1:  I couldn't tell you a single thing about the code and the avionics behind it, but I can tell you all the hardware that makes it happen.
SPEAKER_1:  if that helps.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, that, I mean, to me, it seems like whenever I talk to people, they say it's not.
SPEAKER_0:  that big of a deal in terms of the level of intelligence and the control. But to me, it's just like when you observe it.
SPEAKER_0:  It seems incredible.
SPEAKER_0:  because of all the variables involved.
SPEAKER_0:  all the uncertainties involved, all the...
SPEAKER_0:  Um, because there's aerodynamics, I mean, like there's different temperatures. There's so much going on with the fuel, the burning.
SPEAKER_0:  the combustion, just everything that's going on.
SPEAKER_0:  to be able to perform control at such high stakes.
SPEAKER_0:  Effectively.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, you know, that code is probably not written in JavaScript, I guess is what I'm saying.
SPEAKER_1:  Actually, no, I don't.
SPEAKER_1:  If I remember, again, this is well outside of my domain, but.
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm, they're coding in a common language, it's...
SPEAKER_1:  is
SPEAKER_0:  probably going to be C.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I'm pretty sure it is and that was one of the things that's weird is that Elon when he you know started SpaceX like we're just gonna code in the most common language so that
SPEAKER_1:  We don't have to like have people learn this archaic, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  weird thing and we can just literally pull people off the streets and be like, here, write it.
SPEAKER_0:  That's probably C++. I mean, it'd be epic if it was like Python or something, but I think reliable systems have to be written in C++ probably.
SPEAKER_0:  which is a common language, which is something I imagine like NASA engineers would probably have to use in some kind of proprietary language.
SPEAKER_0:  in the olden days.
SPEAKER_0:  for security, for privacy, all that kind of stuff. eig already beast got that
SPEAKER_1:  old, old days, like they were inventing code and language from scratch.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, for sure. It's still incredible that it's able to do that. Like just the feat of engineering involved is just, it's truly.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like one of the marvels to observe about these rockets coming back to Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  that they're able to land.
SPEAKER_0:  Like the drama of it is just incredible to see.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, well, one of the fun things to remember too, specifically with the Falcon 9 and the Falcon 9, or Falcon Heavy boosters, I mean, it's the same thing basically.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  they shut down all but one of the nine engines.
SPEAKER_1:  and even with that one engine at its minimum throttle setting.
SPEAKER_1:  It's still too much thrust to hover.
SPEAKER_1:  So as this rocket's coming down.
SPEAKER_1:  if they start a little bit too early, if they light that engine too early.
SPEAKER_1:  it will actually stop above the ground.
SPEAKER_1:  and will not be able to.
SPEAKER_1:  Lower itself.
SPEAKER_1:  It will literally stop like, say it stopped 200 feet above the ground.
SPEAKER_1:  their only option is to kill the engine and then it's just gonna fall those 200 feet
SPEAKER_1:  So they, it's.
SPEAKER_1:  what we call like a suicide burn or a hover slam kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  interchangeable terms.
SPEAKER_1:  because your thrust to weight ratio is never below one.
SPEAKER_1:  So they have to actually literally be riding the throttle. So what you do is you kind of start.
SPEAKER_1:  Ideally, you know, you kind of start like in the middle of your window of throttle range. So let's pretend your engine can throttle down to 40%.
SPEAKER_1:  of its maximum rated thrust.
SPEAKER_1:  You might start at like 70% of thrust.
SPEAKER_1:  in the middle of that like window of where it could burn. So that, so if all of a sudden it's kind of coming in too hot, you have room to throttle up. If you're coming into, you're actually, you know, a little too early, you throttle it down. You have a little bit of wiggle room.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just amazing how smoothly and how perfectly they're able to still control that thing, even though they're down to one engine out of the nine.
SPEAKER_1:  and they're still riding like the finest margin of what's possible. They're continually playing with that to try to get it.
SPEAKER_1:  because every every bit of fuel they're using and proponent they're using
SPEAKER_1:  to land.
SPEAKER_1:  is propellant they weren't using to put something into space. So they want that to be as efficient as possible. They're really like watching them hone that in and.
SPEAKER_1:  and just continue to evolve and edit that and just get it to be the workhorse. We're coming up on 100.
SPEAKER_1:  consecutive landings.
SPEAKER_1:  perfect landings, 100. I think they've done like 150 something landings altogether, 168, 160 altogether.
SPEAKER_1:  but we're talking like in a row.
SPEAKER_1:  without blowing up, which five years ago was completely experimental and insane.
SPEAKER_1:  and now we're coming up to the point where we're-
SPEAKER_1:  hundred in a row it's like this is becoming
SPEAKER_1:  more reliable in the landing, which is not the primary mission. This is purely for SpaceX's like gain is to recover the booster.
SPEAKER_1:  It has nothing to do with the effect of getting the payload on orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, most of the time. and
SPEAKER_1:  The landing is really only for their their benefit in their gain
SPEAKER_0:  Long term gain
SPEAKER_0:  like it's a long-term investment.
SPEAKER_0:  in being able to recover the boosters. Can you believe all this was done in basically 10 years? So we've seen this development.
SPEAKER_0:  over a period of 10 years. So like where we started.
SPEAKER_0:  Wow, commercial space flight.
SPEAKER_0:  at scale.
SPEAKER_0:  today where it's almost uh...
SPEAKER_0:  almost starting to
SPEAKER_0:  be mundane. Watch AMN.
SPEAKER_1:  How can I be able to do?
SPEAKER_1:  I can't really believe it. I mean, obviously even just in the
SPEAKER_1:  I think I'm a fairly fair weather fan really didn't start paying attention to like 2014.
SPEAKER_1:  And just seeing what it was like back then to what it's like, like I don't watch every launch at all anymore. Like I'll catch the big ones. I'll stream some of the really big ones. But like back in the day, I, like I said, would wake up in the middle of the night to catch these streams or, you know, catch these launches and watch them.
SPEAKER_1:  because they were such a big deal and there's maybe only.
SPEAKER_1:  Five of them a year, you know? And so it's a really big deal. Nowadays it's like, oh yeah, there's...
SPEAKER_1:  literally like two a week on average now.
SPEAKER_1:  It's insane. From SpaceX alone.
SPEAKER_1:  Let alone, you know, United Launch Alliance, Rocket Lab.
SPEAKER_1:  any of the Chinese missions, you know, I mean, all of there's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's insane, it's hard to...
SPEAKER_1:  really really really hard to keep up with. i wonder what he is doing. the same blank sky, though not perfect,
SPEAKER_0:  at which point in the future.
SPEAKER_0:  the number of launches to orbit will exceed the number of launches of airplanes.
SPEAKER_0:  like on the surface of Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  I have to admit I kind of have a hard time.
SPEAKER_1:  extrapolating out that far.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there's a lot of people that are like big futurists and really do think about like interplanetary stuff and think about colonizing Mars and stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  I have a hard time predicting like.
SPEAKER_1:  when Starship's gonna fly, the orbital launch. You know, and that's like-
SPEAKER_1:  Inmanent ish like month or two scale timeframe and yet I'm still like
SPEAKER_1:  I can't tell you anything about when we're gonna land on Mars or what that's...
SPEAKER_1:  what that economy and what that, you know, the scale of launch operations is going to look like in order to do that because it's just so hard to, I wouldn't have predicted.
SPEAKER_1:  or at today five years ago, you know, it's insane. It's so hard to predict and
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, but it's funny because there's so many like new companies starting up trying to predict that and it's a really exciting.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, startup culture.
SPEAKER_0:  I think when you make certain engineering decisions...
SPEAKER_0:  and hiring decisions and like what you focus on in terms of both business.
SPEAKER_0:  and engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  It's good to think.
SPEAKER_0:  on the scale of 10, 20, 50, 100 years. It's one of the things that you'll
SPEAKER_0:  exceptionally good at.
SPEAKER_0:  which is asking.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... the question of okay this might seem impossible right now but
SPEAKER_0:  What's the obvious way to do this if we look out 20 years?
SPEAKER_0:  And then you start to...
SPEAKER_0:  make decisions. You said make decisions about robotics, about brain and computer interfaces, about...
SPEAKER_0:  space travel there.
SPEAKER_0:  Amik.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of sense when you look at the scale of 10, 20, 15, 100 years.
SPEAKER_0:  and don't make any sense if you look at the scale of just months.
SPEAKER_0:  but of course the actual work.
SPEAKER_0:  of day to day is focused on the next few months.
SPEAKER_0:  There's deadlines, there's missions you have to accomplish.
SPEAKER_0:  Anyway, we are.
SPEAKER_1:  turning back to the brief history.
SPEAKER_0:  rockets.
SPEAKER_0:  Alright.
SPEAKER_0:  The Falcon Heavy, so what else is there? So we talked about Falcon 9 and the rapid development there. What other flavors of Falcon is there and how does that take us to Starship?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, realistically, the Falcon 9 evolved more or less.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of like just got more powerful a little bit longer and more capable
SPEAKER_1:  but nowadays they fly what's called the Block 5, even though it's like the-
SPEAKER_1:  eighth or ninth iteration of the Falcon out, but they call it block five.
SPEAKER_1:  It's the one that has the black landing legs, the black inner stage.
SPEAKER_1:  They have a fleet of roughly ten or so that are doing the majority of the leg work these days.
SPEAKER_1:  and they're flying up to 15 times, I think right now is the current.
SPEAKER_1:  booster leader.
SPEAKER_1:  They're also recovering the fairings to the nose cone of the rockets.
SPEAKER_1:  frequently if not every time being recovered.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Same with the booster for the most part.
SPEAKER_1:  And the only thing being expanded is the upper stage. And that's kind of where the Falcon nine is.
SPEAKER_1:  ending it really doesn't make
SPEAKER_1:  sense to develop that infrastructure any longer. So they went.
SPEAKER_1:  with the next step, which is go even bigger.
SPEAKER_1:  physically so they have more margin for upper stage reusability.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's what we see with Starship and Super Heavy.
SPEAKER_1:  So the super heavy booster.
SPEAKER_1:  The whole system is confusing the whole system is kind of considered Starship
SPEAKER_1:  But technically the Starship is just the upper stage, which is also like the spaceship, which is also the upper stage.
SPEAKER_1:  And then the booster itself is considered the super heavy booster.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's what they've been working on. Publicly, it came out in 2016 as the
SPEAKER_1:  The timer is the ITS, the enter.
SPEAKER_1:  Planetary Transportation System.
SPEAKER_1:  Later and I think about 20s by the end of that year 2017 and kind of became known as the BFR the big
SPEAKER_1:  Falcon Rocket? Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  And then I think it was about end of 2018 they started calling it Starship
SPEAKER_1:  But that is the...
SPEAKER_1:  That is where we're at today and that's what they're.
SPEAKER_1:  working full steam ahead on.
SPEAKER_0:  And what about dragon? I know we mentioned dragon, crew dragon, cargo dragon.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so they went from the
SPEAKER_1:  Cargo version of Dragon that flew about 20 times.
SPEAKER_1:  successfully to the International Space Station, except for that one CRS-7 where the rocket blew up in the
SPEAKER_1:  capsule obviously didn't make it to the ISS.
SPEAKER_1:  Then they went into the Dragon 2, which has two variants. It has a crew variant, so we just call it crew dragon, and then there's the cargo version of Dragon 2.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's just an updated, sleeker, sexier version of Dragon and it's...
SPEAKER_1:  Ironically, it's heavier altogether, so it.
SPEAKER_1:  You'll never see those cool return to launch site landing, the boosters coming back to land for CRS missions anymore like we used to.
SPEAKER_1:  but they landed on the drone ship anyway.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  And yeah, that's been flying successfully. That's kind of the, so there's the Starlink, Dragon, Falcon 9, Falcon Heavy, and Starship system as kind of the whole.
SPEAKER_1:  The whole SpaceX world.
SPEAKER_0:  really in terms of the the the spaceships involved. So what to you are some of the major milestones in that history?
SPEAKER_0:  We kind of mentioned a f-
SPEAKER_0:  you.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Sticking the landing. Kind of stands out.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I would say definitely the big ones, obviously, like any of the first, like the first flight of Falcon one, first flight of Falcon nine, first time they went to the International Space Station.
SPEAKER_1:  the first time they landed a booster.
SPEAKER_1:  The first time they reuse a booster, which is...
SPEAKER_1:  Think about six months after, no, oh, it was a year after. Cheers, FF IT, and ellerzojs.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  20th.
SPEAKER_1:  It was the first time they reused one of those boosters, you know, and that was a big milestone. play.
SPEAKER_1:  And we even, yeah, we recovered one.
SPEAKER_1:  caught one, you know, it's like we got one now what?
SPEAKER_1:  That was the first time that we flew one.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, then Flying Humans was a huge one. DM2, Bob and Doug.
SPEAKER_1:  for NASA.
SPEAKER_1:  Bob and Doug, yeah. Bob and Doug, that was incredible. That was a huge, huge step, I think, for SpaceX, with flying people.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's a first major commercial.
SPEAKER_0:  launching of humans out into space.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and not just into space, because you know, there's been people that have...
SPEAKER_1:  done space flights with suborbital hops.
SPEAKER_1:  going into orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  and especially docking and rendezvousing with the International Space Station is a big deal.
SPEAKER_1:  Until you really understand the physics involved in the scale involved with like just crossing the carmine line going straight up versus
SPEAKER_1:  going into orbit, like they're just completely different things almost.
SPEAKER_0:  What about Starship?
SPEAKER_0:  Are we in a place where we can talk about milestones with Starship?
SPEAKER_0:  Has there been, or has it just been an epic journey of failure and successes of testing?
SPEAKER_0:  and so on.
SPEAKER_0:  What would you classify at this point as a...
SPEAKER_0:  as a milestone, a starship or BFR, whatever the name is, was able to achieve.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, so far the milestones we've seen, I'd say the first one would be the hop of, they call it Star Hopper, and it's basically a very rudimentary rocket, but it was the first time they...
SPEAKER_1:  They utilized their new Raptor engine to produce.
SPEAKER_1:  thrusted to fly something.
SPEAKER_1:  It first flew like
SPEAKER_1:  literally like three meters off the ground or something like tethered to the ground. Then it flew like 15 and then finally it flew 150 meters.
SPEAKER_1:  And that was in 2019.
SPEAKER_1:  And that was the first big milestone of Starship. And then after that we saw...
SPEAKER_1:  SN5, SN6 kind of do the similar like 150 meter hops with a little bit more.
SPEAKER_1:  elegant systems, you know, proving out more of their, their tank building, proving out more of their.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, a lot of just subsystems and then.
SPEAKER_1:  The big ones.
SPEAKER_1:  Physically we're in N.
SPEAKER_1:  End of 2020 and early 2021 when they flew the.
SPEAKER_1:  SN 8, 9, 10, 11, and 15.
SPEAKER_0:  What does the N stand for in SN? Hey guys, welcome back to cover SC?'s New Leave.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't remember or
SPEAKER_0:  start to number. Yeah. So I said these are just names, numbers.
SPEAKER_0:  numerical representations of the different testing.
SPEAKER_0:  efforts.
SPEAKER_0:  They skipped some numbers, right? Yeah. If they scratch, uh,
SPEAKER_1:  tests.
SPEAKER_1:  One foot is always in front of someone else's foot and like the arm is not knowing what the leg is doing sometimes with that, right? They will have someone working on, you know, they'll just be like, I'm going to step up and build 40 of these tank sections.
SPEAKER_1:  and you build the bulkhead and you build the down comer and you build the header tank blah blah blah
SPEAKER_1:  And all of a sudden like, oh, we actually evolved that. We don't use that header tank now. So it's gonna go onto this one. So they'll have like parts of-
SPEAKER_1:  certain rockets built.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like, ask, literally scrap it. Like not scrap it like in the.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, joke term, but like literally just go scrap it.
SPEAKER_1:  And they, so yeah, they just evolve and iterate so quickly.
SPEAKER_0:  There were some epic explosions.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I think Starship.
SPEAKER_0:  something about it.
SPEAKER_0:  probably just the amount of fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  just leads to some epic failures. Would you say Starship is the source of the most epic failures in terms of size of explosion?
SPEAKER_1:  So you can literally measure it in like a yield of explosive power, you know, like you could TNT. Like you can take a look at how much propellant is left over at the time of the explosion. And you know, Starship, what's flown so far, even though it's physically one of the largest flying objects ever.
SPEAKER_1:  Just with the upper stage alone.
SPEAKER_1:  They've not filled it more than like 10 or 20% full of propellant.
SPEAKER_1:  And so it actually hasn't been, the failures have been really-
SPEAKER_1:  epic looking.
SPEAKER_1:  big visual fireballs, but in terms of space flight, they're still
SPEAKER_1:  pretty small explosions, believe it or not. They could still go bigger. Oh yeah, a lot, a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  and of course.
SPEAKER_0:  the test payload of a Tesla Roadster was launched.
SPEAKER_0:  I forget what year that was. Yeah, that was 2018. That was quite epic. Would you put that on the milestone? Seales
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah, Falcon Heavy demo was like.
SPEAKER_1:  Definitely a.
SPEAKER_0:  A big, big, big milestone, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Is that?
SPEAKER_0:  funny to you that there's a roadster floating out there. Do we know the location of that roadster at this point? Oh yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Whereisroadster.com
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah? Oh yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Where's is it orbiting something? Yeah, it's orbiting the Sun
SPEAKER_1:  So it's orbiting the sun.
SPEAKER_1:  And its orbit is basically between the Earth's orbit and beyond Mars. So I think of like 2.5 AU, if I remember right. Like 2.5 AU  alles nicht zh Let's fold it up and focus, and cover it up. Oh yes!
SPEAKER_1:  It's beyond Mars' orbit at its highest point, and it's back at Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of at its lowest point.
SPEAKER_0:  I wonder if there's a mission or a-
SPEAKER_0:  you're going to.
SPEAKER_0:  somehow connect with it once again and place extra things into it
SPEAKER_0:  I wonder how challenging that is technically.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah, it could absolutely be done.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, the hard thing at this point, because it's on an eccentric orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  would be rendezvousing with it, because you kind of had to be in alignment with its orbit to really line up well with it. Yeah. But yeah, I mean, someday I don't see any reason why we couldn't at least send for sure an uncrewed, you know, a felon wanted to just fly a...
SPEAKER_1:  a robot out there to check up on it photograph it or something like we could
SPEAKER_1:  that could be well within the realm of things.
SPEAKER_0:  get an optimus robot up there.
SPEAKER_0:  So that was the story brilliantly told by you of the rockets for SpaceX. What about through the lens of engines?
SPEAKER_0:  Can you give a brief history of the SpaceX rocket engines that were...
SPEAKER_0:  used that we haven't covered. She's mentioned all started with the Merlin engine.
SPEAKER_0:  and a customer engine what...
SPEAKER_0:  their foot through that lens.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, what's there? The engines are relatively small number, which is, which is easy for us. So does the other Merlin and Merlin's evolved throughout time to be.
SPEAKER_1:  from like the Merlin to the Merlin 1C to the Merlin 1D full thrust and all these other kind of
SPEAKER_1:  tweaks of the same architecture.
SPEAKER_1:  Kestrel ended with Falcon 1.
SPEAKER_1:  They also have the Merlin vacuum engine, which is the upper stage engine for Falcon 9.
SPEAKER_1:  Same relative system, but just optimized for vacuum. So as a much larger valve nozzle.
SPEAKER_1:  There's the Draco thrusters, which you kind of can consider engines. Well, they are rocket engines, but they're just.
SPEAKER_1:  Smaller, not like the...
SPEAKER_1:  orbital engines, there's the super Draco engines, which are the abort thrusters.
SPEAKER_1:  on
SPEAKER_1:  on Crew Dragon Capsule.
SPEAKER_1:  And then nowadays they have the Raptor engine.
SPEAKER_1:  and the Raptor vacuum variant. But they've already had two versions of Raptor. We've already seen kind of the Raptor development engine.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm kind of like a rapper one point five words.
SPEAKER_1:  of taking hints of
SPEAKER_1:  the future Raptor, but now we're.
SPEAKER_1:  While within the, while within what-
SPEAKER_1:  you'd consider a Raptor 2 variant.
SPEAKER_1:  That's really it.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, for the Raptor.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe I'll ask you that separately, but I like in general.
SPEAKER_0:  and people.
SPEAKER_0:  Who doesn't know?
SPEAKER_0:  whoever the astronaut is, but if you don't somehow know, go go go check his-
SPEAKER_0:  your YouTube channel out. You're an incredible educator.
SPEAKER_0:  about the the super technical and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  the more sort of
SPEAKER_0:  even though the philosophical the actual like the the actual space travel so you go down to the.
SPEAKER_0:  raw details of it. And there's just great videos on the Raptor engine.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I think you have one on Marlin.
SPEAKER_0:  and also the actual tours with Elon where he discusses some of those things.
SPEAKER_0:  On one of the tours he says, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  He's full of good lines that guy. He says something about.
SPEAKER_0:  the number of fiddly bits.
SPEAKER_0:  And he's, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  the number of fiddly bits was decreased between
SPEAKER_0:  Raptor.
SPEAKER_0:  one or after one. Yeah. I think that's actually a really beautiful representation of, um,
SPEAKER_0:  the engineering efforts there, which is constantly trying to simplify.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... increase the efficiency of the engines but also
SPEAKER_0:  simplify the design so you can manufacture it.
SPEAKER_0:  And in general, simplification leads to...
SPEAKER_0:  better performance and testing and everything. So the number of 50 bits.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm sure there's a Wikipedia page on that now as an index is actually a really good one.
SPEAKER_1:  And when you think about it, I don't know of any other company prior that had
SPEAKER_1:  of try to measure their performance of their engine not in like thrust to weight ratio or like how efficient it is like in specific impulse but literally in like
SPEAKER_1:  dollar to thrust ratio? Are you still here?
SPEAKER_1:  Does this engine cost? How much thrust can it produce?
SPEAKER_1:  and like.
SPEAKER_1:  using that as a trade study instead of just like pure metrics of
SPEAKER_1:  You know, because at the end of the day, like...
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, if it's cheaper and does X amount of work, even if it's less efficient, it can actually be.
SPEAKER_1:  better long term.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I guess another way is not even just thrust.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if that metric is used, but basically the cost of getting one kilogram.
SPEAKER_0:  of thing up into space.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that's basically what they're trying to minimize.
SPEAKER_1:  Especially, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  at the
SPEAKER_1:  at the end of the day, that is definitely the ultimate metric is how much does one kilogram cost to orbit eventually, you know, and but there's it's so funny because
SPEAKER_1:  Spaceflight is just the ultimate.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's the ultimate compromise. Every little thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Any variable can just change everything else. So you can tweak so many different things to get to different.
SPEAKER_1:  numbers and conclusions, you know, but even things like
SPEAKER_1:  on your first stage when the rocket's pointing straight up and the engines are pointing straight down
SPEAKER_1:  you're dealing more with the thrust to weight ratio of the rocket. What thrust is it producing versus how much?
SPEAKER_1:  is gravity pulling down on it.
SPEAKER_1:  is actually a more important metric than how raw, efficient the engine is.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's funny then in space, it's kind of the opposite thrust to weight ratio it doesn't really matter.
SPEAKER_1:  What really matters is the actual, the specific impulse is called.
SPEAKER_1:  nozzle escape velocity of the or the ejection velocity of the
SPEAKER_1:  how fast is the gas moving is like the more important number on orbit, but it's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just so crazy because there's all these like I would just love to see.
SPEAKER_1:  the trade studies, you know, when you're like trying to figure out like, is this more important than this or this or this? like,
SPEAKER_1:  You change this one little thing and all of a sudden, you know, like all the everything changes. It's just.
SPEAKER_1:  Even the profile, the launch profile, the trajectory of it, the, I mean, everything.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything I wonder what that trade-out discussions are like is you can't really perfectly plan everything
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  And you always have to have some.
SPEAKER_0:  Spare.
SPEAKER_0:  leave way and especially as you're...
SPEAKER_0:  testing new vehicles like Starship.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, margins are important.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, having a margin, given all the uncertainty that's there.
SPEAKER_0:  That's really interesting like how they do those kinds of trade-offs because they're also rapidly designing and redesigning and re-engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh... the-
SPEAKER_0:  Ultimately, you want to give yourself the freedom to constantly innovate, but then through the process of testing.
SPEAKER_0:  you solidify the thing that can be relied upon, especially if it's a crude mission.
SPEAKER_0:  at that, how to do that in a rapid cycle.
SPEAKER_1:  I remember at some point...
SPEAKER_1:  that NASA, as they're leading up to flying humans for the first time for NASA.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there's some talk that like, we're going to do a design freeze.
SPEAKER_1:  because SpaceX does evolve and iterate so quickly.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, they were saying that it was leading, because especially at the time, it was a mission called AMOS 6, and they lost a rocket. They only lost two rockets.
SPEAKER_1:  ever really as far as um
SPEAKER_1:  you know, trying to get something to space. For the Falcon 9, sorry.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  The second one, Amos 6, I mean, that was back in 2016. So it's been a long time.
SPEAKER_1:  And uh...
SPEAKER_1:  But at the time, you know, they're looking at.
SPEAKER_1:  flying humans in the near future.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's like, if you guys keep...
SPEAKER_1:  tweaking this thing every time you take it out to the pad.
SPEAKER_1:  really is gonna be a problem, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  And so there is some pressure.
SPEAKER_1:  from NASA to kind of slow down on that iterative process.
SPEAKER_1:  And, but that is also why they were able to evolve Falcon 9 to be what it is today is because they did.
SPEAKER_1:  evolve it so quickly. Literally like one after another was never really the same and we're definitely seeing that with Starship now. Like it's...
SPEAKER_1:  It evolved so quickly.
SPEAKER_1:  that you just can't even keep up with it, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  So there's a fascinating culture.
SPEAKER_0:  Clash there. Have you just?
SPEAKER_0:  in observing and interacting with NASA folks, seen them.
SPEAKER_0:  sort of grow and change and evolve themselves, sort of inspired by this.
SPEAKER_0:  New developments in commercial spaceflight.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah, yeah, yeah. There's a lot of, especially like around DM too, there's a lot of talks and the press conferences and stuff where you'd hear people say.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, this was a big, this is well outside of our comfort zone to work with SpaceX in this manner because we're, we take this approach to things where.
SPEAKER_1:  X, Y, and Z in this way, the way we normally certify things.
SPEAKER_1:  and we're not used to SpaceX like.
SPEAKER_1:  well, let's just try it, you know, like, and do something, you know, to a point. And so they said it ended up being fantastic. They loved working that way because it was just.
SPEAKER_1:  Less paperwork almost and more just do.
SPEAKER_1:  And, um...
SPEAKER_1:  And but at the same time, SpaceX, I think even expressed, I don't remember if it was Hans Koenigsmann or someone in a press conference said.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, we really liked having someone just double check us so that we're not doing something super stupid right before we test something, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  So there was a cool collaboration because it is.
SPEAKER_1:  two very different philosophies of.
SPEAKER_1:  of development and managing.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, space programs.
SPEAKER_0:  I wanted to talk to you a lot about engines.
SPEAKER_0:  and maybe about Starship and maybe about your own.
SPEAKER_0:  becoming an actual astronaut, but like, let's just go there.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  before all that and talk about.
SPEAKER_0:  the actual culture of SpaceX.
SPEAKER_0:  and your conversations with Elon. You've toured SpaceX facilities with him.
SPEAKER_0:  You've interviewed him, you've interacted with him.
SPEAKER_0:  What have you learned about rockets, about propulsion, about engineering, about design, about life from those interactions? What have you learned about rockets, about design, about engineering, about design, about life from those interactions?
SPEAKER_0:  as an engineer as a
SPEAKER_0:  as a leader, as a person.
SPEAKER_1:  I would definitely say the biggest takeaway I've had from...
SPEAKER_1:  by times.
SPEAKER_1:  with Elon at SpaceX is.
SPEAKER_1:  Really? Like the idea of questioning your constraints. He says that a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  also does it a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_1:  There'll be times where like.
SPEAKER_1:  you'll see him change on a dime because he's like rethinking of something in a newer different way and
SPEAKER_1:  For me, you know, I...
SPEAKER_1:  I think we all put constraints on ourselves. We think about our own limits, you know, on
SPEAKER_1:  on things that we can or cannot do. And I think it's made me kind of question like, why am I
SPEAKER_1:  Why did I say no I can't do that or you know?
SPEAKER_1:  Hey, hey.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, just off the top of my head.
SPEAKER_1:  A good example.
SPEAKER_1:  I, so in Iowa, I live in Iowa.
SPEAKER_1:  or half the time or whatever. There's a bike ride across the state of Iowa called Rag Bray.
SPEAKER_1:  And every year you just, you know, like thousands of people get together and they ride across Iowa.
SPEAKER_1:  And it was last summer.
SPEAKER_1:  I met up with some friends and they were like, hey, do you want to go on Rag Bride this year? And I'm like...
SPEAKER_1:  It's like a week away, they're like.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, you wanna go?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I did, you know, without, and it was one of those moments where I was proud of myself because it's easy to just be like, no.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I'm not ready or this is my constraint is like I'm not in shape.
SPEAKER_1:  But like just question that, you know? And so I think when it comes down to questioning your own constraints, it's yes, even to that level of like, why do you question yourself on what you can and cannot do?
SPEAKER_0:  So that's for your personal life is really powerful, but a little bit more intuitive.
SPEAKER_0:  I think what's really hard...
SPEAKER_0:  is to question constraints in a place like aeronautics or robotics or autonomous vehicles or vehicles.
SPEAKER_0:  because there's.
SPEAKER_0:  People, there's experts everywhere.
SPEAKER_0:  that have done it for decades.
SPEAKER_0:  and everyone admires those experts and respects those experts, and for you to step into a room.
SPEAKER_0:  annoying not much more than just
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  What's in a Wikipedia article?
SPEAKER_0:  and to just use your intuition and first principles thinking to disagree with the experts.
SPEAKER_0:  That takes some guts, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, you can't have everyone doing that either. You know, like there has to be some humility of knowing that something is a hardened.
SPEAKER_1:  concept and a hard and you know like especially i'm not an engineer i don't i don't do this stuff you know what i can imagine
SPEAKER_1:  You sitting there having spent six years on a type of valve that
SPEAKER_1:  perfectly manages crowd-genetic propellants or whatever. Someone walks in and says,
SPEAKER_1:  Why don't you just put a heater element in there? Or something that's, you know, something like bec- because-
SPEAKER_1:  You've done that 40 times or whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm sure there are things like that that are.
SPEAKER_1:  very frustrating but
SPEAKER_1:  But see, the thing is- That's like, you know-
SPEAKER_0:  The thing is with the experts, they're always going to be frustrated.
SPEAKER_0:  when the newbie comes in with their first principles thinking.
SPEAKER_0:  but sometimes that frustration is justified and sometimes it's not.
SPEAKER_0:  Sometimes it's just stubbornness.
SPEAKER_0:  for failing to acknowledge a better way.
SPEAKER_0:  and I've seen it both directions.
SPEAKER_0:  which is really interesting. Ryze is nearly as effective as any slow speed mouse where you can tolerate tasks you need...
SPEAKER_0:  You need both, but that tension is always going to be there.
SPEAKER_0:  and there has to be almost like a dictatorial.
SPEAKER_0:  imperative that breaks through.
SPEAKER_0:  the expertise of the way things have been done in the past.
SPEAKER_0:  to push forward like a new way of doing it. Elon's done that. I've seen a lot of...
SPEAKER_0:  great engineers do that in the machine learning world because there's been so much development
SPEAKER_0:  I've seen that happen. Usually when there's like rapid development that starts.
SPEAKER_0:  common to play.
SPEAKER_0:  And yeah, and I've seen that autonomous vehicle space.
SPEAKER_0:  Brain computer interfaces that Elon has evolved with all of it
SPEAKER_0:  It's kind of fascinating to watch.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  What about the actual design and engineering of the engine? What about the design and engineering of the engine?
SPEAKER_0:  about so many different kinds of engines.
SPEAKER_0:  over the past few years.
SPEAKER_0:  Just like what stands out to you about the way that engineering is done at SpaceX or that-
SPEAKER_0:  Elon does engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  Dude.
SPEAKER_1:  hardest thing to do.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of remember is like how much stuff was developed in the 50s and 60s.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, the concepts finally being utilized today were.
SPEAKER_1:  already literally done in the sixties. Yeah,
SPEAKER_1:  You know, so a lot of the things that SpaceX is doing isn't.
SPEAKER_1:  a novel concept.
SPEAKER_1:  per se, you know, they're like, for instance, the Raptor engine utilizes the full flow stage combustion cycle engine.
SPEAKER_1:  And that was already developed by the Soviets in the 60s.
SPEAKER_1:  for an engine called the RD270.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  It makes sense, like on paper, 100% it makes sense because you're
SPEAKER_1:  basically extracting the absolute maximum.
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  chemical energy in both propellants.
SPEAKER_1:  And at the end of the day, you have to be dumb enough to say we're gonna try using this thing because it's actually really complicated to do.
SPEAKER_1:  to do what they're doing.
SPEAKER_1:  But at the same time, like so are so are rockets. Like rocket engines already stupid complicated. So adding.
SPEAKER_1:  You don't.
SPEAKER_1:  10, 20% more.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, painting the butt during the R&D.
SPEAKER_1:  If it's, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  in the long, long, long 20, 30 year existence or whatever, you know, like future of that engine.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that gonna be worth it? Obviously SpaceX said-
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I think we can actually develop this Raptor engine.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's just interesting to see the things that have been.
SPEAKER_1:  Look, even reusability, you know, like the space shuttle was reusable.
SPEAKER_1:  It's fully the upper stage, you know, the shuttle itself, the orbiter was.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I mean, that thing was for all intents and purposes, a reusable rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  Now did it live up to its expectations? Not necessarily.
SPEAKER_1:  So it left a lot of bad taste in people's mouth on the ideas of reusability.
SPEAKER_1:  So for SpaceX to kind of come back into the room and sit on the table and say
SPEAKER_1:  We're gonna use a reusable rocket. Specifically, we're gonna do a fully reusable rocket. You know, a lot of people are, even still today, a lot of people going...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, you're not going to be able to do that.
SPEAKER_0:  Even today. Even today.
SPEAKER_0:  So long-term, you're not gonna be able to reuse a scale.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Bye.
SPEAKER_1:  Definitely, I think the number of people that are saying that today is...
SPEAKER_1:  a small portion of those that were saying that type of thing five years ago. You know, Elon did that announcement in 2016.
SPEAKER_1:  for the ITS. It was very...
SPEAKER_1:  Very aspirational and people were just like, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's a large number of people that had the-
SPEAKER_1:  factual reasons to think that and do that.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, at the time they'd only landed like two rockets or something, you know, when they did that, or maybe three, it was a very small number.
SPEAKER_1:  When they announced that actually they had just lost a couple months prior, they just lost a mo six. So they like.
SPEAKER_1:  there were still this young blossoming company and they come in and be like, we've figured out reusability and now we're gonna go full scale and make the world's biggest, most heaviest.
SPEAKER_1:  most powerful rocket ever and we're going to fully reuse it and it's going to go to Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  pretty out there, like it really was and.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. You know, it's all about perspective. But now again, we're coming up on 100 consecutive landings of an orbital class rocket that's.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, 45 meters tall, 3.7 meters wide. Like this thing is huge.
SPEAKER_1:  Why is 20 metric tons even empty?
SPEAKER_1:  when it's landing.
SPEAKER_1:  That thing's already huge. So seeing the success of that, I think people are now more like, well, okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe, maybe there is actually.
SPEAKER_1:  the opportunity to be fully reasonable. That's definitely probably the biggest.
SPEAKER_1:  constraint that I think has been questioned.
SPEAKER_1:  That is being.
SPEAKER_0:  Yep. And then of course, like the broader one of costs of bringing down costs.
SPEAKER_0:  that you're able to kind of bring down costs so much.
SPEAKER_0:  Something like colonizing Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  or many trips to Mars will be a possibility.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, people don't even...
SPEAKER_0:  It seems so far out.
SPEAKER_0:  That don't even.
SPEAKER_0:  have time or give effort to questioning it. But this is the implied questioning. Can you really do?
SPEAKER_0:  that many launches actually.
SPEAKER_1:  do it.
SPEAKER_1:  can actually do it. Yeah, it's looking. I think it's one of the things where you look at the curve, you know, you look at it like
SPEAKER_1:  10 years ago, that was ridiculous.
SPEAKER_1:  Following this curve, if SpaceX goes from, you know, two years ago launching, I don't remember what it was, 40 times to 60 times to 100 times this year.
SPEAKER_1:  amount.
SPEAKER_1:  And if we just keep extrapolating that out, if they...
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe not that exponential, maybe it goes more linear or whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  What's 20, 30 years like?
SPEAKER_1:  the amount of stuff we can put on orbit and the potential we have to do things.
SPEAKER_1:  Absolutely. Now I don't want to put a time frame, like, you know, yeah, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  But you gotta think, we're increasing the number of launches, we're increasing the amount of things in space, we're increasing the amount of payload on orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  that's probably not going to decrease anytime soon. And therefore,
SPEAKER_1:  Eventually, like the idea of going to Mars is absolutely
SPEAKER_1:  Reasonable.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me ask a difficult question.
SPEAKER_0:  I need to be asked here.
SPEAKER_0:  Can SpaceX continue?
SPEAKER_0:  It successes without Elon.
SPEAKER_0:  this long-term mission to Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the discussion about Tesla and autopilot or robotics.
SPEAKER_0:  or a neural link with brain computer interfaces.
SPEAKER_0:  is a question wholly separate from the SpaceX question.
SPEAKER_0:  because there's a lot of other competitors.
SPEAKER_0:  doing.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... some
SPEAKER_0:  different but amazing engineering that Tesla is doing.
SPEAKER_0:  in both autonomous vehicles, semi-autonomy or full autonomy.
SPEAKER_0:  and obviously in vehicle design and electric vehicles.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a lot of people that are doing incredible brain computer interfaces.
SPEAKER_0:  but while there is a lot of competitors to SpaceX, and we'll talk about many of them, they're doing amazing work, it seems like he's really driving progress here.
SPEAKER_0:  over the past 10 years.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think about that?
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  The first thing I think.
SPEAKER_1:  remind people is just how many brilliant people do work in each of these companies, obviously.
SPEAKER_1:  the
SPEAKER_1:  some of the best teams assembled ever. Just incredible people. He knows this. He will gladly tell people and he says it often like.
SPEAKER_1:  the amazing people, the amazing teams here. So it is important to remember that.
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  That being said, like there is something to Elon's...
SPEAKER_1:  just super far forward.
SPEAKER_1:  not taking no for an answer on things approach that and
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Almost to his dismay, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  He is afraid of the sunk cost fallacy so much that it almost almost gets to the border of like being
SPEAKER_1:  You know, like throw out everything before it's even, we've known or not, but at the same time, like it moves the needle so fast so far.
SPEAKER_1:  So as far as the question of would SpaceX continue to like...
SPEAKER_1:  succeeding and be able to ultimately go to Mars without Elon.
SPEAKER_1:  The Mars thing I think would probably be hard to uphold.
SPEAKER_1:  I think a lot of that drive for Mars is from Elon.
SPEAKER_1:  It is maybe too fantastical for the average person and the average employee and maybe the average CEO that might step in.
SPEAKER_1:  have a company's mission be to go to Mars. or even go to Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Clearly because, like you said,
SPEAKER_0:  The Mars plan was non-existent for NASA. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Still really, there isn't.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, so.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  If
SPEAKER_0:  And how many people, and sorry to interrupt, how many people are talking about...
SPEAKER_0:  It's obvious that we need to become multi-planetary.
SPEAKER_1:  Right, there's not a...
SPEAKER_1:  There's the Mars Society and like.
SPEAKER_0:  serious leaders of engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  efforts or nations and so on. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Which it does seem if you think about it.
SPEAKER_0:  that it's obvious.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and the grand.
SPEAKER_1:  eventuality it is obvious
SPEAKER_0:  of human civilization, this whole human experiment we have here.
SPEAKER_0:  which should be expanding out into the company.
SPEAKER_1:  100%.
SPEAKER_1:  So I think the...
SPEAKER_1:  big mission if we're measuring SpaceX's success on getting to Mars or not.
SPEAKER_1:  I think they'd have a really hard time.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  continuing to fulfill that drive without Elon at the helm.
SPEAKER_1:  Now.
SPEAKER_1:  I think there's a certain balance and beauty of Elon, specifically when it was Tesla and SpaceX.
SPEAKER_1:  where
SPEAKER_1:  Elon will go in.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, have mild tornadoes around the factory and the engineering, you know, and like mix everything up and, and.
SPEAKER_1:  things get sometimes just totally thrown together, and totally just like.
SPEAKER_1:  get it done just to get it done and start moving that direction.
SPEAKER_1:  and then he'll leave and go do that same thing, you know, at SpaceX or Tesla, vice versa.
SPEAKER_1:  And then there's a little bit of a calm where people come back in and they fill in those caps. I think that's kind of always been a pretty healthy thing, honestly, is like.
SPEAKER_1:  I think if he...
SPEAKER_1:  is too focused on any one thing.
SPEAKER_1:  It almost is like a spin too much, you know, like it's like.
SPEAKER_1:  The too many tornadoes. Yeah, too many tornadoes. And I think it could almost be like you need someone to come back in and like.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, like backfill almost because I've heard definitely stories of like
SPEAKER_1:  Like, well, probably a good example would be last.
SPEAKER_1:  Last, what was that last year? Two years ago, 2020.
SPEAKER_1:  Too, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Was that? Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Or no?
SPEAKER_1:  2021.
SPEAKER_1:  They did the first full stack of...
SPEAKER_1:  Starship Super Heavy.
SPEAKER_1:  And they call it the big surge. All of a sudden, like thousands of SpaceX employees.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, came down to Starbase.
SPEAKER_1:  and they just started building like you wouldn't freaking believe. I mean, it's just things.
SPEAKER_1:  going crazy. It was actually in the middle of that first interview I did with him, was in the middle of that surge.
SPEAKER_1:  There was like commotion like you wouldn't believe. You couldn't hardly talk because there's just so much going on. People just welding and blah blah blah, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Everything they did during that period was basically scrap.
SPEAKER_1:  Cause it was just.
SPEAKER_1:  Not done very well.
SPEAKER_1:  BUT
SPEAKER_1:  They got a fully stacked Starship rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  Out on the launch pad.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, and it's set.
SPEAKER_1:  I think at some point you kind of have to...
SPEAKER_1:  Stabilize some things enough and just say like, this is what we're doing.
SPEAKER_1:  to catalyze some things and say, now do this. It's almost like.
SPEAKER_1:  Do it for fake, now do it for real almost.
SPEAKER_0:  funny cause through that time.
SPEAKER_0:  I had a lot of conversation with them.
SPEAKER_0:  That process was hugely stressful.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a sense, I don't know where that sense is today, but there's a sense that's Starship.
SPEAKER_0:  is going to be very hard to pull off.
SPEAKER_0:  like borderline impossible to pull off. And that was really weighing heavy on him and the team and everybody.
SPEAKER_0:  So to have this chaos of development is fascinating. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Big time. I think they really had to push.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, if they hadn't done that, if they hadn't done that big push.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, we might only be now seeing a rocket stacked for the first time.
SPEAKER_1:  Tom.
SPEAKER_1:  It might be a lot more finished rocket, a lot more high fidelity, a lot more flight-worthy rocket finished.
SPEAKER_1:  and stacks but...
SPEAKER_1:  and they might not have to walk stuff backwards, but at the same time, like you do have to...
SPEAKER_1:  in this world.
SPEAKER_1:  You do have to push really hard.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, to make.
SPEAKER_1:  rapid iteration and rapid change in progress. residents.
SPEAKER_1:  It's interesting, I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  So lingering on that.
SPEAKER_0:  Another
SPEAKER_0:  question I really should ask you because of
SPEAKER_0:  you've seen
SPEAKER_0:  You've been in awe of the amazing development.
SPEAKER_0:  of space travel technology over the past few years.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think about Elon?
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  So in this.
SPEAKER_0:  perfect balance, optimized reallocation of tornadoes throughout the various efforts in human civilization.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you think?
SPEAKER_0:  Do you worry about his involvement on Twitter?
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, personally, I just, I see that as a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  less important than and
SPEAKER_1:  Personally for me, inspirational than Starship and the work done at SpaceX and Tesla, to me those were two very...
SPEAKER_1:  impactful and really, really just.
SPEAKER_1:  generally like
SPEAKER_1:  you know, they're uniting, like, you know, something to rally around, get excited about.
SPEAKER_1:  rally and just like a future look forward to.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... you know the idea of her gonna be
SPEAKER_1:  building the world's most powerful biggest rocket ever and it's eventually going to be able to
SPEAKER_1:  get humans on Mars for the first time.
SPEAKER_1:  and we're going to transition the world into fully sustainable.
SPEAKER_1:  awesome, just totally badass cars that do all these cool things.
SPEAKER_1:  To me those were like that bra-
SPEAKER_1:  sense of unity and a sense of like we can do this.
SPEAKER_1:  Personally, I just don't.
SPEAKER_1:  think that social media, no matter what it is, I don't see that.
SPEAKER_1:  in the social media and I don't see.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Any sort of politicking is ever anything that's really ever uniting thing.
SPEAKER_0:  I understand that I totally agree with you especially space on sparring it is I have to push back I do think
SPEAKER_0:  the impact of social media.
SPEAKER_0:  the basic
SPEAKER_0:  level of uh...
SPEAKER_0:  meaningful connections.
SPEAKER_0:  of this collective intelligence that we call human civilization.
SPEAKER_0:  through the medium of digital communication, which is social media, I think that can have a huge impact. It could be the very vehicle that increases the inspiration that SpaceX does and all different.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, the thing I've criticized them.
SPEAKER_0:  a bunch for is like why?
SPEAKER_0:  bring politics into this.
SPEAKER_0:  So the political divisions that we see on Twitter.
SPEAKER_0:  feeding them.
SPEAKER_0:  is tricky.
SPEAKER_0:  Um
SPEAKER_0:  It's tricky to sort of understand what is the value of that? What is the contribution of that?
SPEAKER_0:  to uh...
SPEAKER_0:  to this whole effort with God going on.
SPEAKER_0:  That has been a big challenge, but that said, like...
SPEAKER_0:  Again, this tornado.
SPEAKER_0:  the number of tornadoes in social media, I think is really important because
SPEAKER_0:  Social media has such a huge impact on us as a society.
SPEAKER_0:  have a transparent
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Have a bit of turmoil?
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it's like Tom Way says, I like my town with a bit of drop of poison, with a little drop of poison.
SPEAKER_0:  So like a little bit of that.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, shake things up. I think might be really healthy. I just.
SPEAKER_0:  worry about the long-term impact on the whole.
SPEAKER_0:  Mars projects through that. It's a, but you know what?
SPEAKER_0:  This life one of the reasons that's fun is uh
SPEAKER_0:  through the chaos.
SPEAKER_0:  Like, none of us know how it's gonna turn out and...
SPEAKER_0:  Hopefully we try to help each other to make sure it turns out well.
SPEAKER_1:  And this really isn't like anything about my personal like politics or anything like that, but really just generally.
SPEAKER_1:  Any of my friends that are-
SPEAKER_1:  like
SPEAKER_1:  The first thing you hear about them in their day is something that happened in politics or something that some world leaders doing or not doing or saying and not saying.
SPEAKER_1:  I just don't.
SPEAKER_1:  Find that.
SPEAKER_1:  to be the most important thing, really. I know that obviously that can affect a lot of people that has big real world consequences, politics do.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, like, I just re- and this is just me. I'm such a like, he'll come together, you know, for a while.
SPEAKER_1:  that I just really think like you need something bigger than bickering about.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, what people said and did and what they voted on and all this stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  to really...
SPEAKER_1:  Push humanity forward. Like I, you know, I know that politics and, and they're, and
SPEAKER_1:  by extracting that social media can affect.
SPEAKER_1:  things like space flight and even our like planetary defense like be able to defend ourselves against asteroids like if
SPEAKER_1:  Politics has their way and everything goes to crap and we don't even get to, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, we're not gonna be able to, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Continue space flight and things like that.
SPEAKER_1:  But like, I don't know. I just think there's better ways to do it and more uniting ways to do it than...
SPEAKER_1:  than what feels like immature.
SPEAKER_1:  name calling sometimes, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think the political bickering that most people talk about that's on top of most people's minds.
SPEAKER_0:  is the thing that will be completely forgotten by history. It has actually very little impact.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, politics matters, but like 1% of it. I think most of it.
SPEAKER_0:  is just.
SPEAKER_0:  political
SPEAKER_0:  bickering the push and pull.
SPEAKER_0:  of the red team and the blue team, and then the news media that feeds off the division for the attention, and it's just like a fun athletic event almost with the blue team and the red team. So, that you kind of have to have a historical perspective on it like most things.
SPEAKER_0:  will not really have a significant impact and we should focus on development of science.
SPEAKER_0:  technology engineering which is the thing that grows the pie.
SPEAKER_0:  100% is this is what the economists know well
SPEAKER_0:  which is the innovation, the engineering, that's what actually makes everybody richer. This kind of political bickering is just eating.
SPEAKER_1:  the pie and not just richer, but it improves their lives. You know, we can look at-
SPEAKER_1:  Every.
SPEAKER_1:  modern technology that is.
SPEAKER_1:  bestowed upon us today, air conditioning, electricity, internet access, fresh, clean water.
SPEAKER_1:  running water, blah blah blah.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, 100 years ago, so many of the things I listed either didn't exist.
SPEAKER_1:  or were only accessible by the ultra wealthy.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's through the innovation of technology and engineering and education that we're able to.
SPEAKER_1:  be that even someone below the poverty line in the most of the developed world will have a good number of those things in their life. And that's just continuing to increase and continuing to get better.
SPEAKER_1:  So I think, yeah, that's, to me that's...
SPEAKER_1:  in the grand scheme more important.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  to each their own.
SPEAKER_0:  Speaking of amazing technological development.
SPEAKER_0:  You have a few videos on this, but...
SPEAKER_0:  How does a rocket engine work?
SPEAKER_0:  you're wearing some of the instruction manuals. But for one type of it, like what's the fuel, what are the types of different rock is that you can kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  Give an overview.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Ultimately, a rocket engine converts.
SPEAKER_1:  high pressure and heat.
SPEAKER_1:  into kinetic energy. That's the only real job of a rocket engine is to take
SPEAKER_1:  High pressure gas, hot high pressure gas. I'm very energized. There's a lot of energy involved
SPEAKER_1:  And then literally.
SPEAKER_1:  turning that into.
SPEAKER_1:  molecules shooting in one direction into kinetic energy.
SPEAKER_1:  So, um.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, what you do basically, you know, I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  The simplest version of it is, of course, like famously a balloon. Take a balloon.
SPEAKER_1:  Fill it up with air, you've got a pressure.
SPEAKER_1:  You let go of it, some of the air shoots out in a...
SPEAKER_1:  general direction ish.
SPEAKER_1:  you converted that pressure into kinetic energy. Now, if you start scaling that up.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you can continue to do something like that, like...
SPEAKER_1:  cold gas thruster would be kind of the most simple and easiest rocket engine to make would be a cold gas thruster
SPEAKER_1:  And all that is you literally just take air, or specifically nitrogen, because it's a little bit more dense than all the others.
SPEAKER_1:  or you know, the majority of our atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  You can, or sorry, it's more sparse.
SPEAKER_1:  You can
SPEAKER_1:  condense that down.
SPEAKER_1:  a really high pressure bottle.
SPEAKER_1:  and then just literally shoot it through what's called a D-Lavelle nozzle, which is something that chokes the flow a little bit, gets it to be...
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  takes it and gets it into supersonic speeds.
SPEAKER_1:  Once it's at supersonic speed, you actually can't choke it down anymore. You'll just...
SPEAKER_1:  constrict the flow of mass flow, constrict the airflow.
SPEAKER_1:  So you actually go opposite, you start making it wider. And once it's already at supersonic speeds, if you expand it and make it wider, it actually gets faster and faster. So at first, when it's subsonic gas...
SPEAKER_1:  you start shrinking, you can strict the flow.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's actually speeding up just like, you know, a highway if you go from, you know, or any of these examples, like a,
SPEAKER_1:  water hose you you know if you pinch it down you want to flow the same amount of water from point a to point b through a smaller pipe you can you can flow more water you're the same amount of water from point a to point b with a smaller pipe it just has to go faster
SPEAKER_1:  So obviously you can constrict it, but at some point you actually get to a physical limitation and that happens to be the speed of sound.
SPEAKER_1:  Once it gets to the local speed of sound.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  you can then actually do the opposite. You actually expand it back out and you're continuing to convert.
SPEAKER_0:  the
SPEAKER_1:  the pressure into velocity.
SPEAKER_1:  at that point, but it's now supersonic. And what's interesting is
SPEAKER_1:  While you're doing that, you're actually cooling it down too. Each bit of that pipe that you're making wider and wider and wider, you're cooling down.
SPEAKER_1:  So the more heat energy you have to work with.
SPEAKER_1:  the more work you can actually do. So at some point a hot
SPEAKER_1:  high pressure rocket engine is the best.
SPEAKER_1:  source of like that's the ultimate amount of work you can do.
SPEAKER_0:  And the nozzle, so as you're saying, there's a bunch of different design options.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's a critical part of this, how you do that conversion.
SPEAKER_1:  Which is basically like how much can you convert?
SPEAKER_1:  is really like the ultimate game. How much
SPEAKER_1:  Pressure and heat.
SPEAKER_1:  Can we convert into thrust?
SPEAKER_1:  Like that's really at the end of the day, that's what a rocket engine.
SPEAKER_1:  So you have to have a powerful enough rocket engine to actually lift.
SPEAKER_1:  the rocket and well, rocket is mostly just fuel.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like 90, 90 plus percent.
SPEAKER_1:  the weight of fuel. You just have to lift the fuel that's going to take it.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... you know into orbit and that's
SPEAKER_0:  The Thing.
SPEAKER_0:  specifically for rockets, you're just saying generally rocket engines but
SPEAKER_0:  for the task of.
SPEAKER_0:  going to orbit.
SPEAKER_0:  You're fighting gravity, earth gravity.
SPEAKER_0:  which is fundamentally different than moon gravity or Mars gravity.
SPEAKER_0:  or like you said, traveling out to space earth.
SPEAKER_0:  has a pretty.
SPEAKER_0:  intense.
SPEAKER_0:  gravity.AT health.
SPEAKER_1:  to overcome. We're lucky. Because I think if it was 10% either way, like 10% harder, it'd be like, oh, we could still do it.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, with our current technology, we'd still be able to get stuff into orbit, man.
SPEAKER_1:  Things like reusability and.
SPEAKER_1:  this commercialization, the success that we've seen in the last 10 years, we would just be on two thin margins, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  10% easier and we would have been like.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, it's just like totally different. It's so much easier. It's like this big.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, sliding scale and 10% in either direction we'd be.
SPEAKER_1:  either screwed or really happy, you know, as far as getting into space. So it's just hard enough that it.
SPEAKER_1:  things like fully reusable becomes very, very, very difficult.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's completely achievable.
SPEAKER_1:  We have all the pieces to make it achievable. It does not disobey any laws of physics. It does not disobey any-
SPEAKER_1:  There's no like hard stops, it's just very, very, very hard.
SPEAKER_1:  And so ultimately, yeah, like on Earth for the first bit of launch again, when the rocket's pointing straight up and the engines are pointing straight down, the pointy end up flaming down.
SPEAKER_1:  You're fighting gravity.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that's kind of your biggest enemy outside of the Earth's atmosphere too.
SPEAKER_0:  So what kind of sources of fuel is there?
SPEAKER_0:  This is Chemical Rockets Liquisol-Gas Hybrid.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... this electric so what
SPEAKER_0:  what are the kinds of fuels we're talking about, what are oxidizers, what, can you just explain your shirt, I guess? hahaha
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  the components in the shirt.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, so really, I mean, fuels, it's, there's kind of two terms. Well, you'll generally hear the word propellant.
SPEAKER_1:  being used as anything that is used to propel a spacecraft or used in a rocket engine.
SPEAKER_1:  You can have a fuel.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to have a fuel, you have to have an oxidizer, and you have to have a spark.
SPEAKER_1:  to actually get those things burning.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's just a general law of like.
SPEAKER_1:  the universe. You have to have fuel and oxidizer and a spark.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Now some fuels will.
SPEAKER_1:  by themselves spark like hypergolic fuels.
SPEAKER_1:  but ultimately you're always left with some kind of fuel oxidizer in a spark.
SPEAKER_1:  So the general ones used most often in rockets, liquid oxygen is kind of the king of...
SPEAKER_1:  Well, there's...
SPEAKER_1:  Better oxidizers, but they're extremely, extremely hard to work with.
SPEAKER_1:  Like fluorine.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  but generally liquid oxygen.
SPEAKER_1:  So you just chill oxygen down to its liquid state minus 183 degrees Celsius.
SPEAKER_1:  So it can be dense enough to store in tanks. You know, it's a thousand times more dense when it's in a liquid than it is.
SPEAKER_1:  as a guest.
SPEAKER_1:  RP1, which is basically kerosene.
SPEAKER_1:  is a very common fuel.
SPEAKER_1:  Another common fuel nowadays is methane, liquid methane.
SPEAKER_1:  Liquid hydrogen is another, it's the most efficient potential for the most efficient since it's one of the lightest molecules.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Correct me if I'm wrong, but the...
SPEAKER_0:  Falcon 9 uses kerosene.
SPEAKER_0:  And then Starship uses methane.
SPEAKER_1:  Yep. Liquid methane? Yep, for fuel. And they both use liquid oxygen for their oxidizer.
SPEAKER_0:  oxidizer okay yep
SPEAKER_1:  But then, you know, if you get into hypergolics, you'll normally have nitrogen tetroxide.
SPEAKER_1:  which is your oxidizer and some form of hydrazine.
SPEAKER_1:  for your fuel.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  There's solid rocket propellants, like solid rocket boosters, and those are actually pre-mixed. Your oxidizer is inherently like.
SPEAKER_1:  baked, literally like kind of baked into the sludge of.
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  So like for SpaceX it's all uh...
SPEAKER_0:  chemical liquid fuels. Yep, yep. So how many solid?
SPEAKER_0:  BASS
SPEAKER_0:  are they still being used today? they're most rockets
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and the United States really is the only ones that, well, the only ones that I guess early on, because it was really just the Soviet Union versus the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  The United States started to use solids pretty early on.
SPEAKER_1:  They're simple and easy, but these days, like, you know, you'll still see them kind of as
SPEAKER_1:  traditionally like boosters, like they're used.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  just.
SPEAKER_1:  Help get something off the ground or help give it a little extra boost
SPEAKER_1:  So the space shuttle famously had those two huge white.
SPEAKER_1:  solid rocket boosters attached to the orange fuel tank.
SPEAKER_1:  Those are solid rocket propellants.
SPEAKER_1:  Things like the Atlas V can have up to five smaller solid rocket boosters.
SPEAKER_1:  There's very few rockets that use a pure.
SPEAKER_1:  at least these days that use a pure solid rocket motor for its first stage.
SPEAKER_1:  There still are, especially in China, there's a lot of startup rocket companies that kind of use just missile technology.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there might use like a, there might just be a variant of an ICBM.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, that just use solid rocket field. Cause it is very.
SPEAKER_1:  relatively easy to develop, you know, model rockets use.
SPEAKER_1:  solid rocket motors and stuff like that. After then.
SPEAKER_1:  They're still around, but they're just not as elegant and not as a.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, not as as used these days.
SPEAKER_0:  What are rocket engine cycles?
SPEAKER_0:  I think getting more towards your shirt question. You have a really good video called.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean a lot of your videos that are technical are just exceptionally well done.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah...
SPEAKER_0:  You deserve all the props you get. I mean, thank you for doing this work. Really, really, really well done.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's called rocket engine cycles. How do you power a rocket engine?
SPEAKER_0:  and you go through all the different options. Is there something you could say about?
SPEAKER_0:  open cycle, close cycle, full flow.
SPEAKER_0:  all the different variants that you can use words to explain.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, without all the pretty pictures.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, without the pretty...
SPEAKER_1:  pictures. So ultimately, you know, like we said, we your ultimate goals you want to get
SPEAKER_1:  heat and pressure.
SPEAKER_1:  into an engine.
SPEAKER_1:  So obviously at some point you can either make really thick tanks of your rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  You can like.
SPEAKER_1:  get it so thick that you store the propellants in really, really high pressures.
SPEAKER_1:  But obviously like that doesn't scale very well. At some point your rocket's so heavy you can't even-
SPEAKER_1:  leave the ground or you know, it's just.
SPEAKER_1:  so much of your mass is just literally the walls of the rocket. so
SPEAKER_1:  At some point, people realize, hey, we could actually just pump.
SPEAKER_1:  the fuels and the oxidizer into the engine at a high pressure and increase the pressure.
SPEAKER_1:  through a pump.
SPEAKER_1:  Obviously a pump is going to require energy.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to get that energy from somewhere.
SPEAKER_1:  And again, at some point people were like, well.
SPEAKER_1:  Rock and serve.
SPEAKER_1:  There's already rocket fuel here. You know, we'll just use some of the energy from the rocket fuel.
SPEAKER_1:  spin these pumps.
SPEAKER_1:  So that would be considered like open cycle.
SPEAKER_1:  close cycle.
SPEAKER_1:  full flow stage combustion cycles are ways to.
SPEAKER_1:  Tap into the propellant.
SPEAKER_1:  Actually on them there's tap off, expand or sec, I mean all of them kind of do the same thing.
SPEAKER_1:  but you end up at some point spinning a turbine.
SPEAKER_1:  a turbine.
SPEAKER_1:  can take some of the heat energy and the.
SPEAKER_1:  and the pressure.
SPEAKER_1:  of an engine.
SPEAKER_1:  and then they can...
SPEAKER_1:  that can be connected to a shaft to pumps and those pumps can increase the pressure of the propellants.
SPEAKER_1:  and force it into the combustion chamber.
SPEAKER_1:  Now.
SPEAKER_1:  The difference between open cycle...
SPEAKER_1:  closed cycle full flow all those is what happens.
SPEAKER_1:  after the gas has-
SPEAKER_1:  flown through the turbine. So after you've used.
SPEAKER_1:  the turbine and spun up the engine.
SPEAKER_1:  What happens to that gas? So in an open cycle engine...
SPEAKER_1:  You basically have like a separate small.
SPEAKER_1:  rocket engine in a sense. It's a gas generator, they call it.
SPEAKER_1:  and that will be used.
SPEAKER_1:  to create some, you know, take a little, we'll say 10% of your propellant flowing to the engine. Instead you reroute it to like a smaller rocket engine called the gas generator.
SPEAKER_1:  You point that at your turbine.
SPEAKER_1:  and that will spin your turbine up to ridiculous speeds, 30,000 plus RPM.
SPEAKER_1:  And then after it spins, it's wasted most of its energy.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's just dumped overboard.
SPEAKER_1:  That would be open cycle. You're not worrying about it after that point, but you are left with a lot of unburnt.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, unused fuel.
SPEAKER_1:  a good amount of that fuel is just completely, especially because the turbine.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to keep it.
SPEAKER_1:  from melting.
SPEAKER_1:  So you can't run it at like optimal.
SPEAKER_1:  ratios.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not necessarily stoichiometric and a rocket engine you actually don't want.
SPEAKER_1:  it to be near stoichiometric where you releasing all the energy.
SPEAKER_1:  You actually want to release.
SPEAKER_1:  You actually want to be throwing out the lighter molecules so it can be shot out faster generally in the engine.
SPEAKER_1:  So, but in order to have a turbine survive, you have to actually cool.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to have the gas going through it.
SPEAKER_1:  It can't be stupid stupid hotter, so you're just going to melt your turbine.
SPEAKER_1:  So they normally, especially in the open cycle, just run it really fuel rich.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's a lot of extra fuel being pumped into it.
SPEAKER_1:  that will keep the temperatures at a reasonable.
SPEAKER_1:  at a reasonable temperature.
SPEAKER_1:  So you end up with this like dark, sooty smoke pouring out of that gas generator.
SPEAKER_1:  That's just unburned fuel, just wasted fuel.
SPEAKER_1:  and never got a chance to be used. Oh, interesting. You know, like in the combustion chamber, it's not being used to propel the rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's just being used.
SPEAKER_1:  to cool down the repellent.
SPEAKER_1:  that's being used to spin the turbine, that's being used to spin the pumps, to push a lot of propellant into the engine.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it doesn't take too long before, you know, you're a greedy rocket scientist being like, look at all this wasted propellant.
SPEAKER_1:  all this potential energy that's just literally being spewed out the side of the rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's where the close cycle comes in.
SPEAKER_1:  So now we get to get that propellant, take it from basically.
SPEAKER_1:  what was being wasted through the turbine, and you're going to try pumping it back into the engine.
SPEAKER_1:  Now you don't literally.
SPEAKER_1:  Just pump.
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  that gasset's
SPEAKER_1:  you know, that hot, that gas into the engine is actually way too low of pressure
SPEAKER_1:  compared to the main
SPEAKER_1:  combustion chamber. By that point, by the time it's gone through the turbine, it's lost most of its pressure and heat.
SPEAKER_1:  to the turbine. I tried pumping it into the engine.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, just taking that pipe and sticking it right into the combustion chamber.
SPEAKER_1:  and the much higher pressure, hotter combustion chamber would just go backwards.
SPEAKER_1:  and a
SPEAKER_1:  Right. Stall out the engine and blow up the engine and whatever. There you go.
SPEAKER_1:  So what they actually do is they normally will send.
SPEAKER_1:  There might be some variations of this, but the general concept is you actually flow all of your fuel.
SPEAKER_1:  or all of your oxidizer.
SPEAKER_1:  through the turbine.
SPEAKER_1:  So that would be close cycle.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's fuel rich closed cycle, which would be your flowing.
SPEAKER_1:  all of the fuel through the turbine.
SPEAKER_1:  Or there's oxidizer.
SPEAKER_1:  close cycle, which is where you're flowing all of the oxidizer that's going into the engine through the turbine.
SPEAKER_0:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_1:  Now the trick here...
SPEAKER_1:  is you have to have that turbine.
SPEAKER_1:  after it's done its work. So after it's taken some of the potential energy, some of the heat energy from, we're not calling it a pre-burner by the way, instead of it being a gas generator.
SPEAKER_1:  you now call that device that's.
SPEAKER_1:  creating pressure.
SPEAKER_1:  to spin the turbine. You're now calling that a pre-burner because it's just going to pre-burn.
SPEAKER_1:  some of your fuel or some of your oxidizer.
SPEAKER_1:  The trick is that has to be by the time it's gone through the turbine, it has to be higher pressure.
SPEAKER_1:  than the combustion chamber.
SPEAKER_1:  because otherwise it's going to go backward still.
SPEAKER_1:  So you really have to get that pre-burner up to ridiculously.
SPEAKER_1:  high pressures.
SPEAKER_1:  like at least 20% higher than your main combustion chamber. And these combustion chambers.
SPEAKER_1:  No, we're talking about engines that are at.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  200
SPEAKER_1:  100 to 200 even in SpaceX's Raptor engine up to 300 bar in the main combustion chamber. So that's
SPEAKER_1:  What is that 4500 psi basically.
SPEAKER_1:  insane amounts of pressure inside these combustion chambers. So your turbine has to be even above that or your.
SPEAKER_1:  your gas generator or your pre-burner, sorry, has to be higher pressure than that even.
SPEAKER_1:  in order to have the flow going the right direction through the engine.
SPEAKER_1:  So now you'll have those closed cycles. Have a safe day, take care.
SPEAKER_1:  fuel rich, you have oxidizer rich.
SPEAKER_1:  The tricks now, you're starting to get, it's crazy. There's just so many compromises. Every little-
SPEAKER_1:  decision you have of like, oh, I did this, now I, you know, I'll now.
SPEAKER_1:  gonna do this.
SPEAKER_1:  For instance, fuel rich if you ran kerosene.
SPEAKER_1:  You know how I mentioned soot coming out of the gas generator.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, if you run soot...
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  through your engine like that and how to go through your injectors, like back into the engine.
SPEAKER_1:  It'll clog the pores of the injectors and it'll end up blowing up the engine. The soot itself is so damaging.
SPEAKER_1:  that you can't really run a fuel rich kerosene engine.
SPEAKER_0:  exactly is so it's like fuel somehow mixed up with the smoke like what
SPEAKER_0:  I wonder what.
SPEAKER_0:  What is it, chemically? Is this some weird...
SPEAKER_1:  It's mostly just carbon.
SPEAKER_1:  It's mostly just that carbon, solid chunks of carbon, and it can cake up.
SPEAKER_1:  and just literally like.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, it's like ash almost, you know, like.
SPEAKER_1:  at some point, you know, especially under those high pressures and high temperatures.
SPEAKER_1:  it can physically build up and turn into stalagmites and stalactites of carbon.
SPEAKER_1:  Really hard.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, forged in a rocket engine carbon.
SPEAKER_0:  I wonder how you figure all that out too, is that to be experimented? Some of that has come-
SPEAKER_0:  chemistry like theoretical but like you're gonna have to build the thing at scale.
SPEAKER_0:  and actually test it and try on her. There's many decades.
SPEAKER_1:  And many pieces of vengeance that you're trying to piece back together going like what the hell happened here? Yeah, what happened?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. OK, so that's close cycle. So how do we get to full flow?
SPEAKER_1:  So in either of those situations, you're still actually just having the opposite. So if you're fuel rich, all the fuel is going through the turbine.
SPEAKER_1:  but only a tiny bit of oxygen is actually being.
SPEAKER_1:  put into that pre-burner to spin the pumps.
SPEAKER_1:  and the rest of the oxygen is actually going through the pump.
SPEAKER_1:  the primary pump and straight into the combustion chamber.
SPEAKER_1:  Now full flow, the idea is you're going to actually pre-burn both your propellants.
SPEAKER_1:  Both of your propellants are going to go through a preburner.
SPEAKER_1:  and they're both going to end up spinning.
SPEAKER_1:  One of the pumps.
SPEAKER_1:  So you'll have a gas, a fuel rich pre-burner and you're going to have an oxygen rich pre-burner.
SPEAKER_1:  Each one of those is going to.
SPEAKER_1:  get just, you know, they're gonna heat it up just enough.
SPEAKER_1:  and get it up to just enough pressure.
SPEAKER_1:  to spin up that turbine as fast as they need to do to get the pumps up to the right pressure.
SPEAKER_1:  and still have enough pressure through the turbine to overcome the pressure inside the main combustion chamber.
SPEAKER_1:  and they're both going to arrive. Both your fuel and your oxidizer are going to arrive in the main combustion chamber as hot gas is already.
SPEAKER_1:  So what was liquid oxygen is now.
SPEAKER_1:  gaseous oxygen. What was liquid methane is now gaseous methane and they're meeting in this combustion chamber.
SPEAKER_1:  at still ridiculously high pressures again. And for SpaceX's Raptor engine, they're meeting at 300 bar.
SPEAKER_1:  insane amounts of pressure.
SPEAKER_1:  and then they combust from there on because they're already a gas-gas interaction.
SPEAKER_1:  They're happy to burn, they're ready to.
SPEAKER_1:  They're ready to burn, they're ready to mingle, as opposed to having a gas-liquid interaction, which is what's a lot more normal.
SPEAKER_1:  you'll have two different states of matter and they just might not, they might take a little more coaxing to-
SPEAKER_1:  What's that word?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Coaxing coaxing that doesn't sound like a song correct. Right coaxing coaxing. Yeah. Yeah
SPEAKER_0:  Alright. I don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  We'll cut that in post.
SPEAKER_0:  We'll have Morgan Freeman.
SPEAKER_1:  over double. Yeah, over double. Right on.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, the fascinating thing is their coats as gases.
SPEAKER_1:  combustion chamber. Look at that word. But yeah, they just take a little bit more.
SPEAKER_1:  It takes more time in the combustion chamber to have.
SPEAKER_1:  liquid gas interaction like mix together and and we unleash as much of their energy as you can before it exits the system or some
SPEAKER_0:  the trade-offs here in terms of efficiency, which is most efficient and then also complexity of the design and the engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  and the cost of the design and the engineering. Like what are the different trade-offs between open cycle, closed cycle and full flow?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's a pretty, it's kind of like a.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, what's the-
SPEAKER_1:  the bears, the Goldilocks, you know, like it's like.
SPEAKER_1:  You kind of generally
SPEAKER_1:  The easiest is open cycle.
SPEAKER_1:  because you're just expelling the exhaust gas.
SPEAKER_1:  the gas generator exhaust. You're not having to worry about it. You just spin up that thing as much as you need.
SPEAKER_1:  and deal with it, right? No big deal.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, close cycles.
SPEAKER_1:  offers 10 to 15% greater performance generally because you're not wasting that propellant.
SPEAKER_1:  And but it's it's complicated. It's a lot more complicated, especially if you're doing oxygen rich. Now you're having
SPEAKER_1:  Cassius Oxygen.
SPEAKER_1:  in your engine, which just generally wants to react with everything.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just a recipe like hot.
SPEAKER_1:  Oxygen is just a recipe for-
SPEAKER_1:  things to catch on fire that shouldn't be on fire.
SPEAKER_1:  So metals, you know, under those conditions, supports have been out there for a while.
SPEAKER_1:  spontaneously start burning.
SPEAKER_1:  You'll actually turn your metal and it will now become fuel. You'll be engine rich before you know it because your hot oxygen is beating and using that engine as fuel basically.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Oxygen rich is generally very hard, but that is what the Soviet Union ended up doing with almost their entire line of engines was.
SPEAKER_1:  close cycle oxygen rich.
SPEAKER_1:  But you know, so those two are kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  Generally.
SPEAKER_1:  hard but
SPEAKER_1:  Offer.
SPEAKER_1:  performance benefits over open cycle. But at the end of the day, you know, full flow is by far the it's the ultimate of all of them. It's the most difficult.
SPEAKER_1:  but it also has the most potential to be the most efficient.
SPEAKER_0:  Starship, the Raptor 2, why is that engine using full flow?
SPEAKER_1:  because it's the best. I mean, it's just physics-wise, if you're trying to extract as much energy out of your propellants, there just isn't another cycle type that...
SPEAKER_1:  that is better than it but of course it's very very hard to develop you know so far to date
SPEAKER_1:  The RD-270 in the 60s was built.
SPEAKER_1:  There is a powerhead demonstrator built in the United States in the 90s and early 2000s, I think, maybe just the early 2000s.
SPEAKER_1:  that was just the power, just the.
SPEAKER_1:  the pumps and the turbines and the pre-burners. No chamber, no nothing.
SPEAKER_1:  That was a big deal. Only the United States took millions of dollars to just develop that.
SPEAKER_1:  And then there's SpaceX's Raptor engine.
SPEAKER_0:  So you talked about the combustion chamber.
SPEAKER_0:  how damn hot things get high pressure.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of heat. How do you keep the thing cool? You have a great video on this? collapse applying heat to bones.
SPEAKER_0:  How do you get it from, from...
SPEAKER_0:  Probably call it M-
SPEAKER_0:  Metal rich.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know why he is laughing though.
SPEAKER_0:  from like the metal from melting.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, one of the ways is to let it be engine rich. It was actually, you can use a blade of cooling. You can literally let...
SPEAKER_1:  Make the walls thicker than you normally make it. Make it out of a material that will ablate away, that will kind of chip away and take some of the heat away with it.
SPEAKER_1:  Very, again, primitive.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's actually what SpaceX first used on their first Merlin engines, they used a blade of cooling.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's basically a carbon nozzle.
SPEAKER_1:  and you just let it.
SPEAKER_1:  the inner layer of the engine was carbon, and you just let it get...
SPEAKER_1:  chewed away and eaten away and that's just something you factor in.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not
SPEAKER_1:  uh, very
SPEAKER_1:  elegant and it's definitely not reusable.
SPEAKER_1:  In that sense, so this.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably really good models.
SPEAKER_0:  about like how it melts away, the rate at which it melts away to know what thickness.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. That's a dangerous.
SPEAKER_1:  I just think the question seems so silly.
SPEAKER_1:  So obviously you probably, you know, again, it's not the most elegant. The problem too, your geometry physically is changing too, as you're eroding the walls.
SPEAKER_1:  Now things like your expansion ratio or the ratio between your throat and the nozzle exit is changing because the thickness, like the throat's diameter is actually, like everything's changing. So.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not great.
SPEAKER_0:  It might not be melting away uniformly. There could be some like weird pockets for aerodynamics. A bunch of chaos just can...
SPEAKER_1:  I can't imagine having to like...
SPEAKER_1:  Figure all that stuff out, honestly. Who were you before you started if you think you can complete Dj Vu?
SPEAKER_1:  So the more elegant thing to do, there's a couple other things you can do, but kind of the most common one, especially when we're dealing with liquid-fueled rockets.
SPEAKER_1:  is something called regeneratively cool.
SPEAKER_1:  And the idea is you basically just flow fuel or oxidizer.
SPEAKER_1:  through the walls of the nozzle in the chamber.
SPEAKER_1:  before they go through like into the injector into the actual combustion chamber.
SPEAKER_1:  By doing that, your.
SPEAKER_1:  you're taking heat out of the metal of the walls.
SPEAKER_1:  and you're putting it into the propellant. So you're typically heating the propellant up, which is, remember when I said there's a gas interaction versus a liquid, like.
SPEAKER_1:  liquid gas lots of times, even if you pump them both at.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, as...
SPEAKER_1:  They, you know, are both being pumped as liquids.
SPEAKER_1:  By the time it goes through the walls of the chamber, lots of times one of them is phase changed into a gas.
SPEAKER_1:  So now you do have that gas liquid interaction.
SPEAKER_1:  That's because they're using that.
SPEAKER_1:  the fuel or the oxidizer to cool the walls of the engine.
SPEAKER_1:  So when you look at a rocket engine, although it looks like, you know, a nice.
SPEAKER_1:  beautifully uniform cylinder, you know, smooth thing.
SPEAKER_1:  There's
SPEAKER_1:  Either there's sometimes like a.
SPEAKER_1:  channels.
SPEAKER_1:  actually like milled into the walls.
SPEAKER_1:  that they run fuel through. And even though they're tight, they can be like two, three millimeters thick, they'll actually still have a channel that goes down and U-turns and comes around and comes back.
SPEAKER_1:  all the way down to the tip of the nozzle and everything. So it's.
SPEAKER_1:  Just insane, you know the-
SPEAKER_0:  Isn't that pre-designed and that's like...
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  So they design those channels. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  There's probably some optimization there, like how the flow happens.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, especially because you're thinking about a conical thing or like a semi-conical thing where the
SPEAKER_1:  Areas getting smaller and smaller and smaller, or flowing the same amount of propellant through it?
SPEAKER_1:  as you are down. You know what I mean? Propellant has to.
SPEAKER_1:  They have all these unique things like, you know, sometimes different.
SPEAKER_1:  manifolds where they'll inject more or less fuel in certain areas and
SPEAKER_0:  There must be like propellant simulation software.
SPEAKER_0:  Cause they can't, surely can't like.
SPEAKER_0:  test this on actual physical.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, back in the day, they had to just build it.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you mean back?
SPEAKER_0:  in the day, walked uphill in both ways. It was like, I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  like anything back in the day before computers.
SPEAKER_0:  Will you like head like.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah
SPEAKER_1:  I just had to do it. And they're like, you're.
SPEAKER_0:  Simulation or modeling was like a sheet of paper where you're like calculating stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, but you can heat flux, you know, like you can literally see how much energy and how much heat is inside the combustion chamber, how much
SPEAKER_1:  You know, and that is a measurable thing even without a computer. Now I'm not near smart enough to do any of this. Like I've never tried.
SPEAKER_1:  measuring the heat flux of anything. I barely even know what that means. I'm just smart enough to regurgitate it. You haven't lived, my friend. You haven't lived.
SPEAKER_1:  But that is something that people would calculate and they find out, okay, copper, you know, does a better job of transferring the heat.
SPEAKER_1:  between the walls of it and into the propellant, blah blah blah blah blah compared to XYZ.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  materials people. I've met
SPEAKER_0:  just in all walks of life, especially just through MIT, through everywhere.
SPEAKER_0:  Where's some people?
SPEAKER_0:  are just like...
SPEAKER_0:  100x
SPEAKER_0:  smarter than anyone you've ever met at a particular thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Like you mentioned copper, they'll know the heat dissipation through different materials. So I understand that like.
SPEAKER_0:  more than it's like holy shit it's possible for human beings to deeply
SPEAKER_1:  understand a thing. Dude, aerospace is.
SPEAKER_1:  full of that. People that are so.
SPEAKER_1:  niche in some.
SPEAKER_1:  that no other person has ever even remotely thought of. Yet this person has done it.
SPEAKER_1:  40,000 different ways in an environment being like, well, we found out that if we turn it four degrees that way and add 4% niobium, you know, like just things you're like.
SPEAKER_1:  What is your life and how do you know this?
SPEAKER_0:  If I anything about them, they usually don't think it's a big deal.
SPEAKER_0:  They're usually like, they're so notch-a-lon about it that if you don't actually...
SPEAKER_0:  You have to know enough.
SPEAKER_0:  You actually have to know quite a lot to appreciate.
SPEAKER_0:  how much more they know.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, because otherwise you won't even notice it because they're popular.
SPEAKER_0:  Culture doesn't celebrate the intricacies of.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... scientific or engineering mastery
SPEAKER_0:  which is interesting. There's all these people that lurk in the shadows. They're just geniuses. Like you see, you have like the LeBron's.
SPEAKER_0:  like good at basketball, so we understand that they're good at basketball. They do this thing with the ball and the hoop, and they do it really well, better than a lot of other people under pressure.
SPEAKER_1:  Like we celebrate. It's a big public spectacle. Yeah. Look how great they are. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  the people like, yeah, at these aerospace companies and NASA SpaceX
SPEAKER_0:  the kind of stuff they're doing. I mean, there's geniuses there. It's actually really inspiring.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  I've interacted with a lot of brilliant people in the software world.
SPEAKER_0:  And maybe because I don't deeply understand.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of hardware stuff, materials engineering, mechanical engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  Those people seem like so much smarter.
SPEAKER_0:  It's always like the grass is green or whatever the expression is. But
SPEAKER_0:  There is a depth of understanding that engineers have that do like mechanical engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  that's just awe-inspiring.
SPEAKER_0:  to me.
SPEAKER_1:  Not to get too like.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know what the word would be, introverted or something or whatever, but that's actually kind of the whole point of Everyday Astronaut. That's almost the whole point of what I do each year. From the beginning, I-
SPEAKER_1:  did a thing called the Astro Awards, trying to be like an award show.
SPEAKER_1:  hoping to lift up and celebrate and shine a spotlight on the people that are actually doing the hard work and try to treat them like the rock stars that they are that we
SPEAKER_1:  don't know about. I think that's one of the things that for sure I think-
SPEAKER_1:  I think Elon definitely helped make.
SPEAKER_1:  Space Fight Cool.
SPEAKER_1:  helped make that like a celebration thing where people are
SPEAKER_1:  physically out cheering for rockets and science and space exploration.
SPEAKER_1:  But I think that's just the beginning you know I think like this should be a thing where.
SPEAKER_1:  the general public.
SPEAKER_1:  uh looks to these people as as the coolest ones as the coolest places to work as the most important things you know sports are great and everything a big formula one fan and things like that but.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, at the same time, like.
SPEAKER_1:  We should be celebrating the people.
SPEAKER_1:  doing this crazy work, clocking in countless hours, just trying to figure out this one little thing that's gonna help us further our understanding. I mean, what's cooler than a-
SPEAKER_0:  giant thing.
SPEAKER_0:  with a really hot-
SPEAKER_0:  FIRE!
SPEAKER_0:  that goes boom and goes up into the air. I mean, like, there's no-
SPEAKER_0:  It's like to me, like bridges are inspiring. It's like incredible architecture design and like the humans are able to.
SPEAKER_0:  work
SPEAKER_0:  against nature build these gigantic metal things but like rockets.
SPEAKER_0:  with like a tiny little humans on top of them.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, flying out into space is sick. It's the coolest possible thing. Everything comes together. All the different disciplines come together for the high stakes drama of.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, riding that super powerful thing up.
SPEAKER_0:  away from the thing we call home Earth. That is so amazing. Exactly, so freaking.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I think that's kind of part of my story arc is I just used to be a huge car and motorcycle guy. So I think he's a great guy because especially after traveling like soft rough roads, I just
SPEAKER_1:  You know, things that go fast and you know.
SPEAKER_1:  loud and go fast and.
SPEAKER_1:  make lots of power. And at the end of the day, like at some point you realize
SPEAKER_1:  Nothing goes faster and it's louder and makes more power in the rocket. You know, I think that's...
SPEAKER_1:  I think that's kind of where I eventually just ended up, you know, wound up there just because there is nothing cooler than that.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that's the ultimate level of reach as a car guy is.
SPEAKER_1:  become a rocket guy. Yeah, 100%. And at some point, some car guys literally become rocket guys and strap rockets to cars and try and break land speed records, you know? Yep.
SPEAKER_1:  It's the same universe here, and yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So Elon, with your conversation with him on the Raptor 2, what's talking about, you were talking about...
SPEAKER_0:  Like there's an excessive amount of cooling to be on the safe side as you're developing the engine. What kind of cooling was that?
SPEAKER_1:  So that would be film cooling. So remember how a little bit ago we were talking about keeping the turbine from melting? You can just run it.
SPEAKER_1:  off of like off nominal basically off.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, typically fuel rich, just run more fuel through that so it's cool enough.
SPEAKER_1:  You can actually do that locally kind of in your engine. So you can keep it so, you know, imagine a combustion chamber.
SPEAKER_1:  and the top of it's just a flat, like imagine a shower head.
SPEAKER_1:  and then you have like, you know, the combustion chamber attached to it.
SPEAKER_1:  the outer perimeter there, the part where the flame front would be touching the walls, you can actually have just more fuel injectors.
SPEAKER_1:  So you're injecting locally a more fuel rich.
SPEAKER_1:  zone along the entire nozzle.
SPEAKER_1:  and that would be called film cooling.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's less efficient though. Again, you're kind of wasting fuel. There's fuel that's running.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, and your mixture ratio is off.
SPEAKER_1:  but only for a little portion of the big picture. So that's one of those compromises. You can do additional film cooling.
SPEAKER_1:  to make sure you're not melting your engine.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... you know but at the cost of performance usually
SPEAKER_1:  But you can also be smart and use film cooling. You know, there's fun little clever tricks.
SPEAKER_1:  For instance, you'll notice on the F1 engine that was on the Saturn V.
SPEAKER_1:  the biggest rocket that had been built.
SPEAKER_1:  to date prior now to Starship.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  The F1 has this huge, huge, huge engines. There's five of them.
SPEAKER_1:  on the Saturn V and
SPEAKER_1:  you'll notice that like the gas generator has a pipe that comes down.
SPEAKER_1:  and then it actually splits off in a manifold and wraps around part of the nozzle.
SPEAKER_1:  And that manifold.
SPEAKER_1:  takes the hot gas from the turbine.
SPEAKER_1:  Which is actually, I mean, it's not hot.
SPEAKER_1:  It's actually cold gas compared to the combustion chamber.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's, you know, in human terms, it's still, you wouldn't want to put your hand in it, not live.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, and it actually pipes that gas.
SPEAKER_1:  into the nozzle so that it creates a film cooling, an actual
SPEAKER_1:  Boundary Layer.
SPEAKER_1:  of cooler gas against the hotter combustion chamber gas.
SPEAKER_1:  So basically repurposing.
SPEAKER_1:  that gas that was normally wasted and they pump it back into the engine.
SPEAKER_1:  and then into the nozzle like kind of further down. So the trick there is it has to be.
SPEAKER_1:  far enough down that the pressure.
SPEAKER_1:  at the, in the nozzle, because remember, as the nozzle gets bigger and bigger and bigger, the pressure's getting lower and lower.
SPEAKER_1:  and the temperature's getting lower and lower. So you have to find this trade-off point where...
SPEAKER_1:  The pressure is.
SPEAKER_1:  is lower than that gas from the turbine and then you pump it in
SPEAKER_1:  and it's cooler than the gas still is in the nozzle.
SPEAKER_1:  and it can help not melt your nozzle. So you'll notice that the F1 is actually a good example of regen cooling. So that OK.
SPEAKER_1:  walls you can physically see the pipes actually.
SPEAKER_1:  on the F1 because it's so big and they just literally used pipes and bent them and
SPEAKER_1:  You can see the coolant channels all the way up and down the engine until you get to that manifold.
SPEAKER_1:  Then from there on, it just has...
SPEAKER_1:  what's called a nozzle extension, and it keeps going and going and going, and that section of nozzle is cooled by the film cooling.
SPEAKER_1:  of the gas generator.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, the aerodynamics of.
SPEAKER_0:  Cooler gas and the hot gas.
SPEAKER_0:  because you have to have this kind of
SPEAKER_0:  layer, right? To protect a layer of cool, like understanding that.
SPEAKER_0:  now this is probably has to do a modern times this probably really dissimilar sed animated
SPEAKER_0:  and to do that in terms of pressure too, like.
SPEAKER_0:  to make sure it's in the right place. Yeah, that doesn't-
SPEAKER_1:  Like, go back up. Go backwards, exactly. If they have that manifold.
SPEAKER_1:  Even six inches too high.
SPEAKER_1:  on that nozzle.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's just gonna go upwards, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  Pressure always wants to flow from high to low.
SPEAKER_0:  the number of options you have here that result in it going boom.
SPEAKER_0:  is very large. Near infinity, yeah. Especially because, I mean, you can't do like a small model of it.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe you can. No, you can't. You really scale very well. No, you have to do the full testing. And that's why you have all the kind of.
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  That's why you have with Starship all the tests that you know.
SPEAKER_0:  You think why would you?
SPEAKER_0:  Need to do so many static fires and so many tests and why is it failing so many times? Can't you get it right?
SPEAKER_0:  but like it's very tough to get it right. MUFFLED
SPEAKER_1:  And when you're pushing the boundaries, you want to know.
SPEAKER_1:  where and how it's going to fail. That's right. So that's.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a luxury that SpaceX does have with the scale of Raptor. You know, they're building Raptor cheaper than probably almost any other engine, you know, maybe besides some of their own, at least at that scale.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, then before they're testing, you know, I think since last March or last April.
SPEAKER_1:  They've tested a thousand Raptors, you know, a thousand engine fires, I guess, not just Raptors, but...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, that's just an insane amount of data.
SPEAKER_1:  and an insane amount of edge cases to learn, oh my God, we found out that we were actually slightly overspinning our turbine at this degree and this frequency.
SPEAKER_1:  as harmonic at this blah blah blah and all of a sudden you realize it's rattling and you know it did this and then you can engineer around that you know it's like
SPEAKER_1:  it.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll ultimately.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I think Elon said something like.
SPEAKER_1:  higher production rate.
SPEAKER_1:  solves many ills or something along those lines.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's just true if you have an insane amount of engines and an insane amount of data and insane amount of failures to learn from.
SPEAKER_1:  You just know your system inside and out. You know those margins. You know where the failure points are. You know how to engineer around them.
SPEAKER_1:  That's how I approach dating.
SPEAKER_0:  No, I'm just kidding.
SPEAKER_0:  Cause we're talking about engines.
SPEAKER_0:  So
SPEAKER_0:  Most rockets, I think all rockets have multiple stages today.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe they'll take us into discussion of what ideas that could be for single stage to orbit rockets. But can you describe this whole thing that you've been mentioning here and there?
SPEAKER_0:  multiple stages of a rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, no, that's a good question. So.
SPEAKER_1:  Ultimately, you know, like I said, you're kind of pushing about 90% the rockets like basically just fuel with some skin on it. You know what I mean?
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  That skin weighs a lot of.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, skin and the engines do weigh a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, like I said, the Falcon 9 on someone's about 20 tons. Just the booster is about 20 metric tons.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's not an insignificant amount of weight. So the idea is...
SPEAKER_1:  With staging.
SPEAKER_1:  is you ditch anything you don't need, more or less.
SPEAKER_1:  So Falcon 9 is a perfect rocket to think about this because you have a upper stage.
SPEAKER_1:  and you have a booster, you know, our first stage.
SPEAKER_1:  And the first stage burns through all this fuel. Once it's out of fuel, you let go of the second stage and ta-da, you actually just basically started and lit.
SPEAKER_1:  a brand new fresh rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, this brand new fresh rocket now doesn't have all that.
SPEAKER_1:  that 20 tons attached to it.
SPEAKER_1:  so it's a lot lighter. It doesn't need nearly as many engines to push it around. It needs just one instead of nine.
SPEAKER_1:  Its engine can be optimized for the vacuum of space as opposed to having to operate at sea level with all of our
SPEAKER_1:  Relative actually pretty thick atmosphere, you know, relatively so.
SPEAKER_1:  So staging is basically the idea that you get rid of things you don't need.
SPEAKER_1:  On Earth, again, kind of that whole like 10%
SPEAKER_1:  of 10% easier.
SPEAKER_1:  If it was 10% easier, single-stage orbit would be no big deal.
SPEAKER_1:  And it probably would have been like the.
SPEAKER_1:  the way to get to orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  choice just because like
SPEAKER_1:  It's not that hard.
SPEAKER_1:  with our
SPEAKER_1:  Earth as it is.
SPEAKER_1:  with physics as it is. It's just...
SPEAKER_1:  It's doable and we've had.
SPEAKER_1:  And you know, we almost kind of actually the first rocket to take humans into orbit from the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  which was the
SPEAKER_1:  Atlas rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  was kind of a stage and a half.
SPEAKER_1:  It actually only had like one big fuel tank.
SPEAKER_1:  And what they did is they actually dropped off two of its three engines.
SPEAKER_1:  So it just ditched some of the engines, but if it hadn't done that, you know, so kind of-
SPEAKER_1:  People were like, well, that was single stage. It's like, it still had a staging event. It still had a ditch mass in order to even make it into orbit. Had it not done that.
SPEAKER_1:  it would have not been able to get into orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  So you pretty quickly look at your trade and say.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, well, if I want to stick to single-stage orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  My payload mass becomes.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, like you might be able to put like
SPEAKER_1:  You know, a Falcon 9 booster on its own. Like if you just flew one of the side core boosters to a Falcon Heavy.
SPEAKER_1:  with a nose cone on it and everything just said, I'm just going to fly this on its own.
SPEAKER_1:  you might be able to put like,
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  10 kilograms into space or something, very small amount.
SPEAKER_1:  We'll throw a second stage on that thing and now you can put.
SPEAKER_1:  you know.
SPEAKER_1:  17,000 kilograms into space.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's just an order, you know, orders of magnitude more.
SPEAKER_1:  payload capacity because you did staging, because you ditched the residual weight.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  The other thing that's...
SPEAKER_1:  about that too is that
SPEAKER_1:  the engines again that operate at sea level are often not great in space and vice versa. Like you physically...
SPEAKER_1:  Can't.
SPEAKER_1:  are most optimized for space engines you can't even operate at sea level.
SPEAKER_1:  destroy themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  due to something called flow separation.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  not only are you getting the benefit of ditching all the weight, you're also able to use it much more efficient.
SPEAKER_1:  and typically a much less powerful engine.
SPEAKER_0:  space.
SPEAKER_0:  the multi-stage rockets.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... that maybe the dream would be uh...
SPEAKER_0:  if we weren't living on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  But maybe we can on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  to have a single stage to orbit rocket where it's all one package.
SPEAKER_0:  Reusable.
SPEAKER_1:  Reusable gets even harder. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  and harder. So first of all, what is
SPEAKER_0:  Just a ling on it. What is the single stage to orbit rocket?
SPEAKER_0:  And why is it so hard to achieve?
SPEAKER_0:  on earth. You already kind of explained it a little bit, but if we were to say, that's your assignment.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Tim, you're supposed to get together with Elon and.
SPEAKER_0:  other brilliant people and like you have to do this.
SPEAKER_0:  Why is it so hard?
SPEAKER_1:  Why is it so hard?
SPEAKER_1:  Your the the payload fraction of a rocket is
SPEAKER_1:  like three to five or six or 7% would be like.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, that's...
SPEAKER_1:  the amount of payload compared to the total mass of the rocket. Like you're lucky to get into.
SPEAKER_1:  beyond 5%.
SPEAKER_1:  So if you're now having to deal with the weight of the rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  by the time you're in orbit, like you're...
SPEAKER_1:  payload fraction just.
SPEAKER_1:  You're talking about like margins, it's such.
SPEAKER_1:  It's so small amount of leftover.
SPEAKER_1:  if you have to take all of it with you.
SPEAKER_1:  So the sooner you can ditch weight, the better.
SPEAKER_1:  The sooner you can ditch weight, the better. The sooner you can...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, and that's what you're doing a rocket the whole time is actually ditching weight.
SPEAKER_1:  All of that fuel
SPEAKER_1:  All that big giant flame you see is literally mass being thrown out the back of the rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  but what typically isn't expended, at least during nominal operations, you're not seeing the engines being expelled out the thing.
SPEAKER_1:  until you get to staging, of course. And that's where you're ditching all that dead weight.
SPEAKER_1:  So single-stage orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  Your margins just become so small that it
SPEAKER_1:  It's.
SPEAKER_1:  Border is not impossible.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's just at the end of the day, like almost no matter who you are, you end up saying it's just simply not worth it. I gotta be...
SPEAKER_1:  If you have two rockets that are using the same amount of propellant.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, they're the same physical sizes and one of them.
SPEAKER_1:  cutting on a third and has another little engine.
SPEAKER_1:  It'll have 100 or 1000 times more payload capacity.
SPEAKER_1:  than the one sitting right next to it.
SPEAKER_1:  And now, so there's tricks you can do to like try to offset that things like Aerospike engines, which
SPEAKER_1:  operate at.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  as efficiently at sea level, as efficiently at sea level.
SPEAKER_1:  and just buy their.
SPEAKER_1:  By the way, they're designed the physics of them. They're also efficient in a vacuum, too
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  You can do things like that.
SPEAKER_1:  And at the end of the day though...
SPEAKER_1:  you just end up with a worse rocket than if you had just done stage, like no matter what. And people say like, well, what if you had developed the new technologies? Like, okay, apply that technology to a multi-stage rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's gonna do better, you know, no matter where you end up.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just always better to ditch that weight. Is there a cost-
SPEAKER_0:  to having multi-stage.
SPEAKER_0:  because you can still reuse the different stages.
SPEAKER_1:  that's the dream is, you know, becomes easier to reuse.
SPEAKER_1:  multiple stages because now you know like the booster doesn't have to survive orbital.
SPEAKER_1:  reentry temperatures and extreme environments.
SPEAKER_1:  and you only have to make survival the upper stage. So you only have to put a big heat shield. I mean, Starship's the perfect-
SPEAKER_1:  of this the upper stage has a big giant heat shield
SPEAKER_1:  The booster doesn't need it because it's not going, the booster's not going to orbit, it's only going.
SPEAKER_1:  a fifth or a quarter of orbital velocity. So it's heat that it experiences is survivable just by the stainless steel. You don't need.
SPEAKER_1:  an additional heat shield.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  So all of a sudden, if you're trying to reuse, pretend that you just welded the two stages of Starship together, remove those engines on Starship.
SPEAKER_1:  That whole vehicle, if you're trying to reuse it, the whole vehicle now has to have a heat shield on one side of it. The whole thing has to have these big heavy wings.
SPEAKER_1:  By the time you come down to it, there's...
SPEAKER_1:  Probably just zero payload capacity.
SPEAKER_1:  You basically put your fuel tank in space, you know? Good job.
SPEAKER_0:  So the dream of a single stage orbit.
SPEAKER_0:  A rocket.
SPEAKER_0:  is.
SPEAKER_0:  Is that just even the wrong?
SPEAKER_0:  dream on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  That's what.
SPEAKER_1:  Most convention tells you you know by the time if if you're you're if your goal is cheap
SPEAKER_1:  then you're going to have a physically larger rocket that has more engines, that has more propellant.
SPEAKER_1:  blah blah blah to put the same amount of mass into orbit compared to something else. You know, we're talking like.
SPEAKER_1:  Rocket Labs Electron, a really small rocket. It's like, I think 1.3 meters wide and something like, you know,
SPEAKER_1:  18 meters tall or something. It's a small rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  If you were to, you know, and it can put something like 300.
SPEAKER_1:  or so kilograms into orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  You can either launch something that size or again, like a full like big old Falcon nine.
SPEAKER_1:  Booster.
SPEAKER_1:  The huge, huge thing.
SPEAKER_1:  and that would be lucky to put 300 kilograms into orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, so it's like, which one's going to be cheaper to build, you know, ship around.
SPEAKER_1:  all this stuff and then you also look at you have fixed costs like.
SPEAKER_1:  The idea of flying a...
SPEAKER_1:  But this, again, everything in rocket science is a compromise, because now you have
SPEAKER_1:  Things like people on console time, all the people that are, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  on coms and working on the rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  going down to the pad.
SPEAKER_1:  You know filing paperwork doing range control making sure there's not planes and boats in the way. Flight termination people you have all these fixed costs for any launch i don't care how big the rocket is.
SPEAKER_1:  there's a relatively fixed cost.
SPEAKER_1:  So now you say like, okay.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm gonna be paying, well let's just make a winner. I'm gonna pay $5 million.
SPEAKER_1:  fly a rocket between all the people going on site, all the propellant, all the licenses, blah, blah, blah.
SPEAKER_1:  If your fixed cost is $5 million, you can put...
SPEAKER_1:  300 kilograms in space versus.
SPEAKER_1:  you have a $5 million cost of operation.
SPEAKER_1:  and you can put.
SPEAKER_1:  5,000 kilograms into space, like it.
SPEAKER_1:  it's
SPEAKER_1:  the business case is gonna send you in one direction pretty quickly.
SPEAKER_0:  So you mentioned aerospike engines.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the internet...
SPEAKER_0:  inform me of your love affair with the house by catching, find somebody.
SPEAKER_0:  that looks at you the way Tim Na looks at Aerospark engines.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  Can you explain what these are, how do they work, what's beautiful to them, how practical are they, why don't we use them?
SPEAKER_0:  Does it just boil down to the design of the nozzle?
SPEAKER_0:  So maybe can you explain how is it possible to achieve this thing?
SPEAKER_0:  for an engine to be as efficient in a vacuum and sea level.
SPEAKER_0:  conditions.
SPEAKER_1:  You know what I love about this is that every question you've asked me is like a one hour video on my YouTube channel. I was like, now boil it down to 45 seconds. Go.
SPEAKER_1:  So the Aerospike engine basically...
SPEAKER_1:  is an inside out engine more or less.
SPEAKER_1:  So with a traditional engine, we've talked about the combustion chamber and the throat, and then it expands out into the nozzle.
SPEAKER_1:  Those walls are containing.
SPEAKER_1:  The pressure, right?
SPEAKER_1:  Air spike is the opposite. Basically, the pressure of the engine is on the outside of it.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's pushing inward against a spike.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's almost like the difference of if you were.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me think about this. We're standing in my cub.
SPEAKER_1:  tent or a teepee right and you put your arms at the top and you pushed your arms out like into an iron cross or something you know you can physically lift the tent just by pushing outwards on
SPEAKER_1:  the tent walls, right?
SPEAKER_1:  Well, that would be like a traditional nozzle. Now, aerospace would be almost like squeezing an ice cube.
SPEAKER_1:  If you squeeze an ice cube, you can push in on it and kind of that wedge force.
SPEAKER_1:  We'll shoot that ice cube.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's kind of what is happening. You have the high pressure gases on the outside of the spike.
SPEAKER_1:  squeezing in on that spike and that's and then that's pushing up against the
SPEAKER_1:  because it's equal on both sides.
SPEAKER_1:  against the kind of the ramp.
SPEAKER_1:  is pushing up against the rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's where that force comes in, against the nozzle and against the chambers.
SPEAKER_1:  The hard part with an aerospike. So the cool, okay, I guess the cool thing about an aerospike.
SPEAKER_1:  is.
SPEAKER_1:  that it can operate.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  In space, you can have what's known as a really big expansion ratio. So that's your ratio between the throat.
SPEAKER_1:  the area of the throat.
SPEAKER_1:  versus the area of the nozzle exit.
SPEAKER_1:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_1:  And remember how the bigger the nozzle is.
SPEAKER_1:  the it's continually just converting more and more is converting that high energy.
SPEAKER_1:  Hot.
SPEAKER_1:  high pressure gas into cooler.
SPEAKER_1:  and.
SPEAKER_1:  cooler, lower pressure and faster gas. So each little millimeter along that nozzle is just getting it.
SPEAKER_1:  lower pressure and cooler, but faster.
SPEAKER_1:  Now if you take a big nozzle on earth and you at sea level.
SPEAKER_1:  and you fire it, you can actually get.
SPEAKER_1:  even though we're going from say 300 bar the Raptor engine.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, our atmosphere at sea level is about one bar. It's pretty much exactly one bar.
SPEAKER_1:  depending on conditions.
SPEAKER_1:  but.
SPEAKER_1:  you can actually get a nozzle to get way below.
SPEAKER_1:  one bar of pressure.
SPEAKER_1:  So every little, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  You can go from 300 bar.
SPEAKER_1:  in just two meters down to.
SPEAKER_1:  one bar or below one bar.
SPEAKER_1:  There's actually a limit. You can actually only expand it below.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, we'll say something like 70% so you can get down to like 0.7 bar.
SPEAKER_1:  at nozzle exit before the pressure of the atmosphere is actually squeezing in on that exhaust.
SPEAKER_1:  and tearing it away from the walls of the engine.
SPEAKER_1:  walls of the nozzle exit.
SPEAKER_1:  And what happens is it's kind of unpredictable. You get these pockets, these oscillations.
SPEAKER_1:  and they'll be so extreme that they'll end up just destroying the nozzle.
SPEAKER_1:  So you can't lower.
SPEAKER_1:  You can't have a bigger expansion ratio.
SPEAKER_1:  then again, relatively speaking, something like.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you can't go below.
SPEAKER_1:  You can't get that pressure exit.
SPEAKER_1:  much below ambient air pressure before flow separation can destroy the engine.
SPEAKER_0:  So how come this engine...
SPEAKER_0:  can do so in different pressure conditions.
SPEAKER_1:  So because it's inside out.
SPEAKER_1:  the ambient pressure is pushing the exhaust gas into the wall.
SPEAKER_1:  as opposed to a conventional engine that exhaust, the ambient air is actually squeezing.
SPEAKER_1:  the exhaust gas away from the walls of the engine.
SPEAKER_1:  And that squeezing away from is what can be destructive.
SPEAKER_1:  So that since it's kind of inside out.
SPEAKER_1:  The ambient air is pushing the exhaust gas into the engine walls.
SPEAKER_1:  So you can't have flow separation. You won't have flow separation.
SPEAKER_1:  Now what happens is so you can have this huge.
SPEAKER_1:  amazingly efficient vacuum engine that has a.
SPEAKER_1:  we'll say a 200 to one expansion ratio, which is really big. A lot of C level engines are.
SPEAKER_1:  like 35, 40, 50 to one expansion ratios.
SPEAKER_1:  And then in space, you know, it's common to use like 150, 180, 201 expansion ratios.
SPEAKER_1:  So in the airspec can have something like 200 to one.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just that the at sea level is kind of just getting pushed and it's kind of getting cut off early almost, but it doesn't matter. It's not like destructive. It's just not running at its maximum efficiency.
SPEAKER_1:  as it climbs in altitude as the ambient air gets thinner and thinner and thinner.
SPEAKER_1:  It just inherently is pushing less and less and less against the walls of that.
SPEAKER_1:  Aerospike Engine.
SPEAKER_1:  so it actually continually gets more efficient.
SPEAKER_1:  at, you know, as it climbs in altitude.
SPEAKER_1:  As does the normal engine, but the difference is...
SPEAKER_1:  that you can use that huge expansion ratio.
SPEAKER_1:  at sea level and you can't use.
SPEAKER_1:  a huge expansion ratio.
SPEAKER_1:  at sea level with their traditional nozzle.
SPEAKER_0:  Has anyone actually flown an Air Spike engine?
SPEAKER_1:  No Aerospike engine to date has ever been flown on an orbital rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  Why not? And w-
SPEAKER_0:  I'd like to see a future where they're used.
SPEAKER_1:  purely purely because I think they're cool. Yeah, you know in the same way.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the core of your love affair with air spike engines.
SPEAKER_1:  And I said this in my video actually outside before I came in here I saw.
SPEAKER_1:  on RX-7.
SPEAKER_1:  on the streets that I just love and that uses a rotary engine.
SPEAKER_1:  on paper the rotary engine is like.
SPEAKER_1:  more efficient, smaller, more efficient, all these things, but in practice it's like.
SPEAKER_1:  The thing is actually just like unreliable hot.
SPEAKER_1:  and it, you know, it, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. Burns oil.
SPEAKER_1:  Kind of the same thing with the AeroSpike engine. Like, yes on paper it's more efficient.
SPEAKER_1:  but now you have a lot more surface area of your...
SPEAKER_1:  your throat area no matter what is going to have.
SPEAKER_1:  The throw of the rocket engine is always where it's the hottest. You know, it's the hardest thing to cool.
SPEAKER_1:  And with an aerospike, if...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, if it's inside out, now your throat is.
SPEAKER_1:  no matter what, like way bigger. It's almost like the size of the nozzle exit normally, but now it's your hardest thing to cool and you have a ton of it.
SPEAKER_1:  And you also have
SPEAKER_1:  two edges of it no matter what. So even if you have like a
SPEAKER_1:  you know, a circle inside a circle.
SPEAKER_1:  You have like a just insane amount more.
SPEAKER_1:  surface area to cool with a limited amount of fuel. Don't forget using your fuel.
SPEAKER_1:  As your as your coolant.
SPEAKER_1:  So if you all of a sudden now take your throat area and you have
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  X amount of space that you need to cool.
SPEAKER_1:  You only have, you have a limited supply.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like, ugh.
SPEAKER_1:  Sorry, this is the stuff that just...
SPEAKER_0:  Are there ideas of for cooling?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  of cooling out spike engines.
SPEAKER_1:  the same physics apply for an aerospike as they would. So you just run into a limitation. Like at some point I'm not flowing enough propellant.
SPEAKER_1:  It scales, it scales kind of poorly. You know what I mean?
SPEAKER_1:  You can increase the thrust of an aerospec by making it bigger and increase the mass flow.
SPEAKER_1:  and the fuel going through the throats.
SPEAKER_1:  or the throat.
SPEAKER_1:  But at the same time, like it just, it's at the end of the day.
SPEAKER_1:  It's physically possible.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a lot more complex.
SPEAKER_1:  You have a lot of issues with cooling.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's just you end up kind of right back where you started.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's like, is it worth it to just keep going down this rabbit hole?
SPEAKER_1:  You're trying to engineer this thing to work.
SPEAKER_1:  when you could have probably spent a tenth the amount of time just slightly increasing the performance of your
SPEAKER_1:  normal engine in the first place, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  Again, I'm going to anthropomorphize that lesson and apply it to my dating life. Once again, just kidding. Okay, actually just on a small tangent.
SPEAKER_0:  since you are also a car guy.
SPEAKER_0:  What's the greatest?
SPEAKER_0:  combustion engine car ever made.
SPEAKER_0:  to you if you had to pick.
SPEAKER_0:  something, what's the coolest?
SPEAKER_0:  The sexiest, the most powerful, the...
SPEAKER_0:  Classiest most elegant well-designed. I don't know what
SPEAKER_1:  are different for me but I'd say... they are guitar
SPEAKER_1:  I still, it's funny, because now, maybe it's just because it's fresh on mind, but I love.
SPEAKER_1:  that mid 90s RX-7.
SPEAKER_1:  which you know especially in Japan they had the the 20b a tri-rotor
SPEAKER_1:  That is like the coolest engine ever to me.
SPEAKER_1:  the FD RX-7.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just too darn cool, honestly.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  Ah.
SPEAKER_0:  There you go.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, what about the mid-90s that makes it special?
SPEAKER_1:  just that's the only time everything was it's more that I love the engine and I like the cards attached to him and I'm not actually a big fan of like 90s styling you know personally
SPEAKER_1:  But just that the 20B is just such a cool.
SPEAKER_1:  and his twin-turbo sequential turbos?
SPEAKER_1:  They used um...
SPEAKER_1:  A bigger turbo takes longer to spool up. It takes more, it's using that same, like a turbine and a compressor.
SPEAKER_1:  And it just, if it's a large turbine, it takes more exhaust gas to get it spooled up.
SPEAKER_1:  So if you have an engine that revs to 9,000 RPM and you want to get a lot of pressure out of that turbo,
SPEAKER_1:  You have a big turbo it's gonna take forever. Like you're gonna have your floor and then like.
SPEAKER_1:  Right, it's gonna take a long time for that turbo to get spooled up.
SPEAKER_1:  They actually did a small turbo on it.
SPEAKER_1:  and a big turbo. So the small turbo would spool up first, get some boost going through the engine, get that engine.
SPEAKER_1:  Operating get it up to speed get it. You know get some power to the wheels
SPEAKER_1:  And then once that kind of reaches its limit, you'd flow it into the, divert the exhaust gas into the bigger turbo, this sequential turbo.
SPEAKER_1:  And then that now can supplement and actually increase the overall performance of the vehicle by a lot. And I just.
SPEAKER_1:  That's just so cool. It's just like the ultimate like...
SPEAKER_1:  brute force out of the box thinking.
SPEAKER_1:  And it actually made it into production. You know what I mean?
SPEAKER_0:  Can you, what's the sound like? Can you tell an engine by sound?
SPEAKER_1:  It sounds like a really, really, really angry lot.
SPEAKER_1:  It sounds horrible. It's actually a terrible sounding car. In my opinion, I like its sound.
SPEAKER_1:  just raspy and like
SPEAKER_1:  The opposite of like a big muscle car. You know, like a big muscle car, just deep, guttural, like, it's deep. Oh, it just hits you. This is like, it's just gonna annoy the hell out of you and all your neighbors. you
SPEAKER_1:  But you love the engineering. I love the engineering of it.
SPEAKER_0:  So to you, the car is the engine.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not.
SPEAKER_0:  All the surface stuff, all the design stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  All the you know, yeah the the elegance the curves whatever it is
SPEAKER_1:  Well, those come and go.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, to me, styles change. It's forever. Yeah. I'm going to play.
SPEAKER_0:  that to my dating life once again.
SPEAKER_1:  just keep on coming. Well, if you think about it, my taste has changed throughout the years. When I first saw.
SPEAKER_1:  A model three Tesla. I thought it was the most hideous car ever and then without the grill. I was like, this is so stupid
SPEAKER_1:  It took me all but two months to think that it was one of the coolest looking cars.
SPEAKER_1:  Same with Cybertruck. I mourned Cybertruck. When I first saw that thing, I was at the-
SPEAKER_1:  thing with and I went with we used to do a podcast called our ludicrous future
SPEAKER_1:  So we talked a lot about like, you know, cars and EVs and stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  We went to that unveiling and literally, we had almost a non-alcohol-induced hangover the next morning of like morning.
SPEAKER_1:  the hideousness of Cybertruck.
SPEAKER_1:  come six months later, a year later, and I'm like.
SPEAKER_1:  Damn it, that thing's actually kind of cool.
SPEAKER_0:  That also teaches you something about...
SPEAKER_0:  No, again, it's the thing you said.
SPEAKER_0:  earlier sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  going against.
SPEAKER_0:  the current of the experts of the police or whatever is making a decision from first principles. Some of that also applies to design and styling and fashion and culture and all that. Peace.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of that.
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  So in fashion especially, it's so interesting. So subjective. Being rebellious.
SPEAKER_0:  against the current fads.
SPEAKER_0:  actually is the way to pave.
SPEAKER_0:  the new fads.
SPEAKER_1:  When it didn't take long for others to follow, you look at like currently, like what Hyundai is doing with their.
SPEAKER_1:  I forget which one, like the Ionic or something like that. It's square, it's like, it's boxy. You know, it's a throwback, it's 80s, it's got these beautiful retro taillights, it's got these square headlights.
SPEAKER_1:  It's very inspired by Cybertruck in my opinion. I mean, it might not be. It might be coincidental that we're all kind of getting this.
SPEAKER_1:  Retro future vibe, but.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... i personally
SPEAKER_0:  Boxxy.
SPEAKER_0:  So I never, I still haven't.
SPEAKER_0:  Understood.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Porsche's.
SPEAKER_0:  bushes. I still can't
SPEAKER_0:  quite.
SPEAKER_0:  Understand the small size, the curves. I don't quite-
SPEAKER_1:  I don't quite get it. Like I said, I don't love the look of the RX 7. I don't love it, but I love it because of
SPEAKER_1:  the engineering, I guess, that it represents. You know what I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's not the surface stuff, it's the deep down stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  It's that 50-50 wage distribution that matters.
SPEAKER_0: .
SPEAKER_0:  All right, let's let's talk about Starship a little bit. We've been sneaking up to it from a bunch of different directions.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you just say...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  What is Starship and what is the most impressive thing to you about it? I mean, you've talked about the sort of the engines involved. Maybe you haven't really.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of like dancing around it, but.
SPEAKER_0:  Because this is such a crucial...
SPEAKER_0:  thing.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of the next few years in terms of your own life personally and also just.
SPEAKER_0:  human civilization reaching out to the stars. It seems like Starship is a really important vehicle to making that happen. So what is this thing that we're talking about?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so Starship is-
SPEAKER_0:  is.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Currently in development, the world's largest, most powerful.
SPEAKER_1:  Rocket ever built?
SPEAKER_1:  Fully reusable rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  a two-stage rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  So the booster is landed and...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, all this is currently aspirational until it's working.
SPEAKER_1:  So I'll say it's.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll say what it's aspirationally going to be. And obviously I have faith that that will happen.
SPEAKER_1:  just factually. So the booster will be reused, re-fueled and reused.
SPEAKER_1:  The upper stage will be landed, refueled, and reused.
SPEAKER_1:  And ideally, rapidly, in the sense, not talking about months or weeks of refurbishment, but literally talking about mild inspections.
SPEAKER_1:  and ideally like under 24 hour reuse, you know, where you literally land it and fly it like an airplane.
SPEAKER_1:  So it utilizes liquid methane and liquid oxygen.
SPEAKER_1:  as its propellants.
SPEAKER_1:  It utilizes, the current iterations of it are 33.
SPEAKER_1:  Raptor engines on the booster engine, on the booster.
SPEAKER_1:  and six Raptors on the second stage. So there'll be three that are vacuum optimized and three that are sea level optimized on the upper stage.
SPEAKER_1:  that are primarily, they'll be used, I think, at stage separation anyway.
SPEAKER_1:  in space but their main reason that they use them is so they can use them for landing too.
SPEAKER_1:  See you next time.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... to be able to possibly land the upper stages well
SPEAKER_0:  So the three wrapped engines are the ones that generate the thrust.
SPEAKER_0:  that makes it the most powerful rocket ever built.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  to almost double.
SPEAKER_0:  compared to the Saturn fight.
SPEAKER_1:  The N1 had 45 MN of thrust. The Saturn V had, I think...
SPEAKER_1:  35 or 40 Megan Nunes of Thrust.
SPEAKER_1:  and this has 75 mega newton so we're talking
SPEAKER_1:  Almost double.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a-
SPEAKER_1:  It's a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  of power.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  That could be the sexiest thing I've ever heard. Okay. So what are the different testing that's happening? So like a.
SPEAKER_0:  What's a static fire with some of these Raptors look like and where do we stand you would you're just talking about offline?
SPEAKER_0:  like the thing that happened.
SPEAKER_0:  yesterday. It was impressive.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, everything in this is kind of iterations. And so.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, the milestones that we're seeing, we actually have on everydayastronaut.com, we have a milestone checklist of like all the things we're hoping to see that we kind of need to see before the first orbital flight of this rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  So a big milestone that got checked off yesterday was a wet dress rehearsal. So it's literally like fueling.
SPEAKER_1:  The Rock It Up.
SPEAKER_1:  getting ready to do everything but lighting the engines, basically. So we're talking about loading it with propellant all the way. This is the first time. Yep, right there. Where's the milestones? Right there at the top. Click that big.
SPEAKER_1:  picture.
SPEAKER_1:  Just anywhere, that big pic.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's the what dress rehearsal. So what's the what dress rehearsal?
SPEAKER_1:  So that's where they...
SPEAKER_1:  For the first time, they filled it completely to the brim with both liquid oxygen and liquid methane.
SPEAKER_1:  Now they had done component level testing where they fill it.
SPEAKER_1:  with liquid nitrogen, which is, you know, it's an inert gas. So it's not like, say it leaks out, it's not going to explode.
SPEAKER_1:  You could just have a big giant pool of liquid nitrogen like flooding.
SPEAKER_1:  the area, but it's not gonna be an explosion.
SPEAKER_1:  So they've done that for cryo testing to make sure all the components and stuff can handle.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, being at cryogenic temperatures.
SPEAKER_1:  It's kind of a good analog before you start putting your fuel and your oxidizer in there.
SPEAKER_1:  But now, as of yesterday...
SPEAKER_1:  They fully fueled the rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  with propellant, both stages, the first stage and the second stage while fully stacked on the pad.
SPEAKER_1:  Basically, I mean, it was the first sense we really got off like, this is what it's going to look like right before it takes off.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, kind of breathing coming to life for the first time.
SPEAKER_0:  What does the pad look like? So there's a few interesting aspects of this.
SPEAKER_0:  what's up with the chopsticks and uh... all that
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so the launch pad is unique. I've never seen anything like it in the.
SPEAKER_1:  prior history of spaceflight.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's a really simple launch stand. They basically have like this, it almost looks like a stool, like a milking a cow stool thing.
SPEAKER_1:  with a hope, a big giant.
SPEAKER_0:  you're from Iowa.
SPEAKER_1:  know what that stool looks like. We all been sitting on that stool milking cat.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, with the...
SPEAKER_1:  with a giant hole in the middle. And that hole in the middle of that stool is where the rocket sits. And it sits on these launch clamps.
SPEAKER_1:  And then next to it is the, so that's the Orbital Launch Mount, and then next to it there are the OLM, some people will say.
SPEAKER_1:  Next to it is the Orbital Launch Tower, the OLT.
SPEAKER_1:  And that is not only.
SPEAKER_1:  Integral to fueling up the upper stage and I had the upper stage has to have propellant lines run to it
SPEAKER_1:  so that they can fill it with propellant and all that.
SPEAKER_1:  but it also...
SPEAKER_1:  they ended up making it so instead of having a big crane on site to stack the two on top of each other they literally just use that tower
SPEAKER_1:  as a crane.
SPEAKER_1:  The crane has these giant arms, lovingly called the chopsticks, or the whole system can be called Mechazilla.
SPEAKER_1:  and that will grab onto first, it'll grab onto the booster.
SPEAKER_1:  pick it up off of its transporter that transports it from the production site.
SPEAKER_1:  lifts it up, puts it down onto the launch mount.
SPEAKER_1:  and then it will pick up the second stage of the upper stage starship
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  plop it down on top of the booster.
SPEAKER_1:  And they did that for the first time last year. Actually, I think it was like Valentine's last year, was the first time they used the chopsticks to stack it.
SPEAKER_1:  And now they're doing it.
SPEAKER_1:  quite frequently, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  But ultimately...
SPEAKER_1:  Those chopsticks have to serve a second purpose. They're actually going to utilize-
SPEAKER_1:  If you say, it's not so much they're going to catch the booster with these chopsticks, it's not like it's a dad trying to catch a falling child.
SPEAKER_1:  It's more that the booster and the starship will someday land.
SPEAKER_1:  on those arms.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  They're more or less stationary. I'm sure there's some bit of-
SPEAKER_1:  you know, adjustment of the arms will do, but more or less the rocket's going to propulsively land.
SPEAKER_1:  and get picked up by what's essentially too-
SPEAKER_1:  like relatively small ball joints.
SPEAKER_1:  that hold the entire thing.
SPEAKER_1:  It has to land.
SPEAKER_1:  very precisely on these these mounts.
SPEAKER_1:  then onto the launch mount. And that's what's going to just place it back onto the stand and allow it to be refueled. And that's what's going to just place it back onto the stand
SPEAKER_1:  Fly again.
SPEAKER_0:  What's the idea of using the arms versus having a launch pad to land?
SPEAKER_0:  What's the benefit?
SPEAKER_1:  you are basically removing the mass of what would be heavy landing legs and you're putting kind of that landing infrastructure onto a ground system. So you're not having to carry those landing legs into orbit.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's also elevated off the ground. Is there some aspect to that where you don't have to balance the thrust and all that?
SPEAKER_1:  You- you-
SPEAKER_1:  You can negate some of those like there's like plume plume interactions. There's like, you know, the exhaust hitting concrete and especially with a rocket this big it's gonna
SPEAKER_1:  You know, use like three Raptor engines firing, if you have them.
SPEAKER_1:  firing really close to the ground, you're just gonna absolutely destroy and crater the ground, and you're gonna have to refurbish the ground and the landing pad every time.
SPEAKER_1:  and you know, or have huge landing legs that are super long and tall.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, to make it so it's elevated enough to not do that.
SPEAKER_1:  So yeah, you're kind of, you're avoiding that.
SPEAKER_1:  whole mess by catching it high enough off the ground that you don't think.
SPEAKER_0:  factor that in. That's how many engines are involved in the landing.
SPEAKER_0:  part is the three-ruptor.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, we haven't actually, you know, we haven't to date seen...
SPEAKER_1:  the exact.
SPEAKER_1:  landing sequence. So it might be something like at first they might light up.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, seven or something or nine or something, some number,
SPEAKER_1:  accelerate quickly or decelerate quickly. Same thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  and then shut it down to three or something for a little bit more granular control.
SPEAKER_1:  Because unlike Falcon 9, Starship has enough engines and variability to actually, if it needed to hover.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, to maybe more precisely align itself with the pad.
SPEAKER_1:  it would have that capability.
SPEAKER_1:  and especially having multiple engines. You know, if you only have a single engine running.
SPEAKER_1:  You can't really roll.
SPEAKER_1:  You know your role access you can do pitch and yaw because the
SPEAKER_1:  The engine is kind of like a rudder. It can move in two axes.
SPEAKER_1:  so you can easily pitch and yaw the vehicle.
SPEAKER_1:  but to actually induce roll along its vertical axis.
SPEAKER_1:  You would either need auxiliary engines to roll it, or you'd need a pair of engines so they can...
SPEAKER_1:  Be opposed.
SPEAKER_1:  and induce role. So by having two or three running.
SPEAKER_1:  they have all three axes of control that they would need, kind of like a broomstick, you know, and
SPEAKER_1:  balancing a broomstick on your hand. They can just move it over and if they need to...
SPEAKER_1:  align it to those landing nubs, you know, on the landing arms and stuff like that, then.
SPEAKER_1:  They can do that.
SPEAKER_0:  Speaking of pitching yard, the thing.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... so starship flip says
SPEAKER_0:  bellyflops.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a interesting kind of
SPEAKER_0:  Maneuver.
SPEAKER_0:  on the way down to land. Can you describe that maneuver? What's involved?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so this is definitely a first. I don't think anything's tried landing like this before, but the idea is...
SPEAKER_1:  When you're falling through the atmosphere, the atmosphere could actually do a lot of work for you. You're moving quickly, something is falling from space.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a lot of energy involved.
SPEAKER_0:  You have a really good video on this as well.
SPEAKER_1:  And thank you.
SPEAKER_1:  the as it's falling, you know, you can let the, you want to let the atmosphere do as much work as it can.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  If you have a...
SPEAKER_1:  Unsymmetric, you know, it's not a ball that's falling. This is some kind of object with with shape
SPEAKER_1:  some, you know, and.
SPEAKER_1:  one face of it is going to have more surface area than the other face
SPEAKER_1:  So, you know, in the shape of like a cylinder.
SPEAKER_1:  If you're falling, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Like a soda can if you're falling.
SPEAKER_1:  top or bottom.
SPEAKER_1:  First, it's a certain amount of surface area.
SPEAKER_1:  If you flip that on its side, you actually have a lot more service area.
SPEAKER_1:  So with the same exact vehicle.
SPEAKER_1:  You can actually have a lot more drag. You can actually slow it down a lot more using the exact same like.
SPEAKER_1:  Same atmosphere, same...
SPEAKER_1:  Same vehicle.
SPEAKER_1:  just by turning it 90 degrees.
SPEAKER_1:  You can slow it down substantially like.
SPEAKER_1:  three or four times slower.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's energy that you don't have to use anywhere else. You don't have to use an engine to slow you down. You don't have to do anything else.
SPEAKER_1:  So SpaceX realized, okay, if we flip this thing on its side and let it fall.
SPEAKER_1:  Like a skydiver almost, you know, instead of like pencil diving into the pool, you're belly flopping.
SPEAKER_1:  you're maximizing the amount of surface area.
SPEAKER_1:  that's in the wind stream that's being slowed down.
SPEAKER_1:  But obviously like.
SPEAKER_1:  in order to land, especially if you're...
SPEAKER_1:  SpaceX and you know, Elon's obsessed with like not having
SPEAKER_1:  different parts, you know, he wants.
SPEAKER_1:  The best part is no part.
SPEAKER_1:  So if you're going to land with the engines...
SPEAKER_1:  You might as well use engines that you've already have the engines that are.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, used for the other portions of flight.
SPEAKER_1:  So you kick those on and you use those engines to actually turn it 90 degrees from belly flopping to feet first.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  That way you can use those same engines to land and you don't have to have auxiliary landing engines.
SPEAKER_1:  You don't have to have.
SPEAKER_1:  forces, you know, even if you were to land like on its belly with a separate set of engines, not only would those engines weigh a lot, you know, and be extra complexity, etc, etc.
SPEAKER_1:  but you also don't have to make the ship be able to handle.
SPEAKER_1:  landing, you know, like on its belly, as opposed to having the forces be vertical through it.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a giant thing. You have to...
SPEAKER_0:  Rotate in the air. Huge. As you also highlight, there's liquid fuel.
SPEAKER_0:  slushing around.
SPEAKER_0:  in the tank.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like you can't.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  I guess use that fuel directly after another kind of fuel. Like there's just complexities there. Yeah. They're involved. Uh, plus.
SPEAKER_0:  the actual maneuver.
SPEAKER_0:  It's difficult from the like, like what are the thrusters that actually make that?
SPEAKER_0:  make all that happen. You're adding a lot of-
SPEAKER_0:  complexity, not a lot, but you're.
SPEAKER_0:  complexity to the maneuver.
SPEAKER_0:  and possibility where failure could happen.
SPEAKER_0:  in order to sort of save.
SPEAKER_0:  in order for the air to do.
SPEAKER_0:  some of the work.
SPEAKER_0:  So what is some of that complexity? Just you can linger on it.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, if you think about what it's gonna take to go from.
SPEAKER_1:  horizontal to vertical.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  This rocket in particular, Starship has these big flaps.
SPEAKER_1:  So it has kind of two nose flaps and two.
SPEAKER_1:  rearward flaps.
SPEAKER_1:  The river flaps are a lot bigger because the majority of the mass, the engines and stuff are in the back of the vehicle. So in order to kind of be stable.
SPEAKER_1:  and they just fold themselves inwards, like on their dihedral angle.
SPEAKER_1:  at a dihedral angle in order to...
SPEAKER_1:  increase or decrease the drag. So you can control it.
SPEAKER_1:  All three axes of control while it's falling.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, on its belly, you can control it that way using these four different fins.
SPEAKER_1:  So you have these giant moving surfaces that take.
SPEAKER_1:  Thousands of horsepower is just insane amount of torque in order to move these quickly enough to be a valid control surface
SPEAKER_1:  So that's a huge complication, moving these fins and developing that landing algorithm and the control.
SPEAKER_1:  four of a huge vehicle with flaps going like, you know, in and out, in and out, in and out.
SPEAKER_1:  Stay stable.
SPEAKER_1:  Then, right as you light the engines...
SPEAKER_1:  Now all of a sudden you want the top.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you want to flip the rock at 90 degrees the rearward flaps, the bottom flaps.
SPEAKER_1:  They tuck all the way in to minimize drag.
SPEAKER_1:  That's gonna make it wanna swing down.
SPEAKER_1:  You extend the upper flaps, that makes it so the nose wants to pitch up.
SPEAKER_1:  You kick on the engines.
SPEAKER_1:  They're now lighting all three engines, at least as of the last successful attempts. They light all three of the sea level Raptor engines and they're pitched.
SPEAKER_1:  all the way like, you know, 10 or 15 degrees or whatever the maximum pitch is on them.
SPEAKER_1:  and that induces, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  It does that kick maneuver to kick it over from horizontal to vertical.
SPEAKER_1:  Now the problem is you lit your engines while you're horizontal.
SPEAKER_1:  So they.
SPEAKER_1:  put some horizontal velocity into the rocket. Push the rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, at the time the nose is at the time of lighting those engines, the nose is.
SPEAKER_1:  facing the horizon and the engines are facing.
SPEAKER_1:  The opposite horizon.
SPEAKER_1:  See now shot it a decent amount in.
SPEAKER_1:  and often, you know, the direction that you're not falling, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  So you have to factor that in.
SPEAKER_1:  to where you're landing, because you're gonna land on this precise, in this case you're gonna land on the inside the arm, the loving arms of the chopsticks, the Creed arms wide open.
SPEAKER_1:  You're gonna try to land inside the...
SPEAKER_0:  Exactly the song that you're playing through my head as I watch this now. Thank you. Thank you for forever joining those two. I appreciate this.
SPEAKER_1:  And you have to very precisely control. So what you have to do is now that it's done that kick, you also have to cancel out that horizontal.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's actually going to rotate beyond 90 degrees.
SPEAKER_1:  cancel out that horizontal velocity.
SPEAKER_1:  And then...
SPEAKER_1:  modulate the engines to make it so the thrust is perfect.
SPEAKER_1:  so that it can.
SPEAKER_1:  control itself into a control landing.
SPEAKER_1:  And all this is done in like...
SPEAKER_1:  500 meters, like 1500 feet.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you're doing all of those things.
SPEAKER_1:  stupidly close to the ground. It looks absurd. So far they've done five of these tests.
SPEAKER_1:  All the first four all.
SPEAKER_1:  blew up.
SPEAKER_1:  you know.
SPEAKER_1:  They're all coming in from about 10 kilometers or 33,000 feet.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  falling, flipping, you know, again, this thing is huge. That just the booster or just the upper stage of this.
SPEAKER_1:  is like 50 meters tall.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, so it's 150, it's like 45 meters, about 50 meters tall, about 165 feet tall.
SPEAKER_1:  Nine meters wide, so 30 feet wide. Hit ways, you know, something like.
SPEAKER_1:  God, I don't remember if it's something like 120 metric tons, so 120,000 kilograms.
SPEAKER_1:  quarter of a million pounds empty.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's doing this flip maneuver.
SPEAKER_1:  and it has to do all this.
SPEAKER_1:  Perfectly, so the first four attempts of this were...
SPEAKER_1:  Pretty spectacular failures. So just.
SPEAKER_0:  to clarify which stage is doing.
SPEAKER_1:  maneuver. It's the upper stage is doing this belly flop maneuver.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is the stage.
SPEAKER_0:  that would presumably
SPEAKER_0:  Um,
SPEAKER_0:  have humans on board if we were to use.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  if things continue to play. Now here's something I would love to see.
SPEAKER_1:  Just saying this. Grow nosy and just admit it, stuff's going to climb, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  If you already have these big arrow surfaces, the flaps.
SPEAKER_1:  They also have to move. They're on heavy motors and hinges and flaps and all that stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm actually surprised that for Earth...
SPEAKER_1:  They aren't just looking at landing it horizontally on a runway like space shuttle.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, that worked. The brawn did it.
SPEAKER_1:  the Soviet Union's Iran.
SPEAKER_1:  I rolled my art real hard there, sorry. Wow, wow. Really good.
SPEAKER_0:  Very impressed.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm very impressed. The brown did it. We have other space planes like the X-37B. We have the upcoming Sierra Nevada's Dream Chaser.
SPEAKER_1:  It's...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, you have some extra mass in the wings, but so does Starship. Starship has the extra mass of those flaps.
SPEAKER_1:  And you know, the, the.
SPEAKER_1:  the motors and the hinges and all that stuff. I-
SPEAKER_1:  I would like to see the trade on like, is it actually lighter weight?
SPEAKER_1:  to do that versus doing what SpaceX is doing.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean that's the funny thing. I think realistically if Elon walks in the door tomorrow and says
SPEAKER_1:  Guys, we did some simulations and actually it's like...
SPEAKER_1:  we can get another 5,000 kilograms into space if we just land at horizontal, if we kind of give up on our ego and land horizontally.
SPEAKER_1:  At least on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  then you know...
SPEAKER_1:  I think they could be doing that pretty quickly. Because that's the thing is-
SPEAKER_1:  uh... that's all that things been to land on mars and you know other planets and mars doesn't have a runway doesn't have
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, you know, thick enough atmosphere to utilize aerodynamic flight like that. So you have to do propulsive landing for Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  You're going to land on an unprepared surface, you know, so it has to be able to do this at some point.
SPEAKER_1:  The ultimate- it sounds ridiculous.
SPEAKER_1:  And it is.
SPEAKER_1:  but the ultimate goal of it is to land on Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  There's not much of an atmosphere to like.
SPEAKER_0:  to help you with the belly flop.
SPEAKER_1:  There's only 1% the atmosphere on Mars as there is on Earth, but you still want to utilize as much of that atmosphere as possible. So in the upper atmosphere it's still going to be...
SPEAKER_1:  coming in more or less.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of perpendicular to their stream. I guess it's probably more like.
SPEAKER_1:  Enough.
SPEAKER_1:  60 degrees, 70 degrees to the airstream, like where it's belly flopping.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's going to especially do that on Mars. It's going to need to use up as.
SPEAKER_1:  the little bit of atmosphere there is, you're coming in at insane velocities.
SPEAKER_1:  And so even that 1% thin atmosphere is still going to do a lot of work.
SPEAKER_1:  Now...
SPEAKER_1:  on mars that there's only thirty eight percent
SPEAKER_1:  of Earth's gravity on Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  the belly flop maneuvers a lot, it could be a lot more conservative. You could do that at like.
SPEAKER_1:  5,000 feet up.
SPEAKER_1:  And it just wouldn't matter as much because there's not as much.
SPEAKER_1:  gravity loss or gravity drag. So you can kind of just more slowly, gently.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you don't have to do this crazy extravagant like-
SPEAKER_1:  belly flop, you know, flip maneuver.
SPEAKER_1:  But it would still something at some point you would transition from more or less perpendicular to the airstream to you know a horizontal to
SPEAKER_1:  Landing vertically.
SPEAKER_0:  I like how we're having this old boring conversation about the differences of landing on Earth versus on Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, this is surreal.
SPEAKER_0:  that this is actually a real conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  that this is something that we're discussing.
SPEAKER_0:  because it has to do both.
SPEAKER_1:  But in my opinion, I think we'll pretty quickly see an evolution of Starship that's like...
SPEAKER_1:  dedicated versions for certain tasks.
SPEAKER_1:  And at the end of the day...
SPEAKER_1:  Again, if someone runs a simulation and says it's actually more efficient and...
SPEAKER_1:  It's better just to land horizontally on a runway.
SPEAKER_1:  then that's what's gonna happen.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it.
SPEAKER_1:  It doesn't matter, but...
SPEAKER_1:  they still will develop. If the ultimate goal is to land on Mars, then they'll have a dedicated.
SPEAKER_1:  Mars variant, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  which will likely look different then.
SPEAKER_1:  the earth variant, you know, and they'll still probably be launched on the same booster.
SPEAKER_1:  You know what I mean? Oh, you mean like that?
SPEAKER_0:  particular vehicle will not be returning back to Earth, it'll need to be modified.
SPEAKER_0:  Cause the ultimate is to have one starship that goes to Mars, lands on Mars and takes off of Mars.
SPEAKER_0:  lands back on earth and is reused again.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. Over and over and over. And there's a chance that you, you know, you have just a cycler, just a.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  If you're, at the end of the day, you're just really trying to see what is most feasible, what's the most-
SPEAKER_1:  Efficient. You literally have a vehicle dedicated to Mars. Mars is easy to do with single-stage orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a lot lower gravity, a lot thinner atmosphere.
SPEAKER_1:  You can easily do a single stage orbit. You get into orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  to a dedicated, you know, transfer vehicle that goes between Earth and Mars. It only stays in space. You don't have heat shields. You don't have landing legs. You don't have...
SPEAKER_1:  all these things that you need. And ideally it's nuclear powered, so it's super efficient.
SPEAKER_1:  That gets you back to Earth. Once you're at Earth, you rendezvous again with another landing starship.
SPEAKER_1:  And that starship might be horizontal.
SPEAKER_1:  Runway Starship, you know, like, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  There's no, I don't see the, and I think ultimately.
SPEAKER_1:  it'll win out where we don't have a one size fits all. I think that's.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the flaw of the space shuttle really is that it was trying to do everything.
SPEAKER_1:  and ended up kind of doing nothing well.
SPEAKER_1:  But that's, I think with SpaceX has proven, I mean, SpaceX already has variants coming. There's already going to be a dedicated lunar lander for NASA for the Artemis program.
SPEAKER_1:  There's already going to be.
SPEAKER_1:  a tanker variant. There's already going to be
SPEAKER_1:  likely just a pure cargo version. There's likely going to be a human version. We'll likely see evolutions of this thing happen.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, relatively quickly.
SPEAKER_0:  And once it's all working, it's only a matter of weeks before.
SPEAKER_0:  people riding on it will be complaining about the speed of the wifi.
SPEAKER_0:  Hehehehe
SPEAKER_0:  as the old like, uh, Lucy K joke with like...
SPEAKER_0:  where you're flying on a chair through the air.
SPEAKER_1:  It's incredible. You didn't even know this existed, and now you're complaining about it.
SPEAKER_1:  That's great. Exactly.
SPEAKER_0:  So you yeah, you tweeted fun fact about Starship
SPEAKER_0:  by doing the.
SPEAKER_0:  Flip around 500 meters versus higher up like two.
SPEAKER_0:  2000 meters the difference
SPEAKER_0:  in Delta V is.
SPEAKER_0:  500 meters per second.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a 20 ton fuel saving, which means basically 20 tons more you can put into orbit. That's more than Falcon 9 has ever launched.
SPEAKER_0:  just by flipping later.
SPEAKER_0:  That's really interesting. So that was the decision too, to flip close to the ground. Yeah...
SPEAKER_1:  The closer to the ground, the better. The more again, the more the atmosphere is doing work.
SPEAKER_1:  And, you know, we get into that video really dives into like gravity losses and gravity drag. The more time you're spent.
SPEAKER_1:  every second that your rocket engine is running.
SPEAKER_1:  Earth is stealing 9.8 meters per second of acceleration.
SPEAKER_1:  There's just inherently 9.8 meters per second squared of acceleration.
SPEAKER_1:  So every second that engine is running.
SPEAKER_1:  the first big majority of your thrust is actually being just stolen by Earth's gravity.
SPEAKER_1:  So if you're, the longer you're fighting that.
SPEAKER_1:  the more inefficient it is. So the best thing would be you flip.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, 100 meters off the ground, you light all your engines to maximum thrust and you pull 50 Gs, you know, you land on a dime basically.
SPEAKER_1:  Obviously there's no margin there.
SPEAKER_1:  And there's diminishing returns on that gravity loss thing in your high thrust weight ratios.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's a pretty good compromise. Yes, it looks scary, but they could be a lot more aggressive with that yet and squeeze out even a little bit better performance.
SPEAKER_1:  but there are diminishing returns. So that's kind of the magic number we've seen so far today.
SPEAKER_1:  but we'll likely see that.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, be played with.
SPEAKER_0:  You've attended some of these, what does it feel like to see Starship in person? First of all, when it's just sitting there stacked.
SPEAKER_0:  And second of all...
SPEAKER_0:  One is doing some of these tests, some of these maneuvers.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, first off, if you have the freedom of traveling and happen to live within a reasonable.
SPEAKER_1:  either by playing or.
SPEAKER_1:  car, it's worth going down to South Texas. So Starbase is right on the border of Mexico and the United States and very southern tip of Texas.
SPEAKER_1:  right along the Rio Grande.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's insane because it's right along a public highway.
SPEAKER_1:  You can literally anyone can drive down this assuming it's not closed for testing because they do close the highways
SPEAKER_1:  during the week a decent amount while they're doing tests.
SPEAKER_1:  but...
SPEAKER_1:  sans any of those days.
SPEAKER_1:  anyone can just drive down and see these things up close and personal with their own eyes. Like we're talking-
SPEAKER_1:  you know, from.
SPEAKER_1:  100, 200 meters away.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, so two football fields away from the world's biggest, most powerful rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  Imagine being able to do that.
SPEAKER_1:  during the Soviet Union and during the...
SPEAKER_1:  N1 and Saturn V, you know, I imagine it's been able to drive up right next to the launch pad.
SPEAKER_1:  There's no way.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, and so.
SPEAKER_1:  To have this kind of access to this program is so.
SPEAKER_1:  Incredible, the craziest thing is when you.
SPEAKER_1:  When you're driving out on Highway 4, it's...
SPEAKER_1:  bumpy. It's riddled with potholes now because of all the insane amount of trucks having to go out there and traffic and
SPEAKER_1:  You're going through this, it's just this weird, you're like, where am I? You occasionally are seeing, like you can kind of see that.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, you can see Mexico out your right window as you're driving down this highway, you know, you're just sitting there.
SPEAKER_1:  Where am I? So you kind of turn this corner.
SPEAKER_1:  and the trees and the brush kind of clear out and all of a sudden you get a sense of
SPEAKER_1:  everything on the horizon. At that point, you're pretty much five miles on the nose or eight kilometers away.
SPEAKER_1:  And from there, you can just see through the heat haze.
SPEAKER_1:  through the atmospheric distortion.
SPEAKER_1:  You just see this weird like.
SPEAKER_1:  It looks like a city almost on the horizon, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  tons of these tall buildings.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a weird ominous launch tower thing.
SPEAKER_1:  with arms wide open.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  sometimes, and, you know, a giant metal rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  And it just looks.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, it's...
SPEAKER_1:  The word surreal, I think by definition, I think a few.
SPEAKER_1:  are expecting it, it's not.
SPEAKER_1:  Surreal, I think surreal kind of means like unexpected surprise or whatever, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Even if you're expecting it, even if you've seen pictures, even if everything, it is surreal.
SPEAKER_1:  You stand there and you just go.
SPEAKER_0:  Why?
SPEAKER_0:  is this.
SPEAKER_0:  And also, I mean, there's a kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  magical aspect to the this is the place where over the next few years we'll start
SPEAKER_0:  as a human species reaching out there.
SPEAKER_0:  at traveling out there.
SPEAKER_1:  We'll for sure see the development of the rockets that I think will take us further than ever before.
SPEAKER_1:  be born right there.
SPEAKER_0:  What's it like to witness the actual testing of Starship?
SPEAKER_1:  So far it's been...
SPEAKER_1:  high stakes.
SPEAKER_1:  It's been insane because the first site I mentioned earlier, there's been S and 8, 9, 10, 11, and 15 that have all done these suborbital hops. The highest one went 12.5 kilometers and then...
SPEAKER_1:  The rest of the four went.
SPEAKER_1:  10 kilometers in altitude.
SPEAKER_1:  and then turned off the engines and just fell.
SPEAKER_1:  Now the cool thing about that is.
SPEAKER_1:  The general public could be about five miles away, so again, like eight kilometers away.
SPEAKER_1:  And the weird thing is this rocket's...
SPEAKER_1:  slowly accelerating.
SPEAKER_1:  They didn't want to exceed a certain speed, so they didn't have to worry about the aerodynamics of it. They just slowly climbed, and it probably also appeased the FAA. They're like, here, we'll just...
SPEAKER_1:  limit the thrust to weight ratio and just.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, make it so it's slow and controlled, no big deal.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's basically more or less like slightly above a hover, just climbing.
SPEAKER_1:  for minutes, for like four or five minutes, to hear.
SPEAKER_1:  and feel the roar of this thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Normal rockets like
SPEAKER_1:  After the first 30 seconds or minute.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, they're so far away.
SPEAKER_1:  that you're just diminishing, you know, it's just fading, fading, fading, fading. You still get that rumble, that sense, but those first five flights, the suborbital hops were.
SPEAKER_1:  Just I'll cherish them forever because you just you're watching this thing.
SPEAKER_1:  that you've driven up next to.
SPEAKER_1:  You've seen it with your own eyes. That's bigger than most buildings in a, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  fairly dense urban area.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's this massive thing.
SPEAKER_1:  You stand there, you stood there, you look at it, you're like, wow, that's crazy. You've seen people working on it, they're little ants compared to it.
SPEAKER_1:  Then you drive away and you see it on the horizon and all of a sudden that thing leaves. It starts moving.
SPEAKER_0:  hovering.
SPEAKER_0:  hovering essentially
SPEAKER_1:  And the first time, I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you put for me at least I put my hands on my head when I just I can't help it. I'm not it's not so I don't know. It's surreal. Like you said.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know what in human nature decides this is what to do when you can't believe something but that's what happens.
SPEAKER_1:  And when that thing first took off, it was just like.
SPEAKER_1:  My brain couldn't process.
SPEAKER_1:  seeing, you know, because I had spent.
SPEAKER_1:  so much time driving around and seeing it and all of a sudden you're watching it just take off and you're like
SPEAKER_1:  moving and all these you know most complicated rocket engines ever made are all firing simultaneously
SPEAKER_1:  and it didn't blow up on the launch pad slowly increasing
SPEAKER_1:  And it's just crazy and the sound that.
SPEAKER_1:  everything about it. And so by the time
SPEAKER_1:  The first one specifically is December.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  20.
SPEAKER_1:  was the first.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, SN8.
SPEAKER_1:  It
SPEAKER_1:  went up and I actually, we all lost it in the sky. We couldn't.
SPEAKER_1:  quite see it but our we had telescopes and
SPEAKER_1:  you know, high telephoto lenses tracking it.
SPEAKER_1:  And what's funny is there's a pretty strong wind up there at altitude.
SPEAKER_1:  And it was moving, there's a lot of.
SPEAKER_1:  gaseous oxygen being vented out of the rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's being blown by this air.
SPEAKER_1:  So it looks like it's moving actually quite quickly.
SPEAKER_1:  Away from us like a strafing to one side.
SPEAKER_1:  So I'm watching the monitor, I'm going, Oh my God, they're moving it like.
SPEAKER_1:  over Brownsville and we're all, all of us, everyone on this, this hotel balcony is looking out down like way out over, you know, and we can't find it. We're like.
SPEAKER_1:  they lose it like we're thinking like, oh my God, this is going to crash down in Brownsville.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  And finally they shut the engines off and we're watching it fall. And again, we're tracking it. No, it's falling.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's falling, falling, falling, it's falling, super controlled and we're like, Oh my God, this is perfect.
SPEAKER_1:  and all of a sudden it clicked and I see it.
SPEAKER_1:  with my eyes, I finally like tracking it. It's straight out.
SPEAKER_1:  like straight in front of us and it.
SPEAKER_1:  It looks like it was a blimp, just barely moving.
SPEAKER_1:  No, because it is falling slowly thanks to.
SPEAKER_1:  all of its drag.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Again, that's one of those moments I'm like.
SPEAKER_1:  It's falling so slow, you know, because it's so big, it's so massive, it's falling sideways.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I've seen Falcon 9 boosters and Falcon heavy boosters and they scream. And they come in so fast.
SPEAKER_1:  And you can barely even see them. You can just barely track them and all of a sudden they light their engines and they decelerate so quickly. This was like the opposite. There's like.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that thing ever coming down? It was just falling so slowly and so right there. It just felt like it was so close.
SPEAKER_1:  And so when it finally lit its engine and it flipped, I was losing my mind because I'm like, it's working. You know, this crazy plan, this.
SPEAKER_1:  The huge massive thing is doing this absurd feat.
SPEAKER_1:  And the first one, well, the first four again, didn't work out as planned, but.
SPEAKER_1:  Getting to that point already, getting to that flip maneuver was a huge milestone and it was so exciting just going through those
SPEAKER_1:  Those firsts were amazing and I think.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, we're coming up now on them doing the full stacks of the booster and the upper stage.
SPEAKER_1:  I think when we see that fly, when that leaves...
SPEAKER_1:  Earth for the first time.
SPEAKER_1:  It'll be like I said, almost twice the amount of thrust as anything else. It'll be the biggest, heaviest.
SPEAKER_1:  Largest thing to ever fly.
SPEAKER_1:  It's going to shake.
SPEAKER_1:  Everything.
SPEAKER_1:  Bye.
SPEAKER_1:  can't.
SPEAKER_1:  Wait.
SPEAKER_0:  have all 33 Raptor engines.
SPEAKER_0:  I've been active at once. Have they tested that?
SPEAKER_1:  No, that's coming up. That's kind of the next milestone. I don't know when this will come out, but we're...
SPEAKER_1:  That's like-
SPEAKER_0:  the next. Just a few days very quickly here. Then.
SPEAKER_1:  But if people listening to this, if they're listening to it early on, they'll likely be able to catch, you know, I think at this point, it seems like next week.
SPEAKER_1:  So step one would be step.
SPEAKER_0:  Click fire!
SPEAKER_1:  holding onto the rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  and lighting up the engines.
SPEAKER_1:  And so, so far they've lit at most. They kind of, they went for like a...
SPEAKER_1:  More than 14 engines static fired. I don't recall if it was like.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, 16 or something engines lit at once and they...
SPEAKER_1:  ended up going down to 14 engines.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the most.
SPEAKER_1:  engines they've ever lit.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  So the next step and the final kind of step before they fly this thing is they're actually gonna light all 33 engines simultaneously.
SPEAKER_1:  And although that sounds scary, let's not forget the Falcon Heavy that's now flown five times completely flawlessly.
SPEAKER_1:  has has 27 engines running simultaneously.
SPEAKER_1:  So they definitely have, you know, SpaceX has experience with high number of engines running.
SPEAKER_1:  at the same time, but it is still like, this is going to be.
SPEAKER_1:  a lot of moving parts and a lot of potential and a lot just a lot of everything.
SPEAKER_0:  What are the upcoming?
SPEAKER_0:  milestones, expected milestones.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think there's one in particular I'd like to talk to you more about, but leading up to that.
SPEAKER_0:  of course, is like, what are some of the tests here on the way?
SPEAKER_0:  So is this the static fire?
SPEAKER_0:  Wow.
SPEAKER_0:  the fully stack with the two stages.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll-
SPEAKER_0:  Will there be?
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  and then all that leading to an orbital.
SPEAKER_0:  Launch.
SPEAKER_0:  test.
SPEAKER_0:  What so what are the things which nobody and what do you think?
SPEAKER_0:  Like what do you think the timeline will be after you take the orbital test?
SPEAKER_1:  Timeline.
SPEAKER_1:  The reason we have this website, The Expected Milestones, is because I always tell people to ignore any time you ever hear for any of this stuff. Just pay attention to milestones because...
SPEAKER_1:  When you're doing stuff for the first time, you know, you just have no idea.
SPEAKER_0:  Just to understand the expected milestones here, the first column is the event.
SPEAKER_0:  the second column is the date and status TBD complete. green mean
SPEAKER_1:  What?
SPEAKER_1:  Green means it's been completed and it shows the completion date.
SPEAKER_0:  and the completion date and then the others.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe more, maybe not for the full stack testing, the D stack and the 33 engine.
SPEAKER_1:  So, so realistically we're expecting them to destack and SpaceX, I think just tweeted that actually they're going to be destacking.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, the second stage from the first stage, kind of get the ship safe while they test because they don't want to.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, 33 engines is pretty high risk if they...
SPEAKER_1:  blow up the rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  When they test it for the first time, it's not going to be fully fueled. I don't think at least, but there is a limit to how-
SPEAKER_1:  They do have to have it weighed down enough that the launch clamps can hold onto it. Because if you think about it like...
SPEAKER_1:  Normally the launch clamps are holding onto an entire rocket Wayne.
SPEAKER_1:  Five million.
SPEAKER_1:  kilograms?
SPEAKER_1:  Five million, you know, it's weighing an insane amount. So those clamps don't actually have to hold.
SPEAKER_1:  75 mega Newtons of thrust, they really want to have to hold on 25 mega Newtons of thrust.
SPEAKER_1:  You know what I mean, they're not.
SPEAKER_1:  designed to hold down all 75.
SPEAKER_1:  They do have to have enough weight on the rocket. So even when they do the testing of the 33 engines...
SPEAKER_1:  have to have enough propellant in there that they don't exceed the clamping and the holding force of the stand otherwise it'll
SPEAKER_1:  break free from the launch stand and that booster will go flying off uncontrolled.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a difficult thing to figure out in the test.
SPEAKER_0:  Come Eve.
SPEAKER_0:  simultaneous things you test.
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_1:  So they're kind of mitigating risks, which is why like they're destacking, they don't wanna have, although the ship could be on top of it to help weigh it down and simulate the launch environment better.
SPEAKER_1:  At some point that's a risk they're just going to take when they go for launch. And so for now they're taking the ship off in case something goes wrong during the 33 engine test.
SPEAKER_1:  And then once we see if the 33 engine test goes well, hopefully we see the second stage get stacked back on it.
SPEAKER_1:  We'll see them get closer, like closing out all the items and hope the big one too is the FAA launch license.
SPEAKER_1:  There that's a little be publicly filed will see that.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, in the system.
SPEAKER_1:  having a launch license and
SPEAKER_1:  I have no sense of that type of thing.
SPEAKER_1:  outside of, but that is a big milestone, and it might be something that could potentially hinder.
SPEAKER_1:  hold up the launch date, we'll just be waiting for a launch license.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I'm sure there's a lot of fascinating bureaucracy in politics and, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  legal stuff and all that kind of beautiful magical thing when you live in reality. Because it is, I mean it is a big...
SPEAKER_0:  Uhhhhhh
SPEAKER_0:  Rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, and the biggest thing is not so much the F.A. doesn't necessarily care about the success of the rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  They didn't really just care about the safety of public and public property.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's a matter of being convinced and having the data to prove, okay.
SPEAKER_1:  If this thing.
SPEAKER_1:  blows up, we have a control of how and when it blows up, we have control of.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, X, Y, and Z, here's the potential damage, here's the blast radius.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, this again is.
SPEAKER_1:  over twice as
SPEAKER_1:  powerful and twice as much potential.
SPEAKER_1:  Actually, it's a lot more potential.
SPEAKER_1:  for an explosive energy.
SPEAKER_1:  if it, you know, if it happened to.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, let me walk back a little bit because in order to have a real detonation, you have to have a perfect mixture ratio of your fuel and oxidizer.
SPEAKER_1:  If when a rocket blows up, typically, you know, it kind of unzips and some of the fuel will mix into some of the oxidizer and you could have some explosive energy, but a lot of it's actually just a deflagration. It's just, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  flames and
SPEAKER_1:  There will, there would be explosive energy, but it's not like you're lighting all of it simultaneously because it's a giant bomb.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just really not so.
SPEAKER_1:  That's good, but at the same time, even in those circumstances.
SPEAKER_1:  The amount of energy is still absurd, enough to likely blow out windows, you know, for-
SPEAKER_1:  miles and miles and miles.
SPEAKER_1:  including my studio space.
SPEAKER_1:  Ah, well...
SPEAKER_0:  If the cameras hold up...
SPEAKER_0:  that that will be one heck of a show
SPEAKER_0:  uh... hopefully of course would not uh... would not happen so how does that take us to an uh... orbital launch when do you think that would happen?
SPEAKER_1:  In my opinion.
SPEAKER_1:  This is a very fluid and this will change literally by the hour.
SPEAKER_0:  really think that it's very difficult to really say like even even for something that could very well happen this year even just a few months away
SPEAKER_0:  uh... you can make a prediction
SPEAKER_0:  By the way, are you superstitious on this kind of stuff a little bit? Like you don't you're worried about jinxing it and that kind of stuff?
SPEAKER_1:  I wouldn't
SPEAKER_0:  you would be like waiting.
SPEAKER_0:  for all of these launches that keep getting delayed where you start thinking that there's certain things you do will postponed.
SPEAKER_1:  control the weather. My socks.
SPEAKER_1:  Why am I wearing these socks just scrubbed again? You know, like, yeah. You're lucky you have
SPEAKER_0:  You don't have to wear the same lucky socks, otherwise there's going to be bad weather. Get yourself a
SPEAKER_1:  So the reason that I say this and why it's so difficult is they did a first full stack test in July of 2021.
SPEAKER_1:  And the expectation was we're a month or two away.
SPEAKER_1:  launch.
SPEAKER_1:  So like realistically for 18 months have been in a purgatory thinking that we're a month or two away of an orbital launch.
SPEAKER_1:  Now I did say for the record.
SPEAKER_1:  when that thing stacked and when a lot of speculation was saying, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  a month or two I was saying I don't expect it to fly in 2021.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, and I've been.
SPEAKER_1:  Just say, I just saw the amount of work that still needed to be done. Like on the ground systems, the tanks, the launch mount, all the stuff. So they're like, they're still.
SPEAKER_1:  They're going to have to validate it. They're going to have to test everything.
SPEAKER_1:  every component and you know, people were like.
SPEAKER_1:  How dare you say that even Gwen Shotwell, the president of SpaceX, is saying Q3 of 2021.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, but like...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm just, I'm not gonna be surprised if it slips into 2022.
SPEAKER_1:  And here we are at the beginning of 2023. And I-
SPEAKER_1:  I think we're finally within like two months.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm expecting, like I'm trying to keep my March and April as free as I can.
SPEAKER_1:  We'll put it that way.
SPEAKER_0:  I love it. Actually just in a small tangent on going shower, like what do you, uh,
SPEAKER_0:  from everything I know she's an instrumental a really crucial person to the success of SpaceX and running the show she's the president the COO
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  What do you know about her that...
SPEAKER_0:  sort of
SPEAKER_0:  the genius of Gwen Shotwell.
SPEAKER_1:  Man, my understanding is she's really the glue.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, she's the glue to the tornado. Tornado comes in.
SPEAKER_1:  And then she comes around and just really executes on, and helps.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, a famous story is that.
SPEAKER_1:  At some point, Elan walked in, or she sprinted into a meeting because Elan was actively trying to cancel Falcon Heavy.
SPEAKER_1:  saying it's too far, like it's.
SPEAKER_1:  much development is still too far away and this is like
SPEAKER_1:  this might have been like end of 2017 or something and it flew for the first time in 2018. So we're talking like it's close to the end of development.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there's hardware being built, all this stuff, and Elon's Lego looked like slot cr Messiah. Pretty good, man.
SPEAKER_1:  literally in a meeting telling people they're going to cancel it and we're going to move on to BFR.
SPEAKER_1:  We're now Starship.
SPEAKER_1:  and just go full steam ahead on that.
SPEAKER_1:  And she runs into the meeting and reminds Elon, we have X amount of customers.
SPEAKER_1:  have already purchased a ride on Falcon Heavy.
SPEAKER_1:  We can't delay that.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, so it's that.
SPEAKER_1:  business sense of like, yes, it's great to innovate, but we also have to pay our dues and make the money to continue our operations. And I think she's just a lot better at.
SPEAKER_1:  She has, I think she has such a great.
SPEAKER_1:  perspective on everything. It really seems like everything.
SPEAKER_1:  She doesn't, I wish she did more interviews because I would love to hear more from her.
SPEAKER_1:  but
SPEAKER_0:  Man, like it just seems. Hear that Gwen? For both of us. Yeah, she hasn't actually done them in the interviews, right?
SPEAKER_1:  Not really, no, she's done like a TED talk, a couple of little things here and there, but not really.
SPEAKER_1:  Many interviews and I would just love to hear like what, you know, what on a daily basis, like what is she doing that to keep.
SPEAKER_1:  her head on and keep everything so organized. You know it's-
SPEAKER_1:  You know, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  My understanding is that she is absolutely integral and does just an insane amount of work at SpaceX.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, so it's the project planning, but also the
SPEAKER_0:  how the teams integrate together and the...
SPEAKER_0:  and the hiring and this is the man.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's a lot of it is honestly even just the business making sure the money's flowing
SPEAKER_1:  in a positive trend, more or less.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, Elon's obviously a money guy, but he thinks...
SPEAKER_1:  He's so, I think Elon is so risky. He just loves to throw it all in.
SPEAKER_1:  he leaves little margin for error, you know, he's...
SPEAKER_1:  Been really lucky with rolling his dice, especially like when he-
SPEAKER_1:  started SpaceX and Tesla.
SPEAKER_1:  That was the ultimate roll of the dice, but...
SPEAKER_1:  I think she's a healthy balance to be like, well, here's our-
SPEAKER_1:  Operations and how we can continue to do this without risking everything, you know and Starships clothes. Let me
SPEAKER_1:  Be clear.
SPEAKER_1:  Starship is close to-
SPEAKER_1:  risking everything already. It's just such a big.
SPEAKER_1:  Fast moving.
SPEAKER_1:  high-risk developmental program that like.
SPEAKER_1:  I personally think SpaceX would probably be fine if they shut the doors on Starship and just flew Falcon 9 and Falcon Heavy for the next 10 years, they would still be commercially valid. They could not.
SPEAKER_1:  spend another dollar on research and development. They could fire, I don't want them to, fire everyone involved in anything research and development and just ran operations on Falcon 9 and Falcon Heavy and they would still be dominant for 10 years.
SPEAKER_1:  and they would still have a business case and they'd still be fine.
SPEAKER_1:  But.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  They're all in, like all chips are pretty much, as many chips as possible are in.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  What else?
SPEAKER_0:  I could say is there's not, I've talked to a lot of.
SPEAKER_0:  great leaders.
SPEAKER_0:  There's just not many people like Elon that would push for Starship.
SPEAKER_0:  When they're already.
SPEAKER_0:  We're already a very successful company.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... sort of
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone doubted that it could be a successful company. It was so close to bankruptcy and failing.
SPEAKER_0:  and then to take it into a financially viable, successful company.
SPEAKER_0:  And just when you do.
SPEAKER_0:  You take on a project that again risks everything.
SPEAKER_1:  when he already did this with Falcon 1 to Falcon 9. Like literally people were like, what are you doing?
SPEAKER_1:  They basically signed over and were fully ramping up Falcon 9.
SPEAKER_1:  by the time they finally had their first Falcon 1.
SPEAKER_1:  success they had one more flight they only flew
SPEAKER_1:  Fucking one successfully twice, they flew five times all together, the fourth one was successful, and they flew one more time.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Anyone else out there would have been like, let's keep flying the Falcon one. We have a working rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  We can start.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, making money and profiting.
SPEAKER_1:  And already.
SPEAKER_1:  He was risking it all and saying, nope, we're going.
SPEAKER_1:  From Falcon 1 to Falcon 9 it was A.
SPEAKER_1:  Huge.
SPEAKER_1:  Huge leap.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I think it's at least as big as a leap from Falcon 1 to 9 as it is from Falcon 9 to Starship or one
SPEAKER_1:  relatively similarly.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's just that same thing again. People are going, why are you leaping into this?
SPEAKER_1:  insane program and system.
SPEAKER_1:  and risk.
SPEAKER_1:  when you have such a, you know, you finally have this.
SPEAKER_1:  workhorse of a rocket that's so dominant in the industry.
SPEAKER_1:  Yet they're going.
SPEAKER_1:  10x, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  It so happens.
SPEAKER_0:  You've been selected for the Dear Moon mission that will fly Starship.
SPEAKER_0:  Once around the moon with nine people on board.
SPEAKER_0:  You are one of those people.
SPEAKER_0:  Just pause to take that in.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything that we've been talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  you will not just be reporting on, you will be a
SPEAKER_0:  part of it.
SPEAKER_0:  So tell me about the objective of this mission.
SPEAKER_0:  and how does it feel to be a part of it?
SPEAKER_0:  Well...
SPEAKER_0:  Thanks for watching. Thanks for watching.
SPEAKER_0:  Man.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's.
SPEAKER_1:  Basically...
SPEAKER_1:  It's the Willy Wonka of space.
SPEAKER_1:  A generous individual.
SPEAKER_1:  purchased a ride from SpaceX as early as-
SPEAKER_1:  At least as far as I know, the earliest I knew about it was February 27th, 2017. I was the individual.
SPEAKER_1:  Yusaku Maezawa, but at the time, I'm telling a story, at the time we didn't know. Okay, great. So February 27th, 2017, a press release comes out from SpaceX saying...
SPEAKER_1:  Someone.
SPEAKER_1:  purchased a ride.
SPEAKER_1:  through us around the moon.
SPEAKER_1:  We're gonna fly someone around the moon and at the time it was on a Crew Dragon capsule and a Falcon Heavy.
SPEAKER_1:  Wow, and that was enough.
SPEAKER_1:  That little moment right there, that press release.
SPEAKER_1:  The first time I'm like, I'm going to make a YouTube video about this. I stood up.
SPEAKER_1:  turn on my camera, put on my, at the time, spacesuit, and I basically yelled at the camera for.
SPEAKER_1:  three minutes about someone's going around the moon, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Fast forward to 2018.
SPEAKER_1:  end of 2018 and near the end they
SPEAKER_1:  Introduced there's a SpaceX press conference. Hi, I'm way back in Augsburg right now.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm there as a member of the press.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm reporting on we're going to meet this person that's going around the moon.
SPEAKER_1:  and come to find out, boom, they're going to be riding on Starship now. They change from Falcon, Heavy, and Dragon.
SPEAKER_1:  SpaceX is no longer going to do that. They're going to upgrade them basically to Starship. So instead of being in like a.
SPEAKER_1:  Small tin can there in this giant luxurious.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, Mega Rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  around the moon.
SPEAKER_1:  And it comes out that this individual named Yusaku Maezawa, who is a Japanese billionaire.
SPEAKER_1:  I purchased
SPEAKER_1:  this ride and instead of inviting his friends and colleagues and whatever, whoever his family members or whatever
SPEAKER_1:  He decided the most impactful thing he could do with this opportunity.
SPEAKER_1:  is invite.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm more or less artists in the original thing is like artists you know journalists a painter.
SPEAKER_1:  athlete, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  all of the, you know, photographer, videographer, you know, all walks of life.
SPEAKER_0:  When they said athlete they thought of you
SPEAKER_0:  They're like...
SPEAKER_0:  I know a guy.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for watching!
SPEAKER_1:  This guy rode rag by once.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  But uh...
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  And at the time, you know, I was like, this is crazy.
SPEAKER_1:  I can't believe this is gonna happen. And you know, he had this vision of, we're gonna find people from all around the world. I'm going to invite people from all around the world.
SPEAKER_1:  from different walks of life, different trades.
SPEAKER_1:  And I'm going to share this experience so that they can share it with the world.
SPEAKER_1:  and really have an impact much greater than, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  any one country or any one individual or any.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, set of military trained, you know, astronauts.
SPEAKER_1:  could do. I'll offer up a new perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  Beautiful. I literally, I mean, at the press conference, I cried. Like I had a couple tears in my eyes. Like this is.
SPEAKER_0:  We could just pause on that. So he goes by MZ.
SPEAKER_0:  MZ app.
SPEAKER_0:  How incredible is that?
SPEAKER_0:  It's...
SPEAKER_0:  I'd like, uh, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  You often don't realize the importance of individuals.
SPEAKER_0:  in human history, like they define it because this could be, we talked about the importance of Elon and
SPEAKER_0:  You know, most of the work is done by large groups of people that are collective intelligence that we band together But like these individuals can...
SPEAKER_0:  be the spark.
SPEAKER_0:  of.
SPEAKER_0:  the catalyst of that progress. And I mean, just this idea.
SPEAKER_0:  of getting.
SPEAKER_0:  not just civilians, which is already incredible, but civilians with a sort of an artistic flame that burns inside them, they're able to communicate.
SPEAKER_0:  whatever they do, are able to communicate something about that experience.
SPEAKER_0:  It's just a genius idea.
SPEAKER_0:  did spend quite probably a very large amount of money.
SPEAKER_0:  Look at that.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's, and that will be part of history. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's easy these days for people to be cynical, you know, especially about like
SPEAKER_1:  spaceflight and
SPEAKER_1:  wealthy individuals.
SPEAKER_1:  But really, in my opinion, and maybe just the time.
SPEAKER_1:  I just so couldn't believe this idea.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I'm someone that has studied a lot about.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, the Apollo program, the people that have been to the moon and they're
SPEAKER_1:  Incredible individuals, incredible individuals, but they're so saturated with tasks.
SPEAKER_1:  and they're military trained and often.
SPEAKER_1:  that they didn't really have the luxury of just being able to soak in the experience.
SPEAKER_1:  of.
SPEAKER_1:  going around or to the moon.
SPEAKER_1:  and seeing the moon up close with your own eyes.
SPEAKER_1:  just psychologically has to be.
SPEAKER_1:  Insane.
SPEAKER_1:  And so to have this opportunity.
SPEAKER_1:  be able to observe.
SPEAKER_1:  our closest celestial neighbor.
SPEAKER_1:  with your own eyes and your sole purpose is to soak it in and share it and communicate and create.
SPEAKER_1:  with the rest of our planet, like that to me is just.
SPEAKER_1:  beautiful.
SPEAKER_0:  So that is the objective of the mission.
SPEAKER_1:  That right there is the objective of the mission.
SPEAKER_0:  And how does it feel to be selected?
SPEAKER_0:  as one of the nine to do it.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a gradient. It's slowly.
SPEAKER_1:  It's doing a few things.
SPEAKER_1:  since I've known it's become.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  I think the closer it gets, the more excited and the more nervous I get.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's a more real it becomes the more real it becomes. You know, the announcement was a big, uh, it just got announced at the end of 2022 publicly.
SPEAKER_1:  who's involved and so
SPEAKER_1:  Prior to that, like, I had, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Each step of the selection process, you know, there's a pretty comprehensive.
SPEAKER_1:  selection process with interviews and stuff. Each step I'd-
SPEAKER_1:  Try not to get my hopes up and frankly like this.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me be clear, this was not something that I've always wanted to do.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's not like I'm out there. I didn't start doing YouTube videos because I wanted to even go to space. I did none of that.
SPEAKER_1:  And I've said, hilariously, I've probably said.
SPEAKER_1:  dozens or hundreds of times on air.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I don't ever want to go to space because it's not like my, it's not a driving force. It's not really a thing I even really truly pictured.
SPEAKER_1:  or let myself fantasize about, frankly.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  Each step of the selection process, I didn't really let myself.
SPEAKER_1:  dream about it too much or you know.
SPEAKER_1:  but it would kind of chip away, like, oh my God, this is actually becoming more real.
SPEAKER_1:  It's actually more and more of an opportunity and I'm.
SPEAKER_1:  equally more nervous too. Like, you know, frankly, it is.
SPEAKER_1:  It's, I've seen space flight.
SPEAKER_1:  stuff, go wrong, I've, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  I think about this stuff a lot, so like.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I get more nervous, but I also get more excited about that opportunity. Like it's an opportunity that how can you pass.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's still, I still have to actually stop pause think.
SPEAKER_1:  And actually.
SPEAKER_1:  realize the reality that.
SPEAKER_1:  that I am going to the moon. I'm going to see the moon up close.
SPEAKER_1:  Flying around the moon, I'm sorry, some people get mad when I say going to the moon since I'm not landing on it.
SPEAKER_1:  but flying around the moon seeing the far side of the moon with my own eyes.
SPEAKER_1:  and seeing earth.
SPEAKER_1:  and seeing the Earth rise behind it.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I can't tell you what it's going to be like and feel like. So epic. But it's insane to me that we're having this conversation that that is my reality.
SPEAKER_1:  and that someone was generous enough to...
SPEAKER_1:  consider the option of sharing this with.
SPEAKER_1:  frankly strangers.
SPEAKER_1:  And the process that they had for selecting like how.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  how much thought and time went into the selection process which was incredible
SPEAKER_1:  You know, they did a public call at the beginning of 2020.
SPEAKER_1:  And so the teams involved in.
SPEAKER_1:  in whittling it down from a million applicants. There's a million applicants that whittled it, and they got it down to eight crew members and two backups.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  amazing people. I would have, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know how they wound up where they did, but it's incredible. I feel a very deep connection to everyone that's already involved in.
SPEAKER_0:  What can you say about the crew? You've gotten a chance to meet them and talk to them. And Steve Ioki is on the crew. For this video, please go ahead and subscribe, a lot of fun.
SPEAKER_0:  Who else is there?
SPEAKER_0:  So you're obviously the star, Athne, who else in terms of the artists that are there.
SPEAKER_1:  So, oh man, we might just want to pull up just so I don't totally butcher and forget anybody, but because so far I haven't actually had the chance to meet everyone in person. You know, so far a lot of this was done during the pandemic.
SPEAKER_1:  but we've met through a couple different things. We've had a couple different...
SPEAKER_1:  times to get together, but so far I've not met dev
SPEAKER_1:  or top.
SPEAKER_1:  We've been on calls and stuff. I also have not yet met Dev Joshi.
SPEAKER_1:  who is an actor from India. So yeah, we can get Steve Aoki, American DJ and producer and musician.
SPEAKER_1:  top.
SPEAKER_1:  from South Korea is also.
SPEAKER_1:  a musician and a producer.
SPEAKER_0:  This is all across the world, it's like truly global.
SPEAKER_0:  all different kinds of walks of life, all artists of different forms.
SPEAKER_1:  And Steve is Japanese.
SPEAKER_1:  His parents are Japanese, but he, you know, lip-
SPEAKER_1:  born, raised in the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  Yemi is a dancer and choreographer.
SPEAKER_1:  from the Czech Republic.
SPEAKER_1:  Rhiannon is a fine art photographer from, well, England and Ireland. I guess she lived in both and kind of a bit of a.
SPEAKER_1:  She's all over the place.
SPEAKER_1:  Technically she's Irish, I guess.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh
SPEAKER_1:  I Tim Dodd, yep, that's me from the United States. Uh, then you have Kareem who is from England and does.
SPEAKER_1:  Also is a photographer and documentarian, does a lot of work with.
SPEAKER_1:  oceanography and volcanoes.
SPEAKER_1:  So he does really incredible work.
SPEAKER_1:  Brendan Hall is a documentarian.
SPEAKER_1:  and filmmaker.
SPEAKER_1:  Deb Joshi, sorry, Brendan is also from the United States.
SPEAKER_1:  Dev Joshi is an Indian actor.
SPEAKER_1:  I believe he's also already been producing and things. He's very young. I think he's only like.
SPEAKER_1:  19 or 20 and he's, I mean, he's been acting since he was like.
SPEAKER_1:  five years old or something. He's a Bollywood star, like he is a star in India, which is really cool. All right.
SPEAKER_1:  Caitlin Farrington from the United States is an Olympic.
SPEAKER_1:  gold medalist.
SPEAKER_1:  No border.
SPEAKER_1:  So she...
SPEAKER_1:  Believe it or not, is the athlete not me.
SPEAKER_1:  And then, and she's one of the backup crew members, as so is Miyu from Japan, who's a dancer.
SPEAKER_0:  That's amazing. I mean, it's such an interesting group. I mean, is there something else you could say about MZ?
SPEAKER_0:  about your soccer matchup.
SPEAKER_1:  Yusaku Maezawa. So he's also a musician.
SPEAKER_1:  So he was actually in like some.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of punk hardcore Japanese bands in the early, in the nineties and stuff in early two thousands.
SPEAKER_1:  He started a.
SPEAKER_1:  record company and
SPEAKER_1:  and distribution and sales.
SPEAKER_1:  ended up in fashion.
SPEAKER_1:  And
SPEAKER_1:  owns one of the biggest fashion companies in Japan.
SPEAKER_1:  and has become a fine art collector and just kind of a philanthropist.
SPEAKER_0:  and he's been out
SPEAKER_1:  He's already not only been to space, like, you know, he's been...
SPEAKER_1:  to the International Space Station. He's been on orbit and on the ISS.
SPEAKER_1:  So he, what's cool is like.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there's talks of.
SPEAKER_1:  when there's frankly to be to be honest, like we still don't, I still don't know all of the details about this. You know, we're.
SPEAKER_1:  Not yet into training.
SPEAKER_1:  I kind of always assumed prior that there'd be some professional astronaut, you know, when they talked about in 2018, there's talks of we'll have a professional astronaut on board.
SPEAKER_1:  Realistically now, like, MZ is.
SPEAKER_1:  a trained astronaut, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  He has trained a lot, like six months, you know, plus.
SPEAKER_1:  to be able to fly on Soyuz.
SPEAKER_1:  So as far as like, it's good to know for me that I have someone.
SPEAKER_1:  on the crew that has experience with space flight.
SPEAKER_1:  has trained and has some knowledge on spaceflight as well. That is an important aspect for sure.
SPEAKER_0:  So you made an excellent video about flying in a fighter jet.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... that i think you mentioned maybe relevant
SPEAKER_0:  to the training.
SPEAKER_0:  Is there some high level aspects to training that you anticipate that you may be able to speak to?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so, you know, so far I think we can really lean on.
SPEAKER_1:  what has happened with the other.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, commercial crew missions and in private missions like the inspiration for mission or axiom.
SPEAKER_1:  where SpaceX flew individually. They trained for about six months.
SPEAKER_1:  a lot of like reading manuals and learning the spacecraft.
SPEAKER_0:  Are you gonna do like a Rocky 4 montage or?
SPEAKER_1:  I hope it just gets shredded. I hope it's physical, a lot of physical training. And they're like, we didn't tell you.
SPEAKER_0:  He just seems to want to fill himself shirtless in the snow.
SPEAKER_1:  How is this relevant? Why is he always doing this?
SPEAKER_1:  can't get him to stop punching meat.
SPEAKER_1:  Um
SPEAKER_1:  So yeah, hopefully.
SPEAKER_1:  Realistically.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a manual. I like it.
SPEAKER_0:  But there's a physical component to all of this and that's really, I mean, that's fascinating. It's also inspiring to sort of civilians.
SPEAKER_0:  can do this. That's really interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean this is...
SPEAKER_1:  And to me, this represents.
SPEAKER_1:  this and the other commercial space ain't on.
SPEAKER_1:  private spaceflight missions like this represent really a turning point like truly an inflection and again, it's easy for people to be cynical that
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, you know, why are people wasting?
SPEAKER_1:  all this money doing space flight stuff. It's like.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I'm sure some people were saying that same thing about-
SPEAKER_1:  you know, airplanes and, and.
SPEAKER_1:  early aviation going like, why are we?
SPEAKER_1:  I can't believe those people are wasting the government's, you know, funding these
SPEAKER_1:  stupid planes and stuff. How's this ever gonna benefit me? And nowadays, imagine if all the planes just stopped working.
SPEAKER_1:  would freak out, our economy would collapse.
SPEAKER_1:  It would suck, you know? And it might be a long time before we get to that reality with space flight. No, if-
SPEAKER_1:  If spaceflight halted today...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, space assets, all of our, you know, on orbit assets, our life would be.
SPEAKER_1:  And I don't think people realize that.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's already, we're already reliant on it, but now we're getting to the point where it's-
SPEAKER_1:  We're really turning that corner It's the average person.
SPEAKER_1:  alive today. You know, if you're born.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, from now on, I think there's a real decent chance that by the time...
SPEAKER_1:  you pass, there's an opportunity to have flown in space.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. I mean, I, if I'm being honest.
SPEAKER_0:  I still haven't lost the feeling of magic of flying in an airplane.
SPEAKER_0:  I often catch myself thinking like...
SPEAKER_0:  How's this real?
SPEAKER_0:  How is, and like.
SPEAKER_0:  The contrast of this incredible thing that's incredibly safe.
SPEAKER_0:  flying through the air, taking off and landing.
SPEAKER_0:  while everyone else just looks bored.
SPEAKER_0:  watching like, I don't know, some romantic comedy.
SPEAKER_0:  on their phone with wifi. Yeah
SPEAKER_0:  So it's just, it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  The contrast of that is like.
SPEAKER_0:  Wow, we're...
SPEAKER_0:  We're incredible. We're incredible as a society. And it's like we develop some.
SPEAKER_0:  amazing technology that improves.
SPEAKER_0:  almost immeasurably our quality of life and then we take it for granted and now still reach for the next thing. And the next thing in life becomes more beautiful and complex and interesting. Yeah, it's just...
SPEAKER_0:  and the same stuff will be happening.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yeah, with space travel.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, it'll become mundane and boring.
SPEAKER_0:  At some point. Tough thing about space travel, of course.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I don't even know if it's such a giant leap over airplanes because airplanes are already
SPEAKER_0:  incredible, but the tough thing with space travel is the destination.
SPEAKER_0:  right, is the landing on a whole other world.
SPEAKER_0:  whether it's docking with different transport vehicles or the space station or it's landing elsewhere. It really is incredible. I think you mentioned since there's a...
SPEAKER_0:  There's artists, there's filmmakers and so on.
SPEAKER_0:  And you're all of those.
SPEAKER_0:  on top of being a great athlete.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, I'll just stop the running joke at this point.
SPEAKER_0:  Is there, have you thought about?
SPEAKER_0:  Just in general, we've offline talked about microphones and like...
SPEAKER_0:  all the different ways to film space launch, rocket launches.
SPEAKER_0:  Have you thought about the different options of like how to capture?
SPEAKER_0:  how to capture this. Have you, have the team have been like brainstorming and thinking about this? Do you anticipate it being super challenging?
SPEAKER_0:  There's so many opportunities to sort of...
SPEAKER_0:  think of how to do this.
SPEAKER_1:  So one of the fun things to remember is that Starship is.
SPEAKER_1:  huge. Like its internal volume is.
SPEAKER_1:  The pressurized volume on Starship is bigger than a 747's pressurized volume.
SPEAKER_1:  and it can take 100 metric tons.
SPEAKER_1:  anywhere.
SPEAKER_1:  with enough refueling.
SPEAKER_1:  100 minutes, so.
SPEAKER_1:  We have.
SPEAKER_1:  In theory, very little mass and volume constraints. Unlike prior, all other space flight missions ever, you're counting, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  grams down to, you know,
SPEAKER_1:  just really can't risk, you know, you have very.
SPEAKER_1:  defined.
SPEAKER_1:  parameters on what you cannot do.
SPEAKER_1:  We're going to likely have the luxury of being able to film and capture this in a way that's just never been done before. You know, we won't be.
SPEAKER_1:  inhibited by mass and volume constraints.
SPEAKER_1:  prior.
SPEAKER_1:  So
SPEAKER_1:  All that said and done, I'm hoping that we'll be able to just.
SPEAKER_1:  arm ourselves to the teeth with the absolute best cameras.
SPEAKER_1:  equipment possible backups on backups and.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, and pre-wire, you know, like pre-rig things.
SPEAKER_1:  Starship is going to be a...
SPEAKER_1:  transportation system and it...
SPEAKER_1:  has
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's being built from the ground up. There's no reason why they can't.
SPEAKER_1:  put infrastructure in for cameras that are just housed in the vehicle, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  These are talks that I'm excited to have.
SPEAKER_1:  because I really, ideally, one of the things I'd love to do.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm gonna be pushing really hard to actually try live streaming.
SPEAKER_1:  from inside.
SPEAKER_1:  during the launch.
SPEAKER_0:  during the launch livestream.
SPEAKER_0:  Inside that would be incredible. Wouldn't that be?
SPEAKER_0:  It's possible to pull off. That's really, really incredible. There is the magic to the live stream because like that's real. That's right there. That was.
SPEAKER_0:  The world would tune in. That would be truly inspiring, yes.
SPEAKER_1:  To me, that's one of those things a lot of people ask why they aren't doing it. Of course, NASA and other individuals will have their reasons of why not. There's obviously some technical hurdles, but...
SPEAKER_1:  Now with Starlink and other capabilities, there's...
SPEAKER_1:  less hurdles, there's obviously some transparency reasons, why, you know, and safety reasons, why it might not be a great idea to live stream.
SPEAKER_1:  Risky rocket launch, you know, the Challenger, I think put a pretty bad.
SPEAKER_1:  taste in our mouth as far as publicizing an event and having every student in the United States tune in to
SPEAKER_1:  you know, a tragedy.
SPEAKER_1:  But, um...
SPEAKER_1:  That's something I'm pushing for really hard just because I think it could be magical. I think it could really connect with people in a way that hasn't.
SPEAKER_1:  been done before.
SPEAKER_0:  Speaking of Challenger...
SPEAKER_0:  Have you thought about?
SPEAKER_0:  the fact that you're riding.
SPEAKER_0:  a thing as we've been talking about.
SPEAKER_0:  That's, um...
SPEAKER_0:  That's a giant explosive.
SPEAKER_0:  Powerful Rocket.
SPEAKER_0:  Have you, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Have you thought about the risk of that, the danger of that?
SPEAKER_0:  Have you contemplated your own mortality?
SPEAKER_1:  How could I not?
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I've seen...
SPEAKER_1:  with my I've seen and felt.
SPEAKER_1:  four of these prototype vehicles blow up.
SPEAKER_1:  with my own eyes.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Don't know if there's anyone else.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, early days.
SPEAKER_1:  some of the, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Mercury and Gemini astronauts watched failures of rockets and then got on them.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know of too many people that are dumb enough to do that though, this day and age.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  It's obviously I will have to see.
SPEAKER_1:  a lot of successful launches and have to have a lot of.
SPEAKER_1:  confidence in the engineering, the data.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  they have developed a safe system.
SPEAKER_1:  Currently, the current iteration of Starship has no abort system.
SPEAKER_1:  has no.
SPEAKER_1:  escape tower. So, you know, dragon capsule.
SPEAKER_1:  which is currently flying people has.
SPEAKER_1:  a launch abort system has super Draco engines that.
SPEAKER_1:  either by the push of a button or by the automatic triggering of the flight computer.
SPEAKER_1:  can shoot the capsule off of the rocket in milliseconds.
SPEAKER_1:  pull it safely away, get it far enough away so that it can pull the parachutes and safely splash down.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Starship C-
SPEAKER_1:  by all iterations I've ever seen does not have.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  The space shuttle also did not have that. So it's not absurd.
SPEAKER_1:  to not have an abort system. Like it is.
SPEAKER_1:  There is.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  certain engineering principles that.
SPEAKER_1:  prove that that could be a completely valid thing. The space shuttle flew 133 times.
SPEAKER_1:  Fully successfully, it did have two failures, resulting in the loss of 14 lives.
SPEAKER_1:  um, 85 or what, sorry, 98.5% success rate.
SPEAKER_1:  Pretty, I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  You there's other, I've probably done things that are a lot riskier. I have race motorcycles, drag race motorcycles, and you know, written like an absolute jerk on the streets on a motorcycle, I'm sure I've had a higher than a 98.5.
SPEAKER_1:  percent survival rate or lower than that. I mean, at some point.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's, you know, yes, it's risky, it's scary.
SPEAKER_1:  And, um...
SPEAKER_1:  I think about it a lot, a lot. It definitely is one of those things that I-
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  I will have to see and I'm in no hurry for this to happen either. Personally, I'm in no hurry because it's like I would.
SPEAKER_1:  rather see this thing be developed and iterated and see.
SPEAKER_1:  10, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  I was gonna say ten dozen, but I'd be happy with a dozen.
SPEAKER_1:  fully successful like oh we've got this thing totally nailed down.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, you know, before I get on it.
SPEAKER_1:  but.
SPEAKER_1:  And that likely is the reality. There will likely be a dozen or two or three launches because just even to get to the moon on Starship, they have to-
SPEAKER_1:  refuel it in orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  So it will get to Earth orbit, basically empty and out of fuel. So I'll have to dock with a fuel depot.
SPEAKER_1:  Fill up.
SPEAKER_1:  and then go to the moon.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  just to even get that full, you know, already talking about.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, a handful of launches. So there will be a lot of launches before we fly.
SPEAKER_0:  Would they do a test?
SPEAKER_0:  flight without humans on board that goes to the moon or no?
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not sure. I'm not sure if they'll do that exact flight profile, but by then they will have already flown.
SPEAKER_1:  most likely the Artemis 3 program will have.
SPEAKER_1:  a Starship variant to the moon that lands on the moon.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  So doing at that point, you're pretty much, I would like them to test the heat shield at that entry velocity, though, because it is.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, you know, it takes.
SPEAKER_1:  another.
SPEAKER_1:  it's about 30% faster to get, like it could go 30% faster than the lower orbit to get out to a translunar injection.
SPEAKER_1:  And although that only sounds like, oh, 30% faster.
SPEAKER_1:  It's-
SPEAKER_1:  You know, the reentry heating experienced by a vehicle goes up by velocity cubed.
SPEAKER_1:  Not squared?
SPEAKER_1:  So, and not even, not linear. So it's not like we go twice as fast to get.
SPEAKER_1:  you see twice as much heat, you know, 30% faster, 30% more heat.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not squared, it's not go twice as fast to get four times as much heat. Let's go twice as fast.
SPEAKER_1:  get eight times as much.
SPEAKER_1:  on reentry.
SPEAKER_1:  So 30% faster on reentry is actually a really, really big deal.
SPEAKER_1:  So I would love to see that because, you know, there's certain things that I would love to see milestones that I would love to see tested out and proven.
SPEAKER_1:  before I get on board but
SPEAKER_1:  At the end of the day, I really do believe.
SPEAKER_1:  that just like Falcon 9 and the success of that, that they're going to.
SPEAKER_1:  Push it.
SPEAKER_1:  and get all the kinks out well before anyone's on top of it. Nowadays Falcon, Iron, and Dragon is-
SPEAKER_1:  You know, arguably the.
SPEAKER_1:  one of the safest, most reliable.
SPEAKER_1:  and best rides he could take to space.
SPEAKER_0:  Are you afraid of dying?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Is this one of the first times you get to year young?
SPEAKER_0:  Have you gotten a chance to think about?
SPEAKER_0:  Death is one of the...
SPEAKER_0:  First time you've...
SPEAKER_0:  Really contemplated it?
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, yeah, I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  Like I said, I've had...
SPEAKER_1:  I've had dumb moments on motorcycles where I kind of saw.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, like.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm going to smash into this thing at 120 mile an hour.
SPEAKER_0:  So you've had moments when you realized it could end just like this.
SPEAKER_1:  where you literally, and I have.
SPEAKER_1:  for most of my adult life had dreams of.
SPEAKER_1:  falling.
SPEAKER_1:  and hitting the ground and it just all, you get a ring in your ears, it all goes black, and in my head I go, oh shit, that was it.
SPEAKER_0:  Have you seen a therapist about this?
SPEAKER_0:  Uh-uh.
SPEAKER_0:  I wonder what it means.
SPEAKER_1:  So I'm...
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I'm sure there's a Freudian interpretation somewhere in there.
SPEAKER_0:  that I'm going to also apply to my dating life. no.
SPEAKER_0:  The joke is the running joke continues. Okay, so uh...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's fascinating in general.
SPEAKER_0:  as I hope we'll talk about in the early days of spaceflight that there is a...
SPEAKER_0:  The task of reaching out to the stars is a fundamentally risky one.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to take risks and of course there's really rigorous safety precautions and so on, but it's still a risk.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think like most people that.
SPEAKER_1:  the for me the idea of.
SPEAKER_1:  dying isn't so much about myself, it's about those affected by it, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Bye.
SPEAKER_1:  My loved ones, my family, my girlfriend, my...
SPEAKER_1:  my friends, you know, obviously I don't want to.
SPEAKER_1:  have this be a traumatic experience for anybody, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  It's already going to be hard. Like it's already.
SPEAKER_1:  I know my parents and family and friends are very supportive.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  that my parents are.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, all about it of course, but.
SPEAKER_1:  My mom is also very emotional too, so.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, she's, so my.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of athletes, my brother-in-law's actually been on American Ninja Warrior two seasons.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  phenomenal athlete and even just when he competes, my mom gets so emotional. You can't even hold it together seeing that.
SPEAKER_1:  So what's it gonna be like when she sees her son get on top of a skyscraper and and
SPEAKER_1:  ascend on a column of flames into the heavens. Like that's going to be.
SPEAKER_1:  very difficult, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  I've taken them out, they've seen Star Race and they've seen Starship, they've seen a couple launches.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if that's gonna make him feel better.
SPEAKER_0:  Exposure therapy, I guess. Exposure therapy, okay. Have you had that conversation with them?
SPEAKER_0:  about this like before agreeing.
SPEAKER_0:  of.
SPEAKER_0:  to join, I mean, was that what the...
SPEAKER_0:  Was that, or is it one of those things like...
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  You just, you don't have that conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't have that conversation. There's a love, there's a passion here.
SPEAKER_1:  And realistically, I'm not.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm going to be...
SPEAKER_1:  convinced and statistically convinced that this is
SPEAKER_1:  relatively safe.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, like.
SPEAKER_1:  again in the 99% safe.
SPEAKER_1:  Again.
SPEAKER_1:  There's things that people do every day that are.
SPEAKER_1:  Less safe than this, you know, like you ride in the motorcycle.
SPEAKER_1:  Again, yeah, riding a motorcycle, doing wheelies at over 100 mile an hour. You're not felli-
SPEAKER_0:  Wheelies over hun-
SPEAKER_0:  What?
SPEAKER_0:  Ha!
SPEAKER_0:  All right.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not a smart guy always, okay?
SPEAKER_1:  Formation flying in the fighter jets was likely a more dangerous thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, then.
SPEAKER_1:  What I'll beat.
SPEAKER_1:  doing.
SPEAKER_1:  in spaceflight.
SPEAKER_0:  So as surreal as it is, we're talking about you.
SPEAKER_0:  um, flying around the moon.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's rewind.
SPEAKER_0:  and talk about the origin story.
SPEAKER_0:  What's the origin story of Everyday Astronaut?
SPEAKER_1:  I used to be a professional photographer. So from 2008 till-
SPEAKER_1:  the end of 2016, that was my income.
SPEAKER_1:  full-time.
SPEAKER_0:  Like you were an Instagram model and took butt pictures of yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  fitness model.
SPEAKER_0:  to
SPEAKER_1:  I did a lot of weddings. I shot 150 weddings all around the world.
SPEAKER_0:  all kinds of material like like dude
SPEAKER_1:  portrait also a lot of portrait work and then just you know random like commercial things like
SPEAKER_1:  you know, food and beverages for businesses or like, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  wheelchair ramp company I shot their product like, you know, it's random.
SPEAKER_1:  Whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  professional photographer does in Cedar Falls, Iowa. When did you
SPEAKER_0:  you are a fan love it.
SPEAKER_0:  photography with a visual medium.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you remember?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I do actually remember. I so I drew up. I grew up drawing constantly. I
SPEAKER_1:  I was the weird kid that might, I would bring a.
SPEAKER_1:  sketch pad to the restaurants, like every restaurant.
SPEAKER_1:  When I was growing up, until I was like 18, 19, I literally would just sit there and draw or waiting for food. And my parents fostered that, they-
SPEAKER_1:  you know, and I'd be the weird kid, but I'd be engaging and talking but I'd be sitting there drawing.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  I was always obsessed with realism and recreating and visualizing things.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  When I got my hands on the cameras, I was actually my dad's old Pentax that I...
SPEAKER_1:  first shot on a film camera and developing the film. I didn't personally develop it, like getting the film back back in those days.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I just was like.
SPEAKER_1:  so excited about the idea that I had this visual.
SPEAKER_1:  that I saw with my own eyes.
SPEAKER_1:  And now I can.
SPEAKER_1:  stop time and capture it and show it to other people.
SPEAKER_1:  Just kind of like, to me, that was like the ultimate form of realism was like.
SPEAKER_1:  Literally showing you the photons basically.
SPEAKER_1:  that affected this film.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, and so I, I mean, I was, I was 19 when I got my first digital SLR at Canon 20 D.
SPEAKER_1:  and started shooting.
SPEAKER_1:  And yeah, I just, I fell in love with it. It became like, I got a job at a camera store and-
SPEAKER_1:  You know, basically all my extra money went into.
SPEAKER_1:  buying everything that I could at the time.
SPEAKER_1:  I only worked there for about exactly a year before I went into.
SPEAKER_1:  pursuing photography full time and.
SPEAKER_1:  I basically was shooting weddings that I could.
SPEAKER_1:  travel and pay like, you know, for it to be able to.
SPEAKER_1:  do some big trips every year and develop some kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  portfolio of traveling and
SPEAKER_1:  Not necessarily like it, not-
SPEAKER_1:  for, you know, I guess Instagram wasn't much of a thing at the time. It's really just, I like
SPEAKER_1:  making big prints and...
SPEAKER_1:  having them displayed and...
SPEAKER_1:  that kind of stuff and.
SPEAKER_1:  Pretty su-
SPEAKER_0:  Are you still a canon guy? You still a canon elitist? NOOO.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh no, I moved around, I did Sony for a bit.
SPEAKER_1:  I still kind of shoot mostly Canon glass, but adapted to either Sony, like lenses, sorry, like Canon lenses. Look at you.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think about the...
SPEAKER_0:  these things that I'm using Sony a seven four.
SPEAKER_0:  Great.
SPEAKER_0:  Great, see you.
SPEAKER_0:  I've been, you know, I Googled around just trying to find a camera that can do video and photography pretty well.
SPEAKER_0:  And obviously going was just like...
SPEAKER_0:  generic lens, primelens, I resisted everything.
SPEAKER_0:  My whole journey with these camera things, I'm trying to figure stuff out.
SPEAKER_0:  is like, prime lens, it seems so stupid. So prime lens is like a fixed zoom thing. It's like, why?
SPEAKER_0:  I remember I was going to like Ukraine.
SPEAKER_0:  In thinking it's similar like yeah, very similar to spaceflight, but you're very constrained because you're going into an unknown environment. You're going to a war zone, you're going to a front.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't know what, like you don't know anything. And there's like a little suitcase you have to like see, figure out like, how do you film this was.
SPEAKER_0:  What's robust?
SPEAKER_0:  uh... what gives you like a good image versus the flexibility versus the way
SPEAKER_0:  is as important there you have to think about like.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you really bring like a bunch of zoom lenses and all that kind of stuff? I had to learn really quickly, but yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a whole journey that you've already been on, but it's nice to have a beginner like me.
SPEAKER_0:  to explore that. I think there is a...
SPEAKER_0:  There's nice things just like as we've been talking about with a beginner's mind.
SPEAKER_0:  to um.
SPEAKER_0:  Not let equipment.
SPEAKER_0:  Get in the way of what your vision is of what a thing should look like. Sometimes like...
SPEAKER_0:  especially if you're a professional videographer, photographer, cinematographer, whatever you call it.
SPEAKER_0:  You can like
SPEAKER_0:  Fetishize equipment too much you could get so much equipment And I've interacted that because I've been trying to learn from other people that have so much more experience than me
SPEAKER_0:  I think their advice is often like...
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  very pushing a lot of equipment.
SPEAKER_0:  versus like...
SPEAKER_0:  the final thing, like how do you create the art of it?
SPEAKER_0:  like
SPEAKER_0:  Because to me, even photography is just like storytelling.
SPEAKER_0:  And so.
SPEAKER_0:  like a lot of the discussion to me.
SPEAKER_0:  that I enjoy, especially talking to creative people, is like the final story. Like how, and I've learned, you know, like light, light.
SPEAKER_0:  Light is a weird thing.
SPEAKER_0:  It's so interesting. It's so interesting how you can create a motion with light.
SPEAKER_0:  Like with a little you could take a
SPEAKER_0:  like a phone.
SPEAKER_0:  and like you light your face in different ways.
SPEAKER_0:  And like it changes the emotion. Oh yeah. It's so weird.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_0:  I'm like, holy shit.
SPEAKER_0:  Cause like that's the conversation I want to have. People give me advice how to light a scene and all that kind of stuff is great. But the reality is...
SPEAKER_0:  that a little bit of light in a different direction you have to understand how that changes
SPEAKER_1:  contour on your face.
SPEAKER_0:  and the expression that your face can.
SPEAKER_0:  The...
SPEAKER_0:  the expression
SPEAKER_0:  effective to communicate under different lighting conditions.
SPEAKER_0:  And then like the mystery of like.
SPEAKER_0:  having some of your face.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... in darkness and some not
SPEAKER_0:  when you can only see the eyes and not the face.
SPEAKER_0:  when the background is visible or not. I mean, yeah, it's all just like this interesting art form.
SPEAKER_0:  that can be so powerful when you're telling a story.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, and what's fun for with me with photography and rockets, they're both like the ultimate story of compromise
SPEAKER_1:  When you start learning about photography, learn about how the aperture affects both your exposure but also your depth of field, higher shutter speed affects both your exposure.
SPEAKER_1:  Redepth of Field, how the...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, a medium format camera versus a crop camera effects, you know, everything is a compromise and price versus performance.
SPEAKER_1:  There's always a compromise. You're always literally doing like a trade study of what can I afford.
SPEAKER_1:  What's my outcome? Like blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
SPEAKER_1:  how fast is he out of focus or whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  Same with rockets, like there's a million.
SPEAKER_1:  choices and every single one of them affects every single thing. So there's always all these trades and it's so cool that you can see.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, the same, totally different outcomes based on the same like requirements, you know, like do X.
SPEAKER_1:  then here's how we're gonna do it.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, two teams of people will come.
SPEAKER_1:  wildly different things.
SPEAKER_0:  When did you fall in love?
SPEAKER_0:  with Rockets.
SPEAKER_1:  So yeah, so the story kind of keeps going for me. So I was doing. Yeah. Mottaud genius
SPEAKER_1:  Can't talk photography, man. We'll go on a deep rabbit hole there.
SPEAKER_1:  So
SPEAKER_1:  So it ended, you know, through all this, doing a lot of weddings, I was already getting saturated and feeling.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I'm not.
SPEAKER_1:  being as creative, you know, you can only shoot them so many weddings before you're like, well, now we do this pose, this pose, this pose, you know, even if like they're amazing places like, you know,
SPEAKER_1:  front of a castle in Germany or something. I'm still like, well, I need to be the day I'm.
SPEAKER_1:  not being very creative, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  I remember craving like some, some.
SPEAKER_1:  projects and so
SPEAKER_1:  I was sitting at my friend's coffee shop.
SPEAKER_1:  in my hometown in Cedar Falls.
SPEAKER_1:  Sidecar Coffee.
SPEAKER_1:  and I'm sitting on this red couch and I see this article.
SPEAKER_1:  from I think Gizmodo and it said.
SPEAKER_1:  you could own.
SPEAKER_1:  the flight stick of an Apollo command module.
SPEAKER_1:  And I knew enough to know what that meant, but that's really about the end of my space knowledge.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I clicked on it, the clickbait got me. Like I'm like, oh yeah, I'm gonna see if, you know, and see that the minimum bid was like $250,000. I'm like, okay, no, I can't own the Apollo joystick, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  but it got me on this website called RR Auction. And so I started scrolling through that, looking for things that hadn't been bid on.
SPEAKER_1:  And they had that, you know, at the time they're doing a huge space auction.
SPEAKER_1:  And so I'm looking for things just out of curiosity, fun, these are cool, like it's starting to really, you know, like I said, I like space, but I wasn't like.
SPEAKER_1:  in love with it or anything but I'm
SPEAKER_1:  very v-
SPEAKER_0:  just seeing all the stuff like this.
SPEAKER_1:  So cool, look at all this old history stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  and ended up seeing a...
SPEAKER_1:  There's an article for a.
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  VMS TK
SPEAKER_1:  44 flight suit high-altitude flight suit that came from the Soviet Union
SPEAKER_1:  and looks
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's like a MIG.
SPEAKER_1:  Fighter jet.
SPEAKER_1:  fighter pilot suit very similar to like the SR-71 like kind of pumpkin suit.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, pre semi pressure suit with a full
SPEAKER_1:  helmet. I mean, it looks like a spacesuit, you know, for all intents and purposes, it's
SPEAKER_1:  Kind of like a spacesuit.
SPEAKER_1:  And I just.
SPEAKER_1:  I've been like, I think $325.
SPEAKER_1:  And next thing you know, like, it arrives at my door.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  And from that point on, like literally I got it out.
SPEAKER_1:  immediately try to put it on and the first thing that I do is almost die in it because I
SPEAKER_1:  closed the helmet down on myself and locked it.
SPEAKER_1:  and didn't know how to unlock it.
SPEAKER_1:  So I'm literally and so as soon as I seal it up, I'm.
SPEAKER_1:  realizing I can't breathe.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm going to run out of air. So luckily like there's a hose, you know, kind of that long hose thing that would normally plug into an air supply.
SPEAKER_1:  had a little plug on the end of it, so I just unplugged it and was able to...
SPEAKER_1:  Temporarily breathe through the hose until I figured out the locking mechanism
SPEAKER_1:  So there was my almost, that was my mortality rate thing right there, so that was probably.
SPEAKER_1:  above a 98.
SPEAKER_1:  below that you're there for
SPEAKER_0:  panicking.
SPEAKER_0:  inside.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. For a few seconds. Already reading like my premature obituary, like idiot dies alone in spacesuit in his living room. You know, like just imagine. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  That would be like Darwin Award for sure.
SPEAKER_1:  For sure.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_1:  So I get the spacesuit.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_0:  They kind of. Impji by you.
SPEAKER_0:  Take my breath away.
SPEAKER_0:  Also, don't forget your rights to the organizations you livestream on social travelling........
SPEAKER_0:  Mmm.
SPEAKER_0:  You should feel bad for that one.
SPEAKER_1:  You introduced Creed to me, so...
SPEAKER_0:  You should feel bad about that one. Stars wide open.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  So I ended up like the space suit kind of like more or less haunted me because it kind of just it's sat in like my living room for a long time and I didn't know what to do with it.
SPEAKER_1:  and actually had a friend who is also a photographer wanted to do like a photo. He was just kind of taking pictures randomly. He's like, hey, bring your space suit over. We'll do a picture. It's like, all right, you know, I walk across the street, literally lived across the street.
SPEAKER_1:  Taylor and I.
SPEAKER_1:  put the spacesuit on, I took this funny picture, and I'm like, this is awesome. And I got a lot of like fun out of like creating a character, you know, of everyday astronaut, or at the time, I guess I didn't know, an astronaut.
SPEAKER_1:  And then that kind of just continued. I was like.
SPEAKER_1:  thinking of more and more funny situations where I could have this astronaut on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  doing mundane everyday things.
SPEAKER_1:  and came up with the name Everyday Astronaut.
SPEAKER_1:  And originally it was just literally a photo project.
SPEAKER_1:  this whole art series of.
SPEAKER_1:  an astronaut doing these things.
SPEAKER_1:  Funny Whimsical.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  silly mundane things, but I was researching a lot about like.
SPEAKER_1:  I was trying to hide Easter eggs. I was going to hide in the...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, the echocardiogram of.
SPEAKER_1:  of Alan Shepard, you know, like his first flight into space and photoshopping that into pictures and like.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, doing all these little like facts about space flight, but there's just hidden little elements in these photos.
SPEAKER_1:  And man doing that, I just fell in love with it.
SPEAKER_1:  I just was going over every little detail that I could learn. I just couldn't stop learning.
SPEAKER_1:  And I was getting excited because I was like, I could be teaching people about-
SPEAKER_1:  all this exciting stuff and all the cool things people figured out you know 40 years ago 50 years ago
SPEAKER_1:  and was trying to portray that through images on Instagram. And it took me a little while, but eventually I realized.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, on Instagram, your retention rate, you're lucky if you get like.
SPEAKER_1:  two seconds of someone looking at an image, or maybe nowadays 60 seconds of a quick little Instagram short or something.
SPEAKER_1:  but.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it doesn't give you a chance to really
SPEAKER_0:  teach you to explore a little topic that you felt, like you felt the curiosity about the thing. There's so much to learn here. This is so beautiful. I wish.
SPEAKER_1:  There's so many opportunities to have a light bulb go off for someone to be like, this is awesome.
SPEAKER_1:  And so, yeah, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  I started, so by the end of 2016, like throughout 2016, I realized.
SPEAKER_1:  I want to be done doing photography as a profession, and I want to pursue everyday astronaut. But I didn't know what it meant yet. I just knew I had this thing.
SPEAKER_1:  And at that time I'd been doing it for roughly two years and had...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, seeing, I don't know, like 50,000 Instagram followers or something. I thought like, I could just be a full-time influencer now, you know, like just.
SPEAKER_1:  Go around taking pictures of myself in a space suit and...
SPEAKER_1:  doing public appearances and write a children's book or something, I don't know. I don't know what this thing is.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll figure it out, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  It basically, I gave myself like a runway of one year of 2017 of like, I'm going to throw stuff at the wall and see what sticks.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, so I was doing like Twitch streams. I was playing Kerbal space program.
SPEAKER_1:  which is like a video game.
SPEAKER_1:  like a physics based rocket building simulation game, but it's also like, it's fun and silly. because
SPEAKER_1:  Not playing with like humans, you're playing with these little...
SPEAKER_1:  like
SPEAKER_1:  little alien guys and it's fun and silly.
SPEAKER_1:  streaming that on Twitch and doing things and...
SPEAKER_1:  doing, posting some of those things onto YouTube. But finally, like I said, it actually happened to be.
SPEAKER_1:  February 27th, 2017, when SpaceX had that announcement that they're flying somewhere around the moon that I'm-
SPEAKER_1:  I gotta tell people about this and...
SPEAKER_1:  stood there and...
SPEAKER_1:  Made my first produced YouTube video.
SPEAKER_1:  and I didn't want it to be over three minutes.
SPEAKER_1:  I was afraid that'd be way too long for YouTube.
SPEAKER_1:  And I got it down to like, I don't know, two minutes and 40 seconds or something.
SPEAKER_1:  And that video wearing the I was wearing the spacesuit. Yeah. And very horrible audio. It looks like it was color graded by a seven year old with a tan.
SPEAKER_1:  marker or something like it just looks terrible. Sounds horrible. I'm yelling.
SPEAKER_1:  No one's happy.
SPEAKER_1:  Bye.
SPEAKER_1:  But the video.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, did relatively well. Like I had no followers on YouTube. Like I had maybe 100.
SPEAKER_1:  or something.
SPEAKER_0:  Is the video still up?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, that's great. it's still watched.
SPEAKER_1:  cringy.
SPEAKER_1:  And as it should be, you know, your first video should be terrible. If it's not terrible, then you spent too long trying to make it.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  The thing that clicked for me is I had...
SPEAKER_1:  very little audience, and all of a sudden that video kind of took off.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, relatively, I think it got like 10,000 or 12,000 views. And I was like, holy crap, that's.
SPEAKER_1:  Way more engagement than I have. I'm famous. I'm famous now. 10,000 people? It's almost my whole town.
SPEAKER_0:  It is kind of crazy. Like 10,000 people is crazy. It's crazy. If you
SPEAKER_0:  If you had 500 people attend a thing that you do, that would be like, you're like a rock star. That's crazy.
SPEAKER_1:  We lose
SPEAKER_0:  perspective. Yeah, we were really loose perspective very quickly.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  I'd made another video, this one I spent more time on. and I I
SPEAKER_1:  Before photography, actually, I used to do like wedding videography too, so I did.
SPEAKER_1:  done my woes with videography and weddings and stuff. I hated video like I thought video was the worst.
SPEAKER_1:  Took so long to edit.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I love Darvius. It's like, boom, you snap it, boom, post, you're done in an hour, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  And video is like this whole cumbersome thing. So I thought I'll never do video.
SPEAKER_1:  And here I was making this long, what it's, the time seemed like a long, seven minute long YouTube video about how the Falcon 9 lands.
SPEAKER_1:  And again, like that one I posted and actually it did really bad. And I was really upset. disturbed me, especially, if you like it.
SPEAKER_1:  on the stupid video.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  worked really hard scripting and blah blah blah and then it had like a thousand views or something. It did much worse in the first video.
SPEAKER_1:  and I was so upset.
SPEAKER_1:  And I kind of like was ready to keep throwing more spaghetti at the wall to see what's going to stick for everyday astronaut.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it was like a month or two later, I happened to like, you know, check the analytics on YouTube and all of a sudden, hmm.
SPEAKER_1:  That video, I kinda...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. Took off and I got like 40 or 50 or 60,000 views or something. I was like.
SPEAKER_1:  And it just kept, you know, that just honed it in more like, okay.
SPEAKER_1:  YouTube will bring a bigger, like, bring an audience to me.
SPEAKER_1:  as opposed to like Instagram, I had to find and...
SPEAKER_1:  Young.
SPEAKER_1:  try to get the audience to come to me. And this was like, they were going to do the leg work.
SPEAKER_1:  So if I make decent videos...
SPEAKER_1:  And I realized like really the fun thing for me was explaining.
SPEAKER_1:  a topic that was scary and intimidating and try to make it fun and engaging.
SPEAKER_0:  What were some of the struggles of building up a YouTube channel? So for people who don't know, once again, you have a YouTube channel called Everyday Astronaut and there's some incredible videos on it. So what was the-
SPEAKER_0:  What was some of the challenges and struggles in the early days?
SPEAKER_1:  Definitely like at first you're not gonna find your own voice and I know like even you know, Jimmy talked
SPEAKER_1:  to you about that, like how your first video is gonna suck. You're not gonna be yourself. You're gonna be nervous, you're gonna be...
SPEAKER_1:  not getting on the tone, the pace, the things that are interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  And actually, originally, I had constraints. I was really worried about making a short video because I thought there's no way anyone's gonna watch a three-minute video and then a seven-minute video.
SPEAKER_1:  And pretty quickly I realized like YouTube as a whole was kind of changing.
SPEAKER_1:  But also there's always that.
SPEAKER_1:  historic backbone of like 20.
SPEAKER_1:  two minutes of programming for a 30 minute spot on TV.
SPEAKER_1:  Like no one goes over 22 or 44 minutes, you know, if you have the full hour special or whatever. Like that is.
SPEAKER_1:  the absolute limit of what a human being can watch.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  basically was what I thought. And slowly I just kept playing and getting longer and actually more and more in depth into the topics.
SPEAKER_1:  And instead of getting like pushback, you know, be like, this is so boring.
SPEAKER_1:  I realized as long as I was walking people through the whole step, giving them all the context they need.
SPEAKER_1:  They're happy to get as deep into the weeds as I can get them.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that just kind of fed the snowball that's kept rolling and I'm like.
SPEAKER_1:  All right, and you know, before you know it, I'm making hour long videos like an hour long is.
SPEAKER_1:  more or less a normal length on my channel.
SPEAKER_1:  for a produced video and they're really, really in depth.
SPEAKER_1:  but I love that process of trying to preemptively kind of guess what the questions might be.
SPEAKER_1:  and end.
SPEAKER_1:  Part of that is we do script read-throughs with our supporters.
SPEAKER_1:  and do like cuts of videos and people, a decent amount of people see it before it goes public.
SPEAKER_1:  And we get those questions out of the way. And we get those people asking.
SPEAKER_1:  the questions and then I love nothing more than trying to.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, get all those questions answered by the end of the video.
SPEAKER_0:  question about being a
SPEAKER_0:  A creator on YouTube.
SPEAKER_0:  that could be.
SPEAKER_0:  a challenging psychological aspect to it, which is like, you might invest a huge amount of-
SPEAKER_0:  Your effort.
SPEAKER_0:  into a thing in it.
SPEAKER_0:  doesn't receive much attention at all.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there's something about YouTube and in general social media.
SPEAKER_0:  that makes you feel really crappy about that.
SPEAKER_0:  if you let it.
SPEAKER_0:  if you really look at the numbers.
SPEAKER_0:  It's very, very difficult not to pay attention to that.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, that's the reason why I turn off numbers on my.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  my interface for stuff that I've created.
SPEAKER_0:  Because I just see it having a negative effect on your mind.
SPEAKER_0:  But even then, it still has an effect.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, your epic video on...
SPEAKER_0:  the history of
SPEAKER_0:  Soviet rockets comes to mind. And we'll talk about that in a second, but it's called People Should Check It Out.
SPEAKER_0:  the entire Soviet rocket engine family tree.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's something you've researched for two years. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  You put your heart and soul into it. There's a lot of passion, there's a long journey. I think about like an hour and a half video.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, is there like, uh, is there challenges? Is there like.
SPEAKER_0:  How difficult is that to put so much of yourself into a video?
SPEAKER_0:  and it may be not due so well.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the...
SPEAKER_1:  That's the struggle for sure, honestly, especially as like as we grow, I try.
SPEAKER_1:  to make better and better videos, which means.
SPEAKER_1:  hiring more and more people to do higher end animations and spend more time editing and shooting and
SPEAKER_1:  scripting and just...
SPEAKER_1:  But at the end of the day, like, it still can't be just losing money.
SPEAKER_0:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_1:  And I have videos that definitely lose a lot of money because I hire.
SPEAKER_1:  3D artists and stuff and...
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  And I was so certain. The Soviet rocket engine video I thought was just purely going to be a passion project.
SPEAKER_1:  I honestly was like, if it ever crosses a million, it's a home run.
SPEAKER_0:  And is it, I had to see it cross like a couple million now? I think it's a little.
SPEAKER_1:  to a
SPEAKER_1:  which is insane to me. Like I just really thought this was-
SPEAKER_1:  more something just to put on the shelf as a resource, almost for myself, you know, like, just to kind of have that knowledge bank and something I've always wanted to straighten out in my own head.
SPEAKER_1:  and kind of know the history a little bit better.
SPEAKER_1:  But come to find out, like it took a while. You know, it was a slow turn.
SPEAKER_0:  But I remember when you first released it and that's when I watched it.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember like this has so few views
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I remember being just sad.
SPEAKER_0:  Like I was like sad about the state of the world because I know how much love you put into it. How like how much.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, to me, for some reason, that somehow would directly connect to.
SPEAKER_0:  huge views.
SPEAKER_0:  But see, you know what made me sad is like.
SPEAKER_0:  If you use a different thumbnail or a different title that could affect
SPEAKER_0:  the popularity and then I just could imagine the torment you're going through.
SPEAKER_0:  What if I used a different thumbnail?
SPEAKER_0:  It's that Jimmy, the Mr. Beast torment.
SPEAKER_0:  Just a slightly different title.
SPEAKER_0:  or slightly different.
SPEAKER_1:  And I have videos, ironically, the last like.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, five videos I've produced are-
SPEAKER_1:  horribly flopping like some of my worst videos I've ever made.
SPEAKER_0:  statistically. The interesting one is like...
SPEAKER_0:  the use some rice group incredible video you summarizing
SPEAKER_0:  that people should go watch.
SPEAKER_0:  about all the awards video for 2022, like all the cool stuff that happened between 2022.
SPEAKER_0:  I remember that not being that popular. There's a few ones recently that are not that popular.
SPEAKER_1:  Like riding in a fighter jet. I thought that was gonna be easy like one or two million
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if I've paid the flights off.
SPEAKER_1:  to go there, you know what I mean? Like in that video. It makes no sense.
SPEAKER_1:  And frankly, here's at the end of the day.
SPEAKER_1:  I realized like I have
SPEAKER_1:  Lately, especially the last year or two, kind of disconnected from that aspect of it. I'm super fortunate. I have very generous Patreon support.
SPEAKER_1:  and people that can help me sustain to produce.
SPEAKER_0:  People go support, support Tim on Patreon.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, it's...
SPEAKER_1:  But as you know, as a creator, that is what...
SPEAKER_1:  keeps the lights on it and makes it so it's, you know, I can go this deep. Like if I didn't have that, if I had to rely solely on.
SPEAKER_1:  like YouTube ad revenue.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I would just.
SPEAKER_1:  They'd be super different videos. I wouldn't spend as much time researching because I just, you know, they just be more glossed over. It's like a hurry to turn them out so I can keep the machine going.
SPEAKER_1:  and I have this incredible freedom.
SPEAKER_1:  to really dive into a topic like a video that I've been working on now for almost three months is how to start a rocket engine.
SPEAKER_1:  And let me tell you, it's not as easy as...
SPEAKER_1:  as one might think or I guess.
SPEAKER_1:  as it is as difficult as you might think. I mean, it's an insane topic.
SPEAKER_1:  And I would even by starting.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean like the ignition.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, like how do you physically get them running? You know, like there's all these, you know, the valves and the turbine
SPEAKER_1:  The turbine, you know that we were talking about earlier, like that has to run on the pumps, but itself is powering the pumps.
SPEAKER_1:  So how do you get that, like chicken and egg, how do you get that thing started?
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there's tons of, it's so cool. There's so many ways.
SPEAKER_1:  And so for me, you know, that required reading a lot and talking to.
SPEAKER_1:  people that know a lot more than me.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, and just really trying to make sure I understand enough of it to explain it and try to weave a narrative, you know? So that video is three months in the making.
SPEAKER_1:  We're still probably another two or three weeks out.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's, I don't expect, I mean, I think this one will do relatively well, you know, but in the grand scheme of YouTube, like still.
SPEAKER_1:  child's play, you know it.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm okay, and I'm okay with that. I'm at that point, actually, where I am okay with that. It still stings.
SPEAKER_1:  And I'm more worried about just like, can I continue to do it at this quality and at this level?
SPEAKER_1:  if it's losing money. You know what I mean? Given.
SPEAKER_1:  There is a trade off and I am kind of having to navigate that.
SPEAKER_0:  But you have sort of the depth.
SPEAKER_0:  of the impact you have.
SPEAKER_0:  is a thing that YouTube can't give you numbers on, but it's a really important thing to sort of remember.
SPEAKER_0:  that it's really not just about the YouTube numbers.
SPEAKER_0:  For people like you, they're...
SPEAKER_0:  basically.
SPEAKER_0:  Educating.
SPEAKER_0:  and revealing the brilliance in a.
SPEAKER_0:  technology that.
SPEAKER_0:  will make humans a multiplanetary species and give hope.
SPEAKER_0:  to millions of young minds that will build that future.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, that's immeasurable.
SPEAKER_0:  That's not just the views. That's, uh, but you know, it's, um.
SPEAKER_0:  That's really important to sort of remember.
SPEAKER_0:  as you're creating it. That's something I try to think about as well. So like views.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. And that becomes more.
SPEAKER_1:  Don't matter. I realize that more and more like every day, you know, the more
SPEAKER_1:  the channel matures, the more I realize the importance of it as an overall mission as opposed to like...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, in the first year or two, it's a rat race of growth and...
SPEAKER_1:  of popularity and all that kind of stuff. And you feel that, you feel that it's a driving force. These days.
SPEAKER_1:  Not so much, just because that will wear you out.
SPEAKER_1:  very quickly.
SPEAKER_0:  So back to the Soviet rocket video, the epic video, probably the most epically researched video you've done.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's like, it's truly an epic video.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... so what uh...
SPEAKER_0:  again called the entire Soviet rocket engine family tree.
SPEAKER_0:  Took you two years to research.
SPEAKER_0:  What are some fascinating things you've learned?
SPEAKER_0:  about the history of rocket engines.
SPEAKER_0:  in the Soviet Union and in general through the process of making that video.
SPEAKER_0:  The- the-
SPEAKER_1:  Coolest thing to me is...
SPEAKER_1:  How?
SPEAKER_1:  It's this weird blend for the Soviet Union went.
SPEAKER_1:  through a.
SPEAKER_1:  an insane iteration process and made so many engines. Like I didn't even touch.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  any like maneuvering thrusters or missile engines. Like I only really dealt with main propulsion engines on orbital rockets and they're still.
SPEAKER_1:  way too many to talk about. I mean, it's still dozens and dozens of engines.
SPEAKER_1:  And I could have gone deeper into this, which is hilarious.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  They iterated so much, made a new engine for-
SPEAKER_1:  Just at the-
SPEAKER_1:  Drop of a hat.
SPEAKER_1:  yet they still also like did super primitive things. You know, they physically are still today lighting the main combustion chambers of the Soyuz engines of the RD-107 and RD-108 with essentially matchsticks. Like they literally stick a T-shaped.
SPEAKER_1:  thing up into the chamber.
SPEAKER_1:  and have a pyrotechnic in the...
SPEAKER_1:  in it that.
SPEAKER_1:  ignites the actual propellants in the combustion chamber.
SPEAKER_1:  is not the most elegant solution.
SPEAKER_1:  They're still using that. So they went from like-
SPEAKER_1:  the whole spectrum.
SPEAKER_1:  of like, it's a mixture of like, make it better, faster, harder, stronger.
SPEAKER_1:  Gooder.
SPEAKER_1:  all the way around.
SPEAKER_1:  to also if it ain't broke, don't fix it.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like it employs.
SPEAKER_1:  all of the above.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's like, it's a lot of innovation, but also they use duct tape.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like all of it together.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, aha, that's exactly like
SPEAKER_1:  That's exactly the way to put it. And they did things that are insane. They developed...
SPEAKER_1:  or full flow stage combustion cycle engine. This engine had it been used.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, it would have put the F, it was.
SPEAKER_1:  same relative size as the F1 engine on the Saturn V, in that same category, way up there of like, you know, 6.7.
SPEAKER_1:  like meganeutons of thrust or something around and then the f1 is like seven or something it's it's
SPEAKER_1:  Huge.
SPEAKER_1:  Yet.
SPEAKER_1:  Way more complicated, way more efficient, way...
SPEAKER_1:  just better engine in that sense.
SPEAKER_1:  as far as performance goes.
SPEAKER_1:  yet it never flew.
SPEAKER_1:  It never left the stand, you know, they never built the rocket around it.
SPEAKER_1:  The N1, which is the most powerful rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  to have flown so far to date.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  like it never made it through its first stage burn.
SPEAKER_1:  All four attempts failed spectacularly and yet...
SPEAKER_1:  It had so much technology on it that it was...
SPEAKER_1:  still unrivaled today almost. like finally now we're beating it.
SPEAKER_1:  the NK-33s that they developed for that rocket. Like, finally today.
SPEAKER_1:  were to the point of having better engines than they built in the 60s.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, what stands out to you from the N1?
SPEAKER_0:  family of rocket engines.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, it's interesting because the N1...
SPEAKER_1:  was the Kudsnetsov Design Bureau, and he was actually an aircraft manufacturer. So he's one of the first people outside of kind of the-
SPEAKER_1:  the missile and rocket program, you know, you had all these other
SPEAKER_1:  big wigs kind of in the
SPEAKER_1:  other OKBs that were developing missiles and rockets. And then all of a sudden here comes Nikolai Kutsnetsov who
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  never
SPEAKER_1:  developed a rocket engine. And so his first attempt at a rocket engine was the NK series, the NK-15, NK-33.
SPEAKER_1:  And they're amazing.
SPEAKER_1:  They were brilliant.
SPEAKER_1:  these wonderful closed cycle oxygen rich engines.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  that were awesome. There were awesome engines and that were.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, because...
SPEAKER_1:  I love that because he has direct
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  boss he eats since he wasn't necessarily in the in the aerospace, you know, or in the
SPEAKER_1:  I guess the rocket missile defense world.
SPEAKER_1:  He didn't have to.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  at the fall of the Soviet Union, he didn't have to give away all of his things to the same people as the other people.
SPEAKER_1:  So he hid, you know, like 80 of his engines.
SPEAKER_1:  In a hanger?
SPEAKER_1:  And then.
SPEAKER_1:  We still literally use them.
SPEAKER_1:  In the United States we used altogether, I think it was like eight or 10 of them.
SPEAKER_1:  repurpose them as they're called AJ-26s in the United States, but like we still were flying Soviet rocket engines.
SPEAKER_1:  in the 2000s.
SPEAKER_1:  because they were better than engines we are building today.
SPEAKER_1:  Like that's.
SPEAKER_1:  To me, that's my favorite fact about the N1. How can inse, is that there?..
SPEAKER_1:  Still that good.
SPEAKER_1:  They were the best choice for at the time.
SPEAKER_1:  orbital science.
SPEAKER_0:  of the culture that engineering has led to these things that still work. It's incredible. You said that the RD171 is one of the coolest engines ever made.
SPEAKER_0:  Why's that?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, also...
SPEAKER_1:  One of the fun things about.
SPEAKER_1:  the Soviet engines is it'll look like a lot of their engines look like multiple engines because you see multiple nozzles, you see multiple combustion chambers and you'd think
SPEAKER_1:  Obviously, you know the
SPEAKER_1:  Nozzle is the engine, right?
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  what they actually would do. The real the real heart.
SPEAKER_1:  and the real...
SPEAKER_1:  of the rocket engine actually comes from the turbo pumps, comes from the pumps themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  And as we talked about earlier, that includes the turbine and the actual...
SPEAKER_1:  pumps that
SPEAKER_1:  the propellant into the chambers.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  The Soviet Union was
SPEAKER_1:  incredible at developing these closed cycle high powered turbo pumps.
SPEAKER_1:  But if you try to scale the combustion chamber too big...
SPEAKER_1:  you end up with what's called...
SPEAKER_1:  combustion instability. You're having such a large surface area.
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  crazy flames and combustion happening, they can get these weird pockets and oscillations and frequencies and
SPEAKER_1:  and they just couldn't make big combustion chambers. They never figured it out. They never quite, well, they did actually kind of figure it out, but they.
SPEAKER_1:  They didn't like it. So they ended up just.
SPEAKER_1:  Shrinking.
SPEAKER_1:  down and having small combustion chambers and just sending splitting the pipes basically instead of
SPEAKER_1:  one fuel pump going into one pipe going into one.
SPEAKER_1:  combustion chamber and one oxidizer pipe going into one combustion chamber.
SPEAKER_1:  they'd split it off into two or four combustion chambers.
SPEAKER_1:  and kind of spread that work around so they didn't experience this combustion instability.
SPEAKER_1:  So the RD-171 is like.
SPEAKER_1:  still to date the most powerful rocket engine ever built.
SPEAKER_1:  The turbo pump is insane. I don't even remember how many.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, like 200,000 horsepower or something comes out of that turbo pump.
SPEAKER_1:  in order to flow the amount of propellant necessary at those rates and at those pressures into the combustion chamber. It has four chambers.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's just, it's just an absolute marvel of engineering.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and then the cool thing too is specifically the RD 171, its engine.
SPEAKER_1:  And all four of those nozzles can actually...
SPEAKER_1:  pivot and rotate. I just
SPEAKER_1:  Now, as I'm explaining this realized.
SPEAKER_1:  that has to mean that they have...
SPEAKER_1:  joints, like flexible joints in the...
SPEAKER_1:  high pressure pump lines.
SPEAKER_1:  In order to-
SPEAKER_1:  I never, this is the realization I'm having right now, because normally you put the gimbal.
SPEAKER_1:  above the turbo pump, like the mount where the engine swivels.
SPEAKER_1:  so that you have low pressure coming from the tanks into the pumps
SPEAKER_1:  And then you just have a straight, you know, fixed pipe.
SPEAKER_1:  flowing into the engine so you don't have to bend that pipe and have it be dynamic.
SPEAKER_1:  If they had the four chambers moving...
SPEAKER_1:  independently from each other.
SPEAKER_1:  That means those four chambers all had to have...
SPEAKER_1:  a flexible high pressure.
SPEAKER_1:  pipe going, which I don't even.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if that's, why am I just now realizing this? Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's engineering challenges with that
SPEAKER_1:  I never even thought that was a thing you would ever could do, honestly. I gotta look into why and how and what-
SPEAKER_0:  I wonder why that design decision was made.
SPEAKER_1:  So the easier thing to do normally is you would keep those nozzles fixed, and then a fixed like say the Soyuz engine, the RD-107 and 108, they have a fixed main combustion chambers and they use these little vernier.
SPEAKER_1:  Some people got mad at me for saying Vernier and Werner.
SPEAKER_1:  engines that swivel themselves and those provide your control authority.
SPEAKER_1:  so that the main chambers stay fixed and then you get your roll and your pitch and you're yaw out of auxiliary thrusters.
SPEAKER_0:  By the way, did you get anything wrong in that video?
SPEAKER_0:  that people told you about. Well, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I have a few things, yep.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  First off, we had a graphic error where we actually, we copied and pasted a lot of our After Effects projects.
SPEAKER_1:  So our nuclear engines, one of them on screen says that it runs on RP-1, it does not. It has basically all the wrong stats.
SPEAKER_1:  We just didn't catch it in the edit, that we literally copy and paste it in.
SPEAKER_1:  I say it right on screen, but the-
SPEAKER_1:  and the voiceover, but on screen it's wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  The other thing, and I'm excited to ask you about this.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh oh. I watched and I spoke with a lot of Russian speaking individuals, we had a lot of research assistants that were reading and blah blah blah.
SPEAKER_1:  I tried really hard to learn how to pronounce.
SPEAKER_1:  Sergey.
SPEAKER_1:  Karel- Karelios name.
SPEAKER_1:  And I'm still gonna say it wrong no matter what, but my understanding. Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  And from-
SPEAKER_1:  listening to native speakers is closer to.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  than it is Corlew.
SPEAKER_0:  Jau, visada, Sergei Pavlovich Koralev.
SPEAKER_1:  See, I will never say it that perfectly, but I know it's not just Corlew. I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  Again, the English.
SPEAKER_1:  translation of it likely I should have just said
SPEAKER_1:  Core 11 said, I'm saying it.
SPEAKER_1:  the dumb America way, but.
SPEAKER_0:  But you rolled your R. Hehehehe! Comrade!
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, excellent. So.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, let me just ask you the difference in culture because you've researched so many rockers and
SPEAKER_0:  so many different eras, the set of five, just everything you're seeing now.
SPEAKER_0:  Are there some interesting differences, especially when you look at the space rays?
SPEAKER_0:  between um...
SPEAKER_0:  The Soviet.
SPEAKER_0:  rocket engineers and efforts versus the American.
SPEAKER_1:  There's, I mean there's...
SPEAKER_1:  Definitely huge, huge.
SPEAKER_1:  cultural changes. And the fun thing is that they kind of spawned.
SPEAKER_1:  from the same, they have the same starting place. Both, you know, Soviet.
SPEAKER_1:  rocket engines, and Americans.
SPEAKER_1:  all came from the Nazi V2 rocket and the A4 engine.
SPEAKER_1:  literally physically spawned from that because at the fall of, you know, at the end of World War II.
SPEAKER_1:  We took a handful of German scientists and the Soviets took a handful of German scientists.
SPEAKER_1:  And they both.
SPEAKER_1:  got their own a little bit, some blueprints here and there, and the others got some blue. So we literally have the same, it's a weird thing where we're starting from the same like.
SPEAKER_1:  and letting two divergent paths go.
SPEAKER_1:  crazy on their own development. So it's really fun to see the cultural differences.
SPEAKER_1:  One of the things the United States did is they really would kind of take an engine.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  and just.
SPEAKER_1:  perfect it more or less and then.
SPEAKER_1:  and not really evolve that much.
SPEAKER_1:  They I don't know and I don't know why I actually need to do a history lesson on all of the US entrance, but it's literally like.
SPEAKER_1:  as far as orbital class engines before now.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like.
SPEAKER_1:  a dozen or two.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's a tenth the amount of...
SPEAKER_1:  the Soviets.
SPEAKER_1:  and the Soviets just literally made up a new engine.
SPEAKER_1:  every time they had a new like s-
SPEAKER_1:  They wouldn't uh-
SPEAKER_1:  And it was like a completely different engine. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  I wonder if there's some aspect to the culture. I don't want to overstate it, but uh...
SPEAKER_0:  There is more of a safety culture, I think, in the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think if you care about safety.
SPEAKER_0:  or rather like.
SPEAKER_0:  You have.
SPEAKER_0:  You're more risk averse. Yeah, so you care about safety more about the value of human life. There is taken there
SPEAKER_0:  So just wealth a bit.
SPEAKER_0:  you will iterate less. So I think that's so yes, especially in the early aspects of the program. I don't want to overstate this is.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of it is just...
SPEAKER_0:  through stories, you just hear anecdotes.
SPEAKER_0:  There are more.
SPEAKER_0:  willing to take risks. Yeah. Human life risks with space.
SPEAKER_1:  For example, the first.
SPEAKER_1:  orbital space flights from the Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_1:  The cosmonaut had to
SPEAKER_1:  eject out of the capsule and parachute to a landing. Yes. Not very well known.
SPEAKER_1:  And it wasn't, they hid that even from history as best they could at first because they were
SPEAKER_1:  slightly ashamed that they couldn't have a full recovery system with their spacecraft.
SPEAKER_1:  They could physically recover it, but they wouldn't have been able to recover the cosmonaut in one piece. So instead they had them just eject out of the thing and parachute to safety. Like...
SPEAKER_1:  That's insane. And so there definitely was some, some extra risks and
SPEAKER_1:  but also a freedom to just like.
SPEAKER_1:  push things to the limits and try everything. I threw all the spaghetti on.
SPEAKER_0:  It's funny that most people probably don't even know the first person in the space in America and obviously everybody knows that in
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, um...
SPEAKER_0:  It's kind of interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  How the Space Race
SPEAKER_0:  and even World War II.
SPEAKER_0:  even like the history books.
SPEAKER_0:  You ask most Americans.
SPEAKER_0:  They think.
SPEAKER_0:  that America won World War II.
SPEAKER_0:  without America, like the real heroes of World War II.
SPEAKER_0:  is America-esque.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... british people
SPEAKER_0:  They say, and everybody has a pretty good justification. like...without!
SPEAKER_0:  Britain.
SPEAKER_0:  without Churchill.
SPEAKER_0:  Hitler would have taken over the world.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably the strongest case is the Soviet Union case that they're the ones that won the war.
SPEAKER_0:  The reason it's the strongest case is where most of the fighting happened. Most of the death happened. Most of like most of the destruction, but everyone has their perspective. And certainly in the space race.
SPEAKER_0:  you know the great accomplishment is the first man moon
SPEAKER_0:  consent
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah
SPEAKER_0:  And then Yuri Gagarin from the Russian perspective, first man in space. And that I think still persists in some of that.
SPEAKER_0:  in healthy forms is probably constructive to a little bit of competition pushes all the all the great scientists on each side
SPEAKER_0:  uh... bring you know what do you think about
SPEAKER_0:  this Yorga Gagarin mission of the first human in space.
SPEAKER_0:  and the Vostok mission in 1961. Just in general, when you look back at that time, leading to the...
SPEAKER_0:  the first man on the moon.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, April 12th, 1961.
SPEAKER_1:  Yuri's night baby, that's a-
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's insane. What's insane to me is...
SPEAKER_1:  the first.
SPEAKER_1:  in space didn't just go to space, he went into orbit. Hmm.
SPEAKER_1:  flew around the Earth in orbit and reentered.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a monumental task compared to suborbital.
SPEAKER_1:  So the United States did two suborbital flights in that same year, I believe in that same year at least.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm pretty sure in 1961 they flew.
SPEAKER_1:  for the first time orbitally in 1962. So they weren't terribly far behind to get a human into orbit, like in the grand scheme of things, 10 months difference.
SPEAKER_1:  But at the same time, like the fact that the Soviet Union just went straight to flying someone into orbit is-
SPEAKER_1:  Monumental.
SPEAKER_0:  and I'm sure they did not do excessive.
SPEAKER_0:  rigorous testing here.
SPEAKER_0:  Because there is a space race and you have the first
SPEAKER_0:  is important.
SPEAKER_0:  Just imagine being Yuri.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you say when they're like launching them like, let's go or something like a.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, you're taking, we're talking about you being on Starship. You're taking a pretty big risk.
SPEAKER_0:  being launched out.
SPEAKER_1:  into orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  hopefully a lot less risk than what Yuri went through. So Yuri, the crazy thing, remember those matchsticks we talked about? Yeah. There's 20 main combustion chambers on Soyuz and there's
SPEAKER_1:  for
SPEAKER_1:  hit 12 more vernier engines that all need to be lit.
SPEAKER_1:  So you're sitting on top of this booster.
SPEAKER_1:  and they light all of those 32 combustion chambers.
SPEAKER_1:  On the ground.
SPEAKER_1:  And then.
SPEAKER_1:  It has this insane separation process between.
SPEAKER_1:  but the Soviet Union would call it the first stage and the second stages, but we would call it like the core stage and the boosters.
SPEAKER_1:  They all...
SPEAKER_1:  Four of these boosters have to peel away perfectly from the core stage.
SPEAKER_1:  simultaneously. You know, if one of them sticks on.
SPEAKER_1:  mission failed if one of them
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't inject properly and drags into the other tank, you know, you're, it's, it's, it's a goner.
SPEAKER_1:  So the staging process of...
SPEAKER_1:  of the Soyuz is insane to me that that ended up working out.
SPEAKER_1:  I-I was just-
SPEAKER_1:  technology in stories and I mean more or less that same rocket is what's still flying.
SPEAKER_1:  humans.
SPEAKER_1:  that are cosmonauts from the universe cosmos.
SPEAKER_1:  going to the International Space Station, are flying on a variant of that Soyuz rocket still today.
SPEAKER_1:  It's still.
SPEAKER_1:  like that big of a workhorse.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think about Russ Cosmos as he stands today?
SPEAKER_0:  its history and its future.
SPEAKER_0:  in comparison to...
SPEAKER_0:  NASA and other national efforts.
SPEAKER_0:  and in comparison to commercial space flight.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, utmost respect for the engineers involved and everything that's happened. I think Enurgemosh is like still some of the, one of the greatest engine manufacturers.
SPEAKER_1:  when they have the funding to do so, but man, it seems like they're, they're.
SPEAKER_1:  falling from grace as far as space prowess, you know, that Rosh Kosmos went from.
SPEAKER_1:  I think they got very comfortable at the top of, you know, from 2011 until 2020, they were the only ride to the International Space Station.
SPEAKER_1:  since then, like it started, I feel like in 2018.
SPEAKER_1:  Honestly, I think that's kind of when things, that's the first time I specifically remember a.
SPEAKER_1:  pretty nasty thing happened in 2018. I think it was a Soyuz mission.
SPEAKER_1:  to the International Space Station had one of the boosters not detached.
SPEAKER_1:  and had to have an abort.
SPEAKER_1:  but.
SPEAKER_1:  You know that that happened then all of a sudden next thing you know, there's a progress being docked to the ISS a couple of years ago that spun the ISS cartwheeled the ISS out of control.
SPEAKER_1:  followed a few months later the Pirs module, docks to the International Space Station, spirals the International Space Station out of control again with like a thruster getting fixed on.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a hole in-
SPEAKER_1:  in Russian.
SPEAKER_1:  segment. There's, well, I think the most recent one right now, there's a Soyuz dock to the ISS that has a puncture in it.
SPEAKER_1:  leaking coolant.
SPEAKER_1:  and will not be returning humans.
SPEAKER_1:  on it so they're actually having to fly up and uncrewed soyus.
SPEAKER_1:  And that one likely wasn't a manufacturing error. It probably was like a micrometeorite puncture.
SPEAKER_1:  rendering spacecraft unusable? We don't know for sure yet.
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  but...
SPEAKER_1:  It's just really been like this fall from grace where...
SPEAKER_1:  They have all the potential, they have some of the best engines, some of the...
SPEAKER_1:  the best rockets and especially like right before.
SPEAKER_1:  The collapse of the Soviet Union, the, the Braun.
SPEAKER_1:  shuttle and the Energia rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  were incredible. Had they been able to evolve that into Brontu and the reusable Energia? They had a fully reusable.
SPEAKER_1:  Energia on the drawing board and like
SPEAKER_1:  honestly fully think they could have done it.
SPEAKER_0:  Is it possible to return to a place where there is friendly competition between nations that ultimately benefit us?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  unites and inspires the peoples of these different worlds, these very different worlds.
SPEAKER_0:  have especially recently come to conflict over the war in Ukraine. eBay, yes,
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  The war, the conflict, the suffering.
SPEAKER_0:  is actually creating more and more division, creating more and more hate.
SPEAKER_0:  I think as we've talked about, I think science and engineering.
SPEAKER_0:  and especially the most epic version of engineering, which is...
SPEAKER_0:  Rocketry and space travel unites people.
SPEAKER_0:  the United States.
SPEAKER_0:  conflict and war.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you have a hope that...
SPEAKER_0:  we can return to that place.
SPEAKER_1:  I think historically.
SPEAKER_1:  Space Flight.
SPEAKER_1:  has been one of the most bonding.
SPEAKER_1:  things..
SPEAKER_1:  We have countless examples of.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, Cold War enemies coming together and...
SPEAKER_1:  working together, lending a hand.
SPEAKER_1:  Apollo 13, for example, of course, there is the potential that...
SPEAKER_1:  Who knew where it was gonna reenter since it was not in the plane trajectory at all for reentry?
SPEAKER_1:  And the Soviet Union said, hey, wherever...
SPEAKER_1:  wherever they land, like we'll help you guys out basically. You know, and that was a pretty big thing at the time, obviously.
SPEAKER_1:  We also in 1975 saw the Apollo Soyuz.
SPEAKER_1:  mission which was Apollo spacecraft docking with Soyuz.
SPEAKER_1:  spacecraft.
SPEAKER_1:  first time there's international collaboration. And again, 1975 still-
SPEAKER_1:  very admits the Cold War.
SPEAKER_1:  yet we have this collaboration.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know what else could have done that.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I mean, and think about what it actually takes to do that. You have to come up with a-
SPEAKER_1:  a docking module that is, you know, like.
SPEAKER_1:  takes the two different air environments and the two different docking systems.
SPEAKER_1:  talk to the engineers and mission planners figure out you know train together
SPEAKER_1:  Cosmonauts and the astronauts trained together and got to know each other. Crossing boundaries and borders.
SPEAKER_1:  and coming together for this mission. And even if it was totally a fluff piece, like even if it was totally this like-
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  cynical
SPEAKER_1:  You know, just...
SPEAKER_1:  trying to make a pretty face for everybody, for the cameras or something.
SPEAKER_1:  Obviously it still had an impact.
SPEAKER_0:  The symbolic impact.
SPEAKER_0:  But there's also the practical impact. I mean, a lot of people have to work together. Yes. And that has a ripple effect on the culture of the different engineers.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  100%. And even just the astronauts and cosmonauts involved.
SPEAKER_1:  Think about what probably went through their heads during this process of like going from, oh my God, I'm gonna have to work with them to.
SPEAKER_1:  getting to know them and then sharing meals in space. Like, that's-
SPEAKER_1:  a crazy transformation of timelines and.
SPEAKER_1:  I would love to, I-
SPEAKER_1:  I do think that space flight has the ability to bond us and unite us because it is
SPEAKER_1:  Ultimately, you know this little.
SPEAKER_1:  tiny little planet we're floating around on.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it is the boundary that we all share.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you only can.
SPEAKER_1:  It only takes you getting off this planet to realize, Oh my God.
SPEAKER_1:  We're all neighbors.
SPEAKER_1:  We're all living in the same house together.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  I do think ultimately, you know, as we continue to expand our horizons and expand our exploration that it
SPEAKER_1:  has the potential to unite us more than.
SPEAKER_1:  then it has the potential to divide us.
SPEAKER_0:  So one of the potential conflicts of the 21st century.
SPEAKER_0:  that
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone wants to avoid both in the cyberspace and in the hot war space cold war hot war all kinds of war
SPEAKER_0:  all kinds of economic
SPEAKER_0:  conflict between the United States and China.
SPEAKER_0:  So China is...
SPEAKER_0:  going full steam ahead in developing a space program, doing a lot of incredible work.
SPEAKER_0:  Like you mentioned, 64 launches in 2022.
SPEAKER_0:  with two failures.
SPEAKER_0:  but moving straight ahead.
SPEAKER_1:  And by the way, we had a lot of startups, like a lot of the launches were from brand new companies.
SPEAKER_1:  to have two failures out of 64, I mean that's still.
SPEAKER_1:  If you look at operational launches, it was.
SPEAKER_0:  Follow us.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you see a pathway?
SPEAKER_0:  where there's again in that same way collaboration.
SPEAKER_0:  or friendly competition between...
SPEAKER_0:  all the different companies and nations in the united states and china
SPEAKER_0:  in the next.
SPEAKER_0:  as we push towards the moon.
SPEAKER_0:  Mars
SPEAKER_0:  and beyond.
SPEAKER_1:  I held a dumb hope that-
SPEAKER_1:  China would actually be allowed to sign on to the Artemis Accord.
SPEAKER_1:  to be able to take part in this next step towards the moon.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, just imagine if, like, if they...
SPEAKER_1:  provided a propulsion module or a land or something and we actually came together to land on the Moon.
SPEAKER_1:  instead of having another space race, you know, it's like.
SPEAKER_1:  It would have been so cool and.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I still am hopeful that.
SPEAKER_1:  similar to...
SPEAKER_1:  to back in the...
SPEAKER_1:  Cold War that
SPEAKER_1:  We might have something like that someday where we actually are.
SPEAKER_1:  collaborating and it feels like sometimes we're really close to that and then other times it feels like we're
SPEAKER_1:  really far from that and it just sucks because I know, and you know, I try really hard on my channel to.
SPEAKER_1:  to always separate and celebrate the work being done. Because at the end of the day, there's someone.
SPEAKER_1:  that's just going home to their family.
SPEAKER_1:  clocking in hours, working really hard on.
SPEAKER_1:  pushing their program and...
SPEAKER_1:  and doing engineering work, you know, and it's.
SPEAKER_1:  We don't get to choose where we're born and what we're born into
SPEAKER_1:  So I really like to avoid
SPEAKER_1:  you know, the political aspects of things and the geopolitical aspects and just appreciate the science.
SPEAKER_1:  and the science we're seeing and the.
SPEAKER_1:  The progress that China's doing in the last 10 years is very akin to that.
SPEAKER_1:  early spaceflight programs and with the runway of like just going keep on going. Like I see no reason for them to be slowing down.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's definitely something to watch and.
SPEAKER_1:  and be interested in and.
SPEAKER_1:  Who knows? There really genuinely might be-
SPEAKER_1:  erased to the moon again, and there really genuinely might be a race to Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  The part of me is excited.
SPEAKER_0:  about that cause
SPEAKER_0:  a racist is.
SPEAKER_1:  Pretty cool.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  but hopefully it's friendly competition and some collaboration. It is true that maybe I'm being a bit cynical.
SPEAKER_0:  but nations.
SPEAKER_0:  sometimes the governments and leaders of those governments sometimes ruin things.
SPEAKER_0:  Like you don't often have...
SPEAKER_0:  Statistically speaking, it's harder to have a leader of a nation.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  looks beyond the political, the particular political bickering of that nation.
SPEAKER_0:  And you have like a JFK type character that really steps up and aspires.
SPEAKER_0:  I think statistically speaking it's better to have someone like Elon who's the leader of a company, like a commercial effort.
SPEAKER_0:  that is able to look beyond the borders of nations.
SPEAKER_0:  and certainly inspiring educators like yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  to look beyond.
SPEAKER_0:  the borders.
SPEAKER_0:  of those nations and the geopolitical conflicts and so on.
SPEAKER_0:  to inspire the...
SPEAKER_0:  and to inspire people. I think that's just made so much easier.
SPEAKER_0:  you can have more reach.
SPEAKER_0:  Tim.
SPEAKER_0:  Tim Dodd can have more reach than NASA.
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of inspiring the world and that's fascinating.
SPEAKER_0:  that gives power to the individuals that see past.
SPEAKER_0:  the silly short-term geopolitical conflicts.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the whole police.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you worry that there might be a war?
SPEAKER_0:  in space.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, let's let's let's look out into the future. So forget
SPEAKER_0:  So the interesting thing about these rockets, right? Let's not forget.
SPEAKER_0:  Rockets do what Rockets do.
SPEAKER_0:  that they can carry payloads that can be weapons.
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Do you worry about this?
SPEAKER_1:  I worry most about.
SPEAKER_1:  space wars as leading to the Kessler syndrome of having.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  cascading effect of like a spacecraft blowing up and then
SPEAKER_1:  infecting another spacecraft and that blows up and then all of a sudden you're trapped.
SPEAKER_1:  and have this debris cloud that we can't.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, go, we can't go into space anymore. Like that's my biggest, because frankly, at this point, we could annihilate ourselves with terrestrial.
SPEAKER_1:  stuff anyway, you know what I mean? We don't need space to
SPEAKER_1:  To end society as we know it, you know what I mean?
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  But.
SPEAKER_1:  We do.
SPEAKER_1:  We could really and the good thing is I think everyone, well, mostly everyone.
SPEAKER_1:  seems to understand this for the most part that like.
SPEAKER_1:  really can't be risking.
SPEAKER_1:  blowing up stuff in space in low Earth orbit because
SPEAKER_1:  it could easily, like we could strain ourselves from space assets for 50 years.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, can you elaborate on that? So like, what is the danger of the debris there that could-
SPEAKER_0:  But jeopardize.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  For instance, and it was only a couple of years ago, Russia did an anti-satellite test on a-
SPEAKER_1:  on an orbital.
SPEAKER_1:  There is a, we've done this, the US has done this. Like I'm not.
SPEAKER_1:  pinning it on them, but.
SPEAKER_1:  We kind of know nowadays, like, don't do anti-satellite tests on orbital things because those things stay in orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, when you blow something up in space, it's not like...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, people think, you know, in space, like, oh, you throw something, it's just gonna keep going forever and ever and ever. It's way good.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, that's in the sense that it's not going to be slowed down due to air resistance, it's going to continue to do that, but it's staying in orbit around the earth.
SPEAKER_1:  You just slightly change the orbit of it around Earth when you throw a ball.
SPEAKER_1:  or something, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  The scary thing is, when you blow up a satellite...
SPEAKER_1:  all those pieces of that satellite are now...
SPEAKER_1:  millions of bullets.
SPEAKER_1:  in a halo around the Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  in a very specific.
SPEAKER_1:  Halo, you know, so.
SPEAKER_1:  Some things get blown up faster, according to its orbit, so they'll go a little bit higher elliptically.
SPEAKER_1:  Something's good.
SPEAKER_1:  slowed down in that explosion and actually re-entered.
SPEAKER_1:  Some things would go sideways and change its inclination of that orbit. You have this debris field.
SPEAKER_1:  but it more or less becomes.
SPEAKER_1:  a band of like...
SPEAKER_1:  No, no, like a big scary.
SPEAKER_1:  sharp scary bullets.
SPEAKER_1:  that can destroy another spacecraft.
SPEAKER_1:  And so all of a sudden, especially now Starlink, and we're talking about thousands and thousands and thousands of satellites in space,
SPEAKER_1:  If all of a sudden...
SPEAKER_1:  one you know a couple of them crash and
SPEAKER_1:  blow up and obviously have all the shrapnel going everywhere and then that hits another satellite that creates shrapnel. You can literally blanket our entire low Earth orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  et nul.
SPEAKER_1:  17,500 mile an hour.
SPEAKER_1:  bullets.
SPEAKER_1:  We're talking the kinetic energy in this.
SPEAKER_1:  is so hard for people to fathom, because that's...
SPEAKER_1:  Over 10 times faster than most.
SPEAKER_1:  like rifle bullets, and even like a big 50 cal.
SPEAKER_1:  is not going to be, you know, we're still talking about about 10%.
SPEAKER_1:  that so you think about the kinetic energy.
SPEAKER_1:  It's insane, so.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, fleck of paint.
SPEAKER_1:  can go through panes of glass.
SPEAKER_1:  at that velocity.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, a little piece of metal can puncture.
SPEAKER_1:  straight through.
SPEAKER_0:  So, like...
SPEAKER_0:  So our actions that seem.
SPEAKER_0:  small-scale military actions.
SPEAKER_0:  can have a...
SPEAKER_0:  can have dire detrimental.
SPEAKER_0:  effects to the whole space program, like global space program. Oh yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  It can affect.
SPEAKER_1:  Everything and everyone.
SPEAKER_0:  Including the like including satellites. Oh, yeah
SPEAKER_1:  Especially satellites like that's
SPEAKER_1:  The good and the bad thing is...
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of satellites don't operate in low-earth orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  Like a lot of the ones that we use day to day, a lot of them are.
SPEAKER_1:  in medium Earth orbit like the GPS or their geostationary.
SPEAKER_1:  which are way, way, way out there.
SPEAKER_1:  And because of that, they...
SPEAKER_1:  won't really ever de-orbit, or like it'll take millennia to de-orbit because just because something's in space doesn't mean it's there forever, especially like in low-earth orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  The atmosphere doesn't just suddenly stop. It's not like you hit.
SPEAKER_1:  the Carmen line, 100 kilometers, and all of a sudden there's zero atmosphere. The atmosphere just slowly tapers. You can experience that yourself as you climb a mountain.
SPEAKER_1:  slowly realize there's less and less air. just keep going.
SPEAKER_1:  And just because you're in space 200, 300 kilometers up.
SPEAKER_1:  There's still trace.
SPEAKER_1:  Molecules, you know, there's the occasional
SPEAKER_1:  There's the occasional nitrogen molecule.
SPEAKER_1:  And so that is actually drag. So as a spacecraft in lower orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  depending on its altitude, will...
SPEAKER_1:  Take anywhere from.
SPEAKER_1:  Five years to-
SPEAKER_1:  months to de orbit you know or
SPEAKER_1:  months or one month, depending on its orbit or its altitude.
SPEAKER_1:  we'll have some parasitic drag still and slowly.
SPEAKER_1:  throughout time slowdown, which lowers its orbit, which...
SPEAKER_1:  drags it down more, lowers its orbit, and etc. etc. until it re-enters.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  If we end up with.
SPEAKER_1:  some kind of catastrophic event where the entire low-earth orbit has been inundated and blown up.
SPEAKER_1:  It'll take months for the first band to clear up.
SPEAKER_1:  It'll take years for something like, there's charts, people have all this stuff available.
SPEAKER_1:  you shouldn't look at us there
SPEAKER_0:  terrifying by the way.
SPEAKER_0:  But this is really... THE
SPEAKER_1:  But again, the caveat is...
SPEAKER_1:  For the most part, the low Earth orbit stuff would clear up.
SPEAKER_1:  within years.
SPEAKER_1:  so we could get back to doing some more with it. Starlink stuff would probably be able to be re-
SPEAKER_1:  And you know, we could.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of redo it and build up from the ground up again.
SPEAKER_1:  GPS wouldn't be wiped out and our geostationary satellites wouldn't be wiped out. The scary thing is we wouldn't be able to relaunch.
SPEAKER_1:  and replace new things because we're stuck.
SPEAKER_1:  We're not going to fly through that debris field, you know?
SPEAKER_0:  And we avoid that by avoiding military actions in space.
SPEAKER_1:  And these days, there's more and more.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  requirements and legislation and especially trying to get international collaboration on having end of life plans for satellites.
SPEAKER_1:  that satellites, especially those in low Earth orbit.
SPEAKER_1:  have like drag devices to increase them. Once they're done, they literally pull like, even just a ribbon, like a-
SPEAKER_1:  silly little like, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  40 foot long ribbon, we'll sit there and it'll slowly, or it can.
SPEAKER_1:  speed up its reentry process by months or years or whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  So we're starting to see that this is now an importance. There's a really cool company called Stoke Aerospace out in.
SPEAKER_1:  Washington is one of these launch providers that's really looking not into just trying to be the next SpaceX launch company.
SPEAKER_1:  They're really seeing satellite.
SPEAKER_1:  Bringing stuff down from space.
SPEAKER_1:  is actually being, especially right now, we have all of these.
SPEAKER_1:  hundreds and thousands of satellites being launched every year.
SPEAKER_1:  someone at some point is probably gonna have to do some cleanup.
SPEAKER_1:  And so they're looking at being one of those companies to do that.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... what do you think of a starling
SPEAKER_0:  and the efforts of Starlink.
SPEAKER_0:  to put a very large number of...
SPEAKER_0:  satellites.
SPEAKER_0:  out there and provide internet access to.
SPEAKER_0:  to anyone.
SPEAKER_0:  ,  anyways.
SPEAKER_1:  Generally, I think Starlink is.
SPEAKER_1:  Phenomenal.
SPEAKER_1:  And I would be saying this if it was any company I wanna make that clear that people think I'm just some, you know, SpaceX fan boy or something and anything they do is perfect.
SPEAKER_0:  I think as your fan, I could say you're basically a fan.
SPEAKER_0:  a fanboy or just a fan of.
SPEAKER_0:  everybody that's doing space stuff. And even in this whole conversation, there's no way we cover like 10% of what I wanted to talk to you about, so we're jumping around. I mean, there's, we could talk probably for another.
SPEAKER_0:  an hour about Artemis.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, we could talk about anything with ULA, obviously the all the other.
SPEAKER_0:  all the other commercial efforts. We could talk about the NASA efforts that, you know, the.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, and sat in five, like, are we gonna really go with this conversation? I thought most of it, and we might, okay? So like, anyway, you're a fan of everything.
SPEAKER_0:  Starling.
SPEAKER_0:  is in general exciting.
SPEAKER_1:  to you and not for the space assets, but just the potential for humanity. I really think even as a consumer of the internet.
SPEAKER_1:  personally, our studio space down in Texas.
SPEAKER_1:  We're stuck with
SPEAKER_1:  with MediaCom.
SPEAKER_1:  which has like
SPEAKER_1:  the least reliable internet service.
SPEAKER_1:  Period, that's the only option. Either that or they're trying to charge me like $20,000.
SPEAKER_1:  to run a fiber optic.
SPEAKER_1:  cable like a thousand meters or something like it's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's insane.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not going to do that.
SPEAKER_1:  I bought Starlink.
SPEAKER_1:  helps.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's still not amazing, but you can see where this is going in a year, two, three, five years.
SPEAKER_1:  They're like, oh, I can totally screw this other internet provider and this is now.
SPEAKER_1:  By far the best option.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's available literally anywhere. You don't have to be.
SPEAKER_1:  limited to your local internet service provider.
SPEAKER_1:  And on the global scale, of course you have, you know, people.
SPEAKER_1:  be able to learn and learn about rockets, learn about.
SPEAKER_1:  water management and architecture and...
SPEAKER_1:  city planning and fitness and health.
SPEAKER_1:  all of the modern conveniences that we Google every single day, there's people that don't have access to that.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I'm a self-taught rocket nerd.
SPEAKER_1:  I would not be who I am if it wasn't for the internet in the last seven years, you know? I would have been my own friend if I haven't for nine seven years.
SPEAKER_0:  So unlocking the intellectual potential of places like Africa, of rural areas that don't currently have internet access.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a genuine, that's a huge...
SPEAKER_1:  That's like.
SPEAKER_1:  Humanitarian 101 is give people access to information.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I think we have this.
SPEAKER_1:  potential to try to step in and fix other people's problems. The reality is people are smart.
SPEAKER_1:  No matter where you are, you give them the resources to learn, they're going to solve problems.
SPEAKER_1:  They're gonna problem solve, they're gonna engineer, they're going to.
SPEAKER_1:  If you don't give them access to that information, they're going to be stuck in there.
SPEAKER_1:  And there are cycles, you know, and.
SPEAKER_1:  So I think the potential for Starlink is incredible. I think it's already impactful. It's already affecting.
SPEAKER_1:  people in rural and indigenous areas, and it's already affecting.
SPEAKER_1:  businesses and all that stuff, I think it's great.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it.
SPEAKER_1:  is.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there's some downsides with astronomy.
SPEAKER_1:  with ground-based astronomy that it can hinder.
SPEAKER_1:  observations from the ground.
SPEAKER_1:  There's already a lot of communications between SpaceX and
SPEAKER_1:  astronomical societies and
SPEAKER_1:  things like that because it is a real concern. It can ruin observations, it can ruin data.
SPEAKER_1:  But like one of the big ones, for instance, recently, I think a new
SPEAKER_1:  they're going to be working into is that currently if a Starlink is flying over
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  over a ground-based asset.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of ground telescopes actually have a laser.
SPEAKER_1:  goes up and it measures the atmospheric distortion. And the telescopes literally sit there and-
SPEAKER_1:  by the millisecond fixes.
SPEAKER_1:  like changes the focus and
SPEAKER_1:  fixes those atmospheric distortions.
SPEAKER_1:  and that laser can interfere with satellites.
SPEAKER_1:  So previously, I'm pretty sure that SpaceX actually had to.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, request that.
SPEAKER_1:  As they're flying over these satellites, there are these telescopes that turn off the laser.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  when you have...
SPEAKER_1:  tens of thousands of these things flying, you're going to be turning off the laser more than it's on, you know, and just being this insanely inconvenient thing.
SPEAKER_1:  because you're gonna have these junctions happen often.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think one of the things that SpaceX is like, okay, no, no, no, you guys keep the laser on, we'll deal with your laser.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Good, good stuff, you know, things like that, mitigating the brightness of them so they're not visible.
SPEAKER_1:  Under most conditions, of course, like there's still always going to be visible in some.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  But then ultimately for me, it's like this, you have this weird-
SPEAKER_1:  like almost like a puberty of space flight and.
SPEAKER_1:  and astronomy.
SPEAKER_1:  where currently it's not cheap enough to really do a ton of.
SPEAKER_1:  incredible science or space based telescopes. We have web, we have.
SPEAKER_1:  Hubble, we have all these other.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, awesome.
SPEAKER_1:  Space-based telescopes, Chandra, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Etc, etc, whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  You are.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's still so expensive to launch them.
SPEAKER_1:  that were still so reliant on our ground telescopes. But in the future...
SPEAKER_1:  You can see a world where...
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, this is so-
SPEAKER_1:  We'll just launch like we can launch 50
SPEAKER_1:  James Webb Space Telescope size telescopes this year for
SPEAKER_1:  half the price of doing it on Earth, you know, and get way better data.
SPEAKER_1:  So in the future, I think in 20, 30 years, we'll look at it and be like, Oh man, that was an awkward time where.
SPEAKER_1:  space assets were interfering with astronomy.
SPEAKER_1:  But I think in the future, it's like, can you imagine doing space astronomy from the ground?
SPEAKER_1:  That's insane, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  There could be complexities to just having that many, just another topic. So complexities associated with having so many satellites.
SPEAKER_0:  especially with competing companies and competing nations.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you see that as an issue having tens of thousands, hundreds of thousands of satellites?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. It becomes a very interesting robotics.
SPEAKER_0:  collision avoidance problem.
SPEAKER_1:  The one thing to keep in mind...
SPEAKER_1:  is perspective, like I know 10,000 satellites and 20,000 and 100,000 satellites.
SPEAKER_1:  Sounds insane and it sounds really scary.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, just even look at how many planes are in the air at any given time.
SPEAKER_1:  Planes are bigger, they're flying slower, which actually means there's a greater chance of collision. If you think about two objects...
SPEAKER_1:  occupying space if they're ones moving really fast like imagine trying to
SPEAKER_1:  throw two basketballs at each other relatively easy.
SPEAKER_1:  Now try shooting two bullets at each other.
SPEAKER_1:  and having like, you know, at 90 degrees from each other.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to have your timing down like.
SPEAKER_1:  Really perfect to do that.
SPEAKER_1:  Now take that times 10, you know, and these objects are taking up.
SPEAKER_1:  physical space.
SPEAKER_1:  very small amount of time. They're relatively small, like most satellites are not very big.
SPEAKER_1:  and they have limitless altitudes to deal with. So-
SPEAKER_1:  even though you can have what look like convergences, they can be 10, 20, 50, 100 kilometers difference often. And they're dealing with this, all the...
SPEAKER_1:  All space assets know.
SPEAKER_1:  Hey, I'm at this orbital plane and this blah blah blah blah, and they know their altitudes and know their safe distances and have these margins built in.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's space, so there's like an insane amount of room.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's a lot of margin. There's a lot of margin.
SPEAKER_1:  But of course you can't.
SPEAKER_1:  excuse that all the way, like you have to still.
SPEAKER_1:  have plans and.
SPEAKER_1:  be considering that and considering collisions and considering.
SPEAKER_1:  all of the above.
SPEAKER_0:  When do you think the first human being will step foot on?
SPEAKER_0:  You don't like timelines?
SPEAKER_0:  But is this something, and you're very much focused on...
SPEAKER_0:  kind of the short term.
SPEAKER_0:  of incredible progress that's happening, and that makes total sense.
SPEAKER_0:  But there is the Mars plan.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  Was it the?
SPEAKER_0:  origin of the commercial spaceflight efforts.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, do you still see and dream about that day?
SPEAKER_1:  Let me be clear that I don't want to go to Mars. But I do think-
SPEAKER_1:  If you're making me guess a timeline for when humans will walk on Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  I even a year ago, I still would have said by the end of 2020, like.
SPEAKER_1:  2020th decade, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  Um, so by December.
SPEAKER_1:  31st, 2029.
SPEAKER_1:  Thought humans would have walked on Mars. I'm starting to think.
SPEAKER_1:  That's still too optimistic.
SPEAKER_1:  But I do, I...
SPEAKER_1:  Definitely think by 2040.
SPEAKER_1:  I for sure think that. I really think.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just hard to predict that curve, you know, that project out that curve. We're gonna go from feeling like it's impossible to like it's feeling like it's inevitable. You know, it's.
SPEAKER_0:  It could be another by the end of this decade JFK type moment, especially if China steps up with the space race.
SPEAKER_0:  It could be like, all right.
SPEAKER_0:  NASA, NASA kind of says, all right, this Elon fella.
SPEAKER_0:  Like really make this a gigantic
SPEAKER_1:  effort.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, and if Starship works out as planned and as NASA has invested in human landing system, they're relying on SpaceX to land on the moon.
SPEAKER_1:  SpaceX can land on the moon, they can land on-
SPEAKER_1:  Now whether or not the life support and the human considerations of long-term spaceflight missions and high radiation and
SPEAKER_1:  Blah blah blah blah, refueling on Mars is a huge huge huge deal.
SPEAKER_1:  they definitely could send a starship to Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  and land, ideally land in one piece on Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  as soon as they can land on the moon they can land on mars basically i mean those two things are very in some ways mars is
SPEAKER_1:  Almost easier.
SPEAKER_1:  If you can use because you can use the atmosphere to slow down it actually doesn't take that much more
SPEAKER_1:  Delta V to actually land on Mars than it does. Because on the moon you don't have any...
SPEAKER_1:  First get out to the moon, then orbit the moon. You know, you have to slow down. Every one of those is a maneuver change.
SPEAKER_1:  Then you have to.
SPEAKER_1:  Lower your orbit until it-
SPEAKER_1:  coincides you know.
SPEAKER_1:  hits the moon.
SPEAKER_1:  And then if it's slowed down enough to not.
SPEAKER_1:  when he hit the moon.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's a lot of delta V there, a lot of change in velocity.
SPEAKER_1:  Mars is actually, by the time we kind of crunch the numbers, it's relatively similar.
SPEAKER_1:  just a lot more difficult like timeline wise and.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, accuracy and all of these other communication. You know, there's a lot of other things obviously involved.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm glossing over it making it sound easy.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not.
SPEAKER_1:  But.
SPEAKER_1:  But you know, I think there's a real decent chance we could see a starship vehicle land on Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  uncrewed by the end of the day.
SPEAKER_0:  decade though.
SPEAKER_0:  End of the decade.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, there's also a sociological element, maybe a political one where...
SPEAKER_0:  I think you're allowed to take more risks with Mars than you are with the...
SPEAKER_0:  Cause we've done the moon.
SPEAKER_0:  1969. Yeah, it's been a while.
SPEAKER_0:  PR wise.
SPEAKER_0:  you have to be much safer. With Mars, everyone's like, it's super dangerous. So you could take a little more...
SPEAKER_0:  risk hundred special without with man mission the
SPEAKER_0:  Go back.
SPEAKER_0:  to the moon landing Apollo 11 mission.
SPEAKER_0:  I haven't talked about this.
SPEAKER_0:  What's the amazing engine there? But again, the romantic question and you look back at that moon landing.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  One small step for man, one giant step for mankind.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think about that moment?
SPEAKER_0:  in human history.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you go back to that often? Or are you focused just like with the cars and the engines?
SPEAKER_1:  No, no, no.
SPEAKER_1:  I still, when I need inspiration, I rewatch this documentary called When We Left Earth. I think it was like a, I think it was Discovery Channel did it.
SPEAKER_1:  Six part episode.
SPEAKER_0:  it.
SPEAKER_1:  It was.
SPEAKER_1:  narrated by Gary Sinise.
SPEAKER_1:  phenomenal overview of the space race.
SPEAKER_1:  and that will get my juices flowing every time.
SPEAKER_1:  Every time, just.
SPEAKER_1:  It's so well done and it really just summarizes that program so well.
SPEAKER_1:  And when I and beyond it goes all the way to the space shuttle. But.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, when I, when I watch footage of humans walking on the moon, it's just.
SPEAKER_1:  I...
SPEAKER_1:  I can't believe we're dumb enough to do it with the technology we had.
SPEAKER_1:  and the risks.
SPEAKER_1:  they took to do it and.
SPEAKER_1:  The-
SPEAKER_1:  Insane engineering that it took to do that.
SPEAKER_1:  is just.
SPEAKER_1:  Absolutely astonishing.
SPEAKER_1:  The amount of-
SPEAKER_1:  This year like
SPEAKER_1:  Logistics of what it.
SPEAKER_1:  took to do it with it.
SPEAKER_1:  technology we had back then.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like.
SPEAKER_1:  oh, did we have so much money and effort and energy and time and resources, human resources to do this? like it's just
SPEAKER_0:  Just the weakness of the computers they had back then.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to do so much. I mean, yeah, it's.
SPEAKER_0:  So much was so little.
SPEAKER_0:  That's insane.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  But at the same time, like...
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if we want to talk about conspiracy theories or anything, but like...
SPEAKER_1:  It is all of, we have the proof in the pudding of like.
SPEAKER_1:  The...
SPEAKER_1:  400,000 people on payroll.
SPEAKER_1:  all of the paperwork, all of the...
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, you mean the question the conspiracy if we land on the moon? Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, I mean, I think the receipts are there, like literally.
SPEAKER_0:  We did.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's like a lot of.
SPEAKER_0:  things like that.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, we actually generally live in a pretty cynical time where people distrust institutions. Part of the thing was the space program.
SPEAKER_0:  is one of the things that can help.
SPEAKER_0:  reinvigorate the trust in institutions by institutions.
SPEAKER_0:  Even that word is a bad word now.
SPEAKER_0:  But institutions means a bunch of humans get together.
SPEAKER_0:  and do a big thing together.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, but-
SPEAKER_0:  You know like
SPEAKER_0:  If I was conspiratorially minded, it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  out.
SPEAKER_0:  How did humans do that?
SPEAKER_0:  So I think that's a very cynical take, unfortunately, but it's still an incredible one.
SPEAKER_0:  And also, you know, there's, there's a.
SPEAKER_0:  until you look at the receipts.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  a rationale to that kind of conspiracy theory because
SPEAKER_0:  So much pressure was put on the space race that the PR of it to be the winner so it makes sense that you might want to
SPEAKER_0:  try to take shortcuts and fake things and propaganda.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, different kinds of messaging. And I'm sure stuff like that was happening. Some kind of like.
SPEAKER_0:  Little
SPEAKER_0:  You know adjustment here and there to present things better and so on, but ultimately the actual engineering project.
SPEAKER_0:  of landing on the moon.
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that humans did that.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it is sad that we didn't have better, like...
SPEAKER_0:  Waste to record it.
SPEAKER_0:  And as I watch like SpaceX efforts and Blue Origin and these efforts.
SPEAKER_0:  is still not trivial to record the uh...
SPEAKER_0:  how just amazing, awe-inspiring space is. Is it like,
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it's like Elon jokes about it, like his base does look fake. Yeah. Like I think there is some element of it where you have to be there to experience it really. And I don't.
SPEAKER_0:  Like I think it's currently is still.
SPEAKER_0:  An unsolved problem of how do you capture all of that?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, you're one of the early people that are.
SPEAKER_0:  Part of the crew that is exploring that very question. I'm sure you won't find all the answers, but you'll start to say like how
SPEAKER_0:  Do we convert this into a visual format, some kind of format that captures the magic of it?
SPEAKER_1:  And that's a perspective thing that I think about all the time.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll do a lot of thinking about like, what is the thing that's reacting to people? Is it the sound? Is it the perspective? Is it like seeing a little tiny human next to a landing leg that makes people go?
SPEAKER_1:  Oh my God, this thing is huge.
SPEAKER_1:  reading, you know, and digesting that and trying to...
SPEAKER_1:  Hope.
SPEAKER_1:  to convey that as best as possible because the stuff that.
SPEAKER_1:  we are and have worked on is.
SPEAKER_1:  is so cool. It's so exciting.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's so important and like actually, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  so much bigger than any one of us.
SPEAKER_1:  Physically and metaphorically.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just so, it's just, I wish everyone had that experience and had that light bulb go off.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's the cool thing that you're like...
SPEAKER_0:  smack in the middle of
SPEAKER_0:  solving that really difficult.
SPEAKER_0:  in Fascinating Problem.
SPEAKER_0:  Have a good one.
SPEAKER_0:  How do you capture the magic?
SPEAKER_0:  How do you inspire?
SPEAKER_0:  That's not just an engineer problem. That's an communication problem
SPEAKER_1:  Education. Be of a new
SPEAKER_1:  specifically for myself, that I get most excited about something when I learn a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  when I learn the ins and the outs and I learn all the little problem solving in the
SPEAKER_1:  You know, the cool, like, oh my God, they had to do what to make it work? Wow. That's amazing.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's, I try to just always.
SPEAKER_1:  go back to that root thing of like, what can I teach myself? Like if I'm every video, I expect that I learned something.
SPEAKER_1:  making it no matter what, like no matter how.
SPEAKER_1:  Much I think I know about something at the end of the day if I'm not learning something. It's not a good video, you know
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  I always think that people get excited when they learn.
SPEAKER_1:  and when they have.
SPEAKER_1:  some questions answered for them.
SPEAKER_0:  Let me ask you a couple of quick out there futuristic questions I have to.
SPEAKER_0:  I'd hate myself if I don't ask you.
SPEAKER_0:  So first let's talk about nuclear propulsion. So out there, interesting propulsion ideas. So what do you think?
SPEAKER_0:  Beyond.
SPEAKER_0:  the chemical engines that we talked about.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think about using nuclear?
SPEAKER_0:  Fish in and maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  for uh... for propulsion
SPEAKER_1:  We already have.
SPEAKER_1:  thermal nuclear reactors, they're nuclear engines that...
SPEAKER_1:  have been tested both by the United States and Soviet Union that were
SPEAKER_1:  100% valid.
SPEAKER_1:  like totally ready to go.
SPEAKER_1:  Efficient, super awesome.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, yes, yes, hardcore yes.
SPEAKER_1:  And what they're using is basically a fusion reactor.
SPEAKER_1:  You're flowing hydrogen through it.
SPEAKER_1:  and heating up the hydrogen, taking it from liquid to gas.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, and.
SPEAKER_1:  by heating it up, you're adding energy to the propellant.
SPEAKER_1:  And then you're literally just using that now steam hot.
SPEAKER_1:  Hydrogen.
SPEAKER_1:  and flung it through a D-Lavelle nozzle.
SPEAKER_1:  And you also have to use that energy to spin the pumps to still...
SPEAKER_1:  pump the things you're still kind of using like a lot of the tricks you're using but instead of a chemical reaction
SPEAKER_1:  You're literally just using.
SPEAKER_1:  nuclear fission.
SPEAKER_1:  to heat up.
SPEAKER_1:  propellant.
SPEAKER_1:  and do the same thing. And at the end of the day, you end up with like eight to 900 seconds of specific impulse, which is.
SPEAKER_1:  double that of chemical propulsion.
SPEAKER_1:  Most of that comes just because hydrogen is so light. You're only emitting, you're only ejecting.
SPEAKER_1:  hydrogen out of the nozzle.
SPEAKER_1:  The lighter molecule is.
SPEAKER_1:  the faster it, you know, just like if you had a.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, it's a golf ball versus like a.
SPEAKER_1:  bowling ball. You can only physically throw one so fast and the other one as a human you're not going to do very well with.
SPEAKER_1:  So you can just, you get.
SPEAKER_1:  you have the more potential for a higher.
SPEAKER_1:  exit velocity.
SPEAKER_1:  Nuclear thermal, amazing. You can just shoot these little hydrogen molecules out crazy fast, crazy efficiently. We already have it.
SPEAKER_1:  We can do it.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, yes, yes. And actually we're already re.
SPEAKER_1:  investing in that again as the United States is.
SPEAKER_1:  is looking at a.
SPEAKER_1:  basically ramping back up our nuclear propulsion.
SPEAKER_0:  Why haven't we done it yet?
SPEAKER_0:  And what do you think the challenges that there? And do you think that's an obvious future? Like would you see in 50 years or not using?
SPEAKER_0:  um...
SPEAKER_0:  Like we're not, for major projects, like a Starship type of project, we're not using chemical propulsion anymore.
SPEAKER_1:  For getting off earth, you'll always want to use chemical propulsion because the gas will come irradiated. Like you told me, you don't want to, and actually the thrust to weight ratio of these engines are relatively poor.
SPEAKER_1:  They're very heavy. They have a nuclear reactor. Like they're not.
SPEAKER_1:  They're really.
SPEAKER_1:  The reason we kind of give up on them is they're really most useful for interplanetary.
SPEAKER_1:  If you're trying to get a big, like if you're trying to send.
SPEAKER_1:  A huge payload off to Mars, nuclear thermal is amazing.
SPEAKER_1:  It's.
SPEAKER_1:  still could be beneficial even going to the moon, you know, like in an earth moon system, you could use nuclear thermal.
SPEAKER_1:  very effectively and it could be a great choice.
SPEAKER_1:  But it also, that starts to get into that trade of like, eh, we can just kind of use a little bit bigger rocket and.
SPEAKER_1:  and fly a normal, you know, it's that whole trade thing, but.
SPEAKER_1:  Another reason why we kind of stopped using them.
SPEAKER_1:  The one that the United States developed, Nerva, was so heavy.
SPEAKER_1:  only a Saturn V could actually lift the stage of it, like the upper stage, so replace the S4B.
SPEAKER_1:  with a nuclear thermal with the Nerva engine.
SPEAKER_1:  The Soviet Union developed one about one-tenth the size and thrust.
SPEAKER_1:  that was small enough to fly on a proton rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, but neither of them ever flew.
SPEAKER_1:  Both of them have been tested and-
SPEAKER_1:  thumbs up, ready to go.
SPEAKER_1:  Was it just?
SPEAKER_1:  a huge shame to me because they could unlock a lot of
SPEAKER_1:  interplanetary potential and
SPEAKER_0:  just all around us. Which potentially interstellar as well.
SPEAKER_1:  Not quite, I don't think nuclear thermal.
SPEAKER_1:  not, we're not quite getting there, but then you get into like nuclear pulse drives and things where you're literally like
SPEAKER_1:  basically ejecting a bomb out the back of your
SPEAKER_1:  rocket and exploding and having like a shock absorber and Pogo sticking your way out of the solar system.
SPEAKER_1:  That
SPEAKER_1:  That's.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean by all physics sure, you know, there's not nothing wrong with that. It's not breaking any laws of physics and-
SPEAKER_1:  You know, but I just don't see us getting to that need anytime soon. I don't think we're gonna be. Speed of travel.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean, that's that's I think we're going to want a better understanding of.
SPEAKER_0:  physics and.
SPEAKER_0:  physics itself, yeah, do you have a hope that maybe theoretical physics will open the door to some exciting propulsion systems?
SPEAKER_1:  I do. We're still at the very infancy of our-
SPEAKER_1:  understanding of everything and how things work.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  A hundred years ago, it would be stupid to try to predict the things we know today and
SPEAKER_1:  Who knows? Even things like James Webb.
SPEAKER_1:  looking deeper into our solar system than ever before and physically being able to see objects that we just have not even been able to physically see before.
SPEAKER_0:  on being able to study black holes for example.
SPEAKER_0:  better better the stuff that's happening outside of black holes
SPEAKER_0:  at the edges of black holes and how the information is stored.
SPEAKER_0:  other
SPEAKER_0:  100%
SPEAKER_0:  Holographic principles is there's so much weirdness around black holes. Yes around where
SPEAKER_0:  Gravity starts bending light.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like, all right.
SPEAKER_0:  We get to look at that now and start to wonder like what is going on?
SPEAKER_0:  and hug.
SPEAKER_0:  How can we like use that somehow?
SPEAKER_0:  For propulsion, I mean, it seems like awfully crazy and futuristic at this moment, but I think that's because we know almost nothing about.
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, that those kinds of objects were.
SPEAKER_0:  Again, where the general relativity and quantum mechanics start to...
SPEAKER_0:  statue.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  have to be both considered to describe those kinds of objects. And as we study those objects, we might figure out some kind of unification thing that will allow us to.
SPEAKER_0:  understand maybe how to use black holes to
SPEAKER_0:  for propulsion, like, I could say a lot of crazy things, but like basically...
SPEAKER_1:  But the point is it'd be stupid for us to even...
SPEAKER_1:  guess about things we don't even know about yet. You know what I mean? Like and...
SPEAKER_1:  So therefore I'm not going to say that the best option for interstellar travel is.
SPEAKER_1:  nuclear drives like that could be like someone saying, you know, in 1600, the only way to fly is
SPEAKER_1:  by strapping a thousand birds to your head, you know, like.
SPEAKER_0:  But that said...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything he's saying is right, but human history...
SPEAKER_0:  is such that the beginning of the twentieth century.
SPEAKER_0:  Physicists rutherford they everybody this this brilliant people that said we've basically solved all
SPEAKER_0:  If you talk to most physicists, I think they're going to say like,
SPEAKER_0:  pretty much.
SPEAKER_0:  solved.
SPEAKER_0:  The standard model describes physics extremely accurately.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, general relativity.
SPEAKER_0:  explains the cosmos as we observe them.
SPEAKER_0:  extremely accurately.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, there's a whole dark matter, dark energy thing. Whatever. But outside of that, so like we basically solved like.
SPEAKER_0:  Dude...
SPEAKER_0:  Like where are you going to find?
SPEAKER_0:  gaps in knowledge that are going to somehow create.
SPEAKER_0:  Warp drives or something like that. Warp drives or something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  But that's...
SPEAKER_0:  It seems like throughout history, we prove ourselves wrong time and time again. Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  No, and this is well outside of any of my knowledge base, so I wanna make sure that if I say anything stupid, it's because I'm-
SPEAKER_1:  I just did a peasant here in physics land, but yes.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  We're all peasants in physics land.
SPEAKER_1:  But I really just think like...
SPEAKER_1:  It's very humbling that we're still using chemical.
SPEAKER_1:  propulsion and variance of like injecting mass to propel ourselves.
SPEAKER_1:  no matter how you get at it. And I think someday.
SPEAKER_1:  I would expect that our species has figured out a way to...
SPEAKER_1:  Get beyond that.
SPEAKER_0:  Gotta ask you another wild question.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think of Bob Lazar?
SPEAKER_0:  who claimed that he worked at and saw in Area 51 the propulsion system.
SPEAKER_0:  fueled by
SPEAKER_0:  I'm quoting here, maybe from Wikipedia. I don't know where I got this from.
SPEAKER_0:  fueled by an anti-matter reactor which used as fuel the chemical element with atomic number 115.
SPEAKER_0:  At the time it wasn't synthesized, it was later in 2003 synthesized.
SPEAKER_0:  named Muscoviem.
SPEAKER_0:  He said that the propulsion system relied on a stable isotope of element 115.
SPEAKER_0:  which allegedly generates a gravity wave that allowed the vehicle to fly and to evade visual detection by bending light around it.
SPEAKER_0:  No stabilizer dose.
SPEAKER_0:  of muscovium have yet been synthesized.
SPEAKER_0:  all have proven extremely radioactive, decaying in a few.
SPEAKER_0:  100 milliseconds.
SPEAKER_0:  One, do you believe him?
SPEAKER_0:  I find him fascinating because I find the human mind even more fascinating.
SPEAKER_0:  Then, um...
SPEAKER_0:  then.
SPEAKER_0:  Then something like an anti-matter drive because I think it's such a giant mystery that we haven't even begun to explore deeply anyway In that sense whether he's lying or not are both interesting things to explore from a psychology perspective
SPEAKER_0:  but
SPEAKER_0:  To
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, he's basically saying that I guess it's an alien.
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  extraterrestrial.
SPEAKER_0:  engine.
SPEAKER_0:  thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think?
SPEAKER_1:  I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm happy to change my opinion based on new evidence at any point.
SPEAKER_1:  I have like.
SPEAKER_1:  The biggest part of me wants to just be like, this is obviously just stupid and a hoax and just total.
SPEAKER_1:  Quack.
SPEAKER_1:  And then...
SPEAKER_1:  Another part of me still is like, this is exciting and fun to think that this is all real.
SPEAKER_1:  And then another part of me goes, why?
SPEAKER_1:  How good is this guy at lying and making stuff up? Because it's ALL!
SPEAKER_1:  Really good.
SPEAKER_1:  Like good storytelling, good like...
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know what to think honestly. I don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm really very skeptical about anyone explaining anything like this. I mean, my radar is like screaming at me like.
SPEAKER_1:  This is all app.
SPEAKER_1:  full crap, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  But I'd say like there's still a part of me that's just like...
SPEAKER_0:  Man, that is kinda cool. How did he know that?
SPEAKER_1:  like, you know what I mean? I'm conflicted.
SPEAKER_0:  I think you're actually in the best kind of place because it's
SPEAKER_0:  I'm afraid of being the kind of person that hears something like that.
SPEAKER_0:  and says it's definitely.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  He's definitely full of crap and basically closed my mind off to all that stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm afraid of being somebody who closes my mind off to a thing that's actually
SPEAKER_0:  a early thread to a brilliant.
SPEAKER_0:  to a future, to a fascinating.
SPEAKER_0:  solution to a mystery so
SPEAKER_0:  But in this case, I mean, I have so many red flags from a psychological perspective
SPEAKER_0:  that um...
SPEAKER_0:  that, but again.
SPEAKER_0:  outside of this particular individual.
SPEAKER_0:  I do wonder if aliens have visited us.
SPEAKER_0:  I think aliens are everywhere.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  The universe is teeming with
SPEAKER_0:  Alien Life.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean there's...
SPEAKER_0:  It's very difficult for me to statistically understand.
SPEAKER_0:  given.
SPEAKER_0:  How?
SPEAKER_0:  life finds a way here on Earth just everywhere.
SPEAKER_0:  is the entire history of life on earth.
SPEAKER_0:  from the very origin of life.
SPEAKER_0:  It seems to be damn good at doing its thing, evolving.
SPEAKER_0:  to get better and better and better at doing its thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Now there could be some special aspects to the origin of life itself.
SPEAKER_0:  which is completely not understood.
SPEAKER_0:  So maybe the true magic is in the origin of life.
SPEAKER_0:  Or it could be that there's some magical leaps.
SPEAKER_0:  to eukaryotic cells for example.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  the universe, our galaxies, teeming with alien life, but it's all bacteria.
SPEAKER_0:  They're all boring bacteria.
SPEAKER_0:  exciting bacteria no offense to bacteria
SPEAKER_0:  the but the no intelligence spacefaring civilizations.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  I just, if I were to guess, I'd have to bet all my money.
SPEAKER_0:  There is space-faring civilizations.
SPEAKER_0:  everywhere in the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  and the fact that they're
SPEAKER_0:  not that they have not been
SPEAKER_0:  directly definitively observed.
SPEAKER_0:  confuses me.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think it's a mystery. And if I were to suggest what the solution to that mystery is.
SPEAKER_0:  is they might look extremely different from us.
SPEAKER_0:  then we might be too dumb to detect them.
SPEAKER_0:  and then
SPEAKER_0:  And so there, I think you have to be extremely open-minded.
SPEAKER_0:  What would we be looking?
SPEAKER_0:  And that's a very practical thing to be open-minded about.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Practically speaking...
SPEAKER_0:  if we were to be able to even detect them from a distance.
SPEAKER_0:  get a tech uh... technical signature
SPEAKER_0:  of a distant planet.
SPEAKER_0:  of a distant star system.
SPEAKER_0:  that has alien life.
SPEAKER_0:  Honest seat.
SPEAKER_0:  Number one thing I kinda wanna know.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like.
SPEAKER_0:  What's your propulsion system?
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_0:  travel faster right like there's a bunch of details probably but
SPEAKER_1:  first let's get together
SPEAKER_1:  and teach me how to go fast. Go fast. I like motorcycles, I like rockets. Exactly.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, like how like I'll show you mine if you show me yours kind of thing at the at the inter interstellar intergalactic level
SPEAKER_0:  Um, yeah, anyway, I just wonder.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe it's a cheat code in this video game we call life.
SPEAKER_0:  But I wanna use the cheat code to figure out what kind of propulsion systems are possible.
SPEAKER_0:  and it feels like other alien civilizations.
SPEAKER_0:  might help us.
SPEAKER_0:  Give us.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Give us a guidance on that. Of course, I think even just-
SPEAKER_0:  Discovering.
SPEAKER_0:  Boy, one of the things with the space program, like everything we're doing with Mars...
SPEAKER_0:  Like
SPEAKER_0:  The secret thing I'm really excited about, the romantic thing is humans are more.
SPEAKER_0:  the secret thing.
SPEAKER_0:  is building giant stations on Mars that allow us to definitively.
SPEAKER_0:  hopefully fine.
SPEAKER_0:  Traces.
SPEAKER_0:  Life.
SPEAKER_0:  Either currently doesn't live
SPEAKER_0:  or has once lived on Mars, because if that's the case, that means for sure life is ever-
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, 100%.
SPEAKER_1:  And then you're like.
SPEAKER_0:  And once you know that, sorry to keep interrupting, I'm not shedding a hell of a-
SPEAKER_0:  This is supposed to be an interview, god damn it. Alright, that-
SPEAKER_0:  Alright.
SPEAKER_0:  That just the knowledge of that just the knowledge that a form minute mile can be run
SPEAKER_0:  I think we'll open our minds completely.
SPEAKER_0:  to really, really hardcore push.
SPEAKER_0:  to interstellar travel or colonizing Mars, becoming a multi-planetary species, it'd be truly inspiring.
SPEAKER_0:  You think that.
SPEAKER_0:  You
SPEAKER_1:  Do you get nervous though? I'm the interviewer now.
SPEAKER_1:  Don't you get nervous that we could make.
SPEAKER_1:  spectacular discovery on Mars that.
SPEAKER_1:  Not only has there been life, there's actually like pretty advanced-
SPEAKER_1:  micro you know or
SPEAKER_1:  A multicellular life.
SPEAKER_1:  totally thriving in certain regions, we just hadn't visited them yet on Mars, and we make this big discovery.
SPEAKER_1:  relatively large percentage of people.
SPEAKER_1:  simply wouldn't believe it.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think it's all 100% fake?
SPEAKER_1:  and that they're just doing this to control us.
SPEAKER_1:  and that blah blah blah, like.
SPEAKER_1:  We could make the most important discovery.
SPEAKER_1:  in
SPEAKER_1:  human life
SPEAKER_1:  Like in all of human existence that.
SPEAKER_1:  that we're not alone in this universe.
SPEAKER_1:  What, you know, cellularly at least.
SPEAKER_1:  and a good percentage of people, I'm thinking.
SPEAKER_1:  2030.
SPEAKER_1:  in today's world 40 plus percent of people.
SPEAKER_1:  wouldn't even believe it existed.
SPEAKER_0:  Interesting. I, I, I'd be, it's just a very important thing to think about, especially as an educator like yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the current cynicism towards institutions and science is temporary.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's they're basically the internet woke up.
SPEAKER_0:  The internet smells bullshit?
SPEAKER_0:  and it looked at...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm sorry, I'm not being ageist, but saying older scientists and they looked at them.
SPEAKER_0:  And they kind of said, you're kind of full of shit. You got a lot of ego.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... your you speak down to everybody you're not very good at communicating
SPEAKER_0:  I think there's a lot of truth to what they're saying. And I think the young scientists that are coming up will be much better at not being full of shit.
SPEAKER_0:  being authentic, being real.
SPEAKER_0:  treating people like they're children that can't possibly understand, taking it very seriously.
SPEAKER_0:  that there's a lot of intelligent people out there that are curious that are
SPEAKER_0:  full of desire for knowledge.
SPEAKER_0:  like being transparent about all the uncertainties.
SPEAKER_0:  of the scientific process, all the tensions, the conflicts, all of that. And I think...
SPEAKER_0:  I think once we fix the science communication.
SPEAKER_0:  system.
SPEAKER_0:  adapted to the internet.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  That won't be an issue, I hope.
SPEAKER_0:  I hope.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, that's why people like you are really important, is like communicate with authenticity.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  But yeah, that's definitely something to think about. Yes, the early-
SPEAKER_0:  uh... mean listen scientists to like the phosphine discovered on on the news
SPEAKER_0:  is like they're extremely skeptical always.
SPEAKER_0:  So definitely there will.
SPEAKER_0:  There'll be a lot of skepticism.
SPEAKER_0:  It depends what it looks like if it kind of looks like
SPEAKER_0:  This thing kinda looks like bacteria back on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, so it means contamination is very difficult to avoid in general.
SPEAKER_0:  But if the thing looks like fundamentally different......well yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  then you're like, all right.
SPEAKER_1:  totally different DNA, RNA, like this is not, we've never observed this ever.
SPEAKER_0:  then you're like, all right.
SPEAKER_0:  Ha!
SPEAKER_0:  Of course.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, so that I do what another promising thing that.
SPEAKER_0:  difficult to be definitive about but
SPEAKER_0:  Let's get better and better direct imaging systems.
SPEAKER_0:  There's now a...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know how many, but thousands of.
SPEAKER_0:  planets are being discovered outside of our solar system. There's moons being discovered. Now, Earth-like planets being discovered. So like all of that, if we could do direct imaging of those planets.
SPEAKER_0:  More more more?
SPEAKER_0:  There could be some gigantic
SPEAKER_0:  If there is like a Cardishev like type two civilization.
SPEAKER_0:  We're gonna see the damn thing. It's gonna be producing a lot of, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  it's going to be radiating a lot of energy.
SPEAKER_0:  So the possibility of detecting some of that, that's also.
SPEAKER_0:  a real possibility with something like James Webb telescopes, like those kinds of efforts.
SPEAKER_0:  that starts becoming a reality.
SPEAKER_1:  Have you read Andy Weir's project Hail Mary? I have not, no.
SPEAKER_1:  You're going to.
SPEAKER_1:  Love it.
SPEAKER_1:  Like it is.
SPEAKER_1:  Basically,
SPEAKER_1:  Almost answering that like.
SPEAKER_1:  how could they not see us type of thing almost where.
SPEAKER_1:  He creates this incredible, I don't want to spoil anything, but.
SPEAKER_1:  you know.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just the sense of like.
SPEAKER_1:  We could have totally different perspectives with an alien race and not even like...
SPEAKER_1:  consider that, you know, the two of us are coexisting almost. I don't want to spoil anything. It's really, really, really worth the read. Oh, you mean a different.
SPEAKER_0:  perspective, like the aliens have a different perspective than humans.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, like, we just like, we see with this visual light. Someone could see in x-ray, et cetera, you know, like.
SPEAKER_1:  And just the way we even...
SPEAKER_1:  come to the same.
SPEAKER_1:  perspective and like looking and observing is just so different fundamentally.
SPEAKER_1:  that like we could, I mean, it's not quite like that. It's not like it's like, oh, they were actually on the moon and we're, you know, it's nothing like that, but.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh
SPEAKER_1:  but it's such a unique and incredible story. I think Andy Weir is one of the...
SPEAKER_1:  best science fiction writers at home.
SPEAKER_1:  I can't say that with much authority because I don't listen to much science fiction. So zero authority. I really like Andy Weir's books and that book is noted.
SPEAKER_0:  But that sounds like I'm really worried about that. It sounds like
SPEAKER_0:  I would really love it.
SPEAKER_0:  I've definitely been very.
SPEAKER_0:  I've done a lot of reading in my life, but like the science fiction is one of the things I've been really, really weak on. I haven't really read much and I just...
SPEAKER_0:  made more and more friends over the years recently.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, that say.
SPEAKER_0:  that I absolutely must read some of these things. Do you have a comment?
SPEAKER_1:  Do you physically read or do you do audio books or do you read or do audio books?
SPEAKER_0:  A boat. I do both, yeah. Well, physically I sadly don't.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a kindle, right? Yeah, yeah, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  But while I run, I also do...
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  uh, on a normal day.
SPEAKER_0:  especially now that I've been really focused on reading.
SPEAKER_0:  It's about.
SPEAKER_0:  60 minutes of.
SPEAKER_0:  Reading out of Kindle.
SPEAKER_0:  and one to two hours, because I run about two hours.
SPEAKER_0:  or when I don't have like other stuff like today I won't run.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... says about three hours so on average i would say it's like two two and a half hours a day
SPEAKER_0:  Let her read.
SPEAKER_0:  and audiobooks are just the same, they're a little slower.
SPEAKER_0:  there they can, especially for the classics, they can capture some of the magic with a deep voice.
SPEAKER_0:  Usually with a British accent.
SPEAKER_0:  I love it. I also read that, uh, listen to, sorry.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... what a book on proportionate two years ago i remember
SPEAKER_0:  but I remember that was extremely difficult. Ignition by? Yeah, it was ignition. By Don D. Clark. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  It was very difficult to listen.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, yeah, I see, I don't read, I listen while I'm on road trips or running or stuff that too, so.
SPEAKER_1:  I swear there's probably.
SPEAKER_1:  40 or like not 40, but there's like eight minutes of.
SPEAKER_1:  We tried.
SPEAKER_1:  PMZ 15.
SPEAKER_1:  13.
SPEAKER_1:  BM 412 RMNL mitromyclhydrigeny for like.
SPEAKER_1:  I swear it's multiple minutes of explaining one trial on something because there's just so many
SPEAKER_1:  different chemicals they try, I don't know, it's...
SPEAKER_1:  It's almost a joke. I literally, audibly laughed out loud listening to it because I'm like, this is so ridiculous. I'm sure it makes sense reading it, but listening to it is just hilarious.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's great though.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think of some of the challenges for long-term space travel?
SPEAKER_0:  Do you think about this kind of stuff, the biological stuff?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you worry? Do you think about radiation on Mars?
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, and out in space over periods of, uh, actually the effects on the human body.
SPEAKER_0:  get even the radiation.
SPEAKER_0:  over periods of months and years.
SPEAKER_0:  I think...
SPEAKER_1:  Realistically, we have a really good handle.
SPEAKER_1:  on.
SPEAKER_1:  what the effects are.
SPEAKER_1:  And we actually have the solution to like everything. It's just.
SPEAKER_1:  whether or not.
SPEAKER_1:  we can like, you know, for instance, one of the, you know, low-earth orbit, one of the biggest challenges eventually after your long-term space travel.
SPEAKER_1:  Is bone density loss a not?
SPEAKER_1:  having gravity, you know, you actually have issues with.
SPEAKER_1:  a handful of things and-
SPEAKER_1:  artificial gravities.
SPEAKER_1:  Easy in terms of.
SPEAKER_1:  relatively easy as in terms of space flight, you know, you can
SPEAKER_1:  You'd have two vehicles just tethered together and...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, just.
SPEAKER_1:  spinning.
SPEAKER_1:  as given enough distance and a decent enough spin velocity. And you can get one gene like relatively easy. We're talking again, relatively easy, especially after talking about theoretical physics. Like this is.
SPEAKER_1:  That's easy stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  We haven't.
SPEAKER_1:  done that yet, but like.
SPEAKER_1:  There's no reason why we can't produce artificial gravity. If we say that that's-
SPEAKER_1:  you know, a big enough hurdle that we absolutely have to overcome this.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, cool. We'll just spin up two vehicles that are going to Mars and...
SPEAKER_1:  people will have, but you know, that's the thing is Mars is only about, we'll say six months.
SPEAKER_1:  There
SPEAKER_1:  Then you're hanging out on Mars, you have 38% of gravity, and then six months-ish back.
SPEAKER_1:  People live.
SPEAKER_1:  on the International Space Station at six months' stints. We've had people for basically a year up on the International Space Station.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not like it's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not life altering. Yeah, you have a couple days of...
SPEAKER_1:  not being able to walk very well, and you do have some bone density loss and some other concerns.
SPEAKER_1:  But like again, that's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's solvable. I think the first mission is to Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  It might, we might, we'll probably do the trade. Is it worth it to like-
SPEAKER_1:  land on Mars and have a crippled.
SPEAKER_1:  that can't even physically stand yet.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, for a day or two.
SPEAKER_1:  before they get their feet from underneath them? or is it?
SPEAKER_1:  Do we need to spin up?
SPEAKER_1:  to spacecraft, you know, a tether and have.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you can't do it like Starship, you know, even though it's 30 feet wide or nine meters wide, if you spin it on that one axis,
SPEAKER_1:  That's not enough space to.
SPEAKER_1:  one G without your feet and your head being it too different.
SPEAKER_1:  velocity so you get really sick. You always feel like you're falling.
SPEAKER_1:  Your brain will tell you that you're falling constantly.
SPEAKER_1:  But then again, okay, so this is the whole thing is.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if there's...
SPEAKER_1:  We don't really have the data yet on like.
SPEAKER_1:  Going from zero G, we know the effects of that.
SPEAKER_1:  We know the effects of 1G really well. That's our majority of our data set.
SPEAKER_1:  but we don't really have much data on the long-term effects of.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, you know, one sixth gravity, like on the moon.
SPEAKER_1:  or 38% gravity, is it?
SPEAKER_1:  Is 1-6 gravity actually enough to counteract 95% of the effects of low gravity?
SPEAKER_1:  Or is it?
SPEAKER_1:  15, you know, is it 160? Is it like a linear thing? Is 38% gravity?
SPEAKER_1:  totally 38% as bad as one or whatever, is it a slight like where is it out on the scale?
SPEAKER_1:  So there's a chance that we don't need anywhere near one g of gravity to counteract the bulk majority of these problems. We could have.
SPEAKER_1:  point one year whatever is that you have the right compromise of.
SPEAKER_1:  of vehicle complexity and human biology and.
SPEAKER_1:  All of these other effects like we this is absolutely a solvable thing.
SPEAKER_0:  That is and and we figure some of this out through just experimentation 100% along the way
SPEAKER_0:  uh... one of this is back to my dating life i think one of the essential
SPEAKER_0:  fundamental research questions I'm wondering about.
SPEAKER_0:  is the dynamics.
SPEAKER_0:  And...
SPEAKER_0:  So the details of how you have sex in space.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, asking for a friend, of course. I mean, that's, there literally is sort of work on this, right? Cause like-
SPEAKER_0:  if you think about long term space travel.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean...
SPEAKER_0:  sexist is uh
SPEAKER_0:  So like there's the recreational aspect of sex, but the most important aspect of sex.
SPEAKER_0:  for long-term space travel is...
SPEAKER_0:  procreation
SPEAKER_0:  and also the full biological cycle of that. So from the embryo, the development of the baby, the giving the birth and all that kind of stuff. It's like.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there's a lot of really difficult...
SPEAKER_0:  problems of biology there to understand.
SPEAKER_0:  and perhaps that's all. Some of that, again, just like you said brilliantly.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of that can be just solved with engineering outside of the human body by creating a gravitational field like
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  but maybe along the way you can figure out how to do that without doing it.
SPEAKER_0:  We're balancing the costs.
SPEAKER_1:  And radiation is the other thing. I know we have a really good-
SPEAKER_1:  data set on what radiation and doses do to humans.
SPEAKER_1:  We know.
SPEAKER_1:  We can measure radiation, we know.
SPEAKER_1:  We can approximate and kind of give edge cases for the Mars transient and getting to Mars and being on Mars.
SPEAKER_1:  And the simple answer to that is like.
SPEAKER_1:  At the end of the day, if we have to.
SPEAKER_1:  dig into Mars or find a tunnel to...
SPEAKER_1:  live in so you get some extra mass in between you and.
SPEAKER_1:  cosmic radiation, so be it. Like that's the answer then. Again, none of these are like.
SPEAKER_1:  insolvable problems are just.
SPEAKER_1:  things, hurdles you would have to overcome based on.
SPEAKER_1:  the risk exposure and the posture there.
SPEAKER_0:  Magic Bing
SPEAKER_0:  the first.
SPEAKER_0:  Child, the first baby born.
SPEAKER_0:  Outside of Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  That'd be pretty cool. Yeah, that'll be pretty cool. I'd love-
SPEAKER_0:  alive to see that.
SPEAKER_0:  That'll be a big one.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know if he'll, um...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, because it's such a dangerous thing.
SPEAKER_0:  It's so risky. I think that could be in our lifetime.
SPEAKER_1:  You think so? Yeah
SPEAKER_1:  I would like to think in a perfect world of overthinking futurism that-
SPEAKER_1:  30 to 50 years, I definitely think we could have a full time.
SPEAKER_1:  permanent.
SPEAKER_1:  major civilizations, you know, like
SPEAKER_1:  Like, um.
SPEAKER_1:  like what Blue Origin wants to develop where they have a
SPEAKER_1:  a huge like sphere, you know, and you're doing a lot of.
SPEAKER_1:  Bye.
SPEAKER_1:  heavy industry off of Earth so you're not polluting Earth. That makes so much sense to me.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, yeah, I think, I think we.
SPEAKER_1:  we could live in a lifetime where, you know, we thought that since the 50s and 60s that people are gonna be living and working in space, like crazy.
SPEAKER_1:  And at any given point, we're lucky to have 12 people in space today.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  But I really think in our lifetime, we're finally getting to that point of
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  that that's a reality.
SPEAKER_0:  Let me, cause you mentioned Blue Origin.
SPEAKER_0:  Can we just lay out some of the competitors to SpaceX?
SPEAKER_0:  So much of what we talked about is SpaceX.
SPEAKER_0:  specifically because they're sort of pushing the boundaries of what's possible in the commercial space flight, but there's a lot of like you said incredible
SPEAKER_0:  work being done for large companies, small companies, startups and so on.
SPEAKER_0:  So who are the competitors to SpaceX?
SPEAKER_0:  ULA, you know, Launch Alliance, Blue Origin.
SPEAKER_0:  as a virgin.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Is it galactic orbit? Orbit would be the competitor. Virgin orbit, there's rocket labs, electron rocket that you mentioned.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  There's the folks you covered, Firefly.
SPEAKER_0:  And, uh,
SPEAKER_0:  What am I missing? There's the epic.
SPEAKER_0:  bass launch system.
SPEAKER_0:  Komm!
SPEAKER_0:  NASA, I guess that is.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, thankfully NASA, but prime contractor Boeing and Northrop. Lockheed? Northrop is the boosters, yep.
SPEAKER_0:  Nice, so like what's interesting to say to lay out the land here that you're excited about?
SPEAKER_1:  Just in general, I think if you aren't-
SPEAKER_1:  working on a reusable.
SPEAKER_1:  some form of a reasonable vehicle like.
SPEAKER_1:  physically working on it.
SPEAKER_1:  pen to paper, or not beyond pen to paper, like.
SPEAKER_1:  Bending metal for a reusable vehicle, you're gone. You're toast.
SPEAKER_1:  I think we're well into that being.
SPEAKER_1:  The only.
SPEAKER_1:  provable.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, way forward. The only way you're gonna compete and survive is a reusable rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  Fully reusable would be great, but that's obviously massively aspirational still.
SPEAKER_1:  But it will come.
SPEAKER_1:  But to me...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, the list, you pretty much had it.
SPEAKER_1:  right on the head. There's Astra was another.
SPEAKER_1:  Orbital Rockets Company.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  They there's a lot of companies. I think right now the
SPEAKER_1:  The ones that I personally really believe in.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, Rocket Lab is awesome. I really think that they are.
SPEAKER_1:  One of the few that I believe can actually build a Falcon 9 class rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, like.
SPEAKER_1:  today with their technology, with their knowledge, with their
SPEAKER_1:  investments with their funding, you know, and they've proven themselves. There's very few, they have actually made it look.
SPEAKER_1:  Easy. I think there's a lot of startups and a lot of new rocket. There's too many launch providers.
SPEAKER_1:  popping out of the woodwork right now.
SPEAKER_1:  They won't all survive, of course.
SPEAKER_1:  I think realistically, if you look at like airplanes, how many...
SPEAKER_1:  Airplane, you know, there's a handful of airplane manufacturers. There's not hundreds and thousands of airplane manufacturers.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it'll be a similar thing for space flight. I think we'll see.
SPEAKER_1:  We'll see.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, realistically in the terms of jubbo-jest and passengers, there's basically two.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there's Airbus and there's Boeing.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  So I.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  In the long run, there'll be two or three major players.
SPEAKER_1:  I think there'll be, you know, 10.
SPEAKER_1:  minor like as far as launch providers as far as the ones actually leaving earth and getting into orbit
SPEAKER_1:  I just don't think there's a ton of room for...
SPEAKER_1:  individuality really, you know? yeah I-I would-
SPEAKER_0:  I'm supposed to see it like a really serious competitor.
SPEAKER_0:  to SpaceX in the way that SpaceX does things. I don't know if you'll like is quite.
SPEAKER_0:  What I-
SPEAKER_0:  It's quite the rage kind of co-
SPEAKER_1:  Let me let me say this you will a
SPEAKER_1:  Has all of the potential, but just operationally there, you know, either power will be there.
SPEAKER_1:  either Lockheed Martin and Boeing's like love child. Yeah, but they're.
SPEAKER_1:  of set up in a far too traditional manner where they just really aren't given the opportunity to
SPEAKER_1:  innovate like a lot of these startups.
SPEAKER_0:  Sorry. So Rocket Lab is a little bit more of that nature. What do you think about?
SPEAKER_0:  sort of just blue origin in general.
SPEAKER_0:  The virgins childhood
SPEAKER_1:  I man I
SPEAKER_1:  What Blue Origin has done with New Shepard is amazing and people...
SPEAKER_1:  just lot it because it's suborbital and it looks very phallic
SPEAKER_1:  It's the...
SPEAKER_1:  It's so I guess the meme.
SPEAKER_0:  matters also.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's sad because people don't see what they are also working on, which is New Glenn.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I see comments almost every day still of like.
SPEAKER_1:  It doesn't matter because you know, they're.
SPEAKER_1:  they're working on Tiny, it's like no, New Glenn is more powerful and more capable than Falcon Heavy.
SPEAKER_1:  New Glenn is almost more of a competitor too.
SPEAKER_1:  Not quite as to Starship, but it's almost in that class. It's a-
SPEAKER_1:  It's a heavy lift launch vehicle. It's huge.
SPEAKER_1:  It'll be nuts.
SPEAKER_1:  They're very actively working on it. You know, I still think we're.
SPEAKER_1:  three years away from it launching.
SPEAKER_1:  but that's a very strong competitor.
SPEAKER_1:  class of rockets that SpaceX is currently making.
SPEAKER_0:  So SpaceX is currently leading the way but...
SPEAKER_0:  that it could become a close race.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm, it's just, I-
SPEAKER_1:  We'll just, for now, we'll ignore SpaceX. We'll just kind of talk about like, I think who's kind of coming around the corner here. Who's here? So let me just do a quick overview. I'm gonna shoot myself in the foot for getting some cool people here and some exciting companies, but Relativity's one that.
SPEAKER_1:  If you, you should definitely get Tim Ellis on the show, who is the person on the show
SPEAKER_1:  CEO of Relativity, they're doing 3D printed rockets.
SPEAKER_1:  The ones that have the world's largest 3D printer.
SPEAKER_1:  getting really close to their first orbital launch.
SPEAKER_1:  The cool thing about them, the reason that I think they're exciting.
SPEAKER_1:  The reason that I...
SPEAKER_1:  I think they have the potential is.
SPEAKER_1:  just how quickly they can iterate.
SPEAKER_1:  I think 3D printing a rocket is really dumb.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  Iterating with 3D printing on a rock is brilliant.
SPEAKER_1:  because you can literally change software and have like.
SPEAKER_1:  very little, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  upload a file and have a new rocket.
SPEAKER_1:  That's amazing.
SPEAKER_1:  So in terms of.
SPEAKER_1:  long-term iterative process.
SPEAKER_1:  if we're really talking about hitting the ground running and...
SPEAKER_1:  and just seeing where the evolution takes you, I think that's about as good as you can get.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I think what SpaceX is doing at Starbase just physically bending cheap steel is probably
SPEAKER_1:  Also a very valid solution.
SPEAKER_1:  So I really think, and they have the engineering chops, I think they've got some amazing people.
SPEAKER_1:  Again, Rocket Lab.
SPEAKER_1:  adore what they work on. And you know, like everyone, there's a caveat here that everything takes longer. Anything any company tells you it's two or three times longer, just period. Lab's no different.
SPEAKER_1:  But I really they're they're working on a neutron rocket. That's gonna be
SPEAKER_1:  I think 8,000 to 15,000 kilograms to lower the orbit. It's a good medium class rocket will compete.
SPEAKER_1:  right along with Falcon 9, hopefully.
SPEAKER_0:  By the way, Neutron would be its name.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not some kind of fascinating new physics breakthrough where they're using neutrons.
SPEAKER_1:  No, no, but they are using, they're also using liquid methane and liquid oxygen.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, I just think it's a really, it's a, it seems like a great rocket and
SPEAKER_1:  assuming they can actually get it flying in two or three years, I think they're going to be.
SPEAKER_1:  It's here to stay, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  I'd be remiss right now I'm editing a video from an interview with Stoke Aerospace out in Kent, Washington.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just one of these companies that they have a long ways to go. Like they're still in the very they're they're behind the curve, frankly, in terms of launch vehicles right now, because, like I said, there's so many coming out of the woodwork.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, the idea they're working on.
SPEAKER_1:  Their solution to a fully reusable rocket is.
SPEAKER_1:  Amazing.
SPEAKER_1:  one of the coolest concepts I've ever seen. You got
SPEAKER_0:  cover in the video.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, yeah, yeah, that'll be hopefully coming out the next depending on
SPEAKER_1:  what the schedule like is down there. I'm actively editing that as we speak and it is.
SPEAKER_1:  So cool. I mean, it is like.
SPEAKER_1:  It's, it's...
SPEAKER_1:  Genius, and the
SPEAKER_1:  If they can actually get it to work, I can see them merging. I can for sure see someone.
SPEAKER_1:  potentially like I
SPEAKER_1:  perfectly in a perfect world they've merged with Rocket Lab.
SPEAKER_1:  Stoke develops the upper stage, and maybe even the engines, they are.
SPEAKER_1:  the two guys, the CEO, the co-founders of that company.
SPEAKER_1: bieces? you
SPEAKER_1:  They are engine, like propulsion engineer.
SPEAKER_1:  magnificence. They have they used to they both have worked at Blue.
SPEAKER_1:  developed engines in a hurry there and then left blue and it felt like it was getting too slow for them and now they are.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, these guys fired a...
SPEAKER_1:  15 chambered rocket engine.
SPEAKER_1:  instead of four from the Soviet. We're talking 15 chambers, single turbo pump.
SPEAKER_1:  70 times in the month of October.
SPEAKER_1:  That's impressive.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's like, that was on average, you know, if you think about like days off.
SPEAKER_1:  Time off, you know, parts changing.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  over twice a day on average of a Hydrolux engine?
SPEAKER_1:  That's insane. So I....
SPEAKER_1:  I love them and I hope the best for them. But they're also topical right now. They're at the top of my head. What about Firefly?
SPEAKER_1:  What I like about Firefly.
SPEAKER_1:  They've already got kind of a traditional aerospace backing. They're starting to buddy up a lot with Northrop Grumman. They're going to be building the booster stage.
SPEAKER_1:  for Antares, which is currently flying only out of Wallops, Virginia.
SPEAKER_1:  and is one of the only other commercial providers for the International Space Station. And Northrop Grumman is very-
SPEAKER_1:  traditional aerospace company, you know, like lots of solid rocket boosters and they've
SPEAKER_1:  purchased ironically there.
SPEAKER_1:  their current Antares.
SPEAKER_1:  is reliant on Russian engines.
SPEAKER_1:  and Ukrainian boosters.
SPEAKER_1:  that I don't think you're gonna be able to get your hands on too much anymore. So they're looking to some US propulsion and stages. So they actually.
SPEAKER_1:  are partnering with.
SPEAKER_1:  with Firefly and their new Antares rocket will be
SPEAKER_1:  a first stage built entirely by Firefly. So I'm excited that Firefly already has.
SPEAKER_1:  the propulsion technology.
SPEAKER_1:  And they actually developed, ironically, their tap-off cycle engine was developed.
SPEAKER_1:  in partnership with Ukraine with Ukrainian engineers.
SPEAKER_1:  who developed the whole turbo pump system.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's like, is this cool?
SPEAKER_1:  meddling of these worlds.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, their former CEO, Tom Rekusick was like, I have an interview with him and he's
SPEAKER_1:  Anyone that can just...
SPEAKER_1:  Spout.
SPEAKER_1:  nuances and facts. I just love I just
SPEAKER_1:  soaked that guy's information up as best I could because he is.
SPEAKER_1:  Brilliant. Literally a doctor, a rocket doctor.
SPEAKER_0:  So yeah, I mean, that's what like you said, that's the fascinating thing about these folks. They're legit. They're such great engineers, the people that bring these rockets to life. And then there's all this stuff that we.
SPEAKER_0:  know and don't know about in China and other parts and other nations that are putting stuff into orbit. One of the sad things also is like you know with Lockheed and Boeing.
SPEAKER_0:  is uh
SPEAKER_0:  and just military applications in general.
SPEAKER_0:  so much technology that's currently being developed.
SPEAKER_0:  that we probably know nothing about.
SPEAKER_0:  And that makes me a little bit sad, of course.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... for several reasons one is that the use of that technology is
SPEAKER_0:  has really much
SPEAKER_0:  It's not that inspiring, it's like a very military focus. Yeah, it's to kill someone. It's to kill someone, yeah. There's not even like a-
SPEAKER_0:  a side application.
SPEAKER_0:  Right. And the big one is that it's shrouded in secrecy as opposed to being a source of inspiration.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's the way of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  Like what was that one plane that you covered that was like we know nothing about?
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, the X37B.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, there's
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, orbited for over 900 days and returned.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I want to know about that thing. I don't know. That's what's-
SPEAKER_1:  It's so frustrating, we know when it launches, people...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, amateurs track and no.
SPEAKER_1:  They even will be like, oh, it changed orbit. You know, it raised and lowered its orbit, blah, blah, blah.
SPEAKER_1:  I generally have just almost no idea what it's doing up there.
SPEAKER_1:  I just...
SPEAKER_1:  That saddens me, because I wanna know!
SPEAKER_1:  And it's awesome, it's a great vehicle.
SPEAKER_0:  War.
SPEAKER_0:  What is it good for?
SPEAKER_0:  You mentioned Kerbal Space Program, the video game. Someone asked you what video game you recommend for learning about space and rockets and you said...
SPEAKER_0:  Duh.
SPEAKER_0:  Kerbal Space Program. So tell me about this game. What is this game?
SPEAKER_0:  And I also saw...
SPEAKER_0:  heard.
SPEAKER_0:  second one is coming out.
SPEAKER_0:  So what? This is your Watch...
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, you know, I've been playing more games recently.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... cuz
SPEAKER_0:  Games are fun and they remind you.
SPEAKER_0:  That life is awesome.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Why should I play this game? If you want to learn about.
SPEAKER_1:  rockets, how to fly, how to build, how to get into orbit, how to get to other planets.
SPEAKER_1:  There's no better way to learn about rockets.
SPEAKER_0:  What does it entail? Like, do you actually like-
SPEAKER_1:  It's like SimCity.
SPEAKER_1:  and Microsoft Flight Simulator.
SPEAKER_1:  for rockets.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh interesting, so you will get to like...
SPEAKER_0:  Would you design rockets? Yeah?
SPEAKER_1:  It's.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so I started playing it in like 2014, I think around...
SPEAKER_1:  as I'm like falling in love with space. And I became obsessed with this game. Like literally you, you know, you.
SPEAKER_1:  You, you.
SPEAKER_1:  Take a look at the get a little command module. Click you click on a fuel tank. Boop you choose your engine. Boop you choose a stage connector. Boop you connect more tanks and build these.
SPEAKER_1:  space planes and fantastical things and it's all like physics based.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a fail. This sounds like a commercial.
SPEAKER_1:  It's available on PC and Mac and console. It's available everywhere. But wait, there's more. And you can send me a message there and there should be next time
SPEAKER_0:  You said like you streamed yourself playing this. Are those any of those videos up? Oh yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, yeah, there's some of my, actually the first videos I ever uploaded to YouTube were recaptured streams from Twitch.
SPEAKER_1:  that are just physically.
SPEAKER_0:  uploaded to YouTube. This is awesome.
SPEAKER_1:  And so it's me playing. We I see this kind of like a podcast style thing.
SPEAKER_1:  I should get back into this because it's one of my favorite things I ever did. It's called-
SPEAKER_1:  We called it today-ish in space flight history, but these days that probably just-
SPEAKER_1:  play Kerbal, but I had my friend come sit next to me.
SPEAKER_1:  His name's Jacob.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  He is a former professional pole vaulter.
SPEAKER_1:  Just this really.
SPEAKER_1:  knows nothing about rockets, knows nothing about space, hilarious, like in the sweetest-
SPEAKER_1:  most fun way he, you know, as an adult asked me which is bigger the earth or the moon?
SPEAKER_1:  And I love that for him, you know, that's fantastic. He's just a delightful human.
SPEAKER_1:  He would sit next to me.
SPEAKER_1:  we would recreate a historical space flight mission in Kerbal Space Program. And he would just sit there and play guitar and sing about what I'm like doing and asking questions. And it's still one of my favorite things I've ever done.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, you should definitely do something like that. So basically
SPEAKER_0:  Just, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Shoot the shit with a friend.
SPEAKER_1:  Get their curiosity going, let them just sit there and ask questions.
SPEAKER_1:  It was awesome, like.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean it.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Those are some, I've done it a handful of times. I think we probably did like 20 or 30 episodes or something in this.
SPEAKER_1:  It's definitely something I would like to get back to doing.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you in the game go to the moon?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so it's technically a different solar system. It's the Kerbal system and you're on the planet Kerbin.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's the Mun.
SPEAKER_1:  M-U-N. There's a second moon.
SPEAKER_1:  in the system on this planet.
SPEAKER_1:  It's called MinMess.
SPEAKER_0:  They didn't want to pay licensing fees or what?
SPEAKER_1:  Well, it's just a little easier. It's a little bit smaller, so the physics are easier.
SPEAKER_1:  Also tries to
SPEAKER_0:  be consistent.
SPEAKER_1:  physics. Yeah, oh yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  The physics are all real world.
SPEAKER_1:  physics and I mean there's aero simulations there's
SPEAKER_1:  All of its-
SPEAKER_1:  like one-to-one, you know, for Earth physics. It's just on an easier scale, solar system. So it's easier.
SPEAKER_1:  to navigate, but there's still like, there's a planet called Eve that's kind of like Venus.
SPEAKER_1:  So it has a really thick atmosphere, really thick, really soupy.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a lot more gravity, so it's just really, really hard to get off of.
SPEAKER_1:  It's relatively easy to land on Eve, but that's kind of like the ultimate boss in the game, is getting off of Eve. So that's one of my favorite things to do.
SPEAKER_1:  is build these crafts to get to Eve and try to return home.
SPEAKER_0:  You mentioned that there's almost like a podcast thing. You also did our Ludacris feature.
SPEAKER_0:  What, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Is there a podcast in the future? Are you thinking, do you enjoy the media? You're so incredibly good at talking.
SPEAKER_0:  It's less effort to...
SPEAKER_0:  sort of to produce. Is that something in the back of your mind also?
SPEAKER_0:  Ah man.
SPEAKER_1:  I love.
SPEAKER_0:  talking. Yeah, you're very good at it. I mean, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, I.
SPEAKER_1:  I find...
SPEAKER_1:  DRIVE
SPEAKER_1:  It's just.
SPEAKER_1:  The problem with for me is.
SPEAKER_1:  podcast and I guess the podcasts that I've done.
SPEAKER_1:  tried to be relatively topical about like the current spaceflight.
SPEAKER_1:  Affairs.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  See ya.
SPEAKER_1:  three or four years ago, that was actually.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, manageable for me to keep up with these days.
SPEAKER_1:  Man, I can't.
SPEAKER_1:  just can't keep up with it.
SPEAKER_1:  I gave up on trying to be super topical and I realized.
SPEAKER_1:  that maybe my...
SPEAKER_1:  biggest talent and the things that resonate most with people is
SPEAKER_1:  just trying to explain the basics and the root. So I'm really just trying to like.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm trying to do less live streams if I can, but then again, like, Starship, I gotta stream that. There's no way I'm not gonna do that.
SPEAKER_1:  but I'm really just trying to get back to making the deep dive videos where I have no
SPEAKER_1:  limit on how long and how deep and just really go for it. Because that's actually what I love to do.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, that's like, uh, views aside.
SPEAKER_0:  Those are just works of genius and you're getting better and better at them. And like that's the.
SPEAKER_0:  in terms of the beautiful things you can create in this world, those are that. So like if you continue, especially where the way space travel is developing.
SPEAKER_0:  Like that, your voice is very much needed.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's wise to...
SPEAKER_0:  to do what you do best.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think I'm feeling more and more, especially this last year, I did a lot of like live streaming and traveling back and forth between Florida and California and here. And just.
SPEAKER_1:  handling major like big live streams.
SPEAKER_1:  really stressed myself out and at the end of the day I was like
SPEAKER_1:  All of this is taking away from my ability to make videos.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's ideally, honestly, if I had my choice of things, I would just ignore everything else and just sit and lock myself in a-
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  in my house for a year and just sit there and make videos and go and travel every...
SPEAKER_1:  every other month, you know, for fun, like not for space stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  just go and do some light traveling, you know, some.
SPEAKER_0:  Like around the moon or what?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, just some light traveling.
SPEAKER_0:  What advice?
SPEAKER_0:  you would you give the young folks are just folks struggling to find.
SPEAKER_0:  their way in life, whether they're in high school, college, or beyond.
SPEAKER_0:  I kind of have a life that can be proud of.
SPEAKER_0:  to have a career they can be proud of. You've had a-
SPEAKER_0:  Really interesting journey yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  What from that can you draw?
SPEAKER_0:  Give good advice to others.
SPEAKER_1:  To be honest, I feel like...
SPEAKER_1:  It's so...
SPEAKER_1:  painfully obvious to follow your heart and follow what makes you happy that I'm just shocked that people allow themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  to sit on like mediocrity, you know, like to just sit there and be like, well, this is just what I do. Wait on some and...
SPEAKER_1:  for a lot of people that's perfectly fine. Like I have.
SPEAKER_1:  some of my best friends are.
SPEAKER_1:  They're clocking in and out and they're perfectly happy. They have a wonderful life. Absolutely no judgment there, of course.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  but.
SPEAKER_1:  for people that are stuck feeling like they're.
SPEAKER_1:  not sure if you know.
SPEAKER_1:  what's next and how to.
SPEAKER_1:  bring light into their world.
SPEAKER_1:  You really just gotta listen to like what does make you happy, you know, people feel guilty about I play video games for eight hours
SPEAKER_1:  then start learning how to make a video game.
SPEAKER_1:  Learn how to do reviews of video games or make
SPEAKER_1:  There's so many, you can work in the video game industry. You don't have to isolate your love from your work.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just funny that we, you know, maybe.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe you feel guilty that you drink too much. Okay, I don't know if this is a good advice. Go learn how to make alcohol. Start a liquor company. Yeah, start a liquor company. But, yeah, make sure you make a perguntt.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's great advice, but it's also in your own story. It seems like you've almost stumbled on
SPEAKER_0:  Like.
SPEAKER_0:  Some of it is just exploration and keeping your mind and heart open.
SPEAKER_0:  discovering that thing that grabs you.
SPEAKER_1:  What are you fall asleep thinking about?
SPEAKER_1:  You know, like...
SPEAKER_1:  But you stumbled on-
SPEAKER_0:  the space almost accidentally, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Any?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, yeah, I get the good deal would you when you were doing up being a professional photographer, would you have known?
SPEAKER_0:  Oh no.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you want to know what I wanted to be when I was a kid?
SPEAKER_1:  Well, first when I was young, I wanted to be a tractor. I'm not quite sure I understood.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  how that works.
SPEAKER_1:  then I wanted to be a scorpion trainer.
SPEAKER_1:  Thought I could train them to cut people's lawns. Better and better. Yep.
SPEAKER_1:  And then honestly, the majority of my childhood was long. Got it.
SPEAKER_0:  I think your understanding of physics early on was just a little.
SPEAKER_0:  The Pintures, man.
SPEAKER_1:  Get it off. Ahh.
SPEAKER_1:  from like probably six until like early college, I wanted to be a prosthetic engineer.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Never once did I think about.
SPEAKER_1:  anything rockets really. You know, I had like a.
SPEAKER_1:  I had like a space shuttle poster, I had some space shuttle Legos.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I liked space and you know, I knew of the space shuttle, but.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, is it?
SPEAKER_1:  Far down the list as far as.
SPEAKER_1:  Things that I thought were cool.
SPEAKER_1:  Ninja Turtles.
SPEAKER_1:  Lamborghini Countach.
SPEAKER_1:  B-17G Flying Fortress.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I guess, I guess that.
SPEAKER_0:  That means if you just keep your heart open to falling in love with an idea, with a passion, yeah. You could start from that, from Ninja Turtles and Scorpions and lawn.
SPEAKER_0:  to a being.
SPEAKER_0:  one of the best, one of the top educators.
SPEAKER_0:  inspirational figures in space.
SPEAKER_0:  and actually traveling around the moon. And who knows maybe one day stepping foot on the moon and
SPEAKER_0:  Mars even though you say you're not interested.
SPEAKER_0:  It seems like...
SPEAKER_0:  you stating that you're not interested in certain things somehow results.
SPEAKER_1:  And you are, and you're doing those things. My friends joke that like, I'm gonna be the first person to go to the moon against their will. But anyways, have fun..
SPEAKER_0:  Like I guess, all right. Yeah, dang it. What's the thing?
SPEAKER_1:  Guys, we're going to start a fundraiser. Please, like.
SPEAKER_1:  Tim just doesn't want to go. Definitely don't want to do it.
SPEAKER_0:  All right, Tim, you're an incredible person. Thank you so much for everything you do. I've been a fan of yours for a long time. Not just the content, but just who you are as a human being, just how excited you are.
SPEAKER_0:  for everything, it's just an inspiration, you're a joy to watch. Thank you for being you, thank you for doing the stuff you're doing.
SPEAKER_0:  I can't wait to see.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you do next, man?
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you so much for talking with me today. This is awesome.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you so much, it's my pleasure.
SPEAKER_0:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with Tim Dodd.
SPEAKER_0:  support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_0:  And now...
SPEAKER_0:  Let me leave you with some words from H.G. Wells.
SPEAKER_0:  Life.
SPEAKER_0:  Forever dying to be born afresh.
SPEAKER_0:  forever young and eager.
SPEAKER_0:  will presently stand upon this earth as upon a footstool.
SPEAKER_0:  Stretched out.
SPEAKER_0:  It's Realm.
SPEAKER_0:  I miss the stars.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you for listening.
SPEAKER_0:  and hope to see you.
SPEAKER_0:  next time.