SPEAKER_0:  Narcissism is not arrogance. Narcissism is the opposite.
SPEAKER_0:  of arrogance. There is such a deep sense of inadequacy.
SPEAKER_0:  and incompetence in the self.
SPEAKER_0:  that the defensive structure around that.
SPEAKER_0:  becomes dominated by rocket fueled.
SPEAKER_0:  ENVY.
SPEAKER_1:  The following is a conversation with Paul Conte.
SPEAKER_1:  a psychiatrist, and a brilliant scholar of human nature.
SPEAKER_1:  My friend.
SPEAKER_1:  Andrew Huberman
SPEAKER_1:  told me that Paul and I absolutely must meet and talk.
SPEAKER_1:  Not just about the topic of trauma, which Paul wrote an amazing book about.
SPEAKER_1:  but broadly about human nature.
SPEAKER_1:  narcissism, sociopathy, psychopathy.
SPEAKER_1:  Good and Evil.
SPEAKER_1:  Hate and love.
SPEAKER_1:  happiness and envy.
SPEAKER_1:  As usual...
SPEAKER_1:  Andrew was right.
SPEAKER_1:  This was a fascinating conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  as the old meme goes.
SPEAKER_1:  one does not simply doubt the advice of Andrew Huberman.
SPEAKER_1:  Allow me to also quickly mention.
SPEAKER_1:  that I disagree with Paul a bunch in this episode.
SPEAKER_1:  as I do in other episodes, even with exports.
SPEAKER_1:  in part for fun and in part because I think
SPEAKER_1:  The tension of ideas and conversation is what creates insights and wisdom.
SPEAKER_1:  My goal is to always empathize, understand, and explore ideas of the person.
SPEAKER_1:  sitting across from me.
SPEAKER_1:  Disagreement is just one of the ways I think it's fun to do just that.
SPEAKER_1:  As long as I do so.
SPEAKER_1:  from a place of curiosity and compassion.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the Lex Freedman Podcast.
SPEAKER_1:  To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now, dear friends.
SPEAKER_1:  Here's Paul.
SPEAKER_1:  Conti.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you see psychiatry as fundamentally a study of the human mind and not just a set of tools for treating psychological spanning?
SPEAKER_0:  Absolutely. I think psychiatry is our best way.
SPEAKER_0:  to understand who we are as
SPEAKER_0:  It looks at our biology.
SPEAKER_0:  How does our brain work? How does it connect the parts with one another? How does the chemistry in it work?
SPEAKER_0:  It's the very foundational aspects of.
SPEAKER_0:  who we are and then it manifests as
SPEAKER_0:  psychology, what do we think, what do we feel, what are our strivings, what are our fears?
SPEAKER_0:  So yeah, I think psychiatry provides.
SPEAKER_0:  tools that we can use to help each other, but those tools come through it being a discipline of understanding.
SPEAKER_1:  So with every
SPEAKER_1:  patient you see with every mind you explore.
SPEAKER_1:  Are you picking up a deeper understanding of the human mind?
SPEAKER_0:  I think I'm trying to, I think we should learn.
SPEAKER_0:  should be able to.
SPEAKER_0:  take something away from.
SPEAKER_0:  everything we do, you know, every...
SPEAKER_0:  interaction to some small degree.
SPEAKER_1:  conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  It doesn't have to be a patient, just anywhere.
SPEAKER_1:  at Starbucks, getting a coffee.
SPEAKER_1:  You can learn something from that little experience.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, even if you just reinforce sort of-
SPEAKER_0:  gentle kindness and gratitude and
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  decent human interaction. There's a reinforcement of that, that even if we don't take away memories or lessons, so to speak, we can reinforce who we choose to be.
SPEAKER_1:  So understanding ourselves from those interactions too, not just the general sort of philosophical human mind, but
SPEAKER_1:  understanding our own.
SPEAKER_1:  mind.
SPEAKER_1:  introspect.
SPEAKER_1:  and how our own mind works.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, because everything we understand about anyone or anything else...
SPEAKER_0:  is coming through here, right? So
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, or understanding others where.
SPEAKER_0:  We're also understanding ourselves, it's all feeding.
SPEAKER_0:  through us.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, but it's a tricky thing to step away and look at your mind.
SPEAKER_1:  and understand that it's just a machine.
SPEAKER_1:  and you can kind of control the way the machine processes the external environment.
SPEAKER_1:  and the way that
SPEAKER_1:  machine converts the things it perceives into actual emotions.
SPEAKER_1:  Like how it interprets the things it perceives.
SPEAKER_1:  You just sort of step away and analyze it in that way.
SPEAKER_1:  and then you can control it. You can...
SPEAKER_1:  you can oil the machine, you can control how it actually interprets the perceptions.
SPEAKER_1:  in order to generate positive emotions.
SPEAKER_1:  and be like a, what is it, like a mechanic.
SPEAKER_1:  for the...
SPEAKER_1:  for the gears in the machine.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I think to some degree, to some degree, a bit.
SPEAKER_0:  The difference, I think, at least as I.
SPEAKER_0:  Understand I think of machines as not being
SPEAKER_0:  inscrutable.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, that if there's enough.
SPEAKER_0:  study there's enough acumen applied
SPEAKER_0:  that
SPEAKER_0:  we can understand whatever it is we're trying to figure out. Where as
SPEAKER_0:  part of understanding ourselves.
SPEAKER_0:  is understanding that there are things we can't understand.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think that's.
SPEAKER_0:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  Indispensably important.
SPEAKER_0:  to health and happiness and also.
SPEAKER_0:  to having enough humility to see.
SPEAKER_0:  how people can be different from us, how we can be different from ourselves.
SPEAKER_0:  at times, so knowing that we don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot.
SPEAKER_0:  and having some idea of what that might be, I think is.
SPEAKER_0:  an indispensable part of the process, which I think is different from machines.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, the machines, you're basically saying machines generally because they're engineered.
SPEAKER_1:  from a design, they're usually going to be simpler.
SPEAKER_1:  therefore understandable.
SPEAKER_1:  And you're saying the complexity of the human mind is...
SPEAKER_1:  at least from our perspective, nearly infinite.
SPEAKER_0:  Is there a meta-phenomena, what sometimes gets described as sort of levels of emergence where at increasing levels of complexity?
SPEAKER_0:  you have novelty evolve that you can't predict from lower levels of complexity. Like for example,
SPEAKER_0:  atoms to molecules. It's just one.
SPEAKER_0:  example. I think
SPEAKER_0:  neurons to consciousness, consciousness to culture.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Meta phenomena that separate from the phenomenon.
SPEAKER_0:  for the phenomena underneath of them.
SPEAKER_0:  and thereby add an entire aspect of novelty.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think we are.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I really think this is true that we are all infinitely fascinating because of these levels of emergence of novelty that are inscrutable because you can't predict from one level.
SPEAKER_0:  to the next or understand.
SPEAKER_0:  fully are what make us.
SPEAKER_0:  And not just us, but I think sentient creatures, human beings, but sentient creatures, inestimably more.
SPEAKER_0:  interesting than creatures that aren't sentient. And I don't know, I think when...
SPEAKER_0:  When we think about machine learning and artificial intelligence, I think it's that.
SPEAKER_0:  that we're trying to create levels of emergence that now.
SPEAKER_0:  we don't fully understand.
SPEAKER_0:  anymore, which I guess is both exciting and maybe scary too.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so you started the physics of atoms.
SPEAKER_1:  quantum mechanics.
SPEAKER_1:  go into chemistry, go into biology.
SPEAKER_1:  from the biology, you have the functional phenomena, especially as manifested in the human brain. Then
SPEAKER_1:  Multiple brains connecting together through consciousness and intelligence creates civilizations.
SPEAKER_1:  It's pretty interesting. Where do you think the magic is?
SPEAKER_1:  at which layer of the cake.
SPEAKER_0:  every layer.
SPEAKER_0:  because every time you emerge from one thing to another, I see it as an analog with the concept of the dialect.
SPEAKER_0:  right, where I think it was Hegel, right, who...
SPEAKER_0:  who realized...
SPEAKER_0:  Hey, when you have like...
SPEAKER_0:  thing A and thing B and they're complicated and they come together.
SPEAKER_0:  you don't get a hybrid of A and B, right? You end up getting something that's new, that's novel.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think that...
SPEAKER_0:  describes to some degree that like what emergence is.
SPEAKER_0:  except there's
SPEAKER_0:  There's a whole new, it's a universe of novelty.
SPEAKER_0:  That comes in each layer of.
SPEAKER_0:  emergence that allows infinite possibilities that weren't.
SPEAKER_0:  possible before and I think that's why we're so complicated that we're our
SPEAKER_0:  functional neuroscience, right, which I think is psychology, right, our ability to think about ourselves, about others, to be reflective.
SPEAKER_0:  is sitting on top of.
SPEAKER_0:  So many.
SPEAKER_0:  layers of emergence, like the idea of standing on the shoulders of giants that we're...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, each of us, our consciousness is standing on the shoulder of a giant.
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  Many many many...
SPEAKER_0:  levels of emergence, of novelty.
SPEAKER_0:  so many of which we don't understand. I mean, about subatomic particles, everything that quantum physics means, when does time become important?
SPEAKER_0:  right, as opposed to.
SPEAKER_0:  things happening outside of time and outside of space.
SPEAKER_0:  When do we slide into one?
SPEAKER_0:  temporal perspective and then the complexity just I think grows and grows and grows.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, the interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  where he uses novelty.
SPEAKER_1:  If true, this really blows my mind.
SPEAKER_1:  either shallow or deep sense, it is true.
SPEAKER_1:  trying to figure that out.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if you know something about cellular automata, it's this very simple
SPEAKER_1:  mathematical objects where you have rules that govern each individual little cell and they interact locally.
SPEAKER_1:  and that you understand the very simple operation of those individual cells but
SPEAKER_1:  add another layer of abstraction when you just kind of zoom out with blurry vision.
SPEAKER_1:  this.
SPEAKER_1:  matter object starts appearing that.
SPEAKER_1:  function you could build.
SPEAKER_1:  a torrent machine where they can build arbitrary complexity of compute of
SPEAKER_1:  of computation on top of this kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  Very simple object.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes. Questioning question whether.
SPEAKER_1:  That was always there.
SPEAKER_1:  the arms
SPEAKER_1:  somehow know about love.
SPEAKER_1:  Right?
SPEAKER_1:  like about consciousness.
SPEAKER_1:  about war and violence and evil and hate and all that.
SPEAKER_1:  that's already laid in, the possibility of that, the capacity for that's already in the atoms.
SPEAKER_1:  It's already in the physics, it's already in the...
SPEAKER_1:  in all the different chemistry that builds up. And it's like even the origin of life.
SPEAKER_1:  Still a mystery.
SPEAKER_1:  That's.
SPEAKER_1:  That's known.
SPEAKER_1:  That's in the physics.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  That's known to the universe, the basic...
SPEAKER_1:  background physics in the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  Because if this is that's not the case
SPEAKER_1:  It's like, where does that come from? Where's that magic?
SPEAKER_1:  And how many layers can the cake possibly have?
SPEAKER_1:  How many are we gonna keep building?
SPEAKER_1:  If we're constantly through this process of abstraction.
SPEAKER_1:  of adding a layer to the cake, adding novel things.
SPEAKER_1:  Like where's the ceiling?
SPEAKER_1:  as we expand out into the cosmos.
SPEAKER_1:  if we successfully can do that, are we gonna keep building like-
SPEAKER_1:  more miraculous complex.
SPEAKER_1:  objects and then the brain is just like a
SPEAKER_1:  middle layer.
SPEAKER_1:  We tend to think of ourselves as truly, truly special.
SPEAKER_1:  manifestations of what's possible in the universe, but maybe we're just like the basic like-
SPEAKER_1:  tiny building block or something much much
SPEAKER_1:  much bigger. We're in the early days of
SPEAKER_1:  being a brick.
SPEAKER_0:  and a very large building.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's entirely...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I think...
SPEAKER_0:  The only-
SPEAKER_0:  emergent thing, so to speak, that we build this culture, right? The aggregation of us. So you have individual human minds.
SPEAKER_0:  Which...
SPEAKER_0:  You are entirely
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, even the fact that time is different for you and me, right? Maybe by picoseconds, right?
SPEAKER_0:  We
SPEAKER_0:  can engage because our.
SPEAKER_0:  perceptions of time are parallel enough, they're close enough, right, that we can share a reality, right? But we're all living.
SPEAKER_0:  in a different dimension of time.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, we know that, right? So we're unique.
SPEAKER_0:  in that way and then.
SPEAKER_0:  the unique individuals that we are, just like the cells, start to create.
SPEAKER_0:  not just one thing, not just a culture, but culture on top of
SPEAKER_0:  hour.
SPEAKER_0:  individuality, right? Our uniqueness, our even dimensional uniqueness of time and experience and consciousness.
SPEAKER_0:  So we create cultures on top of us.
SPEAKER_0:  what could be beyond culture, right? and what
SPEAKER_0:  is.
SPEAKER_0:  different from us either on underlying levels like quantum physics or chemistry or biology or entirely different and unconceived I think is.
SPEAKER_0:  It's an immense.
SPEAKER_0:  question and I think it's one that should create humility in us, right? Look how much we don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  and then how reckless we are.
SPEAKER_0:  with ourselves, with our resources, with...
SPEAKER_0:  with
SPEAKER_0:  human life. And I think there it's important to say, think about how entropy rules.
SPEAKER_0:  the universe around us. I mean, how over-
SPEAKER_0:  selected are we? How many?
SPEAKER_0:  Not just...
SPEAKER_0:  hundreds or thousands of times, but how many millions of times does there have to be a selection branch point before
SPEAKER_0:  we get into a sort of eddy pool of counter entropy, right? where you can begin to create.
SPEAKER_0:  which I think is why you say, okay, do the atoms know about love, right?
SPEAKER_0:  The- the- the-
SPEAKER_0:  The fact that anything is being created, right, means there's this over-selection for counter entropy where there can be a building of...
SPEAKER_0:  greater complexity of ultimately of
SPEAKER_0:  novelty and we don't often think about.
SPEAKER_0:  that of how far removed we are, maybe light years, so to speak.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, from.
SPEAKER_0:  any other location, temporally, physically in the universe where this could happen.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't think about what does that.
SPEAKER_0:  ME.
SPEAKER_1:  Everything they just said love
SPEAKER_1:  Everything.
SPEAKER_1:  is counter entropy goes against the way.
SPEAKER_1:  the basic physics of the universe. So maybe actually the atoms really don't like what we're doing.
SPEAKER_1:  They want us to stop. They've been trying really hard to stop.
SPEAKER_1:  and despite that we somehow
SPEAKER_1:  uh... started this whole bacteria thing for for the bill
SPEAKER_0:  million years and now we're here.
SPEAKER_0:  I should think of it.
SPEAKER_0:  Kind of the other way.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think there's any purpose to purposelessness, right? So why would anything be here if we...
SPEAKER_0:  The drive weren't.
SPEAKER_0:  chords.
SPEAKER_0:  creativity, right? If it's a derived warrant towards those subatomic particles.
SPEAKER_0:  not being nothingness that blips in and out of existence, right? Like we think is going on in empty space, you know, for light years upon light years, right? But is
SPEAKER_0:  Is there...
SPEAKER_0:  a design, either natural or intentional.
SPEAKER_0:  for a schema, right, a scenario.
SPEAKER_0:  that allows for the incredibly rare but not non-existent
SPEAKER_0:  any pool of counter entropy where
SPEAKER_0:  Good can happen, right? Good can happen, right?
SPEAKER_0:  creativity can happen where ultimately
SPEAKER_0:  something can grow, something novel.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no novelty in the vastness of space even though there's not nothing.
SPEAKER_0:  there.
SPEAKER_0:  There's novelty here.
SPEAKER_0:  because I think the layers of emergence start stacking very, very, very high when we're in a place of counter entropy.
SPEAKER_0:  Which then.
SPEAKER_0:  could provide.
SPEAKER_0:  even thoughts about like good and evil, right? The idea that creating...
SPEAKER_0:  that preserving is good, right? It's what we build upon. It's how we get to the eddy pool of counterenters.
SPEAKER_0:  So then destruction is
SPEAKER_0:  not good, what good comes of...
SPEAKER_0:  aggression and destruction.
SPEAKER_0:  Unless we're protecting, we can think of...
SPEAKER_0:  outlying cases, but just think in general concepts, right? Stephen Ban мин wir wir «Sch cockro prevent»
SPEAKER_0:  destroys, it brings us towards a state of entropy, towards a state of nothingness, whereas
SPEAKER_0:  a goodness commonality collaboration, right?
SPEAKER_0:  nurturing brings.
SPEAKER_0:  novelty, it brings new existence into the universe. And I think we don't think about that. We're in the middle of something so vast and built on top of so many layers. And I think it leads us to be.
SPEAKER_0:  Cavalier.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, with, with...
SPEAKER_0:  human life, including often our own.
SPEAKER_0:  So you think this.
SPEAKER_1:  There's an underlying creative force to the universe.
SPEAKER_1:  that uh...
SPEAKER_1:  that might even have a kind of...
SPEAKER_1:  built in morality to it.
SPEAKER_1:  Where?
SPEAKER_1:  Creating is better than destroying.
SPEAKER_1:  and then that somehow maps on to our society.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, we kind of try to figure out what that actually means.
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of good and evil.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's that's some something is there like that. It's like panicking
SPEAKER_1:  But it has to be.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like so nice, it's so perfect, cause it's rare.
SPEAKER_1:  It's sufficiently rare where we have our own space. Like you can close the door and say, I need to be alone right now as our human civilization to work on my thing.
SPEAKER_1:  So sufficiently rare that there's not other alien civilizations. They're just like constantly knocking on our door destroying us.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  but it still exists.
SPEAKER_0:  That's weird.
SPEAKER_0:  It's so fantastically improbable that I think we should be very.
SPEAKER_0:  respectful of it. And I think you said there's a creative force that values creativity. Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  Well sure, if it's a creative force, right?
SPEAKER_0:  It's existence.
SPEAKER_0:  its ability to exist and to create.
SPEAKER_0:  comes from something other than entropy, right? Something other than so much dispersion that there's nothingness, right? So the creative force will value...
SPEAKER_0:  sanctity of things, right? You know, keeping things together, not destroying things, right? Building...
SPEAKER_0:  novelty, including novelty of knowledge, novelty of sentience. I mean, it fits.
SPEAKER_0:  with the idea that we're not nothing, that that's incredibly improbable.
SPEAKER_0:  and that there are these many, many layers of emergence that we're standing upon.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think it tells us something that we're not.
SPEAKER_0:  doing ourselves a service to ignore.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not just a jump to saying.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, there's a religious answer to everything. No, it's saying.
SPEAKER_0:  science isn't a god either, right? So if we think of science as a tool...
SPEAKER_0:  and not as an endpoint in and of itself, what is the science telling us? like I remember
SPEAKER_0:  showing up at medical school and it really is true. I mean, I knew...
SPEAKER_0:  so little about the human body. I'd only been in hospitals to visit people. I'd taken pre-med classes, but sort of
SPEAKER_0:  intensely at once after I didn't take any and I was working in business. I knew next to nothing and I had this idea that was so naive in retrospect that
SPEAKER_0:  I was gonna learn so much, right? I was gonna answer these questions, because I was gonna learn what's going on in the body, what are these organs doing, what are these cells?
SPEAKER_0:  And what I learned was...
SPEAKER_0:  There was so much more that was amazing.
SPEAKER_0:  mysterious and seemingly impossible, like even how a cell functions.
SPEAKER_0:  Like what is going on inside of a cell, the transport mechanisms and...
SPEAKER_0:  energy functions and diffusion functions, and then you can go down to smaller levels than that. But when you come back out and you say, how all those cells make a kidney?
SPEAKER_0:  It's not.
SPEAKER_0:  explanatory. I remember asking the OB who had delivered my first child. I was so amazed and I asked him like.
SPEAKER_0:  What do you think? What do you know? You do this, right? You're seeing this life created and-
SPEAKER_0:  You know, and his thought was...
SPEAKER_0:  Nothing, I just marvel. I mean, I get to do this, but I just-
SPEAKER_0:  Marvel at it and I think the more we know
SPEAKER_0:  about us.
SPEAKER_0:  the more we respectfully marvel.
SPEAKER_1:  And we should do that. We should proactively marvel at every aspect.
SPEAKER_1:  at every layer.
SPEAKER_1:  that where the novelty emerges.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  we'd be a lot less likely to say,
SPEAKER_0:  hey, I don't like you because of something, whatever it is, you know, race, religion, culture.
SPEAKER_0:  sexuality, gender identity, whatever it is, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  I want rights that you don't have, right? Or I want what you have.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, there's so much of this and I understand it's driven by scarcity and by human insecurity and envy and all of these things that I think could drive us towards destruction.
SPEAKER_0:  But-
SPEAKER_0:  All of that recklessness comes from.
SPEAKER_0:  not having this initial appreciation and respect that you're referring to and just marveling at, like, wow, okay, we're here.
SPEAKER_0:  That's amazing. Let's start with that.
SPEAKER_1:  But if we marvel at this...
SPEAKER_1:  whole thing.
SPEAKER_1:  the human project, the human condition, all the different kinds of human beings that are possible.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you then make of that?
SPEAKER_1:  some humans.
SPEAKER_1:  do evil onto the world.
SPEAKER_1:  First of all, are all human beings capable of evil?
SPEAKER_1:  If we're in the process.
SPEAKER_1:  Now we've got a little bit of momentum in terms of marvelling.
SPEAKER_1:  the layers of the cake.
SPEAKER_1:  Should we also marvel at the capacity for evil in all of us?
SPEAKER_1:  Is that capacity there? I believe that it is.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  So what do we understand about the psychology of evil? Where does it originate in the human mind?
SPEAKER_1:  Is it there in your biology?
SPEAKER_1:  Is it there in the environment?
SPEAKER_1:  Any upbringing?
SPEAKER_0:  Can I clarify first? I think the capacity for evil, I do believe is in all of us.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a difference between.
SPEAKER_0:  enacting evil and
SPEAKER_0:  and a suit of-
SPEAKER_0:  preset
SPEAKER_0:  followed developed plan of evil.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, I don't believe that all of us are capable of doing.
SPEAKER_0:  What?
SPEAKER_0:  the people who perpetrate the most evil do.
SPEAKER_0:  But I do believe that we're capable.
SPEAKER_0:  of
SPEAKER_0:  of.
SPEAKER_0:  perpetrating evil.
SPEAKER_0:  And the thought, one thought would be that...
SPEAKER_0:  There are...
SPEAKER_0:  drives in us. I mean, there certainly seem to be drives.
SPEAKER_0:  in us towards.
SPEAKER_0:  survival towards gratification, in some ways towards.
SPEAKER_0:  and that can get very complicated because pleasure inside can be relief of distress.
SPEAKER_0:  If I feel very badly about myself...
SPEAKER_0:  and I can feel a little better about myself by making you feel worse about yourself, right? Which that plays out in a lot of human beings. Is that an indirect way of bringing pleasure, right? So it gets very complicated what's going on inside of us. And sometimes the perpetration of...
SPEAKER_0:  Evil things can be through misunderstandings, anger, impulsivity. I mean, there are things that we can...
SPEAKER_0:  that we can have.
SPEAKER_0:  in us and other times there can be other things going on which are through the lens of unhealthy human psychology. So for example, the psychology of envy, which I think drives
SPEAKER_0:  the lion's share of the orchestrated evil, right? There's a difference between...
SPEAKER_0:  Impulsive reflexive.
SPEAKER_0:  evil and
SPEAKER_0:  highly orchestrated evil, which I think is driven by.
SPEAKER_0:  Envy.
SPEAKER_0:  highly orchestrated.
SPEAKER_1:  evil.
SPEAKER_1:  Are we talking about a scale of societies like totalitarianism?
SPEAKER_1:  if we're thinking about somebody like Hitler.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  as at scale.
SPEAKER_1:  orchestration of evil and be driving that so.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, that's really interesting to.
SPEAKER_1:  to think about it. I'd love to hear more about it. So some of it, there might be some.
SPEAKER_1:  psychological forces that are in tension.
SPEAKER_1:  with each other. So one is.
SPEAKER_1:  If you look at somebody like Hitler.
SPEAKER_1:  It's difficult to know.
SPEAKER_1:  what was going on in his mind.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's possible to imagine if you just look at dictators thought history.
SPEAKER_1:  that he thought he was doing good.
SPEAKER_1:  not just for himself but for
SPEAKER_1:  The people.
SPEAKER_1:  he believed have value.
SPEAKER_1:  So one way you can have.
SPEAKER_1:  you can achieve what we consider as evil.
SPEAKER_1:  is by devaluing some group of people.
SPEAKER_1:  And that could be all group of people. So it could have sort of a narcissistic type of.
SPEAKER_1:  idea that
SPEAKER_1:  You basically don't care about other human beings.
SPEAKER_1:  That's one. That's one.
SPEAKER_1:  different, I mean maybe they can collaborate together.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  or even like you mentioned, you can actually enjoy doing bad to others.
SPEAKER_1:  That's almost like different because if all it is is like narcissism
SPEAKER_1:  You disregarded
SPEAKER_1:  You don't care how others feel.
SPEAKER_1:  then you can just make cold calculated military.
SPEAKER_1:  almost economic decisions.
SPEAKER_1:  And you don't care if a million people die here or there.
SPEAKER_1:  But if you actually enjoy some aspect of that.
SPEAKER_1:  Or there is like a resentment that fuels it. It's not just-
SPEAKER_1:  It's like fueled by some kind of personal.
SPEAKER_1:  or cultural resentment. The city gets off-field by that.
SPEAKER_0:  You think so? I think it's all field, but I think the idea that, say Hitler thought he was doing good, right?
SPEAKER_0:  It is like.
SPEAKER_0:  is such a thin facade that it flies away like a handkerchief in a hurricane.
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, thank you. That's wow. That's beautiful. Yeah
SPEAKER_0:  It's built upon.
SPEAKER_0:  It says.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll explain logical lies, right? Because no.
SPEAKER_0:  people can build lies upon specious logic, right? So the idea that...
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, I am doing good because I believe that this ethnicity of
SPEAKER_0:  People is.
SPEAKER_0:  good and this is bad. And now I'm going to do this and I'm going to make the world different and it's going to bring better to the world. And now I'm raising armies and I'm building concentration camps. And I think like, this is all in the service of good. I don't-
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think anyone ever thinks that.
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_0:  or they think that but with, because they're living.
SPEAKER_0:  in the surface patina, right? Like they're not allowing the hurricane in that blows away the handkerchief and says like, this is all, this is all.
SPEAKER_0:  This is all evil, right? I mean, how do you decide that-
SPEAKER_0:  Some group of people is good and some is bad. What is it that you take upon yourself?
SPEAKER_0:  to, to, to.
SPEAKER_0:  play God or make decisions about the world. And I think what really is going on is people are not doing that.
SPEAKER_0:  There's something cobbled together to say like, why this is right and this is okay, right? And this is even good, right?
SPEAKER_0:  It is all.
SPEAKER_0:  a lie, right? It's a lie that's adorning.
SPEAKER_0:  The
SPEAKER_0:  What I believe is the fact, I believe that what's going on is the gratification of envy.
SPEAKER_0:  inside of the person and whether someone says, oh, I think this is good and it's okay if a million people die or
SPEAKER_0:  I'm gonna enjoy that a million people die, I think is the same.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the enjoyment, the gratification.
SPEAKER_0:  of the orchestrated evil is there and that it all comes from.
SPEAKER_0:  Vulnerability and insecurity, it all comes from deficits.
SPEAKER_0:  in the sense of self.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm gonna have to process that.
SPEAKER_1:  My slow penny and PC is processing that so Envy underlies all of it.
SPEAKER_1:  the psychological concept of envy.
SPEAKER_1:  What is that?
SPEAKER_1:  I keep putting myself in the mind of Hitler, I guess. That has nothing to do, it doesn't have to do with Jews or Slavic people.
SPEAKER_1:  Does it have to do with specific?
SPEAKER_1:  amorphous.
SPEAKER_1:  Other
SPEAKER_1:  in his mind.
SPEAKER_1:  that he's envious of.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it has all to do with him.
SPEAKER_0:  All to do with
SPEAKER_0:  There's not a love of the people with whom he allied or even a sense of the people who he persecuted were worse than him. It's all projections out of what was going on inside of him.
SPEAKER_0:  which was an intense.
SPEAKER_0:  sense of inadequacy.
SPEAKER_0:  a rage at being someone he perceived as lesser.
SPEAKER_0:  then.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the difference between so we can define words in different ways even within psychology. Let's say we take the definition.
SPEAKER_0:  here of sort of jealousy as being sort of benign, right? The idea that, oh, I might see something that you have that I don't, and I might think, I'd like that. Maybe I'll work harder to get it, right? Or maybe I can't get it. Maybe it's that you're younger than I am.
SPEAKER_0:  They say, okay, you have that and I don't. I mean, I have other things too, I'm okay anyway.
SPEAKER_0:  But I might
SPEAKER_0:  want those things, but it's very benign, the jealousy. I'd like to be younger, I'd like to be richer, whatever it is that we people think, right?
SPEAKER_0:  but it's just a thought.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's a thought that can...
SPEAKER_0:  result in strivings or acceptance, right?
SPEAKER_0:  It's very, very different. It's completely different than Envy.
SPEAKER_0:  which is destructive.
SPEAKER_0:  It's the thought of I.
SPEAKER_0:  see something that you have that I don't have, right? And instead of me working for it or accepting that I don't have it, what I'd like to do then is bring you down.
SPEAKER_0:  take you down to where I am and then I'll feel better.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, because from the perspective of envy, it is all.
SPEAKER_0:  Relative.
SPEAKER_1:  So his jealousy is about, as he said, completely different.
SPEAKER_1:  but is jealousy potentially like a gateway drug to envy?
SPEAKER_1:  Like, is it a slippery slough?
SPEAKER_0:  I think no, I think that jealousy...
SPEAKER_0:  is a natural just part of the human phenomenon that we go through life and we see like, oh, I'd like to have that. I think it's part of our incentives, right?
SPEAKER_0:  You know, for FF
SPEAKER_0:  I'm-
SPEAKER_0:  farming and I have one row of crops and I look over and I see that you're working harder and you have two and I'd like to have two that can make me work harder to have two.
SPEAKER_1:  is a slippery slope from one to the other to...
SPEAKER_1:  At first you're like, I'd like to work harder, but then you keep failing and the weather sucks and you keep failing and the other person becomes more successful. Plus he's got a new hot wife now. There's a nice tractor.
SPEAKER_1:  Does it feel this all working and then you get this idea that you know what I'm gonna
SPEAKER_1:  steal all his stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  I gotta murder him.
SPEAKER_1:  And that, don't you think that's just like a leap?
SPEAKER_1:  No, I actually think not. Of the same phenomenon?
SPEAKER_0:  No, because I think.
SPEAKER_0:  There are things that are in us as humans, right? So-
SPEAKER_0:  So the things are just by being human, like we can, for example, feel, we can feel compassion, right? We can feel interest, right? We can feel jealousy in that benign sense. Like, it's all part of just being human.
SPEAKER_0:  If we start going from.
SPEAKER_0:  Hey, you have more crops than I have and, and you know, it seems like I actually have a better life in a lot of ways than I have. I'm gonna kill you. That's not-
SPEAKER_0:  That is not a progression of something benign.
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_1:  That is... But wait, wait a minute, but there is a human leap of the same thing, isn't it?
SPEAKER_1:  is you're drawing a line, stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  You're saying like, this is the, this human stuff is regular life is benign.
SPEAKER_1:  but it feels like this benign thing is just a low magnitude thing.
SPEAKER_1:  version of the thing that's not benign.
SPEAKER_1:  There's probably a gray area where it stops being there. Like jealousy.
SPEAKER_1:  You can have like healthy jealousy. You can have a little bit slightly unhealthy. There's a, that's I think jealous guy. This John Lennon song that I love is just beautiful. I mean, there's like.
SPEAKER_1:  This jealousy inside relationships can make you feel like...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, take your minds and all.
SPEAKER_1:  kinds of silly directions.
SPEAKER_1:  It's crazy, but like it feels like that.
SPEAKER_1:  That's an extra neighbor to like.
SPEAKER_1:  being really crazy and toxic and all that kind of stuff inside relationships. And then that feels like a next door neighbor. It's like an apartment building. That feels like a next door neighbor that eventually gets to Hitler with a.
SPEAKER_1:  with envy and resentment of entire population of people.
SPEAKER_0:  you're writing that there's a causal...
SPEAKER_0:  There can be a causal chain, right? If I'm not feeling jealous.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe I won't ever feel envious, right? So as you can see, okay, so it can kind of lead to can open gates to, huh, like how much do I dislike that you have things that I don't have, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So yes, in that sense, but, and I think.
SPEAKER_0:  this is the part I think is so important that I think there is a disjunction.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? It's, it, there's an asymptotic shift, right? From one thing to another, because it is very- Why are you speaking my language?
SPEAKER_1:  mathematically. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  leap yep.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, that's, it's a way to convey, right, something that's entirely different. Because if I start thinking.
SPEAKER_0:  You know what?
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not gonna try and make things better, right? I'd like instead to harm you. That's qualitatively different.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, it's almost like, you know what it is? It could be, I don't know what you think about this, but...
SPEAKER_1:  It's a...
SPEAKER_1:  In which direction?
SPEAKER_1:  your motivation is pointing.
SPEAKER_1:  So if in the response to the feeling of jealousy.
SPEAKER_1:  your sort of
SPEAKER_1:  The motivation says, okay, I understand this feeling. I want to do less of it.
SPEAKER_1:  I think there must be a threshold to which you actually want to do more of. Like it becomes a vicious downward cycle.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's what envy becomes.
SPEAKER_1:  Like the first feeling, this idea.
SPEAKER_1:  that I'm gonna kill the farmer.
SPEAKER_1:  It turns into like more and more and more and you can't sleep and you're visualizing the farm and he becomes the devil and like you have this
SPEAKER_1:  very, you know, it's basically a thing that builds into the negative direction versus returns to the stable center.
SPEAKER_0:  Now a person is cultivating evil. Yeah. Right, they're saying, hey, there can be seeds of evil in all of us.
SPEAKER_0:  Let me take that seed out, dust it off, plant it, nurture it, right, and then grow that seed of evil, which will affect all other.
SPEAKER_0:  parts of the person's life, right? They won't behave the same towards others.
SPEAKER_0:  in their life. Will they still become different?
SPEAKER_0:  as they nurture fantasies of evil, as they begin to.
SPEAKER_0:  create with inside of themselves the motivation and.
SPEAKER_0:  the will to enact evil. The Hitler analogy would say, when you take someone who had a bad childhood, who was not loved, who was...
SPEAKER_0:  taught and told that he was less than.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, like that.
SPEAKER_0:  And we know that happens. I mean, that's why child abuse is so-
SPEAKER_0:  evil, right? It's telling children.
SPEAKER_0:  the worst possible wrong lessons, right? They're not good enough, they'll always be hurt, they can't keep themselves safe, they don't deserve safety, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So then you take someone.
SPEAKER_0:  Who then?
SPEAKER_0:  nurtures that seed of evil, which is a choice. And this is why I can't paint well enough and no one appreciates me and I don't like how I look and I don't fit in with the people I wanna fit in with and then and on and on and on and on and on.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's a hatred of self.
SPEAKER_0:  through that lens of
SPEAKER_0:  misery of just being repulsed by the self.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's...
SPEAKER_0:  unacceptable to the self.
SPEAKER_0:  or it has to be someone else's fault.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? It's not my fault, whose fault is it?
SPEAKER_0:  Right? And then you see en masse the inaction of evil.
SPEAKER_0:  towards groups of people who
SPEAKER_0:  who somehow in this person's mind are responsible for his-
SPEAKER_0:  misery and there's the justification of evil and then all the
SPEAKER_0:  You know, whether it's...
SPEAKER_0:  this will be better for the economy, this will be good, this will be that. Like that's all lies built to justify.
SPEAKER_0:  the evil.
SPEAKER_1:  Those are surface level narratives.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  and the envy.
SPEAKER_1:  is the deep down mechanism.
SPEAKER_0:  that enabled and that's the end point that's being served. What's being served is destruction.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, which is why.
SPEAKER_0:  It always brings more destruction.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, how many times do you do?
SPEAKER_0:  wars that were started for purposes that we would look and say like those were evil purposes. Like how many times?
SPEAKER_0:  There's good come of that. Even if we look at the modern world, what comes of it is...
SPEAKER_0:  more evil is more destruction. And Hitler's outward destruction eventually came inward and you know you see pictures of what Berlin.
SPEAKER_0:  look like after the second world.
SPEAKER_0:  It wasn't just destruction perpetrated outward as awful as that.
SPEAKER_0:  is it's it's
SPEAKER_0:  It's catchy.
SPEAKER_0:  Like people used to work during the time of the Manhattan Project, right? If you start this chain reaction, you know, will you?
SPEAKER_0:  blow the whole world up, right? Will it stop within this bomb or not?
SPEAKER_0:  and we see, okay, the chain reaction of evil.
SPEAKER_0:  hasn't yet blown the whole world up, but look at how the catastrophe.
SPEAKER_0:  You think 50 to 60 million people dead in the Second World War, which truly was a world
SPEAKER_0:  War!
SPEAKER_0:  what destruction was spread.
SPEAKER_0:  around the globe.
SPEAKER_1:  and this is something that
SPEAKER_1:  can't be stopped.
SPEAKER_1:  once the chain reaction starts, like if Hitler was
SPEAKER_1:  Successful.
SPEAKER_1:  Like it would just keep going.
SPEAKER_0:  If he had been...
SPEAKER_1:  in the industrial psychological
SPEAKER_0:  Right, because if we think from the perspective of destruction...
SPEAKER_0:  success would have needed, led to the need to conquer more, then there's factions and infighting and eventually you get the same mass.
SPEAKER_0:  destruction, right? And never
SPEAKER_0:  does the inaction of evil satisfy what the person is initially seeking? People want to feel better about themselves. But this is not something that everyone is able to accomplish.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... in abridged
SPEAKER_0:  uh... pediatrician who who wrote about
SPEAKER_0:  children and adults from very deep perspectives. He wrote about the idea of good enough, right? And you can sort of extrapolate that to like, we all wanna feel good enough, like not just limp over the line good enough, but I wanna feel good enough that I'm a decent person in the world and like what I do matters and...
SPEAKER_0:  I can have an impact on people and people can like me and care about me. There's a simplicity there that people want.
SPEAKER_0:  that when people don't have and there's certain other factors, maybe they're temperamental factors or historical factors.
SPEAKER_0:  can lead.
SPEAKER_0:  to trying to soothe that.
SPEAKER_0:  deficit, right, through
SPEAKER_0:  envy. And I think it starts with that. And it often starts in childhood, not always, but it often starts in childhood when the...
SPEAKER_0:  child's brain and psychology are so vulnerable. And you see salient child abuse. If you look at what was Hitler's background and what was Stalin's background, then I mean, you could look at almost anyone who's perpetrated evil, serial killers, whatever it may be.
SPEAKER_0:  The majority, not everyone, but the majority.
SPEAKER_0:  had these lessons in childhood that said, you're not good enough, you can't keep yourself safe, no one cares about you and-
SPEAKER_0:  and in a subset of people.
SPEAKER_0:  that's going to generate envy and that seed of evil then gets planted and nurtured.
SPEAKER_0:  as a fighter jet.
SPEAKER_0:  The sound of a fighter jet above us.
SPEAKER_0:  It's been good by an orchestra.
SPEAKER_1:  You forget.
SPEAKER_1:  You quickly forget.
SPEAKER_1:  the comfort of being in a peaceful place. That's one thing I saw in Ukraine.
SPEAKER_1:  is um...
SPEAKER_1:  Hey, you quickly get comfortable here. I'm going to take the whole trip back.
SPEAKER_1:  I was thinking.
SPEAKER_1:  It's so damn good to be in America.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a whole, just a whole like, it's like a three day trip back.
SPEAKER_1:  It's so good to be American.
SPEAKER_0:  You might take that for granted as a population, but I do agree.
SPEAKER_1:  so that destruction never alleviates.
SPEAKER_0:  the envy.
SPEAKER_0:  are all.
SPEAKER_0:  humans capable of envy.
SPEAKER_0:  I believe the answer is yes. Do we all have the possibility of evil in us?
SPEAKER_0:  I think the answer to that is yes.
SPEAKER_0:  but we have...
SPEAKER_0:  We have choice. We can choose what we do.
SPEAKER_0:  with that.
SPEAKER_0:  Which is why just because someone is
SPEAKER_0:  A sociopath, for example, doesn't mean that they're not responsible.
SPEAKER_0:  medical legal jurisprudence.
SPEAKER_0:  has absolutely borne that out, that legally, medically, we believe that completely.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  You were responsible.
SPEAKER_0:  presuming we're healthy, we're not unhealthy in other ways, that eliminates our ability to be circumspect, but that we're responsible for what we do.
SPEAKER_0:  and don't nurture.
SPEAKER_0:  inside of us. There are plenty of things we could decide to nurture anger and hatred.
SPEAKER_0:  about. I could think of slight difficulties, whether it's something someone else has done to me, or I could blame fate, or I could be mad at God, or the world. We can all make those.
SPEAKER_0:  choices and where...
SPEAKER_0:  responsible for them or for recognizing things in us. They're like, oh, I too have that in me.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't want to nurture that, I don't want to foster.
SPEAKER_0:  that or do I choose?
SPEAKER_0:  nurture and foster that. And I think ultimately, you know, our subject of
SPEAKER_0:  Hitler is as evil if if he had
SPEAKER_0:  kept winning and winning. I think ultimately he would have been the only person on earth.
SPEAKER_0:  And I really do believe that ultimately everyone, everything else would be.
SPEAKER_0:  because it's such destruction, right? Destroy everything, right? And
SPEAKER_0:  Probably when that didn't work, then there's the destruction of the self, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Nothing
SPEAKER_0:  soothes.
SPEAKER_0:  envy that is stoked by the sort of flames of evil.
SPEAKER_0:  And what you see is more and more anger and more and more frustration, which is why I really do believe someone.
SPEAKER_0:  like that, who nurtured evil in themselves that way, ultimately would
SPEAKER_0:  They'd be like him and one other person, and then he'd kill the other.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that's really powerfully said.
SPEAKER_1:  but even just to return to the jealousy vs envy.
SPEAKER_1:  I still f-
SPEAKER_1:  Think.
SPEAKER_1:  that it's the same flame.
SPEAKER_1:  And Envy is just the bigger version of it. So I think...
SPEAKER_1:  I just did my own personal life.
SPEAKER_1:  I f-
SPEAKER_1:  felt jealousy towards others, like you said, like, Oh, this person.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, a cooler thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Trinket.
SPEAKER_1:  whatever trinket I cared about. And usually it's when somebody is really close to the trinket you're building.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  And I-
SPEAKER_1:  Early on, like in my teens.
SPEAKER_1:  I realized that...
SPEAKER_1:  Just, just empirically speaking.
SPEAKER_1:  that jealousy over a period of a week just doesn't feel good.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's not productive. It doesn't help me build a better trinket.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  or it does if I
SPEAKER_1:  turn it into jealousy.
SPEAKER_1:  towards another person.
SPEAKER_1:  but
SPEAKER_1:  into a love for building a better trinket.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like, oh cool. Almost, you know what, like proactively speaking.
SPEAKER_1:  And later in life, people like Joe Rogan actually have been really powerful in this for me, just as a fan of his.
SPEAKER_1:  to celebrate other people.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's almost as opposed to ignoring that other person with a cool trinket, it's like celebrating their awesomeness in my mind.
SPEAKER_1:  Like just saying how awesome.
SPEAKER_1:  that humans are able to do that. And actually just how awesome is that exact.
SPEAKER_1:  person and being able to do that. Yeah. And that somehow made me more capable to build my own trinket better.
SPEAKER_1:  And it feels good also. Like it makes me feel happy.
SPEAKER_0:  And now you're not jealous anymore.
SPEAKER_0:  You're not jealous anymore. Right? So that's why I think jealousy is different, right? Because you're saying there's a week of jealousy, like I don't like this, right? I don't like, but if you take that in a way that says.
SPEAKER_0:  Wait a second, actually this is awesome. This is fabulous and this person did this. That person's awesome, right?
SPEAKER_0:  then you're not raining on anyone's parade, right? and in not doing that even inside your own mind
SPEAKER_0:  you gain a greater cognizance of your own capability.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, well if he can do that or she can do that, why can't I too? Like I wanna make the better Trinket too, right? Now you're thinking creatively.
SPEAKER_0:  Nowhere in there.
SPEAKER_0:  Nowhere in there was the emergence of evil.
SPEAKER_0:  I just disagree with that. I think there was a choice made.
SPEAKER_1:  Where I- Huh?
SPEAKER_1:  I looked at my, if my life was darker, more difficult, I think has nothing to do with my life.
SPEAKER_1:  with the actual little flame of jealousy I felt.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it has to do a lot more with the other context. And they have come out Voc avisca going surdr, Discover
SPEAKER_1:  If I...
SPEAKER_1:  If my life were.
SPEAKER_1:  more difficult, there was more abuse.
SPEAKER_1:  there was more challenges.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that decision, I could have made that decision in a different direction. Yes yes yes.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know what, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  You've written brilliantly about trauma. There's a bit more trauma.
SPEAKER_1:  as the background noise of my decision making.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll be more likely to-
SPEAKER_1:  uh... not be able to uh... pull away from the gravitational field of that jealousy and would build the ml in 멋있
SPEAKER_1:  So I think.
SPEAKER_1:  I disagree with the
SPEAKER_1:  with a brilliant person, but I feel like that flame.
SPEAKER_1:  That flame has the capacity.
SPEAKER_1:  to engulf the whole world. I guess the initial flame of jealousy, the little bit.
SPEAKER_1:  Like especially the younger you are.
SPEAKER_1:  It's almost like a habit.
SPEAKER_0:  You get to...
SPEAKER_0:  Build.
SPEAKER_1:  in either direction, because I've early on built a habit.
SPEAKER_1:  of saying.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm going to, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Channel that jealousy.
SPEAKER_1:  into productivity and into celebrating other people and that jealousy disappears. That was like a little discovery for me.
SPEAKER_1:  I discovered that. I get it.
SPEAKER_1:  You kind of discovered that little thing. I could have easily not discovered it.
SPEAKER_1:  I could have easily discovered.
SPEAKER_1:  that it kind of feels good to.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  Like.
SPEAKER_1:  mess with that other person to like
SPEAKER_1:  Think
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, shitty thoughts. Think negative thoughts.
SPEAKER_1:  do negative things to that other person. Because that could also, I just think the capacity in that initial feeling is there.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think it's a decision with me, because otherwise.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it dissolves responsibility.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, well surely I'm not Hitler.
SPEAKER_1:  Therefore...
SPEAKER_1:  this jealousy is normal. No, I just feel like every jealous is the capacity to turn into maybe not Hitler, but a toxicity.
SPEAKER_1:  that destroys in a small way in your own little private life, but it could destroy.
SPEAKER_0:  I agree that-
SPEAKER_0:  Jealousy brings us.
SPEAKER_0:  can bring us dangerously close to envy. I mean, maybe, maybe, let's see if if.
SPEAKER_0:  If I'm...
SPEAKER_0:  A heuristic we could agree on, right? Let's see. Let's see.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, if we look at the...
SPEAKER_0:  terrain of the mind is geography, right? So if I'm feeling...
SPEAKER_0:  happy, satisfied, proud. I'm pretty far from envy land, right? But if I'm feeling jealousy now, I'm, I'm.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm coming kind of closer to that border.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  I still, I think there's.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a big thing to go over the border, right? That the border isn't a gray area, right? There's a border to go over. And I think that I agree completely, one certainly about trauma, that the more trauma there is, because then the more misunderstandings there are about self and feelings that I'm not good enough, and then that can be anger about why and who might be oppressing me and, you know, I mean, I hate myself and everyone else who seems to be better. So trauma...
SPEAKER_0:  can drive us in these negative directions, but we're still crossing over some.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? So if you have the trinket and I think that's awesome, I want that, I want to work harder.
SPEAKER_0:  You know what I could do though is...
SPEAKER_0:  I could sneak in tonight when no one's around and I could move something.
SPEAKER_0:  No, no, wait, I don't wanna do that, right? But it's like I came over the border a little bit and I thought maybe...
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe that's a better way, but then I came back.
SPEAKER_0:  right? And we're responsible for that, right? Because it is a choice to say, I don't want to work hard. I'm already working how hard? I don't want to make my trinket better. I want to think mine's the best one.
SPEAKER_0:  I could destroy yours, right? Then, you know, we're letting our mind go over that border and do we say, right, run that forward, right? Let's run that forward and put people around us who feel the same way and start doing it so we think less of ourselves and we debase ourselves.
SPEAKER_0:  Do we run headlong in or do we come over that boundary?
SPEAKER_0:  And that's maybe the capacity for evil in us, that we come over that boundary, all of us.
SPEAKER_0:  right, at times, but do we come over it and then say, no, that's not my choice.
SPEAKER_0:  That's not my self definition.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm coming back. But I'm trying to justify, maybe there's certain other sociological forces that help us cross the border too.
SPEAKER_1:  So in Nazi Germany...
SPEAKER_1:  uh... we've been talking about hitler but then there's also the
SPEAKER_1:  the the german people
SPEAKER_1:  And so maybe when there's a bit of a mass hysteria, so all these effects.
SPEAKER_1:  of like.
SPEAKER_1:  combination of propaganda with
SPEAKER_1:  the small jealousies and resentments of the people that don't cross the border.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... together they can
SPEAKER_1:  with great charismatic leaders that...
SPEAKER_1:  sort of really fuel that fire that we feel when we're a part of the crowd. So maybe those individual kind of psychological barriers that you have.
SPEAKER_1:  take that leap from jealousy to envy.
SPEAKER_1:  those can be.
SPEAKER_1:  made easier the the leap can be catalyzed to this matter and you
SPEAKER_0:  percent.
SPEAKER_0:  100%. I think that to me is a massive point. We're talking about layers of emergence, right? So if there's individual consciousness, then there's culture.
SPEAKER_0:  And we're products of the soup we swim in, so to speak. People would say that when I was growing up. We're products of the soup we swim in. So if the soup that we're swimming in...
SPEAKER_0:  is the soup of hatred.
SPEAKER_0:  Then it's going to foster all of those things. So then you think about...
SPEAKER_0:  just in a painting with a very broad brush.
SPEAKER_0:  the culture created in Germany prior to the Second World War, and what was the impact of the reparations after the First World War?
SPEAKER_0:  of the punishing reparations, impoverishment, and basically humiliation that people were feeling. Okay, there were a whole bunch of decisions that impacted that cultural perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  right, then there must have been aspects just like I see in many ways parallels.
SPEAKER_0:  in America now of what are our standards for.
SPEAKER_0:  what we're communicating to others, right? How is the media deciding like what's real and what's not real, what's true, what's not true, what's hatred?
SPEAKER_0:  that is only gonna do...
SPEAKER_0:  evil versus what's hatred that's okay because I might sell something by by
SPEAKER_0:  putting it out there. That was, we know that was going on.
SPEAKER_0:  in
SPEAKER_0:  Germany during the rise of the Nazis and I think there's a parallel to, do we value truth? Can we stand together and say, no matter how much I might disagree with you politically, we can still understand that there's right and there's wrong, right? There's truth and there's lies, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So I think those are just two examples of determinants of culture. And then the culture.
SPEAKER_0:  is a determinant of, is someone like.
SPEAKER_0:  Hitler marginalizes like that's a crazy evil person. Oh my goodness, like, whoa.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, or is that someone who gains a greater following, a more adherence, and then there starts to be a momentum. Because why? Because what do demagogues do? I think they have a giant lasso and they harness.
SPEAKER_0:  the envy of thousands upon thousands upon thousands of people. That's right, you feel worse about yourself too. Doesn't matter what the reasons are. Maybe it's your childhood, maybe it's not. Maybe it's job failings, maybe it's professional, maybe it's personal, doesn't matter. Like you have envy too.
SPEAKER_0:  let's put it together and do some destruction because that'll make us feel better
SPEAKER_0:  Which is a lie.
SPEAKER_1:  So we've talked about Envy.
SPEAKER_1:  Where does, from the leader perspective...
SPEAKER_1:  of things like narcissism or sociopathy, come into play.
SPEAKER_1:  What can you make of?
SPEAKER_1:  world we live in.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe the leaders that run the world.
SPEAKER_1:  from the perspective, from the lens of narcissism.
SPEAKER_0:  I am struck.
SPEAKER_0:  20 years of doing.
SPEAKER_0:  what I do now.
SPEAKER_0:  I've been a psychiatrist for 20 years and I practice in so many different settings and I consult in different settings. I've been fortunate to have a very wide...
SPEAKER_0:  purview of what's going on in people and in the world around us.
SPEAKER_0:  and I am.
SPEAKER_0:  struck with amazement.
SPEAKER_0:  of all the things I see that are say abnormal, let's say from the mental health perspective. This could be depression, panic attacks.
SPEAKER_0:  I hearing voices, addiction, but there's so many things that cover everything.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  Narcissism?
SPEAKER_0:  is not.
SPEAKER_0:  frequent compared to a lot of other things. So it's small in terms of narcissistic diagnosis, right? It's much less than many other things.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  it causes the lion's share. I don't just mean the most compared to anything else, but I think more than 50%, the majority of...
SPEAKER_0:  Bad things.
SPEAKER_0:  evil things, destructive things that I see in the world around us. I think narcissists are,
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  destructive because they are driven completely, they are lodged completely in the lane of.
SPEAKER_0:  Envy.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  try to sneak up.
SPEAKER_1:  and we don't want to be lost in definitions, but can you try to sneak up to a definition?
SPEAKER_1:  non-clinical definition of narcissism that we're talking about
SPEAKER_0:  Narcissism is...
SPEAKER_0:  I ate.
SPEAKER_0:  deep.
SPEAKER_0:  pervasive and unquestioned.
SPEAKER_0:  sense of inadequacy.
SPEAKER_0:  in
SPEAKER_0:  The Self.
SPEAKER_0:  that comes along with anger and fear and vulnerability.
SPEAKER_0:  fear of destruction, fear of annihilation.
SPEAKER_0:  that is compensated for.
SPEAKER_0:  Bye.
SPEAKER_0:  aggression by the mechanics of envy.
SPEAKER_0:  trying to make the self.
SPEAKER_0:  seem better at the expense of others by
SPEAKER_0:  taking from others.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... by being
SPEAKER_0:  completely cavalier to the thoughts and feelings.
SPEAKER_0:  of others, that narcissism is not arrogance, narcissism is the opposite.
SPEAKER_0:  of arrogance. There is such a deep sense of inadequacy.
SPEAKER_0:  and incompetence in the self.
SPEAKER_0:  that the defensive structure around that
SPEAKER_0:  becomes dominated by rocket fueled.
SPEAKER_0:  Envy.
SPEAKER_1:  the machinery of narcissism is envy.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you make of the kind of more popularly discussed kind of symptom?
SPEAKER_1:  of narcissism.
SPEAKER_1:  which is a seeming...
SPEAKER_1:  not caring about other people.
SPEAKER_1:  sort of a very...
SPEAKER_1:  inward-facing focus in terms of the calculation you make when making decisions about the world.
SPEAKER_0:  narcissistic people.
SPEAKER_0:  definitely care about other people, right? it's the people who are schizoid?
SPEAKER_0:  Right, and say that don't necessarily register other people, right? But narcissism, people care about other people, but it's entirely vis-a-vis the self, right? If I'm schizoid, I don't really notice or care much who you are, right? But if I'm narcissistic, I absolutely care, because I'm watching every last detail of you. What might you have that's better than me?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  It's an incredibly intense focus upon individuals.
SPEAKER_0:  and demographics of people.
SPEAKER_0:  but the priority, the...
SPEAKER_0:  The goal is entirely about
SPEAKER_0:  the self, which is why they can become easy to say, I don't care if a million people die, right? How different is that from?
SPEAKER_0:  going out and destroying one person or a million people, right? It's in the same category of those people only, their existence is only meaningful in how it.
SPEAKER_0:  relates to me.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's still...
SPEAKER_1:  Meaningful it just seems like a very difficult leap to take that I don't care that a million people die
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  seems to be even with envy.
SPEAKER_1:  That seems to be a big...
SPEAKER_1:  like feeling and thought to have.
SPEAKER_1:  if you at all care about them.
SPEAKER_1:  are other people.
SPEAKER_0:  I guess.
SPEAKER_1:  tools for it.
SPEAKER_1:  alleviation of your sense of inadequacy.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, I mean, I don't even care about in that like being caring at all. I mean, caring about in that noticing.
SPEAKER_0:  that the person exists.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, someone who wants money and notices that there's a hundred dollar bill out.
SPEAKER_0:  cares about that. They don't care about the hundred dollar bill and that doesn't mean anything to them. It's of thoughts and feelings.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's gonna attract attention, they care about it because.
SPEAKER_0:  It's something that they want.
SPEAKER_0:  The same way people will care about others, but only from the perspective of, do you have things that I want?
SPEAKER_0:  Or can I feel better about myself by taking something from you by making...
SPEAKER_0:  things worse for you.
SPEAKER_1:  People often talk about narcissism as like the opposite of empathy.
SPEAKER_1:  but sort of empathy again, depends how you define it, but.
SPEAKER_1:  is uh...
SPEAKER_1:  is a careful consideration.
SPEAKER_1:  of the mental space of another person, of how the other person sees the world.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  You're kind of saying that narcissism, narcissistic people would also be very good at that.
SPEAKER_1:  in order to understand.
SPEAKER_1:  how maybe the other person can be manipulated or something to alleviate your sense of inadequacy.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, so there's a difference between the mechanics.
SPEAKER_0:  of empathy. So let's say, and we can define things different ways. Let's say empathic attunement.
SPEAKER_0:  is the ability to be attuned and to think, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  What's going on in you? What might you be thinking? What might you be feeling?
SPEAKER_0:  Some people have a lot of empathic attunement.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's, we can look at that as mechanistic, right? It doesn't equate to care.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, an empathic attunement.
SPEAKER_0:  can come along with empathy or not.
SPEAKER_0:  So yes, people who are narcissistic, they can mentalize well. So you mentalize meaning the ability to.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  understand or to consider thoughts, feelings, motivations in other people, right?
SPEAKER_0:  People who are narcissistic can have empathic attunement or mentalization depending upon how we want to describe those things.
SPEAKER_0:  But that has nothing to do...
SPEAKER_0:  with
SPEAKER_0:  care with actual empathy or kindness or
SPEAKER_0:  or
SPEAKER_1:  So in that sense, empathy, usually popularly used means...
SPEAKER_1:  that you care, like your happiness is aligned. This is a
SPEAKER_1:  I need to read this book. I've read so little science fiction. That's been one of my goals for this year, to catch up on some science fiction.
SPEAKER_1:  So Robert Highland from Stranger in a Strange Land has this quote about love.
SPEAKER_1:  which is love is that condition where another person's happiness is essential to your own.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's a good definition, I guess, of empathy where...
SPEAKER_1:  Yes. You're very sensitive. So mechanistically very sensitive to the state of another person's mind.
SPEAKER_1:  and your goal.
SPEAKER_1:  is to maximize their happiness.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like essential to your own happiness.
SPEAKER_1:  so that the happiness is that our line
SPEAKER_1:  And when that's elevated to its highest form, you can call that.
SPEAKER_1:  love romantic love friendship and so on
SPEAKER_0:  Okay. There's one more thing about the narcissist is some people can be sort of benign narcissists where
SPEAKER_0:  They want...
SPEAKER_0:  great things for themselves, right? but if they have enough
SPEAKER_0:  great things, they can sort of tolerate others being happy too.
SPEAKER_0:  And these are people who sometimes are actually quite highly liked, right? Because they have to have the most money, the most power, the most of anything, anything more than anyone else could challenge.
SPEAKER_0:  But as long as I have that, it's okay that you have some too, right? And then that can make you happy and can make you like me, right? So benign narcissists can be well-liked from that perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  it's still all about them and that can change if for example there's a scarcity of resources now right
SPEAKER_0:  But they're generally, they're not people who are being overtly destructive, although that...
SPEAKER_0:  They're over the border into the...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, into the envy territory, right? Malignant narcissists are very different where they then want to have everything. So even if I have...
SPEAKER_0:  thousand times more than you do I still envy you what you have because I want to have I don't think I can feel good enough about myself unless I have everything
SPEAKER_0:  And once I have everything, I won't feel good enough about myself either and then I'll have to have more, right? Take differences Influence Contact Bana
SPEAKER_0:  That's
SPEAKER_0:  malignant narcissism which we think of as
SPEAKER_0:  Sociopathy, right? We can define these words in different ways, but...
SPEAKER_0:  They're very, very negative concepts. That's profound sociopathy, malignant narcissism.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, envy writ large.
SPEAKER_0:  sociopathies.
SPEAKER_1:  as malignant narcissism.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a convenient way to think about it.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, no, because we can do sort of sociopathic things that, but not be sociopathic, like, well, you know, tell a white lie. It's, it's like sort of sociopathy on steroids, right, is then.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, envy writ large is malignant narcissism.
SPEAKER_1:  But just like you're saying, there's empathic attunement, as you said. So there's the mechanistic.
SPEAKER_1:  aspect of empathy and sociopathy. And then there's the big label you get attached if you're just doing that thing regularly.
SPEAKER_0:  I guess.
SPEAKER_0:  living your life through that lens. Take care.
SPEAKER_1:  And is there a nice spectrum that's like.
SPEAKER_1:  narcissism, sociopathy and psychopathy? Is it all the same kind of
SPEAKER_1:  Nice stroll through the woods.
SPEAKER_0:  So off the cliff or? Not really because the words don't have clear definitions like psychopathy and sociopathy. There's no, there's no.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no real definition of...
SPEAKER_0:  psychopath or psychopathy, or does that mean someone's sociopathic but psychotic? Like there's really not a- we end up using those words colloquially.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, which is why.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, concepts that we can define, like you like envy, empathic attunement.
SPEAKER_0:  narcissism, even though there might be nuances and definitions, like we can define them in ways that though're
SPEAKER_0:  were widely accepted, including within.
SPEAKER_0:  psychology and psychiatry.
SPEAKER_1:  So it's nice to just think about this broad umbrella of narcissism and the levels to which it's benign or For those of you who don't know this yet, and like, subscribe to my channel, denied
SPEAKER_1:  malignant.
SPEAKER_1:  and then also separating into the different mechanisms.
SPEAKER_1:  like interaction by interaction, sometimes can be narcissistic but broadly speaking.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you do everything through the lens of malignant narcissism?
SPEAKER_1:  That makes you a
SPEAKER_1:  sociopath or
SPEAKER_0:  a malignant narcissist.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, and the thing I would add to that is the thought about culture.
SPEAKER_0:  It's like how does the cultures were in whether it's a culture of a household?
SPEAKER_0:  Right? The culture of a community, the culture of a nation or the world.
SPEAKER_0:  How does that impact?
SPEAKER_0:  what unfolds in that person and then how does what unfolds in that person
SPEAKER_0:  impact that culture.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, that's the question is what unfolds in that person?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, how does culture affect it, but how does your own?
SPEAKER_1:  psychological development.
SPEAKER_1:  on Foldit.
SPEAKER_1:  because narcissism in leaders is the most.
SPEAKER_1:  impactful thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Right.
SPEAKER_1:  Who are the most impactful individuals? What is the most impact of individual psychology we have? Usually leaders of countries
SPEAKER_1:  or leaders of major organizations and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  And one of the things you mentioned was benign narcissism.
SPEAKER_1:  That seems to be...
SPEAKER_1:  aligned with success, right?
SPEAKER_1:  If you care about your own success...
SPEAKER_1:  that's going to be, you're more likely to be.
SPEAKER_1:  have narcissistic tendencies, I suppose.
SPEAKER_1:  U 15
SPEAKER_1:  And so my question is when you.
SPEAKER_1:  Follow that threat of narcissism to become the leader of a country.
SPEAKER_1:  Now you have a lot of...
SPEAKER_1:  new interesting psychological complexities to deal with like power.
SPEAKER_1:  That old cliche that power corrupts.
SPEAKER_1:  Does that?
SPEAKER_1:  Is it possible?
SPEAKER_1:  for power to corrupt the human mind, to where it pushes you farther and farther.
SPEAKER_1:  into malignant narcissism.
SPEAKER_1:  into this destructive envy.
SPEAKER_1:  What are your thoughts on power?
SPEAKER_1:  like the effect of power in the human mind.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_0:  Power is...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  It's also an accentuator, right? It's an intensifier.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, so.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think it is.
SPEAKER_0:  that there are people who can be sort of in a gray area where there are malignant narcissistic
SPEAKER_0:  tendencies and behaviors.
SPEAKER_0:  But there are also ways in which that person can think outside of themselves and think in a broader way and think kindly about others.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  and they're trying to navigate.
SPEAKER_0:  whether they're aware or not that they're trying to navigate between one and the other. And then the allure of power is, well, just look, just exercise that power and you'll feel better, right? It'll show you, right, that you're good enough. Look at the power you have and whatever may be going on in the person's mind.
SPEAKER_0:  that then power, yes, can.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that's why we have to have checks and balances, right? Because we don't-
SPEAKER_0:  You know, we...
SPEAKER_0:  We are all inscrutable to ourselves, let alone to others. So we must have checks and balances and we should always have them on ourselves.
SPEAKER_0:  as well as on others. We should want that for the health of ourselves and the world around us.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... so i think all of that is
SPEAKER_0:  true but there are also people who don't necessarily.
SPEAKER_0:  become corrupted by...
SPEAKER_0:  There can be an understanding and a grounding that they're a steward of power, a shepherd. There are ways people describe utilizing power and utilizing it in a benign way.
SPEAKER_0:  that then.
SPEAKER_0:  fosters the healthy aspects.
SPEAKER_0:  of self, right? So like gratitude and humility, right? If I mean, if we could.
SPEAKER_0:  add a healthy dose of gratitude and humility to everyone or to our society, there would be a sea change. But how do you feel gratitude? How do you feel humility? Good night, my dear.
SPEAKER_0:  Those things are incompatible.
SPEAKER_0:  with.
SPEAKER_0:  narcissism envy, right, with really the bad pole of things that were.
SPEAKER_0:  talking about and part of the reason I
SPEAKER_0:  I'm so focused in my work and in really what runs through all of my.
SPEAKER_0:  about life is the impact of trauma, right? Because trauma-
SPEAKER_0:  creates these false lessons and it walls us off from truth, then it starts to point towards
SPEAKER_0:  the unhealthy ways of
SPEAKER_0:  of trying to feel better.
SPEAKER_0:  about ourselves, but we have the health in us.
SPEAKER_0:  And two, we have those seeds of health too that can grow into being a steward of power and sharing power, being considerate and kind. We see a lot of that in the world too.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, it's not all just.
SPEAKER_0:  the evil we you know we see plenty people who
SPEAKER_0:  do good and who are generous of spirit. We have both in us, and it is, I think, your time at our culture and the seeds that we sow and the climate that we set, including putting governors in boundaries. How do we rein in or say that the more aggressive, the more envious or destructive is unacceptable?
SPEAKER_0:  Right? How do we foster?
SPEAKER_0:  the part that's kind and considerate and reflective and slow to judge of like, hey, let's learn a little bit more. Like how do we foster that and.
SPEAKER_0:  I think a lot of that comes back to...
SPEAKER_0:  to early childhood education. I mean, I think we don't do nearly enough to protect.
SPEAKER_0:  and as a corollary to that, we don't do nearly enough to educate.
SPEAKER_0:  children. I want to write a book.
SPEAKER_0:  The second book I write is going to be everything I needed to know about life.
SPEAKER_0:  I learned as a second year post-graduate psychiatry resident.
SPEAKER_0:  Why? Why then did I learn so much about?
SPEAKER_0:  unconscious motivation, about the impact of trauma, about how we can be envious and how we can act out, even about how our emotions trump logic in us. Why, why—
SPEAKER_0:  Why don't we teach these things?
SPEAKER_0:  when we're young enough to understand, like, why is that other kid bullying me?
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Or why just because I'm a little bit bigger, do I want to go bump that other kid on the head?
SPEAKER_0:  But what's going on?
SPEAKER_0:  that we don't.
SPEAKER_0:  We don't do those things, we're just tripping ahead of ourselves and we don't stop and think.
SPEAKER_0:  How are we using our resources? How are we using our resources?
SPEAKER_0:  How are we shepherding forward the next generation, which by the way is a generation that's going to determine our fates too as we get older?
SPEAKER_0:  We don't.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, do that. I often think of like in the Olympics, you know, you see like the great sprinters, right? And they've got to come out of the blocks perfectly, right? So if they come out of the blocks a little bit too fast, they're going to fall over, right? They're going to just fall forward and
SPEAKER_0:  And I often see that in my head about us as humans and as a culture that we're rushing so far forward we don't stop and say wait let's-
SPEAKER_0:  Let's keep the basics.
SPEAKER_0:  Here are the basic techniques of how are we navigating forward.
SPEAKER_0:  in life or do we just throw all those away? Because I can get some benefit by-
SPEAKER_0:  saying that you're bad even though what's being leveled against you is wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Like what? Why? Why? Do I take that? Or do I say, no, there's something more important here.
SPEAKER_0:  that we want to shepherd forward in ourselves as a culture. And I think...
SPEAKER_0:  preventing childhood trauma.
SPEAKER_0:  and changing the ways that we educate children and adults could again make a sea change.
SPEAKER_0:  and maybe set us on a course towards.
SPEAKER_0:  even towards a greater likelihood of survival as a species.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so.
SPEAKER_1:  talking to like people in elementary school.
SPEAKER_1:  about human nature.
SPEAKER_1:  and teaching them was so.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... how people can be resentful and envious and
SPEAKER_1:  how to deal with your emotions.
SPEAKER_1:  How to yeah, so these basic interaction things about human relationships about friendships
SPEAKER_1:  Bob the trail.
SPEAKER_1:  about love, about all those things.
SPEAKER_1:  Like it just...
SPEAKER_1:  It's actually strange that we don't.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of hope the parents talk about that kind of stuff. Right.
SPEAKER_1:  But then the parents often...
SPEAKER_1:  uh you know need therapy themselves
SPEAKER_0:  The parents didn't learn it.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I'm not joking that I was mad.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, second year after medical school, like how is it? I think of even things in my own life and-
SPEAKER_0:  You know how I...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, how much shame I felt after my brother's suicide. I was already an adult, right? As a young adult, but-
SPEAKER_0:  I felt so much...
SPEAKER_0:  Shame, I didn't, like I had no understanding that.
SPEAKER_0:  that, oh, it's a reflex to Trump.
SPEAKER_0:  right, to feel guilt and shame. And that of course I was feeling.
SPEAKER_0:  that it didn't mean it was true because I felt it.
SPEAKER_0:  But I mapped the fact that I felt ashamed to the fact that I should have felt guilty and ashamed and it like led to some very negative things in my life that I had to sort of pull myself back from and recover from.
SPEAKER_0:  I didn't know that. I didn't know the automaticity of the reflex and how pervasive it can be and how it can put blinders on us. And I mean, it's just one example.
SPEAKER_0:  But it's an example of something big that happens to people.
SPEAKER_0:  that we don't learn about. And I find myself sometimes.
SPEAKER_0:  having conversations with a person. So I still do a lot of clinical care of having conversations with a person after a tragedy.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm saying, I can't believe it. Again, I'm saying.
SPEAKER_0:  the things that this person didn't learn.
SPEAKER_0:  in elementary school because like none of us did, right? And then look at the misery and the suffering. And then I think this is one person among how many.
SPEAKER_0:  millions among us who
SPEAKER_0:  who try and go about their way.
SPEAKER_0:  without knowing things that are easily knowable because they don't even know that they're knowable because we don't know
SPEAKER_0:  teach them.
SPEAKER_1:  So how to deal with trauma.
SPEAKER_1:  The trauma happens, first of all.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... that
SPEAKER_1:  suffering can happen.
SPEAKER_1:  and small trauma and big trauma.
SPEAKER_1:  all that can happen.
SPEAKER_1:  and there's natural ways to deal with it.
SPEAKER_1:  So in the case of traumas, you write about.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  You can also just talk about some more of the details of that.
SPEAKER_1:  is it's good to uh... bring to the surface to talk about it too
SPEAKER_1:  not be ashamed to hide it inside.
SPEAKER_1:  to be some kind of secret that it's actually.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, there's a lot of positive things to say here, at least from my perspective. One is it's discussing trauma and dealing with trauma together with other human beings by talking about it.
SPEAKER_1:  is a path to deep friendship and intimacy.
SPEAKER_1:  with those people.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a dark.
SPEAKER_1:  aspect.
SPEAKER_1:  to trauma, to war.
SPEAKER_1:  that...
SPEAKER_1:  communicating it or sharing it?
SPEAKER_1:  bonds you.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  So like the other side of trauma is like love, is you need that hardship, not you don't need it.
SPEAKER_1:  But hardship and trauma can often be a catalyst for a deep human connection. If you bring it to the surface, it's supposed to kind of...
SPEAKER_1:  on the inside. If we can just linger on it because you've been through a few
SPEAKER_1:  very traumatic events in your life.
SPEAKER_1:  when you were 25 years old, as you mentioned.
SPEAKER_1:  Your brother committed suicide.
SPEAKER_1:  What did that event teach you about life?
SPEAKER_1:  Death.
SPEAKER_1:  and about the human mind.
SPEAKER_0:  What certainly brought me face to face with.
SPEAKER_0:  the truths of.
SPEAKER_0:  Life and death.
SPEAKER_0:  because I had not had.
SPEAKER_0:  A major trauma before then?
SPEAKER_0:  So there wasn't a major trauma sort of in my developmental years.
SPEAKER_0:  that what can carry forward.
SPEAKER_0:  is a sort of omnipotence defense, right? I mean, the thought is that when we're toddlers, we all have like an omnipotence defense, which is like, I can just try and get up and run and move. And if I run into something, I'll get up and do it again, right? That we kind of have to.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's partly the protection of the parent, et cetera, but we think we can get out there in the world and do things and we just do. And if we don't have major traumas, we can sort of carry through the, oh, like bad things aren't gonna happen to me.
SPEAKER_0:  I know that they're there and I know they happen to people, but they don't happen to hear me.
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  sometimes what will happen is being confronted with such a tragedy.
SPEAKER_0:  wipes that away very, very quickly. And then the person feels extremely exposed. Like, oh, I thought.
SPEAKER_0:  that I was gonna be okay and now I know that I'm not, and then, and that can start to lead to, and what does that mean? Now, is this all coming for me?
SPEAKER_0:  now? Did I get so lucky for 25 years, nothing bad happened? Nothing but bad things are going to be happening. Am I cursed?
SPEAKER_0:  is my family cursed, right? And I think that
SPEAKER_0:  leads to say what the learning about the human mind.
SPEAKER_0:  In retrospect, I think I understood at the time to some degree.
SPEAKER_0:  but not like I do now, I can put words to it now, right? like HOW!?
SPEAKER_0:  incredibly important.
SPEAKER_0:  powerful.
SPEAKER_0:  powerfully important negative emotion is.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? That how a sense of guilt and shame and vulnerability.
SPEAKER_0:  can just pervade.
SPEAKER_0:  our entire life.
SPEAKER_0:  So all of a sudden we're swimming in a very different soup.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's a frightening soup and it's a toxic soup.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm most struck.
SPEAKER_0:  by that and that
SPEAKER_0:  goes along with the idea that we're not taught that.
SPEAKER_0:  Emotion always beats logic.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, like I think the idea of Descartes, the idea that we're rational creatures, you know, that kind of comes down to us through Western thought.
SPEAKER_0:  is like
SPEAKER_0:  not true. Like we're rational creatures.
SPEAKER_0:  Only if there is an emotion.
SPEAKER_0:  grabbing for our attention, right? Like, you know, we're attending to one another, we're being very logical, right? What we're doing now, if we heard a frightening noise...
SPEAKER_0:  right outside the door, we'd be entirely different. The emotion would trump everything. It's like, stop paying attention to this. Now safety is at stake and we'd think differently, feel differently, behave differently, right?
SPEAKER_0:  This is what happens to us, not just in situations where...
SPEAKER_0:  Something drags us from one emotional state to another, but it can be very, very pervasive. So my sense of anger...
SPEAKER_0:  Frustration.
SPEAKER_0:  inadequacy and then soothing in unhealthy ways, soothing by drinking too much and then kind of hating myself in the first place and hating the world around me and then starting to think, well, who cares what happens? You know, there's some very dark thoughts.
SPEAKER_0:  And choices.
SPEAKER_0:  that came from...
SPEAKER_0:  a changed perspective of self in the world.
SPEAKER_0:  So what do you do in that?
SPEAKER_1:  Um, because of trauma.
SPEAKER_1:  Again, small or large.
SPEAKER_1:  You find yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  swimming or drowning in a soup of negative emotion.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you do?
SPEAKER_1:  What do you do with that emotion? I mean, we don't have to even talk about trauma, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  The interesting thing is...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, um.
SPEAKER_1:  Any one of us throughout the day can find ourselves.
SPEAKER_1:  taking a bit of a dip in the pool of negative emotion.
SPEAKER_0:  What do we do with that?
SPEAKER_0:  The first thing is to separate.
SPEAKER_0:  how we feel.
SPEAKER_0:  from what's true.
SPEAKER_0:  is we don't do a good job of that.
SPEAKER_0:  as humans if I feel
SPEAKER_0:  bad about myself, it's very easy then I conclude like, I'm bad.
SPEAKER_0:  If I feel ashamed of myself, I conclude I'm a terrible person who's shameful.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? This is the, you know, there's an old psychodynamic concept of what they used to call an observing ego. It still gets called that. It's not ego in the sense of arrogance, right? It's the ability to step outside and to see ourselves.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  So that's what lets us keep the difference between our feelings.
SPEAKER_0:  and what we know to be true. We could be very angry at someone. So I think that person's terrible. I think the person's stupid.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that right now because like something negative is passed between us.
SPEAKER_0:  this inside of me, it's just because of how I feel. Like when I can separate that, how do I actually think about that person, right? And-
SPEAKER_0:  You know, we get.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  so frequently by how we feel.
SPEAKER_0:  because how we think, therefore what we believe.
SPEAKER_0:  right, just kind of comes on its heels as if the feeling is dragging it along
SPEAKER_0:  And I've been struck by that. That's one of the things that has struck me so.
SPEAKER_0:  the most, right, among the very most in 20 years of working as a psychiatrist is how we are led by our our
SPEAKER_0:  feelings or emotions as if they are truth and then they create truth.
SPEAKER_0:  Because...
SPEAKER_0:  we embrace what they're telling us as true.
SPEAKER_0:  And that is, I think, incredibly, I think it's how people learn prejudice. I think it's how people learn self-hatred. I think it's how we learn so many destructive behaviors. And then the blinders on us come in more and more and more.
SPEAKER_0:  and more. So separate, you know, we're driven by what we feel unless we understand.
SPEAKER_0:  that what we feel is different from what we.
SPEAKER_0:  know to be true or what we can decide on one way or another.
SPEAKER_1:  And that requires.
SPEAKER_1:  Realizing and catching the emotions themselves, realizing that it's an emotion.
SPEAKER_1:  A feeling comes into your mind overtakes you, a feeling of...
SPEAKER_1:  Anger.
SPEAKER_1:  Dislike, hatred, all of that just comes in.
SPEAKER_1:  I think why did that person just
SPEAKER_1:  me off in traffic or something like that, that feeling.
SPEAKER_1:  to where you just kinda...
SPEAKER_1:  Take it as a feeling and.
SPEAKER_1:  Realize it's a feeling that doesn't represent some deep reality about the world that's fundamental or you
SPEAKER_1:  They just kinda watch it?
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Let it pass.
SPEAKER_1:  which is the natural way of things.
SPEAKER_0:  We'll decide if it means anything.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, if I'm mad, right, someone cut me off and...
SPEAKER_0:  I feel hatred and I want to destroy them, right? To stop and think, look, I've got that in me. I can...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, are the stressors running too high in my life? Like, is it really good? Should I be-
SPEAKER_0:  Should I be on this road 10 minutes behind schedule? Like, what am I really doing? We can learn.
SPEAKER_0:  But yes, it's an observation skill, right? And it's an observation skill that we can.
SPEAKER_0:  develop. I often think of it as something called the tapestry theory, which I think initially was a theodicy of explaining. I believe this is true. I'm not sure of this.
SPEAKER_0:  The idea was that, oh, we don't see God's plan.
SPEAKER_0:  because we're up too close to it, right? Like as if there was a beautiful tapestry on the wall and we're standing right up it, we're only gonna see one part of it, we need to stand back from it. And-
SPEAKER_0:  And I remember learning that religion studies class being really fascinated.
SPEAKER_0:  with that at the time and I think that.
SPEAKER_0:  There are a lot of things we do that.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, and in...
SPEAKER_0:  training ourselves to have an observing ego.
SPEAKER_0:  What we're saying is...
SPEAKER_0:  Hey, like just the busyness of life or my own impulses or the pool of emotions are trying to pull me up right close to whatever tapestry there is there. And I want to sort of resist that. I mean, I'm better off if I really stay further behind it and then I make a choice if I want to come.
SPEAKER_0:  If there's some really positive emotion, or it's friendship, or it's love, or it's nurturing, you know what, let me come right up to this, right? But I wanna choose when I'm doing that. I don't want...
SPEAKER_0:  some drive I didn't decide to like take me by the back of the head and
SPEAKER_0:  put me up against that tapestry.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  The interesting exercise.
SPEAKER_1:  For me and I think for a lot of people in modern civilization is the the internet with social media
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  it.
SPEAKER_1:  It's almost like going to the gym or something like that. At least that's the way I see it.
SPEAKER_1:  Because there's a bunch of forces.
SPEAKER_1:  Un-
SPEAKER_1:  social media that
SPEAKER_1:  are trying to make you feel things.
SPEAKER_1:  Most of it is kind of in the negative space of feelings.
SPEAKER_1:  U a
SPEAKER_1:  There is actually a strong gravity.
SPEAKER_1:  to negative feelings for some reason.
SPEAKER_1:  and so
SPEAKER_1:  The
SPEAKER_1:  uh... and the brain notices them more and i don't know what that pool is but it's there
SPEAKER_1:  and you get to observe it on social media. Like if you actually just.
SPEAKER_1:  Scroll through social media.
SPEAKER_1:  You feel the gravitational pull of negative emotions.
SPEAKER_1:  And I just see as a kind of exercise of like.
SPEAKER_1:  You feel the pull just like when you go to the gym, there's a resistance.
SPEAKER_1:  and I practice like a stepping way to look at the tapestry. Right? And there's different mechanisms I think all of us have to learn.
SPEAKER_1:  for me.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a kind of, you mentioned gratitude and humility.
SPEAKER_1:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  Like if somebody
SPEAKER_1:  If it's me personally, I've recently gotten attacked.
SPEAKER_1:  places here and there.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... uh... you know if if they're saying that they're much smarter than me
SPEAKER_1:  I practice kind of humility, like you mentioned.
SPEAKER_1:  And I kind of imagine that they are smarter than me.
SPEAKER_1:  Those things like help me to kind of like
SPEAKER_1:  pull away like.
SPEAKER_1:  and then maybe they have a lesson to teach me. Like I don't take their sort of-
SPEAKER_1:  Negative comments to heart?
SPEAKER_1:  But I imagine the human being and like that they might have a lesson to teach me. And in general, when it's more amorphous kind of negative feeling, I think the other thing is the gratitude.
SPEAKER_1:  Just like.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... different versions almost meme-
SPEAKER_1:  meme-ifiable versions of like, oh, this is pretty cool.
SPEAKER_1:  Like we got a thing going here. There's a human civilization like.
SPEAKER_1:  bickering and having a little fun like lunch.
SPEAKER_1:  food fight.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's kind of cool. Like we get to interact in this way.
SPEAKER_1:  And...
SPEAKER_1:  There's a bit of humor. There's, it's like Thanksgiving dinner. Like if you, like Thanksgiving dinner, if you're arguing about politics, it can feel like really intense. Like, I can't believe you said this, but if you zoom out, it's like.
SPEAKER_1:  Family
SPEAKER_1:  This is like...
SPEAKER_1:  This is amazing. So that kind of feeling really helps.
SPEAKER_1:  And, but it's like, it really is like going to the gym. It's like building up a muscle.
SPEAKER_1:  To be able to, um.
SPEAKER_1:  Pull away from those emotions, I-
SPEAKER_1:  I don't think I get to practice that kind of emotion in regular day to day life.
SPEAKER_1:  like you can't it's hard to get those reps.
SPEAKER_1:  On social media you can really get the reps in. It's kind of cool. Like that's the way I see social media.
SPEAKER_1:  is a chance to sort of practice that stoicism.
SPEAKER_1:  of gratitude, of humility, of loving other people in the face of this negative emotion, all that.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes and.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a certain kind of psychotherapy that talks a lot about this idea that everything is as it should be.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, which doesn't mean.
SPEAKER_0:  from some moral or justice point. It's just that often if you look at things,
SPEAKER_0:  one thing leads to another to another to another in a way that's actually very, very predictable.
SPEAKER_0:  even though we might be surprised about it.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? So an example, so I would.
SPEAKER_0:  Say that.
SPEAKER_0:  Gratitude often does come along with a healthy price.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? So you could say in the example you gave,
SPEAKER_0:  Here I'm being assailed on social media.
SPEAKER_0:  So you can say, well.
SPEAKER_0:  there was a time I sat out, I set forth to impact people, right? To be able to reach people and to impact them.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? And look, I feel a sense of both gratitude and pride that I've done that.
SPEAKER_0:  right? Because you did it because of your
SPEAKER_0:  Your effort, right? Your work, your intelligence, your thoughts, like you're responsible for it, right?
SPEAKER_0:  but also...
SPEAKER_0:  you feel gratitude because any one of us who's here and has any opportunity has reason to feel immense gratitude, right? So then you can say, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  What's actually going on here is something success.
SPEAKER_0:  I set out to do something.
SPEAKER_0:  and I'm doing it.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  What it brings with it absolutely includes being a sale.
SPEAKER_0:  There's no surprise there, right? That because of, you know, people who have...
SPEAKER_0:  Anything good serve as lightning rods for envy.
SPEAKER_0:  So then, yes, there will be people who...
SPEAKER_0:  want to make up lies or whatever they want to do because you become a lightning rod for envy by having succeeded at the thing you set out to do about which you can feel a healthy pride and gratitude. And then I think that kind of puts it in its place.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, you're still gonna make decisions about it, but.
SPEAKER_0:  It makes sense then, like you have a mechanism of understanding it.
SPEAKER_0:  that...
SPEAKER_0:  not only makes sense to you, but reflects the truth of...
SPEAKER_0:  what you actually have done and achieved and what's going on in the world around you.
SPEAKER_1:  Well...
SPEAKER_1:  I wonder if we're all kind of a little bit unique in this because for me
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe it's useful to connect.
SPEAKER_1:  talk through my own experience of it.
SPEAKER_1:  is, um,
SPEAKER_1:  For me, I try to avoid, especially in those situations, to feel pride.
SPEAKER_1:  Because...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm just looking empirically.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel way happier if I focus on humility.
SPEAKER_1:  If I ever think...
SPEAKER_1:  of like
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah, you know, when you do something meaningful or you become more popular, you're going to experience these kinds of, I feel the attacks more and it's like me versus the world. That's the feeling that you start getting.
SPEAKER_1:  And that does not create a pleasant feeling.
SPEAKER_1:  So to me the pleasant feeling is like...
SPEAKER_1:  uh... stepping away
SPEAKER_1:  like kind of laughing at it all.
SPEAKER_1:  Like with a smile and not like in a negative, like laughing at people, but just like.
SPEAKER_1:  laughing at the...
SPEAKER_1:  The theater of it, the circus of it, like this whole absurd existence we've got going on.
SPEAKER_1:  And then just having a humility in like.
SPEAKER_1:  Everybody has a lesson to teach me. It just makes me feel good. The pride thing.
SPEAKER_1:  I do like feeling.
SPEAKER_1:  when in a positive pool of emotion.
SPEAKER_1:  So if I'm building a trinket...
SPEAKER_1:  and I finish it.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm like really happy with myself. Like I finished this thing. And I usually like to do that alone.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I don't need an audience for Pride. I like to sit there.
SPEAKER_1:  and just like, ooh, this is cool. I did that, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  But I just I find that in social interactions.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  Pride is just a danger.
SPEAKER_1:  it's a dangerous drug for me because it like it's such a small
SPEAKER_1:  It's a small step away from then losing all the humility and then you start getting very defensive and that's not going to, it just starts you on a spiral of negative emotion.
SPEAKER_1:  But I also, I mean with
SPEAKER_1:  with everybody you've mentioned this, you will probably sneak up to it in different directions.
SPEAKER_1:  um...
SPEAKER_1:  I do think there's different.
SPEAKER_1:  brains that we all have.
SPEAKER_1:  My brain is exceptionally self-critical.
SPEAKER_1:  Non stop ışıkları.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like an engine that's always there.
SPEAKER_1:  And, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  But at the same time...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm able to zoom out and have gratitude. And it's as if there's like two brains.
SPEAKER_1:  And they're like.
SPEAKER_1:  cohabitating happily.
SPEAKER_1:  And I can, uh, the better I get at this, the more I can use the one that's self-critical when I'm trying to be productive.
SPEAKER_1:  Because naturally I'm super lazy. So I'm trying not to be less lazy. I'll be self-critical.
SPEAKER_1:  And then, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  When I'm not being lazy, when there's a special moment I want to enjoy that moment, I'll turn on this.
SPEAKER_1:  The gratitude engine.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like generic advice that people would give.
SPEAKER_1:  If your brain is self critical, that's not a good thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you should probably get rid of that.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know about that.
SPEAKER_1:  this is the warning
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, like I kind of like it.
SPEAKER_1:  I kind of like this grumpy old man that's in there.
SPEAKER_1:  The Psych.
SPEAKER_1:  That thing you did, that really sucked.
SPEAKER_1:  I was like, and I kinda, you know, there's a movie, Grumpy Old Men. Okay, I like that grumpy voice, the grumpy cat is in there.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's nice, but yeah, I can have a bad.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks and...
SPEAKER_1:  relationships and on maybe
SPEAKER_1:  My well-being maybe is to get older and all that kind of stuff. So yeah, you have to monitor all this kind of stuff, but
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, I don't know which one is like, because you've kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  Highlighted it's good to have gratitude and humility. It's also good to have a little bit of pride. I wonder what that like
SPEAKER_1:  set of ingredients for healthy what like
SPEAKER_1:  healthy life looks like for each of us.
SPEAKER_1:  whether we have to customize and figure out.
SPEAKER_1:  what that is.
SPEAKER_1:  Some of the cake is already baked is the problem.
SPEAKER_1:  and because of the trauma.
SPEAKER_1:  Like if I was like...
SPEAKER_1:  eight years old maybe I could be a little more flexible. But at this point...
SPEAKER_1:  Like you got the thing you got and it's hard to like.
SPEAKER_0:  You can do a lot with it. You could. It may not be easy, but there's a lot of plasticity and a lot of pliability.
SPEAKER_0:  across all ages.
SPEAKER_0:  And people are different and they may be.
SPEAKER_0:  idiosyncrasies of why one person is in a different place. As a general rule, I think the answer is absolutely yes.
SPEAKER_0:  evolved and I've worked with people who've
SPEAKER_0:  really change themselves and broaden their conception and understanding. you know they're in their 80s or
SPEAKER_0:  I think we can do it at any stage of life.
SPEAKER_0:  I would make a case for...
SPEAKER_0:  for intrasychic, so not between people necessarily, right? But inside of oneself for the feeling of pride. And maybe if we call it self-esteem, right? Let's say we call it self-esteem.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Or we could call it healthy pride. We could put either...
SPEAKER_0:  word to it, but if you think about what we're trying to avoid...
SPEAKER_0:  is a sense of inadequacy.
SPEAKER_0:  then it is good to sort of own what's ours.
SPEAKER_0:  we can put ourselves a little bit out of balance.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  either in terms of building up resentments or in terms of decreasing self-confidence.
SPEAKER_0:  If we're not owning everything...
SPEAKER_0:  That's ours, right? So a thought-
SPEAKER_0:  thought I would have about...
SPEAKER_0:  let's say about some pride or some self-esteem, right?
SPEAKER_0:  It can work against vulnerability, right? Which we know can also in some situations push us towards jumping.
SPEAKER_0:  boundary into envy and all of that. So, so, so let's think about vulnerability.
SPEAKER_0:  If
SPEAKER_0:  You conceive, okay, people are assailing me.
SPEAKER_0:  and you just go to a place of gratitude.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it can send a message.
SPEAKER_0:  that
SPEAKER_0:  okay, I'm just lucky and I hope I continue to get lucky as opposed to like, that's not true, right? Like there's ability inside of me and discernment inside of me that tells me...
SPEAKER_0:  I can have a greater sense of confidence that I'll navigate what comes my way.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  So, because the pride or the self-esteem part.
SPEAKER_0:  is owning what we've contributed to the goodness we've created.
SPEAKER_0:  right, which does in a sense helps us feel better about ourselves. And it also helps us feel armed against say the slings and arrows of.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, whatever outrageous fortune may come next. I don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, I don't know. Again, disagreeing with an expert here. Yes, I think that's generally good advice, but I think you mentioned vulnerability.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's like I've just been.
SPEAKER_1:  doing a lot of research on rocket engines and fuel.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of fuel...
SPEAKER_1:  I just think...
SPEAKER_1:  I get a lot from being vulnerable.
SPEAKER_1:  because vulnerable leads to intimacy.
SPEAKER_1:  in friendships and relationships.
SPEAKER_1:  I get a lot from being intimately close with human beings, just on a friendship, on a...
SPEAKER_1:  on like an ideal level.
SPEAKER_1:  in conversations and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  And so...
SPEAKER_1:  I would rather...
SPEAKER_1:  Error on the side.
SPEAKER_1:  of vulnerability. To me, pride is destructive.
SPEAKER_0:  I think I already...
SPEAKER_0:  I already have a pretty good-
SPEAKER_1:  engine that says like...
SPEAKER_1:  Life is awesome.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't need help for that.
SPEAKER_1:  That's fine. That one is working.
SPEAKER_1:  It's the it's I just feel like the way to face the world
SPEAKER_1:  that's full of uncertainty, that could be full of cruelty is with...
SPEAKER_1:  humility and gratitude. I don't know, this pride thing...
SPEAKER_1:  feels like.
SPEAKER_1:  I know that for a lot of people it's really important to
SPEAKER_1:  Really v-
SPEAKER_1:  Umm...
SPEAKER_1:  really work on pride to make sure they don't crumble under the pressure of like
SPEAKER_1:  that they don't give into this insecurity that destroys them.
SPEAKER_1:  But I just, for me, empirically speaking, I seem to be happier.
SPEAKER_1:  facing the world with humility.
SPEAKER_1:  and just being grateful. The pride I'm really worried about.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, it just feels more.
SPEAKER_0:  destructive than anything.
SPEAKER_0:  See what I think as you're telling me that.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't want to be presumptuous, but I make some thoughts or some conclusions that tell me, hey, you're in a pretty healthy place, right? And the reason I say that is because...
SPEAKER_0:  I agree completely about vulnerability. I mean, think about humility and gratitude.
SPEAKER_0:  make us vulnerable, right? If like, wow, I'm grateful, thank you. I'm grateful for you. You know, we could get shot down or something, you know, something bad could happen, something could make us feel bad. So yes, we need vulnerability. If we try and eliminate vulnerability, we're living miles into the envy.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, land, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  you're describing a healthy vulnerability, but then my brain says that's because on the other side of this the seesaw so to speak
SPEAKER_0:  has to be a healthy sense of self.
SPEAKER_0:  whether we call it self-esteem or healthy pride. And then I'll cite what I think is the evidence for that is you describe the negative voice.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? As like the grumpy cat.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm f-
SPEAKER_0:  that's a good negative voice to have, right? Because it's telling you like, hey, that wasn't your best. Like, come on, do better or, right? Like, you can do better. There's a negative voice in some ways.
SPEAKER_0:  but it believes in you, right? It's where that voice could be, it could be a negative voice that says.
SPEAKER_0:  You didn't do that well because you suck. You don't deserve anything.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  Why should you even be alive? That's the negative voice that can gain so much force if there isn't a balance of healthy self-esteem. So I think because you're well-balanced...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, you have what you need and then having more of it seems like, oh, that's not so good.
SPEAKER_0:  But they're people whose negative voice isn't the...
SPEAKER_0:  Grumpy.
SPEAKER_0:  had, it's hateful, right? And then that's a person who needs to...
SPEAKER_0:  to bring that into greater balance.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I think my, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  My negative voice is like a grumpy cat that's like a.
SPEAKER_1:  French existentialist, maybe a little bit of an nihilist.
SPEAKER_1:  was just kinda...
SPEAKER_0:  Sartre's cat.
SPEAKER_1:  such as gas it doesn't get hateful it's not like a hitler cat so it's a little more it's a little more me there but like every single day
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I guess there is kind of like this line that we've...
SPEAKER_1:  across a couple of times between the benign and the malignant.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... but of course if the monitor that line edges
SPEAKER_1:  I think you have to be careful.
SPEAKER_1:  Wow.
SPEAKER_1:  when you face really difficult situations of.
SPEAKER_1:  as you go on through life more and more difficulties you face a lot of loss and suffering especially later in life
SPEAKER_1:  You have to be careful with that voice.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, that, that grumpy cat can get awfully confident. And then if you don't have any source of it.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... positive emotions in your life you can become too
SPEAKER_0:  heavy of a burden.
SPEAKER_0:  which I think this leads us to a-
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's a really important.
SPEAKER_0:  right, that there are some people, like a significant subset of people.
SPEAKER_0:  Who get?
SPEAKER_0:  happier.
SPEAKER_0:  as they get older, they have more contentment, a stronger sense of self. You might think...
SPEAKER_0:  How could that ever happen, right? Like we're getting closer to death.
SPEAKER_0:  We're accumulating insults, right? Like everything hurts a little bit more and we have less energy and we accumulate losses and traumas. Why would anyone-
SPEAKER_0:  be healthier across time, be happier across time.
SPEAKER_0:  And what we see is it's linked to the things that we're talking about, right? It's linked to say, let's say vulnerability versus pride. There's a good balance there, right? There's a lot of humility. There's a lot of self-esteem. The person is spending a lot of time standing back from the tapestry and looking.
SPEAKER_0:  at it, right? And what can come into people?
SPEAKER_0:  isn't sort of a sense of equanimity. Like I sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  understand, you know, I'm being the best person I can be. I'm, you know, and that's not always even great. And there are things that I don't feel great about even while I'm trying to do that, but...
SPEAKER_0:  But look, I'm being...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm choosing to be, right? And that doesn't have to be in some big way. I'm not saying that means any one specific thing. That can mean the person who's...
SPEAKER_0:  taking care of their cat and tending their garden. Like that's enough. We have to have
SPEAKER_0:  you know, love, the ability to put good things out in the world, right, and to put our...
SPEAKER_0:  our ability to work and be, to make things different out into the world and make things better. And if we're doing that, we get happier across time because we come to a sense of peace.
SPEAKER_0:  with ourselves. I'm not supposed to be everything. I'm not supposed to do everything. I'm not supposed to fix everything.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, I'm also not supposed to suffer all the time for the things I haven't.
SPEAKER_0:  gotten right, you know what?
SPEAKER_0:  I guess I'm kind of, and it leads back to Winnicott, right?
SPEAKER_0:  the British physician of I am.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I'm good enough.
SPEAKER_0:  And that seems to help people feel happy.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, contentment and be generative and productive into later life. It's like that's what we all should be wanting. But it's even it's kind of an afterthought though. Some people are like that as opposed to...
SPEAKER_0:  Wait a second, right? What's going on with them?
SPEAKER_0:  and let's do all of.
SPEAKER_0:  Albert Camus.
SPEAKER_1:  writes in Mythicissivus, quote,
SPEAKER_1:  There's only one real serious philosophical problem, and that is suicide.
SPEAKER_1:  Deciding whether or not life is worth living is to answer the fundamental question in philosophy
SPEAKER_1:  All other questions follow from that.
SPEAKER_1:  So basically, to be or not to be.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think there's a...
SPEAKER_1:  uh, truth to that statement.
SPEAKER_1:  This question of why live?
SPEAKER_1:  Ron?
SPEAKER_1:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think there's truth to that statement being a really, really important question for us to answer?
SPEAKER_0:  Yes.
SPEAKER_0:  I will see you next time.
SPEAKER_0:  I think the answer is yes.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think Kemu answered it.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes too.
SPEAKER_0:  I love his writing and
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I think there was a...
SPEAKER_0:  a streak of nihilism.
SPEAKER_0:  that I think grew in his writing.
SPEAKER_0:  over the years and the thought is that K. Mu died by suicide. I think we're not sure of that because it was a car accident.
SPEAKER_0:  But I've always read that as the primary scholarly opinion.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think it's interesting that after his death...
SPEAKER_0:  A book called The First Man was published, which I don't know if he had intended to publish it. I don't know the specifics about it, but it's about him as a child.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's interesting, the first man, he was the first.
SPEAKER_0:  man in his existence, right? The most
SPEAKER_0:  the one that felt and experienced everything. And there's sadness and distress and all in that book, but there's a beauty of life and living and experience. And all three of us, in the first chapter came together
SPEAKER_0:  And I think to compare.
SPEAKER_0:  that beauty, like that's.
SPEAKER_0:  life, even if something's difficult and scary and sad, like there's something beautiful around the corner and here's a kind person and a new discovery. You know, more what was in him as a child.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think that we can get.
SPEAKER_0:  jaded as you and I were just talking about a few minutes ago. We can accentuate the negative and foster the negative.
SPEAKER_0:  and come to a place where we're looking for.
SPEAKER_0:  some in-depth philosophical answer, some thick book that's going to explain all that to us.
SPEAKER_0:  instead of the simplicity that we've been.
SPEAKER_0:  talking about. I think humility, gratitude.
SPEAKER_0:  helps us have.
SPEAKER_0:  Just simple.
SPEAKER_0:  positive experiences, feelings of contentment, feelings of connection with another person, learning, discovery. And I think the answer to Keimu's question is yes, and I think
SPEAKER_0:  It lies in his writing about when.
SPEAKER_0:  He was a child, which I think he saw as less important.
SPEAKER_0:  then his later writings in the intellectual heaviness went.
SPEAKER_0:  I think maybe...
SPEAKER_0:  He had lost his way a little bit from the things he understood when he was younger.
SPEAKER_1:  So another way to talk about it.
SPEAKER_1:  I'd love to hear what you think is.
SPEAKER_1:  about...
SPEAKER_1:  these broad categories.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me be started with Kierkegaard.
SPEAKER_1:  of existentialism, absurdism, and nihilism.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think Camus considered himself an absurdist, not actually an existentialist.
SPEAKER_1:  is kind of a middle ground where I think existentialist.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't want to characterize it in the wrong way. And there's a lot of different definitions, but I think existential is ultimately.
SPEAKER_1:  Do think that there is meaning.
SPEAKER_1:  instead of
SPEAKER_1:  Pursuing the passion of life, like pursuing the most, like.
SPEAKER_1:  in living life. That's where you discover the meaning of it.
SPEAKER_0:  that individual.
SPEAKER_1:  level.
SPEAKER_1:  of.
SPEAKER_1:  Fully embracing life.
SPEAKER_1:  And I think...
SPEAKER_1:  Sort of nihilism.
SPEAKER_1:  is again, it's kind of like a spectrum, where nihilism basically says...
SPEAKER_1:  There's no meaning.
SPEAKER_1:  and it doesn't matter.
SPEAKER_1:  Nothing matters.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't even know, but somehow that lands you in a place.
SPEAKER_1:  that's totally uninspired.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe.
SPEAKER_1:  An atlas would disagree with that.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe there's a way to live a creative life.
SPEAKER_1:  in an nihilistic mindset.
SPEAKER_1:  I think absurdism is somewhere in the middle.
SPEAKER_1:  where...
SPEAKER_1:  Pursuing meaning at all.
SPEAKER_1:  is not a good idea.
SPEAKER_1:  So kind of I think existentialists say you should be looking for meaning.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's to be discovered in your own actions, in your own life, in the moment.
SPEAKER_1:  And uh...
SPEAKER_1:  absurdism says life is absurd nothing makes sense
SPEAKER_1:  Don't look for the meaning.
SPEAKER_1:  Just live. Just be.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that's kind of the later Camus kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  philosophy. I don't know if you can sort of comment on
SPEAKER_1:  these kind of nuanced ideas here if there is no
SPEAKER_1:  religious.
SPEAKER_1:  guide.
SPEAKER_1:  your life.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think about this kind of search for meaning?
SPEAKER_1:  Do you see that there's some wisdom in the existentialist perspective of discovering it?
SPEAKER_1:  in your own life and this passion and this kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  day to day existence in the moments of your life that bring
SPEAKER_0:  you joy, that kind of thing. Bringing different sort of perspectives and trying to tease apart, like, well, wait, what are the differences in those perspectives, right? And I think what it points out is that
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, we tend to conflate things as human beings, right, and to take two different things and try and make them into one. But we also, I think on the other end of the spectrum, get very overly reductionist. And I think that when we get to overly reductionist...
SPEAKER_0:  we lose the ability to learn from anything or to generate meaning, right? I mean, the thing about...
SPEAKER_0:  Sartre, who is the thought of existentialism is so consistent with him, right, who on the one hand,
SPEAKER_0:  wrote about, in very clear terms, like this is what it is and this is what it isn't, and here's how you're gonna make your meaning in a very academically proscribed way.
SPEAKER_0:  But he also wrote short stories like
SPEAKER_0:  the wall, right, where something totally absurd happens, right, as part of the story, right? So I think...
SPEAKER_0:  What ends up happening is people either reduce themselves or get associated with something.
SPEAKER_0:  that by being overly reductionist takes us away from meaning.
SPEAKER_0:  The idea that, look, we don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  if there is an overarching religious meaning or, you know, what we call a religious meaning or purpose. We don't know that.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  So, okay, if we take that as a given, that people who say that they know are having faith, like how Spinoza described faith, right? Faith is that you don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  But you believe anyway.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not because you have faith now you know something, right? Because I think that's
SPEAKER_0:  a slippery slope to the persecution of others, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So if we say, okay, we don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  then
SPEAKER_0:  we're left either deciding, okay, well then to hell with everything. There's that movie, A Strange Brew, right? With Bob and Doug McKenzie where the brakes don't work on the car and one of them says, oh, why bother steering? Right? So if we don't know that there's meaning, like why bother steering? Let's just give up the ghost, right?
SPEAKER_0:  And I don't think that's even what the nihilists said. I mean, I think Bakunin said, we should get rid of everything.
SPEAKER_0:  that we've ever created except Beethoven's Ninth Symphony and start over from there.
SPEAKER_0:  But so even people who are very nihilistic are associated with that.
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of them were just not liking what we had built, right? So if we accept that...
SPEAKER_0:  A lot of what we have built as humans inside of us and outside of us is really counterproductive and doesn't help us. And that absurd things happen.
SPEAKER_0:  in the world, right? And that often the way social structures and systems build up, you build themselves up is absurd. I think our health care system.
SPEAKER_0:  operates in a way that's absurd.
SPEAKER_0:  So if we accept that there are absurdities that we don't know if there's truth
SPEAKER_0:  then what are we left with? but like well let's try and make meaning
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Or take it, you got set.
SPEAKER_0:  I said, I am myself and my circumstances. She's like, look, we can't control everything. We live in circumstances around us.
SPEAKER_0:  But within those circumstances...
SPEAKER_0:  we can make decisions and define.
SPEAKER_0:  ourselves. And I think the brilliance of that and I think tying it all together, right, in a way that's not trying to be
SPEAKER_0:  And since it ties it all together by not trying...
SPEAKER_0:  to answer everything concisely, that yes, we can make meaning. Like we see that if someone trips in front of me.
SPEAKER_0:  I could walk around them or I could help them up. I mean, no one can tell me that it doesn't matter.
SPEAKER_0:  what I do. I absolutely reject the idea that, oh, I could step over them or on them.
SPEAKER_0:  or I could help them up and it doesn't matter. Oh yeah, try being the person on the ground.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  we create meaning.
SPEAKER_0:  But we live in our circumstances and there are absurdities both within us and outside of us in our social.
SPEAKER_0:  And there are a lot of things that
SPEAKER_0:  pretend to have meaning that don't. There's the shades of nihilism but ultimately there's something going on here.
SPEAKER_0:  that's doing the best we can in the context of just not knowing.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I tend to see, I don't know if it's genetic, I think.
SPEAKER_1:  I tend to think just observing the internet.
SPEAKER_1:  the number of memes there are.
SPEAKER_1:  I think many other people are like me. I tend to see the humor in the absurdity.
SPEAKER_1:  I tend to enjoy it from that kind of angle. I see the Kafkaesque nature of society, different aspects of society and just kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  Notice the magic with a smile.
SPEAKER_1:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_1:  And just laugh at the circus of it all
SPEAKER_1:  Because it is magical that the circus all comes together.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like a little bit out of sync and then just a guy playing trombone, but like overall it's pretty
SPEAKER_0:  Good.
SPEAKER_0:  Pretty good.
SPEAKER_0:  And we can look at that and just kind of marvel and go, huh.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, which I think...
SPEAKER_0:  Is it a relation to at least a lot of what we?
SPEAKER_0:  in the Western world think of as Eastern, right? It's like as non-attachment, right? Because then if there's something absurd...
SPEAKER_0:  And it's like, not good for me.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, then I accept that too, instead of getting angry about it and railing about it or seeing some cosmic meaning in it, right? I think there's also a healthy non-attachment in what you're saying too.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's, I mean, you mentioned Eastern thought, there's...
SPEAKER_1:  Dostoevsky, Nietzsche, but also Buddha.
SPEAKER_1:  have kind of spoke of life as suffering.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you think that's true to that?
SPEAKER_1:  that suffering is a-
SPEAKER_0:  is a fundamental part of life.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it is a fundamental part of life.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think that means that life is suffering.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, if we say, well, life is suffering, then.
SPEAKER_0:  What am I doing that I'm trying to erase from my mind like the birth of my children, right? Things that were filled with joy, right? Like life is not entirely suffering.
SPEAKER_0:  But life brings a lot of suffering.
SPEAKER_0:  And for some people it brings such disproportionate
SPEAKER_0:  suffering and the people don't survive the suffering. I think when people are conscientious and empathic, they don't survive the suffering.
SPEAKER_0:  that really bothers us, right? The suffering in our own lives and the fact that others at times could...
SPEAKER_0:  could seem to be so overwhelmed by suffering that they don't even get a chance.
SPEAKER_0:  to see good. I think that there's.
SPEAKER_0:  I do think there's truth to that and there's sadness and distress to that.
SPEAKER_0:  But to say therefore life is suffering, I think is completely untrue.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it ignores the fact that someone even made a trombone, right? Let alone that there's a little bit out of sync and someone's playing the trombone. Like, that's cool. There's a there's a there's a
SPEAKER_0:  you know, there's elements of the absurd that are neat and interesting and if we start accepting that we can't understand or control everything.
SPEAKER_0:  then we can accept and I think really.
SPEAKER_0:  love and foster the beauty.
SPEAKER_0:  in Ireland.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I think...
SPEAKER_1:  The word suffering.
SPEAKER_1:  is doing a little bit too much work.
SPEAKER_1:  because I think it's probably referring to the philosophical concept of
SPEAKER_1:  that uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it is absurd, the absurdity.
SPEAKER_1:  That stuff just happens randomly.
SPEAKER_1:  Evil people succeed, good people fail.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a seeming random injustice on occasion.
SPEAKER_1:  and on occasion there's justice.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, all of it that feels like...
SPEAKER_1:  and maybe because it.
SPEAKER_1:  Often there's a lot of loss.
SPEAKER_1:  And then there's...
SPEAKER_1:  as a kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  matching complimentary aspect to any good feeling that all comes crashing down. like every hello
SPEAKER_1:  from a physics perspective.
SPEAKER_0:  ends in a goodbye.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  That's a really sad thing.
SPEAKER_1:  of uh...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, all the amazing people I get to meet in my life.
SPEAKER_1:  All the amazing experiences eventually they have to end.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's part of what makes them amazing.
SPEAKER_0:  Why is that sad?
SPEAKER_0:  is because we're taught to think.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'd say, look, at some point you and I are gonna say goodbye today. I hope we're richer for it. And then we take that goodness off with us. I wanna celebrate that because it's all part of the goodness. I think we're taught to think, oh, that's so bad and it equates to death and misery.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's often not that way.
SPEAKER_1:  I think there is a sadness to it, but I also don't think that sadness isn't
SPEAKER_1:  a negative thing.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a different way to celebrate a beautiful thing. So there's a melancholic nature to it, something passing of themselves and day after day.
SPEAKER_1:  If it leaving.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's that old Louis CK thing that I go back to over and over from his show, Louis, where.
SPEAKER_1:  He was all heartbroken that he just broke up
SPEAKER_1:  You know, with the...
SPEAKER_1:  with somebody he loved.
SPEAKER_1:  And he told about that to an old man.
SPEAKER_1:  And the old man said,
SPEAKER_0:  You're a fool.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the best part.
SPEAKER_1:  I missed that part.
SPEAKER_1:  or you sort of...
SPEAKER_1:  are lingering in that loss, feeling the pain of that loss.
SPEAKER_1:  because that lasts the longest, it's the most intense, it's the most reliable, and it's a kind of celebration of the love you had.
SPEAKER_1:  Like losing the love.
SPEAKER_1:  is still.
SPEAKER_1:  a celebration of the love.
SPEAKER_1:  with I think
SPEAKER_1:  You don't want to over romanticize that, but there's some aspect of truth to that.
SPEAKER_1:  Like that melancholic feeling.
SPEAKER_1:  of remembering.
SPEAKER_1:  a beautiful time that's no longer there.
SPEAKER_1:  is a kind of celebration of it and is a kind of joyful experience even though
SPEAKER_1:  It's very easy to experience it.
SPEAKER_1:  as a negative emotion.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's just like you said, I mean, it's up to our mind to determine how.
SPEAKER_1:  that emotions really felt. But it's a tricky one, because it's like heartbreak to experience that as a positive thing.
SPEAKER_0:  people can reminisce at funerals, right?
SPEAKER_0:  and laugh because people can be very very very sad and perceive.
SPEAKER_0:  that this person has died and perceived the sadness of it.
SPEAKER_0:  but in perceiving.
SPEAKER_0:  that and really living in it, then you can have people who want to remember that person by telling a funny story. Why? Because each of those people carries that with them.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think.
SPEAKER_0:  What you're saying is consistent with.
SPEAKER_0:  healthy function as human beings because we're gonna encounter sadness and loss. Like what do we do with that?
SPEAKER_0:  Right? And do we do things that ultimately create some redemption or even reparation inside of us? And like reparations are big.
SPEAKER_0:  Word and psychology, right? It's how we repair damage and loss. So if we lose someone and we're sad.
SPEAKER_0:  Can we, by telling funny stories.
SPEAKER_0:  about that person remind ourselves that, hey, they're still inside of us. Whether they're out there looking at me, I don't know, but I can call that person of mine inside of us and then.
SPEAKER_0:  we have something that's good and beautiful that comes with that too.
SPEAKER_0:  in the...
SPEAKER_1:  Introduction to your book.
SPEAKER_1:  on Trauma?
SPEAKER_1:  Lady Gaga wrote it, she wrote the intro.
SPEAKER_1:  She said this about you, quote,
SPEAKER_1:  I can now say with certainty that this man saved my life.
SPEAKER_1:  He made life worth living.
SPEAKER_1:  This goes to our discussion about.
SPEAKER_1:  the mythicistivist Kamu question.
SPEAKER_1:  about why I live.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  I think, at least to me, she's one of the most brilliant and unique artists ever.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a difficult question, but a question of creativity.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, what?
SPEAKER_1:  role does trauma play?
SPEAKER_1:  in, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  in somebody like that, in this artist that has created some...
SPEAKER_1:  incredible things.
SPEAKER_1:  wood positive.
SPEAKER_1:  constructive.
SPEAKER_1:  A role does trauma serve and what limiting role?
SPEAKER_1:  does it serve?
SPEAKER_1:  and preventing that person from flourishing more.
SPEAKER_0:  The trauma can certainly
SPEAKER_0:  drive us to...
SPEAKER_0:  creativity.
SPEAKER_0:  The two even to push against or to protest against what the trauma.
SPEAKER_0:  tells us, you know, trauma tells us lessons like nothing matters.
SPEAKER_0:  you don't matter and nothing will ever be good and nothing is beautiful and we can.
SPEAKER_0:  push against trauma. They know there is life in me. There's something, there's goodness for me to spread in the world, to express and spread.
SPEAKER_0:  So I think trauma fuels.
SPEAKER_0:  creativity in many, many, many ways, trauma also shuts down creativity, right? People who are, for one example, trauma.
SPEAKER_0:  that escalates to the point where now the person is soothing it with alcohol. It's one example. And now the impact of the alcohol shuts down any creativity.
SPEAKER_0:  So can people be creative and outward thinking without trauma?
SPEAKER_0:  I think sometimes, if I remember correctly, people will use Emmanuel Kant as an example of someone who I think hadn't traveled much and didn't have trauma and like look at what he knew. So, okay, there are going to be exceptions, right? A lot of our creativity...
SPEAKER_0:  is in some ways fueled by our suffering, although it's complicated because it comes from generative places in us, right? So those places are there, they're not created by suffering, but maybe suffering.
SPEAKER_0:  makes an incentive or a passion.
SPEAKER_0:  inside of us and a person.
SPEAKER_0:  Stephanie, who you referred to is just such an incredible.
SPEAKER_0:  astounding creative.
SPEAKER_0:  And sure, some of that comes from trauma, some of it comes from...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, trauma fueling the generative creative places.
SPEAKER_0:  in her, but what I helped her to do, she's very generous with her words, but...
SPEAKER_0:  What I helped her to do was to see
SPEAKER_0:  all that she is and all that the creativity in her is and all that there is to create through.
SPEAKER_0:  love and caring and
SPEAKER_0:  compassion.
SPEAKER_0:  and to again see that. I mean, a lot of time that's what I'm doing clinically. I think it's what's good psychiatrists or mental health professionals do is we help people see the beauty that is there.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Because oftentimes we're way too close up to that tapestry. And what brings us close is often the sad thing. So we're up close and all we see is a tapestry.
SPEAKER_0:  is the negative. It's easy then to get classically nihilistic, but by helping someone take a step
SPEAKER_0:  back and to see who they are and what's in them.
SPEAKER_0:  That's how people get better and it's how people reengage in.
SPEAKER_0:  in life.
SPEAKER_1:  It's such a...
SPEAKER_1:  difficult thing because if you were to.
SPEAKER_1:  for studying human beings.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like the optimal trajectory.
SPEAKER_1:  is having some trauma.
SPEAKER_1:  that doesn't destroy you.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  forces you early in life to really struggle with the
SPEAKER_1:  intricacies of the human condition.
SPEAKER_1:  And then later in life, as you form and like you build an expertise around and mastery.
SPEAKER_1:  start to do exactly what you said, which is step back and look at the tapestry.
SPEAKER_0:  If you don't have the...
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like just empirically speaking, there's of course just a huge amount of data and all kinds of-
SPEAKER_1:  anecdotal.
SPEAKER_1:  evidence but it and I'm going to be careful here because maybe I'm romanticizing
SPEAKER_1:  hardship.
SPEAKER_1:  but it does seem that hardship in childhood.
SPEAKER_1:  If it doesn't break you can be constructive.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like you said.
SPEAKER_1:  Having that trauma one of the ways to fight it.
SPEAKER_1:  is to say I am worth something. I am.
SPEAKER_1:  And this is
SPEAKER_1:  you know, uh.
SPEAKER_1:  David Goggins talks about this.
SPEAKER_1:  I am somebody, I can be somebody special and I'm gonna prove it to you, I'm gonna do this, I'm gonna do this big thing, this is this engine.
SPEAKER_0:  that drives you.
SPEAKER_1:  forward.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, comment on that because like.
SPEAKER_1:  from a like a parent's perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  You want-
SPEAKER_1:  A child to have an easy.
SPEAKER_1:  life.
SPEAKER_1:  Right, you want them to.
SPEAKER_1:  not have hardship, certainly not have trauma.
SPEAKER_1:  But that's such a difficult dance because, um...
SPEAKER_1:  in some ways.
SPEAKER_1:  a little bit of hardship
SPEAKER_1:  and it
SPEAKER_1:  gradually increasing amount of hardship that doesn't break you.
SPEAKER_1:  can really develop you into a really interesting, complicated
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  person and it helps you flourish as a creative being.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know what to-
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know if there's a question there. I just keep saying right-
SPEAKER_0:  of things. No, it makes, look, I think it makes good, it makes good sense to me. I think what you're trying to get at, like, dude, we need trauma.
SPEAKER_0:  And how are we defining it, right? Because we say trauma, hardship, difficulties.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, we could set aside, we could set apart, say, and differentiate things.
SPEAKER_0:  that are difficult?
SPEAKER_0:  but that are overcomeable.
SPEAKER_0:  versus things that we could use the word trauma this way, if we chose to, that are just entirely negative, like someone saying.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh.
SPEAKER_0:  you can't do that and you'll never succeed because what? And then they tell you something about yourself, okay? Because you're from here or you're this race, religion, whatever it is, right? We think well,
SPEAKER_0:  You know, that could make someone say, hey, I'm going to show you, I'm going to overcome, right?
SPEAKER_0:  but then they're overcoming something bad.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Like it's just like, there's nothing good or helpful about that, right? If someone's saying that, so the person has to overcome it.
SPEAKER_0:  That's different than something.
SPEAKER_0:  that is placed in front of a person where...
SPEAKER_0:  where
SPEAKER_0:  the whole conception of it is something positive.
SPEAKER_0:  that you can make through effort, right? So, you know, I remember...
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, I think I was 15 years old. There was some rule, like you could then go...
SPEAKER_0:  I think it was picking raspberries or blueberries, right? And I think, and my parents wanted me to see, like, hey, go see how that works with you. Now you got 50 cents at the end of it, right? And then you think about that when, you know, you wanna buy baseball cards or you, you know, you think about it and you work hard. And I could remember, like, it was hard and I was sweating and I was tired and...
SPEAKER_0:  but I learned from it. I mean, it's the reason I remember it today. So —
SPEAKER_0:  So yes, parents might want their kids to have a good life, but not this is certainly an easy life.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, and I think.
SPEAKER_0:  That was done.
SPEAKER_0:  They took me to do that so I'd have a greater sense of responsibility in a sense of like hard work is meaningful and it's important and
SPEAKER_0:  And I think that that kind of thing is good, but if we separate that from something that's just...
SPEAKER_0:  denigrating, prejudicial. I think those things aren't good, but they're unavoidable.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's not necessarily that, oh, is some trauma good?
SPEAKER_0:  I would look at it more that some trauma is unavoidable. I mean, it's hard to-
SPEAKER_0:  How do you go through life and not have any losses or anything negative or anything sad?
SPEAKER_0:  And then people are people. There may be people who have not a lot of that. And then there's a sort of complacency and they don't do it as much as they could or feel as good as they could. You know, then there's other people who have a highly attuned emotional, so there's people with very highly attuned emotional compasses.
SPEAKER_0:  for which a little bit of trauma becomes so intrusive.
SPEAKER_0:  It's so much of it is person driven, but I do want to distinguish between things that are just purely bad that we might overcome or find some fire in our belly about or whatever the case may be.
SPEAKER_0:  and things that may be boundaries or barriers either directly, purposely placed or not.
SPEAKER_0:  that in a sense invite us or inform us of the possibility of striving and overcoming.
SPEAKER_0:  Finally in tune to mo-
SPEAKER_1:  compasses it's so true that there is
SPEAKER_1:  That's a component of it too.
SPEAKER_1:  It's.
SPEAKER_1:  This is almost genetic.
SPEAKER_1:  how sensitive you are to particular trauma, so little things can have a huge impact.
SPEAKER_1:  or gigantic things.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... serious abuse in
SPEAKER_1:  in childhood can be.
SPEAKER_1:  by some people overcome.
SPEAKER_0:  easily.
SPEAKER_0:  It's not just what's the trauma, it's what's the trauma that makes certain problems.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to match the trauma to the person. And a big part of what you're matching to is that
SPEAKER_0:  genetically based characteristic of how finely attuned is that.
SPEAKER_0:  and path the cartoon men to that compass.
SPEAKER_1:  So when you think about, it was just returned to childhood.
SPEAKER_1:  when you think about trauma in childhood.
SPEAKER_1:  What can we say about the impact?
SPEAKER_1:  of
SPEAKER_1:  child abuse.
SPEAKER_0:  on the development of a human being.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  The impact of it is so...
SPEAKER_0:  disproportionately.
SPEAKER_0:  bad and hurtful.
SPEAKER_0:  compared to things that happen when we're not children. And I wanna be very careful about how I'm saying that because people can...
SPEAKER_0:  through their strength and resilience and...
SPEAKER_0:  human interconnectedness can overcome that. I don't mean to say.
SPEAKER_0:  that
SPEAKER_0:  anyone who's experienced those things is...
SPEAKER_0:  can't make it through it or over it.
SPEAKER_0:  That part is not true.
SPEAKER_0:  But it is true that the impact is so disproportionate to anything else that can happen because the brain is... I
SPEAKER_0:  So, both, if we say psychology is like applied neurobiology, and we look at both of those as a guess
SPEAKER_0:  as
SPEAKER_0:  different ends, right, even though there's a lot of gray in the middle.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, the neurobiology is changed. So just one example of a much greater salience.
SPEAKER_0:  of vigilance mechanisms, of...
SPEAKER_0:  of mechanisms of self-protection, mechanisms that can make a person…
SPEAKER_0:  feel more fear and more insecurity and hide themselves away from the world.
SPEAKER_0:  and not trust the world. And I mean, not trust the world even enough that, oh, I'd like to have a better job and-
SPEAKER_0:  There's another one that's here that I could take but...
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe it could be worse, you know, they think of being afraid of that, right? Like there are all sorts of ways in which...
SPEAKER_0:  in which the changes to those pathways impact someone. And that's just one of...
SPEAKER_0:  We could bring trauma experts together that could talk about that for days. What is the impact upon the brain biology?
SPEAKER_0:  So that then gets changed inside the person. And from the perspective of those changes, the psychology on top of it changes. Like, what do I think about myself? Do I think that I'm worthwhile?
SPEAKER_0:  you know, even in my mid-20s after...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I-I-I-
SPEAKER_0:  without formative traumas and a pretty strong sense of self and some achievements.
SPEAKER_0:  There was a big trauma then with the death of my brother and I start questioning, am I cursed? Am I worth anything? I mean, I was 20 something years old and doing reasonably well.
SPEAKER_0:  at the time. What how does this impact.
SPEAKER_0:  child of 6'7".
SPEAKER_0:  10, 12 years.
SPEAKER_0:  old, right? We're sending such powerful messages that then change conception of self.
SPEAKER_0:  And that negatively changed conception sits upon the negatively changed neurobiology. And I think if we really thought...
SPEAKER_0:  Hey, let's do the best we can just for humans in general, for the human race, for species in general is
SPEAKER_0:  We would handle children and caring for children so much differently in terms of protection mechanisms.
SPEAKER_0:  intervention mechanisms. How many times do you see where...
SPEAKER_0:  where now there's been some tragedy and the child gets a little bit of support and
SPEAKER_0:  You know, they had some therapy that was provided by some...
SPEAKER_0:  insurance carrier, you know, that they get once a week for 16 weeks or whatever. I mean, we should be wrapping our societal resources.
SPEAKER_0:  around.
SPEAKER_0:  but we don't use our resources.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, you know, I was just reading, it's a little bit of an aside, but.
SPEAKER_0:  about $300 and something billion a year.
SPEAKER_0:  in cost to the US economy.
SPEAKER_0:  just from schizophrenia.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you think?
SPEAKER_0:  And it costs a fraction. What do we actually put into caring for people who have schizophrenia? So first there's a moral imperative, but let's say we put that aside and we only care about the economy, right? Because there are.
SPEAKER_0:  Mechanisms of thinking that look at it that way. How could we not amend that right, but we are so reckless
SPEAKER_0:  with our resources and we're tripping ahead of ourselves that we don't think, oh my goodness.
SPEAKER_0:  There is no better place on God's earth for prevention.
SPEAKER_0:  then.
SPEAKER_0:  Here, prevention in terms of human suffering, and also where do people like that go? I mean, more often, people like that go to place of increased suffering, inability to take care of themselves or...
SPEAKER_0:  to be in supportive relationships. Okay, we know there's a higher prevalence of that.
SPEAKER_0:  but we're also creating the pool of people through which.
SPEAKER_0:  the envy, the narcissism, the sociopathy, the destruction.
SPEAKER_0:  arises. So again, if we care about people, we would be so focused on that.
SPEAKER_0:  If we don't care about other people and just ourselves or just economic costs, we would still be so focused, but-
SPEAKER_0:  You know, we're not and we tend to just kind of call it good because
SPEAKER_0:  We don't see anything disastrous happening at the moment.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think there's a societal negligence there to the shame really of all of us.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  when child abuse and the impact neurobiologically and psychologically is potentially the greatest cause of suffering directly and indirectly on the face of the planet.
SPEAKER_0:  How much is trauma?
SPEAKER_1:  of that kind and later in life affect your ability to love another human being.
SPEAKER_1:  say inside a relationship.
SPEAKER_1:  Connect.
SPEAKER_0:  with another human being.
SPEAKER_0:  it can impact it a lot. And again, I wanna say, can people overcome and be as loving to a partner or a child or anyone else? YES!
SPEAKER_0:  But we're talking across society, right? How are we setting the odds, right? We're setting the odds towards a higher sense of vigilance.
SPEAKER_0:  a decreased sense of.
SPEAKER_0:  self-confidence, an increased sense of vulnerability, right? A decreased comfort interacting with others, right? What we're doing is we're pushing towards isolation and misery and depression and resentment. I mean, those factors push towards that. You know, we know that the research is so strong that...
SPEAKER_0:  at adverse childhood experiences, these things that happen.
SPEAKER_0:  The more, the worse, the more prolonged.
SPEAKER_0:  the more that person is up against.
SPEAKER_0:  as they try and navigate.
SPEAKER_0:  life.
SPEAKER_1:  and uh... i suppose one of the
SPEAKER_1:  elements of intimacy like what we're talking about is vulnerability.
SPEAKER_1:  and maybe there's a...
SPEAKER_1:  Is there fear?
SPEAKER_1:  of being vulnerable.
SPEAKER_1:  of being hurt again.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that ultimately the barrier?
SPEAKER_0:  to intimacy.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're taught a lesson that says the world is not safe.
SPEAKER_0:  and you're not good enough for someone to keep safe.
SPEAKER_0:  and you're not strong enough to keep yourself safe.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a final common pathway of.
SPEAKER_0:  of the vast majority of child abuse is telling those lessons
SPEAKER_0:  See you then.
SPEAKER_0:  How
SPEAKER_0:  How can that not?
SPEAKER_0:  change the lay of the land against openness, against the ability to rationally consider trust and mutuality and to protect oneself, but also take chances and do the things that we have to do to create the greatest happiness.
SPEAKER_0:  in our lives. We set the odds so much.
SPEAKER_0:  against them.
SPEAKER_1:  pathway which I think is really...
SPEAKER_1:  interesting because of
SPEAKER_1:  I've seen it in people is this kind of ability to detach yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  from feeling any emotions.
SPEAKER_1:  to like protect yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  It's almost like you're not.
SPEAKER_0:  quite there.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a word for it, it's isolation of affect. This is a defense mechanism.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Isolation of F.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Is that a common way another?
SPEAKER_1:  Common way to deal with trauma.
SPEAKER_0:  Well...
SPEAKER_0:  Isolation of affect can cut-
SPEAKER_0:  both ways so f-
SPEAKER_0:  If there's been a major trauma, let's say someone has seen something terrible.
SPEAKER_0:  and they're isolated from their affidavits.
SPEAKER_0:  And at one time it was thought, well, maybe that's good, right? They're not hysterical, they're not distraught, but we see that is not good.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, because what needs to be beheld.
SPEAKER_0:  process to get our arms around in some way, shape or form has just been separated off.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So we know that is not good.
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_0:  But...
SPEAKER_0:  Isolation of affid can also serve us very well.
SPEAKER_0:  When I think back to being.
SPEAKER_0:  an intern, a medical intern in the hospital, and you might have to go and-
SPEAKER_0:  pronounce someone dead with
SPEAKER_0:  you know, with.
SPEAKER_0:  hysterical family members.
SPEAKER_0:  And then 10 minutes later.
SPEAKER_0:  five minutes later, might be two minutes later, really, you know, you have to go to
SPEAKER_0:  another room and you've got to maybe do some procedure that involves having your focus on a certain thing and making sure your hand movements are the right way or talking to a person in a way that is
SPEAKER_0:  that's very different than where you just came from, that's very hopeful.
SPEAKER_0:  So then you have to isolate the affect of what's going on around you. And it happens not just in, it's just one example, but we have to do it in life.
SPEAKER_0:  so that we can.
SPEAKER_0:  put affect aside to process later or not feel the full weight of affect.
SPEAKER_0:  where we know the meaning, like I know the meaning of the tragedy of the person I just pronounced dead
SPEAKER_0:  but I wanna separate that from myself because I'm also aware that it's not my tragedy so that I can then, okay, put that affect aside and go do the next thing that I have to do. So that I think can cut both ways.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, but then you have to like...
SPEAKER_1:  Reattach it.
SPEAKER_1:  Understand that is good to be close with emotion even painful emotion
SPEAKER_1:  Right.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, because that's the human experience.
SPEAKER_1:  Right. I feel like.
SPEAKER_1:  If you build up a skill that you can detach yourself from
SPEAKER_1:  Emotion.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that could become its own kind of... Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  It becomes too easy to do it, right? And to reinforce, that's when people are suffering too much.
SPEAKER_0:  over too long a period of time.
SPEAKER_0:  then we're creatures of habit.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? And even though our brains are, you're talking about our brains are sitting on the shoulders of the giant of the maybe thousand levels of emergence that come underneath of them.
SPEAKER_0:  Our brains are also.
SPEAKER_0:  also work in very simple habit-based ways. Like if you and I chose a word right now.
SPEAKER_0:  and set it 500 times.
SPEAKER_0:  We would know, it's just a silly experiment, but we'd both be saying it.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Because our brains are also creatures of habit. So if you over and over and over have to isolate yourself,
SPEAKER_0:  from affect and you develop those mechanisms, well you develop those mechanisms and
SPEAKER_0:  they don't go away any easier than if we said the word 500 times and decided to forget.
SPEAKER_0:  We won't forget no matter what we decided.
SPEAKER_0:  So...
SPEAKER_1:  How do we find our way back?
SPEAKER_1:  How do we overcome?
SPEAKER_1:  What are the different pathways?
SPEAKER_0:  The very first thing is to acknowledge.
SPEAKER_0:  ourselves and often to others, which might be one other person. It might be in words, spoken, it might be written.
SPEAKER_0:  what the trauma has been.
SPEAKER_0:  Because the lessons of trauma...
SPEAKER_0:  the evil lessons of trauma.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'll use the example of my own life, the lesson that told me that
SPEAKER_0:  I was shameful.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, cursed.
SPEAKER_0:  and hopeless.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  It's a very evil lesson.
SPEAKER_0:  but my brain will say it over and did say it over and over and over to me. And if that just sits inside.
SPEAKER_0:  That's how trauma festers, that's how trauma hijacks our thoughts, our emotions.
SPEAKER_0:  So being able to say.
SPEAKER_0:  to ourselves and to another, like this is what's happened.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Okay. This is what's happened. We're built to
SPEAKER_0:  massage words and to create meaning through words, right? Like we don't massage pictures, right, images. We talk and massage meaning with words.
SPEAKER_0:  So when I finally went to see a therapist and I could say...
SPEAKER_0:  No.
SPEAKER_0:  My brother.
SPEAKER_0:  whatever words I would have said, like he killed himself. and I can't
SPEAKER_0:  accepted or I can't imagine it and like I let it happen. Like, so I had to say those things, right? So then I could begin to bring some sense of truth to it, you know, and I think it was a long time ago, but the therapist probably said something like, okay, probably season you let it happen. It's your fault, right? Cause you got to get at those things.
SPEAKER_0:  so that one can begin to bring.
SPEAKER_0:  into focus what does a trauma mean and what does it not mean?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, a classic example is the, what would you say to someone else example? You know, it will say, well, I.
SPEAKER_0:  Now how many times have I...
SPEAKER_0:  It's just, I cry if I stop and think about it enough. It's just stop and talk to someone who is sexually assaulted through no fault of their own.
SPEAKER_0:  who comes in and tells the story they've been telling themselves about how it's their fault. They should have walked home a different way, they should have dressed differently, they should have left earlier. Summary
SPEAKER_0:  I wrote about it in the book over and over and over.
SPEAKER_0:  They have a person.
SPEAKER_0:  Who?
SPEAKER_0:  Let's say you take a person who's intelligent, engaged in the world, who's capable of understanding lots and lots and lots of things, but doesn't understand that.
SPEAKER_0:  If it were someone else, that person would understand in a moment, it's not that person's fault. So what you want to do is overcome the fact that the negative emotions, the hijacked emotion systems of trauma are telling that person a lie and they're telling them so strongly and so strongly.
SPEAKER_0:  Awfully so meanly.
SPEAKER_0:  that the person just takes it inside and starts to see it as.
SPEAKER_0:  So you begin to hold that up to the light of day. And again, one example could be, okay, so someone, the person who's coming in next has actually been through something similar, right? And can you stay and just...
SPEAKER_0:  tell her how it's her fault, right? And like, oh my God, no, oh, because I could never, like then they see, right? I mean, again, this is not always how you do it, you can get a person to see like.
SPEAKER_0:  Well that would be the most horrible-
SPEAKER_0:  How could you do that? Right? Maybe they're doing it to themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  So you begin.
SPEAKER_0:  you begin to put words in a structure and say, okay, let's look at what's going on inside of you. You don't have to be scared of anything you're thinking and feeling. In fact, the fear is in not.
SPEAKER_0:  exposing it to the light of day. That's where it gets the best of us.
SPEAKER_0:  And now, everything is different. And whether that involves...
SPEAKER_0:  use of medications for intrusive thoughts and depression, or there's no medicines needed, but it's all reframing, like whatever it may be that comes next.
SPEAKER_0:  The whole world has changed.
SPEAKER_0:  when the person has...
SPEAKER_0:  acknowledged what's happened, exposed it to themselves and to trusted others around them and begun to look at it in some way other than...
SPEAKER_0:  the stuff in an evil box place that the trauma initially puts us through our.
SPEAKER_0:  The reflexes it creates in us.
SPEAKER_1:  It's interesting that there's power to just saying it out loud.
SPEAKER_1:  First, saying your perception of it aloud.
SPEAKER_1:  other than in that case, that might be your fault.
SPEAKER_1:  And then...
SPEAKER_1:  working out loud, working through.
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_0:  It may not be.
SPEAKER_0:  Any experienced therapist will tell you this that.
SPEAKER_0:  Every now and then it will happen.
SPEAKER_0:  that someone will come and they'll say something.
SPEAKER_0:  Usually it's very early on in the process, they'll say something they've never said before and they immediately...
SPEAKER_0:  are in an entirely different place than they may have been for decades.
SPEAKER_0:  And I can remember a person saying...
SPEAKER_0:  that the coach had raped him.
SPEAKER_0:  and just saying it. This was Aknie Sane.
SPEAKER_0:  decades before.
SPEAKER_0:  Everything was different.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not saying everything is perfect, but his life was in a different, but as soon as he said it, he could see how dare, like he thought that person did that.
SPEAKER_0:  to this child.
SPEAKER_0:  The child was me.
SPEAKER_0:  He never thought it until he said it out loud because his mind was going over and over with why it was his fault, what he did to deserve it, how he kept going back, so it must be his fault. It was in it, as soon as he put words to it, he saw the truth of it.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  You lose a bifurcation in the path of life then. And any therapist has-
SPEAKER_0:  you know, stories like that, which just shows the immense power that it can even be that just uttering the words.
SPEAKER_0:  makes just a cascade of change all at once.
SPEAKER_1:  Just saying those words to another human being.
SPEAKER_1:  It makes you wonder what that compulsive
SPEAKER_1:  loop that happens in our heads.
SPEAKER_1:  until it's...
SPEAKER_1:  brought to the surface.
SPEAKER_1:  That's so interesting.
SPEAKER_0:  entirely non-productive the loops. And sometimes even if we put, what would I say to another? Let me write it down. It can get rid of those loops in our.
SPEAKER_0:  in our brains. Any even thought of outward expression is the enemy of those.
SPEAKER_0:  internal persecutory negative thought loops.
SPEAKER_0:  How do you find a good therapist?
SPEAKER_1:  I tend to think of...
SPEAKER_1:  Listen, I'm a fan of podcasts.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm a fan of conversations. It feels like a real, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like finding a good friend.
SPEAKER_1:  or something. It feels like a difficult journey.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe I'm wrong in that, but it just feels like such a...
SPEAKER_1:  It feels like a partnership, a journey together versus like some very
SPEAKER_1:  simple clinical
SPEAKER_0:  procedure.
SPEAKER_0:  The first thing I would say is.
SPEAKER_0:  to change the entire paradigm. Like most people, like, okay, I need a therapist. So people feel often like they're in a weakened position because they need, you know, quote unquote, a therapist.
SPEAKER_0:  then therapists are rationed.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? How many insurance panels have
SPEAKER_0:  lists a mile long of qualified therapists.
SPEAKER_0:  who could be on that insurance panel.
SPEAKER_0:  but there's a certification process. Like these things make no sense, right? The state's already certified the person, right? But there's so many barriers to entry that now we're rationing.
SPEAKER_0:  this resource, which we should all stop and pause for a second and think like we're okay with that as a society. And by the way, everything else is like that too, when we're trying to get help for our health.
SPEAKER_0:  So let's step back from that for a second.
SPEAKER_0:  Now it's a resource that's not in great supply, and then a person begins to think.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, essentially I'll take what I can get. Like I just gotta get somebody I don't know enough to know anyway, right?
SPEAKER_0:  And those are very disempowering.
SPEAKER_0:  thoughts as opposed to saying, look, I'm going to be an empowered consumer and
SPEAKER_0:  I need to choose someone.
SPEAKER_0:  who gets over just some basic hurdles of what I think are reasonable human interaction, right? So like, is a person making eye contact? Do they seem interested, right? Like, these are basic points about any human interaction, including a therapist, right?
SPEAKER_0:  then you can say, okay, is there a word of mouth? Anyone else has something good? Nothing better than a word of mouth recommendation from someone you trust, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Or anybody can have a good website, but you say, let me look at the website. What is it saying if there is one, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Does it?
SPEAKER_0:  resonate with me or not, right?
SPEAKER_0:  But after all of that, then you go to see the person.
SPEAKER_0:  with the idea that you're interviewing them.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? The idea that, yeah, I hope this person can help me. And if so, great, I'm with the program, but I'm thinking about it. Do I want this person? Do I feel heard? Do I feel cared for?
SPEAKER_0:  Which doesn't mean is it easy, right? What it might mean is it hard and...
SPEAKER_0:  I leave and I feel like...
SPEAKER_0:  Emotional for a couple of days, but but I see that I'm facing new things
SPEAKER_0:  Now this process of assessment...
SPEAKER_0:  so that one isn't settling for something.
SPEAKER_0:  that is formulaic, over-packaged, and I'm not trying to be overly critical of therapists. I mean, there are people everywhere who do their jobs well and people who don't do their jobs well.
SPEAKER_0:  but most therapists are working in systems.
SPEAKER_0:  that push against doing.
SPEAKER_0:  the job well, right, because they're rationing care and there's a lot of number of sessions and there's enough time before a person can return.
SPEAKER_0:  So often it's an uphill battle because we're trying to be helped.
SPEAKER_0:  within systems we've created and tolerate.
SPEAKER_0:  that are pushing.
SPEAKER_0:  against helping us.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, but you know that
SPEAKER_1:  process.
SPEAKER_1:  It's tricky. I mean, if you're in a rough place mentally.
SPEAKER_1:  just like with
SPEAKER_1:  with any kind of interview, it's hard not to.
SPEAKER_1:  that a failed interaction failed interview.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, there's, there's something wrong with you.
SPEAKER_0:  Sure.
SPEAKER_1:  There is an authority to a therapist, I think, where you think like...
SPEAKER_1:  They've got it all figured out.
SPEAKER_1:  and I'm a mess and therefore
SPEAKER_1:  If there's something off...
SPEAKER_1:  It's all my fault.
SPEAKER_1:  Alright, so it's very tricky and it's easy to then give up and then...
SPEAKER_1:  It's like the step to try to get a therapist, the first step.
SPEAKER_1:  To get help, if I get therapists, like any kind of help, that's a big leap to take.
SPEAKER_0:  Especially when you're in a rough place. I agree completely. We should not make people.
SPEAKER_0:  swim against such a strong current.
SPEAKER_0:  to get their needs met.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, we see this in such obvious places where...
SPEAKER_0:  You have an elderly homebound person.
SPEAKER_0:  who can't get their medicine.
SPEAKER_0:  because, oh, there's been some change and they didn't put the new number into the form or Lord knows what, I mean, it's, it's
SPEAKER_0:  incredible how we force people to swim against strong currents.
SPEAKER_0:  to get things that are just basic at times for their survival.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  And with that in mind, I don't have a lot of respect for where healthcare is at or where mental health is at.
SPEAKER_0:  is at. The field that I work in has accepted all sorts of
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  aspects of how things go, someone else controlling.
SPEAKER_0:  how long the interaction can go on, how the interaction is bounded, what can be said and done, what medicines can be prescribed.
SPEAKER_0:  There's so many external controls in the systems we work in.
SPEAKER_0:  that
SPEAKER_0:  We, and I say me included, like all of us in the field.
SPEAKER_0:  have let it get to a place where it's obscenely difficult.
SPEAKER_0:  to get help.
SPEAKER_0:  obscenely difficult.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  We should
SPEAKER_0:  Say that's not okay.
SPEAKER_0:  I think psychiatrists and
SPEAKER_0:  therapists and masters level social workers, psychologists and you name it, I think.
SPEAKER_0:  we should all say, this is not okay. And then we as a society should be saying, this is not okay. Otherwise what you're saying, which is I think...
SPEAKER_0:  true will only become worse as there's more and more barriers.
SPEAKER_0:  to getting the help a person needs and each time a person isn't helped
SPEAKER_0:  it sets the odds against them getting more help.
SPEAKER_0:  I should say, Hugh, that you're...
SPEAKER_0:  When I started working, there were times I would send people to an emergency room, right, if there was some emergency, you know, emergency in their mental health and they were at risk.
SPEAKER_0:  And there were times I'd send somebody to an emergency room where if you stopped and looked,
SPEAKER_0:  It would have been malpractice not to do that.
SPEAKER_0:  All right.
SPEAKER_0:  Now!
SPEAKER_0:  It's not just me who...
SPEAKER_0:  Who?
SPEAKER_0:  has an incredibly high threshold.
SPEAKER_0:  for sending someone to an emergency room because you just send someone who's in a lot of distress and oftentimes they're sitting on a gurney in a hallway or they're locked in a small white room and all they had was depression. They're scared when they go in and 36 hours later, oh, they're feeling a little better. Wikes are desperate to get out of there and someone sends them home. I mean…
SPEAKER_0:  So our systems have shifted so much that we tolerate.
SPEAKER_0:  Now, on mass.
SPEAKER_0:  what is egregious to the individual.
SPEAKER_0:  So you are.
SPEAKER_1:  psychiatrist in terms of
SPEAKER_1:  uh, doing therapy.
SPEAKER_1:  Psychotherapy.
SPEAKER_1:  What does a successful interaction look like?
SPEAKER_1:  Perhaps a fun question, perhaps not.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think of the psychiatrist Sean and good will hunting played by Robin Williams?
SPEAKER_1:  So what is the full range of interesting interactions? Can there be an intimacy, a friendship, a kind of...
SPEAKER_1:  um, varied
SPEAKER_1:  interaction that kind of blends the lines of
SPEAKER_1:  you know, 30 minutes session once a week or whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  versus like a really kind of...
SPEAKER_1:  deliberate long-term project that cares about the well-being of a person.
SPEAKER_1:  across the months and years.
SPEAKER_1:  What can you say about a successful?
SPEAKER_1:  interaction between.
SPEAKER_0:  therapist and patient.
SPEAKER_0:  I think we're much better served by the latter.
SPEAKER_0:  And again, it doesn't have to be over.
SPEAKER_0:  years, we may be pressing this person might need that over weeks, they might need it over months, they might need it over years.
SPEAKER_0:  If I'm understanding correctly, you're describing something that is...
SPEAKER_0:  like a real human engagement.
SPEAKER_0:  And I work in a field that...
SPEAKER_0:  for...
SPEAKER_0:  years and years and years.
SPEAKER_0:  the patient didn't get to see. The therapist was sitting in a place, he was sitting behind the person, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  That's not of course the only tradition and there are aspects of that tradition that can be very humanized.
SPEAKER_0:  But the idea that...
SPEAKER_0:  we're supposed to not be human. I mean, this medicine is shot through with this, right? That the doctor's supposed to be God and it protects the doctor.
SPEAKER_0:  And that makes its way into therapy and the idea of.
SPEAKER_0:  the superiority, the therapist knows more.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean in some ways
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, but the idea is to know more about mechanical things.
SPEAKER_0:  right to know more about like.
SPEAKER_0:  and knowledge not as a human being, right? If we approach
SPEAKER_0:  therapy as a collaborative human endeavor.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? We're gonna do it together.
SPEAKER_0:  Of course I'm gonna learn from you too, right? I mean, we're two human beings and we're talking about things that are deep and personal and intimate. And I'm not gonna participate in a way that makes it like about me.
SPEAKER_0:  as much as it's about you, but we're two humans and what's gone on in me may have relevance and sharing it may have relevance. And at times,
SPEAKER_0:  you doing something back for me may have relevance. I'll give you an example of a person who would not...
SPEAKER_0:  let me help him. It was a young man. So when I was in training, who was very
SPEAKER_0:  very sick and needed to change certain choices and habits.
SPEAKER_0:  or he was not going to survive.
SPEAKER_0:  and I had no...
SPEAKER_0:  ability to help him whatsoever.
SPEAKER_0:  And I went and I saw a supervisor who is existentially trained. Where here it's different from existentialism in the classic sense, but it's about really human connection, right?
SPEAKER_0:  And the guy was always wanting to teach me.
SPEAKER_0:  something, right? Because I can get by in Spanish, but he was fluent in Spanish. And he wanted to, he'd, oh, you traveled here and he'd say, you know, a word to see if I knew. And I was always directing back to what I was supposed to do, right? And the supervisor, I've never forget, he said,
SPEAKER_0:  Let him teach you Spanish. Come on, so we had a couple sessions where if you look from the outside, you say, what is going on there? Like,
SPEAKER_0:  Right, like they were Spanish lessons. Heh, I do National Longing
SPEAKER_0:  me, right? And then at some point he brought in his mother and...
SPEAKER_0:  We hadn't brought her in yet and he was in part showing off.
SPEAKER_0:  that he taught me something, right? And I said a couple things and he felt.
SPEAKER_0:  more powerful, like he was younger than me and he felt sick and disempowered
SPEAKER_0:  but he didn't feel that way once he taught me something and we showed it off to his mother, right? you
SPEAKER_0:  and his behavior started to change, he started taking better care of himself.
SPEAKER_0:  He could see a little more what I was saying. He was like, you're a wonderful person. Look, you love your mother and your aunt and they love you. And he could start seeing that about himself.
SPEAKER_0:  But that came from humanness and if-
SPEAKER_0:  And I think that's the way we help people.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't understand why we don't do everything that way. It's like, we're two humans.
SPEAKER_0:  But if you're doing something for me, then there's something you have an expertise in, I don't, that's why you're doing it for me. The reverse could be true, but it doesn't mean we're not just two humans doing something together.
SPEAKER_1:  And the healthcare system and the legal system should not get in the way of that. I mean, there's liability and all these kinds of things.
SPEAKER_1:  that uh...
SPEAKER_1:  can get in the way.
SPEAKER_1:  of the humanness.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, some of that is justified. You have to be careful. You have to make sure there's irresponsible, but.
SPEAKER_1:  A little too much can destroy the humanness.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll use it where I don't usually say something is insane. Like it's not consistent with sanity. And the presence of.
SPEAKER_0:  of the legal system. Look I'm all for of course physicians have to be held.
SPEAKER_0:  We have to be responsible and everybody makes mistakes and we have to be accountable for their mistakes.
SPEAKER_0:  I understand all of that.
SPEAKER_0:  But what we see now, it's so...
SPEAKER_0:  absurd that, oh, like everyone is frightened.
SPEAKER_0:  Everyone is frightened and then just looking to like, how do I slot into the box, check the boxes of what I'm supposed to do and not get in trouble?
SPEAKER_0:  You know, people get...
SPEAKER_0:  sued because
SPEAKER_0:  someone was at that hospital and that doctor touched their care. It happens in the VA system. It happens in other systems too.
SPEAKER_0:  So you might have touched their care and no one's even saying you did anything wrong, but they say the next person did. Oh, someone settled on your behalf and now you have a malpractice.
SPEAKER_0:  and maybe you can't get a license somewhere else. Like, doctors are terrified?
SPEAKER_0:  and they're terrified for good.
SPEAKER_0:  They're terrified for good reason, because the same society that is
SPEAKER_0:  given doctors in many ways too much power over time and treated doctors maybe too much like gods, now is I think enacting some of society's anger and envy.
SPEAKER_0:  Out on the...
SPEAKER_0:  physicians, even the idea that like.
SPEAKER_0:  person would know what medicine like I saw a couple of TV commercials give me this
SPEAKER_0:  Like it's interesting, right?
SPEAKER_0:  because
SPEAKER_0:  Even if.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's say I take myself out of it. It doesn't feel good, obviously, but it's like, wow.
SPEAKER_0:  Like I went to school for like eight years for this and you didn't even wanna hear my opinion, right? You're not taking good care of yourself, right? It doesn't mean you should think my opinion is gospel because I said it.
SPEAKER_0:  But, but-
SPEAKER_0:  People then don't have an understanding of like, what is expertise? What do people learn?
SPEAKER_0:  how can people help us understand and make better decisions? it kind of goes out with the wash and then
SPEAKER_0:  the position of the expert, I mean a lot has been written about this, right, gets diminished over time.
SPEAKER_0:  very much to our own.
SPEAKER_0:  and then often with aggression in the medical world.
SPEAKER_0:  coming.
SPEAKER_0:  Back towards.
SPEAKER_0:  the alleged expert.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, expertise is a-
SPEAKER_1:  tricky one. Such a tricky thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Because, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  coupled with expertise, the attention is this arrogance that can come with expertise.
SPEAKER_1:  The arrogance can
SPEAKER_1:  Make the ac-
SPEAKER_1:  the expert feel like they're more of an expert.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, and then it's a vicious cycle and then the arrogance in the current, in the 21st century, especially with the internet, the arrogance can.
SPEAKER_1:  uh, completely forced the public to distrust the expert because it all this is the gare arrogance vs the expertise
SPEAKER_1:  So, um...
SPEAKER_1:  Ultimately you have to have...
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  the greatest experts and masters I know are the ones that have.
SPEAKER_0:  complete humility. Right, humility and gratitude. Benefit of humanity is taking advantage of what is right and what is wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  back. Which is usually a really good sign that somebody...
SPEAKER_1:  as at the top of their field.
SPEAKER_0:  And they'll acknowledge that they don't know everything.
SPEAKER_1:  Which is hilarious, right? So like the best experts I know are the ones.
SPEAKER_1:  that will.
SPEAKER_1:  say that they...
SPEAKER_1:  don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  that would not call themselves next.
SPEAKER_1:  It's very confusing.
SPEAKER_0:  Or know that they know a lot, but don't know the answer to this. You see that a lot in medicine. That person knows they're an expert surgeon, but they also acknowledge they don't know if this is the right time to operate. That's how you get to the best answer instead of someone who is an expert and always knows the answer.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... if actually
SPEAKER_1:  rewind to the beginning of our conversation we talked about
SPEAKER_1:  You mentioned something I wanted to return to.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's a...
SPEAKER_1:  There's layers that are...
SPEAKER_1:  There's an emergent
SPEAKER_1:  novelty and you mentioned that we as human beings and we.
SPEAKER_1:  introspect and omind.
SPEAKER_1:  We really can't know most of it.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Which of course...
SPEAKER_1:  makes me think of this the unconscious mind subconscious mind
SPEAKER_1:  and Carl Jung, how much is hiding there in the shadows? You've, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  investigated a lot of trauma. How much is there in our mind?
SPEAKER_1:  that's not directly accessible to us.
SPEAKER_1:  Like what can you say, maybe philosophically?
SPEAKER_1:  about how much is there.
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh...
SPEAKER_1:  lurking in the
SPEAKER_0:  in the shadow.
SPEAKER_0:  I think there's a tremendous amount.
SPEAKER_0:  but I wouldn't.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't immediately go to.
SPEAKER_0:  an ominous perspective, right? Because if it's lurking there, right, it can come get us, right? And to some extent, that's true, right? Because the seeds of evil are there if we want to plant and nurture them. You think good things can't lurk?
SPEAKER_0:  I guess I realize. I was being poetic. So we are just gonna do a GOOD.
SPEAKER_1:  But you're right, you're absolutely right. And the young in shadow is supposed to not just be dark things, it's supposed to be everything. It's supposed to be a lot of positive things as well, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  which I think brings us to.
SPEAKER_0:  self-knowledge to truth, where I think the opposite of envy.
SPEAKER_0:  narcissism, sociopathy, I do think is all rooted in.
SPEAKER_0:  It's both the truth of the good things about us or the ways we're not.
SPEAKER_0:  we're not blame worthy for the things we're blaming ourselves for etc.
SPEAKER_0:  but the self-knowledge and the truth and...
SPEAKER_0:  getting away from the reflex of anger, frustration, envy, shame.
SPEAKER_0:  What I think happens then is all of that underneath the surface. If we look at like the consciousness is the top of the iceberg, you know, outside the top. So outside the water. So is what's underneath like.
SPEAKER_0:  shifting and it can pull the top under right or is it supporting the top?
SPEAKER_0:  and in it.
SPEAKER_0:  really I believe is honesty, truth, self-knowledge, humility, gratitude, all this simple stuff, good mental health.
SPEAKER_0:  is always consistent with simplicity. You know, humility, gratitude are easy things.
SPEAKER_0:  to say, like, we know what that is, right? We understand what that is. Soothing envy by having immense power and subjugating others is getting very, very complicated, right, what that is and how that plays out.
SPEAKER_0:  So if we are in touch with ourselves, if we're honest with ourselves, if we own what's ours...
SPEAKER_0:  We don't try and own what's not ours, right? What happens then is something isn't waiting inside of us to sort of jump us with some new...
SPEAKER_0:  a fact of self or challenge of self, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Then I think what happens are...
SPEAKER_0:  phenomena like intrinsic learning, like the way that so much happens inside of us automatically.
SPEAKER_0:  how people who have high levels of expertise.
SPEAKER_0:  know the answer.
SPEAKER_0:  complex questions.
SPEAKER_0:  more rapidly.
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't take them longer to think through it, but they have more knowledge to think through. The more happens rapidly and unconsciously, so they know the more complex answer, the
SPEAKER_0:  more quickly and readily. We can build that in ourselves, not just in terms of factual knowledge, but in terms of how we respond to things.
SPEAKER_0:  If I make a mistake, do I respond with reflexive shame? If I see someone has something I'd like, how do I respond?
SPEAKER_0:  We're more in accord with ourselves.
SPEAKER_0:  And then the automaticity in us is.
SPEAKER_0:  is serving us better.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's in the positive. Do you think, do you draw some wisdom from the early pioneers?
SPEAKER_1:  of psychotherapy like Freud and Jung.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes. There's some repressed.
SPEAKER_1:  There's some stuff to work through.
SPEAKER_1:  that is in the income.
SPEAKER_0:  conscious mind.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, I think there's
SPEAKER_0:  Always, like 100%.
SPEAKER_0:  of the time. You have a living human, you have things to work through.
SPEAKER_0:  in the unconscious mind.
SPEAKER_0:  There's too much that goes on around us that we might find.
SPEAKER_0:  unacceptable and suppress.
SPEAKER_0:  There can be.
SPEAKER_0:  smaller but important examples, right? Someone who...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  feels that they're not a good enough parent and
SPEAKER_0:  They, I don't know, they dropped the child's.
SPEAKER_0:  plate.
SPEAKER_0:  Right and.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  and there's a feeling about that of badness.
SPEAKER_0:  in them that the person that can't tolerate and pushes away, right? maybe they become a little bit less confident, a little bit less assertive.
SPEAKER_0:  Those small examples are important because they may be low valence, but there can be many, many, many, many, many, many of them.
SPEAKER_0:  Then you can look at the opposite end of the spectrum where someone, for example, feels that they're repressing their sexuality.
SPEAKER_0:  unconsciously, something that is...
SPEAKER_0:  so important, say, to how a person feels about themselves, to whether they can seek fulfillment, to how they feel about themselves, to how they feel about themselves, to how they feel
SPEAKER_0:  feel about their ability to interact and engage with others in ways that are loving and generative over time.
SPEAKER_0:  So from smaller things?
SPEAKER_0:  that accumulate often at rapid pace to really big things.
SPEAKER_0:  We are pushing things into the unconscious because they're not.
SPEAKER_0:  acceptable and we need to explore like why is that not acceptable? Maybe there's not an acceptable urge because it's really not acceptable to me, right? Like a violent urge.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe there's an unacceptable urge.
SPEAKER_0:  Because...
SPEAKER_0:  I'm actually listening to the lies society is telling me about what's okay and what's not okay. So in exploring those things,
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, we become happier and healthier. And that could mean if we're already happy and healthy, it gets better. We get more insulated against the negative.
SPEAKER_0:  Or it can mean the person who's really nurturing some of those seeds of
SPEAKER_0:  of evil and envy does that less or steps away.
SPEAKER_0:  So whether it's good or it's bad, it's in there inside of us.
SPEAKER_0:  and we benefit from.
SPEAKER_0:  understanding that idea of the observing ego, right? Like we said, the part that can stop and say, hey, this is what's.
SPEAKER_0:  This is where I see what's going on in me.
SPEAKER_0:  What have you learned?
SPEAKER_1:  about exploring the human mind, about the art of conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  is ultimately therapy's conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there something you can put into words?
SPEAKER_1:  Like what makes it a
SPEAKER_0:  Good.
SPEAKER_0:  I think language is among the most amazing gifts we have.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's also one of the most like.
SPEAKER_0:  clunky routes to misunderstanding.
SPEAKER_0:  I think of like, there's a concept of facticity, things that are like, I guess, unnecessary evils. And from the religious perspective, I think is where the word started.
SPEAKER_0:  but of language being like a facticity.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  We need to communicate with one another. We want to communicate. So we develop words and we have these amazing brains that can have language and that's all well and good.
SPEAKER_0:  but our fantasy would be more like Mr. Spock.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, you know, the Vulcan mind meld was like, I communicate with you because we put our hands on one another and we know, you know, by doing this, what,
SPEAKER_0:  what we're thinking and what we're feeling and we won't have misunderstandings.
SPEAKER_0:  So because I think we can approximate that, we can come kind of close with language, right?
SPEAKER_0:  or we can be so far away.
SPEAKER_0:  it that we can say the same word and of opposite meanings and have it generate immediate animosity.
SPEAKER_0:  Hi.
SPEAKER_0:  that we need to be very.
SPEAKER_0:  Very careful.
SPEAKER_0:  with language, with communication, with conversations. And I've come to understand that much, much more.
SPEAKER_0:  as I've gotten older, both in terms of how hurtful.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, reckless.
SPEAKER_0:  speeches, which is why I'm horrified by so much of what we see in our political discourse, right? The slurs, the negativity that's attached to something, to some word, you know, how one can utter something and it can go into another person just into the ear, but then goes through so many parts of the meaning of the brain that that person feels a pervasive sense of.
SPEAKER_0:  shame or beleagueredness, right?
SPEAKER_0:  So yes, reckless language absolutely hurts.
SPEAKER_0:  people and we see that all the time in ways that I think are just atrocious.
SPEAKER_0:  And also how bad miscommunication.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, I really learned that through a lot of different ways, but in the work as a therapist of like really wanting to make sure...
SPEAKER_0:  that I'm really understanding you and you're really understanding me. And a lot of work goes into that communication. I think people, we can get into a rhythm of it and then it happens more easily. But I think it's a life and death difference.
SPEAKER_0:  at times, lots of times, right, in the world around us between.
SPEAKER_0:  clear and accurate communication. So I said a word because I think you know what I mean or something like that.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, so to that, I mean, there's the the
SPEAKER_1:  Camus quote that I like
SPEAKER_1:  as much unhappiness has come into the world because of things left unsaid.
SPEAKER_1:  So that has to do with clear communication.
SPEAKER_1:  But there's also, um...
SPEAKER_1:  a dance.
SPEAKER_1:  to up.
SPEAKER_1:  a conversation, a...
SPEAKER_1:  poetry to it, there is ambiguity to language.
SPEAKER_1:  And if you have a kind of awareness of that ambiguity and you play with it, that's where wit and humor come in.
SPEAKER_1:  That's.
SPEAKER_1:  allows you to sneak up to difficult topics.
SPEAKER_1:  without trampling on them.
SPEAKER_1:  i don't know uh... there there's an art to his wealth
SPEAKER_1:  There's an art to the silence.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, the...
SPEAKER_1:  just allowing both human beings, one of the most intimate things you can share with the human being is silence.
SPEAKER_0:  That's communicates. It's a different communication.
SPEAKER_0:  at times more powerful.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, giving a person space.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  accumulate, to integrate, to make sense of their thoughts.
SPEAKER_1:  Enough to say a word?
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe a memory spark so they can think about that memory.
SPEAKER_1:  and process that memory.
SPEAKER_0:  So it's not just words, sorry to do this, but it's not just words, right? It's now time for communication as.
SPEAKER_0:  It's body language, it's...
SPEAKER_0:  you know, it's expressions of empathy, it's movements, it's pauses, right? The communication processes
SPEAKER_0:  very very complicated.
SPEAKER_0:  and deep.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, and some of that is building trust, but also challenging a person.
SPEAKER_1:  I wonder about that whole process with strangers, for example.
SPEAKER_1:  of how you do that successfully. Like you and I just met today.
SPEAKER_1:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_1:  But I think.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of our interaction is very free. We can get to know each other in any way we want.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a few conversations I have coming up.
SPEAKER_1:  In general, where there's a lot of other pressures and constraints on those conversations, there's a lot of pressure on those conversations.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a danger to it, there's risks.
SPEAKER_1:  there's a political forces involved like what what what it would be from not from my perspective but probably from my
SPEAKER_1:  as well as the
SPEAKER_1:  How do you say this thing? What are the words that are going to offend? Watch the show on YouTube for the members of the club h pela focuses on outra a
SPEAKER_1:  And you're learning that about a stranger at the same time, you know, and you don't.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a, it's a, it's an interesting dance.
SPEAKER_0:  because you have to.
SPEAKER_0:  Wok
SPEAKER_0:  carefully but deliberately.
SPEAKER_1:  carefully because
SPEAKER_1:  I've learned this about myself, about others.
SPEAKER_1:  There's certain words.
SPEAKER_1:  that can trigger a person.
SPEAKER_1:  that they can.
SPEAKER_1:  Make a person feel.
SPEAKER_1:  poorly.
SPEAKER_1:  about themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  So you can push, you can challenge a person about something.
SPEAKER_1:  and they're totally okay with it but if you use a certain word to do it
SPEAKER_1:  It's going to, it's, it may be maps that some childhood thing that their father mother used to say or something like this.
SPEAKER_1:  and uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, part of the art of conversation is actually...
SPEAKER_1:  being a little bit free in using those words, being extremely sensitive.
SPEAKER_1:  in detecting when a person reacts to a particular.
SPEAKER_0:  Word.
SPEAKER_1:  and like storing that away.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like, okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Then we might want to return to that later.
SPEAKER_1:  There might be an interesting, that could be a tip of an iceberg that's actually representing something beautiful.
SPEAKER_1:  or you might wanna just.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a nothing word they just want to avoid because it's a distraction.
SPEAKER_1:  And so all of that kind of has to be integrated into the dance of language. This is really interesting, especially when the stakes are really high. When you get one conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  We have.
SPEAKER_1:  When you sit down, you have one conversation and it makes.
SPEAKER_1:  the difference between like, say you had one conversation with a patient.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the only conversation you get.
SPEAKER_0:  to help. Sometimes it is the case. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  and like
SPEAKER_1:  This is pretty high stakes.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh man.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's tough. I guess you get over, um...
SPEAKER_1:  And like.
SPEAKER_1:  Over time, I guess.
SPEAKER_1:  You get used to the...
SPEAKER_1:  the high stakes nature of it.
SPEAKER_0:  when you develop an ability.
SPEAKER_0:  and all that unconscious processing. Right, right. All that part of the iceberg that's underneath the surface is doing all of that, right? Is reading behavioral cues, verbal cues, and recognizing the primacy of emotion over logic, right? If we're all logic,
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, we're going to talk about this thing. I'll say things you say things back, even if it's-
SPEAKER_0:  politically contentious say. So where is it going to talk logically? You know, that's not.
SPEAKER_0:  the case, right? There could be...
SPEAKER_0:  a word that raises a certain emotion and you know you don't want to tread there because the emotion will color the person's ability to engage. So you're aware of all of this. And then I think.
SPEAKER_0:  from the perspective of all of that. It's like standing on the shoulders of your own internal giant, right? That understands language and emotions and body language and attunement and history and it's triggering and all of that.
SPEAKER_0:  And then on top of that, as you're standing up on those shoulders, you're trying to be effective.
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_0:  And then I think that's where...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, effectiveness can be unilateral.
SPEAKER_0:  or it can be together. I mean, I think some of what emerged
SPEAKER_0:  from Viktor Frankl's writing after the Second World War was.
SPEAKER_0:  how.
SPEAKER_0:  much shared humanness means to us, how much of that.
SPEAKER_0:  can be an incentive for survival beyond all others, right? So the idea of are we doing something before communicating unilaterally?
SPEAKER_0:  Like I want...
SPEAKER_0:  information from you or I want you to do a certain thing when we're done talking, right?
SPEAKER_0:  right, done communicating. That's a very unilateral type of effectiveness, which can make sense. Sometimes I want information out of a patient because I want to know what to do next, right? So it doesn't have to always be negative.
SPEAKER_0:  but it can also be a tool of manipulation.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? If someone would say coming from envy or narcissism, I want to communicate with you in a way that makes you do what I want you to do.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  Different from that is...
SPEAKER_0:  where it's a shared communication, where there's like an umbrella, so to speak, over us, and we're doing something that can only happen together because we're us, we're each person, right? And we come together to do something that's a shared effectiveness. Like I think we're doing...
SPEAKER_0:  now of like elucidating and pursuing thoughts and getting ideas out. And I think the best situations are shared effectiveness situations because you call upon the resourcefulness and the internal resources of both.
SPEAKER_1:  But you, especially with strangers.
SPEAKER_1:  especially when it's not labeled the therapy session.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  you kind of actually stumble into that.
SPEAKER_1:  cooperative state.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, uh.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to...
SPEAKER_1:  organically.
SPEAKER_1:  develop a trust.
SPEAKER_1:  together.
SPEAKER_1:  and almost lose yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  Ultimately, I think you put it really nice. I think successful conversations, even when it's with.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... like you know if it's like with world leaders or logicians
SPEAKER_1:  people that operate in the space of reason.
SPEAKER_1:  the most successful conversation will ultimately be.
SPEAKER_1:  in the layer and in the landscape of emotion.
SPEAKER_1:  Like that's where the interesting stuff will happen. That's where you'll discover anything. And that's where you get to actually meet to start getting an understanding of each other or what you actually mean even by the...
SPEAKER_1:  statements that are supposed to be kind of rationally based.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like you lose yourself. You lose yourself in the way you do when you're-
SPEAKER_1:  when you're children and you just...
SPEAKER_1:  Not shooting the shit about whatever topic and you just forget yourself. Forget what you're supposed to say. Sex.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, well you kinda-
SPEAKER_1:  plug into the unconscious mind a little bit.
SPEAKER_1:  and you get to speak.
SPEAKER_1:  maybe indirectly but
SPEAKER_1:  to the things that really drive you.
SPEAKER_1:  to the thing that really, to the things.
SPEAKER_1:  to the emotions I suppose that...
SPEAKER_1:  underlie your worldview.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like that.
SPEAKER_1:  That's where productive conversations can happen, whether it's a patient or just a stranger you're talking to.
SPEAKER_1:  at a bar about geopolitics.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... the rest of it to franco what would he make of his work man search for meaning
SPEAKER_1:  What are like the-
SPEAKER_1:  the lessons you draw from his work.
SPEAKER_1:  of him as a psychologist, but also.
SPEAKER_1:  from that very powerful work that reflects on his experience in a Nazi concentration camp.
SPEAKER_0:  I think that...
SPEAKER_0:  It was.
SPEAKER_0:  almost a
SPEAKER_0:  profound
SPEAKER_0:  reinvention of
SPEAKER_0:  Human-ness?
SPEAKER_0:  Right, after something so...
SPEAKER_0:  Awful.
SPEAKER_0:  so bleak and so despairing.
SPEAKER_0:  to.
SPEAKER_0:  Speak anew.
SPEAKER_0:  about
SPEAKER_0:  shared humanness, human connection, meaning, compassion.
SPEAKER_0:  that.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it was in in.
SPEAKER_0:  intellectual direction that was adorned with all of the emotions.
SPEAKER_0:  that we need to adorn the logic with.
SPEAKER_0:  in order to make real change.
SPEAKER_0:  in the world. bank.
SPEAKER_0:  fueled.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, so many branches have come.
SPEAKER_0:  from his work, the existential psychotherapy and its place in helping human activities today. I'm
SPEAKER_0:  a trend away from the idea that
SPEAKER_0:  that we're all quite isolated and that what's going on between us is all very transactional. I'm putting something out and you take it in. You put something out, I take it in. They're like, no, there's a difference. There's a shared humanness.
SPEAKER_0:  that creates a meaning.
SPEAKER_0:  beyond the transaction. Kind of like you were just saying, the logical stuff isn't really that interesting because-
SPEAKER_0:  you know, the logic is there's an answer to whatever logic is. We can do math, right?
SPEAKER_0:  It's where does the surprises come in?
SPEAKER_0:  Right? In terms of
SPEAKER_0:  of wonderful behavior or destructive behavior, right? They're coming from people's emotions. So that's what we want to understand. And that occurs in the context of a person.
SPEAKER_0:  and other humans, even if it's the conception of someone and other humans as enemy, or it's the conception of two people.
SPEAKER_0:  sitting together the idea that there's a shared humanist and it's not all transactional and that he could take that out of
SPEAKER_0:  you know, the pinnacle of human tragedy.
SPEAKER_0:  and utilize it in a way that informs us.
SPEAKER_0:  being a better as a species going forward, I think is really monumental.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you think, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  is the role of emotion in the human mind.
SPEAKER_1:  in the human condition.
SPEAKER_1:  Because you've, we've talked.
SPEAKER_1:  several times.
SPEAKER_1:  different ways.
SPEAKER_1:  that emotion matters.
SPEAKER_1:  and it's a big part of who we are.
SPEAKER_1:  But...
SPEAKER_1:  Why is it there?
SPEAKER_1:  Why is it useful?
SPEAKER_1:  What's good about it?
SPEAKER_1:  I... I... I...
SPEAKER_1:  We've almost said it's almost like a negative thing.
SPEAKER_1:  that we just have to live with.
SPEAKER_1:  but why is it also maybe a beautiful
SPEAKER_0:  thing. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I think you said, what's the role of emotion? Emotion is the king.
SPEAKER_0:  if we want to use that analogy. It's the CEO if you want to use that analogy, right? Emotion rules.
SPEAKER_0:  Rules all.
SPEAKER_0:  We're taught that we're logical creatures, but we have innumerable pieces of data, even over the course of just a day, let alone a human experience to tell us that is not.
SPEAKER_0:  Is it ever logical to run into a burning building?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, logic's never gonna tell one to do that. Okay, so many love is in the building. Person's already sprinted halfway to the building.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  Emotion
SPEAKER_0:  rules us and so on.
SPEAKER_0:  to the thought.
SPEAKER_0:  A thought is...
SPEAKER_0:  Some of that is evolutionary.
SPEAKER_0:  Right?
SPEAKER_0:  strong negative emotion stays with us very, very profoundly. So example I'll give is if we're hunter-gatherers and like I find a new berry and it tastes good and it seems nutritious, and then and it is right everywhere, everything's fine. It'd be good to remember them.
SPEAKER_0:  But if I find a new berry and it tastes good and it seems nutritious and we both eat it and almost die of sickness?
SPEAKER_0:  We better remember.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? So, the primacy of emotion...
SPEAKER_0:  is in us for reasons that are about survival, that the emotion of it's my child in that building or my loved one is why I don't give a damn about logic and run into the building, right? The emotion of I thought that was good and I got really sick and I better never forget.
SPEAKER_0:  It is also about survival.
SPEAKER_0:  And the same applies to humans. If we're from different tribes back then and-
SPEAKER_0:  In my tribe, when you put your hand out, it's a greeting.
SPEAKER_0:  In your tribe, if someone puts their hand out, it means, hey, I'm going to attack you and take your stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  Right then.
SPEAKER_0:  I put my hand out and you slug me, right? Then I was like, I better remember.
SPEAKER_0:  that right but you see how that can lead into.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, are the constructs around that. I say, oh, people in your tribe are violent, right? Do we start then to make stories around that?
SPEAKER_0:  But the primacy of emotion, whether it's berries or it's humans who might threaten us or it's humans we love,
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's hard to even look at that anthropological, psychological literature and to look at what's out there.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think the face validity, that's part of survival.
SPEAKER_0:  It's part of survival. It's so cool.
SPEAKER_1:  that you get also things like love, which are not often rational or grounded in logic and so on. If you look from a transactional perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  a lot of times falling in love or...
SPEAKER_1:  whether it's with friends or...
SPEAKER_1:  friendship or romantic love.
SPEAKER_1:  It doesn't really make sense. I don't- I'm still don't-
SPEAKER_1:  I'm still not sure what the hell it is.
SPEAKER_1:  because like,
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, it's the thing that is one of the things.
SPEAKER_1:  or love for your kids when they're born.
SPEAKER_1:  Like that love, the parental love.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  What is that?
SPEAKER_1:  That's so cool that we get to have the, like, if you're looking for the, in the menu of items.
SPEAKER_1:  They give life meaning. That seems like a pretty.
SPEAKER_0:  Pretty good one.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so my-
SPEAKER_0:  Response.
SPEAKER_0:  you said that gives life meaning, my response initially was gonna be, it's the meaning of life.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Because saying, okay, emotion is about survival. That's one part, right? That's a very important part, right? If we don't survive.
SPEAKER_0:  then we're not there to have emotions, right? So yes, it's about survival.
SPEAKER_0:  As important as that is, that's the small part.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it is about
SPEAKER_0:  the meaning of life because it's about the beyond self.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think it relates back to what we were talking about at the very beginning and the sort of levels of
SPEAKER_0:  emergence, right? And when we feel love, we feel happiness because that person
SPEAKER_0:  feels happiness, right? There's something that's so generative, so creative about that. Like we wanna bring order to things and we, you know, happiness
SPEAKER_0:  is consistent with simplicity, right? If we're healthy, there's nothing negative to say about our health, right? If we have health problems, there's a lot to say, right?
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  It's emotion that pushes us towards the goodness that I think makes all.
SPEAKER_0:  the meaning for us. I mean, it's interesting. I actually was wondering what your thoughts about this as a scientist, right? Because we accept it by and large that we have free will, right? The only way of free will, but then we get upset that there's not justice.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? So, but how is it like if we have free will, I could act in an unjust way and then you're surprised or, you know, Viceroy's like, why, right? We have these thoughts because I think because we're
SPEAKER_0:  we're rooted, we want logic to rule. Like there's a way in which I can understand logic, I can manage it, I can manipulate it.
SPEAKER_0:  We sort of want it to be that way.
SPEAKER_0:  So then we glorify.
SPEAKER_0:  logic, and then we misapply it, like ideas like, oh, I know we have free will, but I'm now shaking my fist at the heavens because there's no justice, right?
SPEAKER_0:  And I think maybe what we're looking for is
SPEAKER_0:  we should go back and look at the givens. Like why is there, there's only goodness if there's justice? I mean that doesn't-
SPEAKER_0:  I think the goodness...
SPEAKER_0:  Why does the goodness have to be tied to that? Maybe it goes back to the counter entropy and the fact that when there is something, there is not nothing.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? And where there is something, there can be awareness, there can be...
SPEAKER_0:  goodness, there can be compassion, right? Is it that...
SPEAKER_0:  that what's really going on is not about justice. Yes, we have free will.
SPEAKER_0:  It's that.
SPEAKER_0:  Goodness creating.
SPEAKER_0:  shoring up, making better.
SPEAKER_0:  That is...
SPEAKER_0:  the meaning that is the good, right? And that the evil is the destruction as evidenced by the fact that it's overdetermined probably a million times that we're in this eddy current of counter entropy and we could destroy that quite readily.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? And then we're nothingness like.
SPEAKER_0:  like everything else that we know of that's not.
SPEAKER_0:  us that doesn't have the ability to do something that's creative.
SPEAKER_0:  or
SPEAKER_0:  constructive. I mean, I think...
SPEAKER_0:  that that's...
SPEAKER_0:  The answer, and I think that our science really tells us.
SPEAKER_0:  that that's the answer. And I think it beckons us with ideas like.
SPEAKER_0:  We know that things happen outside of space and time.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, they're physics experiments, right? We know this from the science of it.
SPEAKER_0:  yet we don't stop and look and say, wait, is that?
SPEAKER_0:  the magic and the idea Einstein said, God doesn't play dice with the universe. In whatever happens, you may start a laisser pace sustainable revolution.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, maybe.
SPEAKER_0:  God doesn't play dice with the universe. That quantum indeterminacy and all of that is not just a flip of the coin, so to speak.
SPEAKER_0:  But maybe it's in that.
SPEAKER_0:  indeterminacy that we're given the opportunity to.
SPEAKER_0:  assert ourselves, right, to make something one way.
SPEAKER_0:  or another. Maybe it's not God playing dice with the universe, but it's God loading the dice in our favor.
SPEAKER_0:  if we'll only listen to
SPEAKER_0:  The truth, the truth that being destructive...
SPEAKER_0:  doesn't help or soothe anything, even in the person who thinks it will for themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  creativity and generativeness and
SPEAKER_0:  kindness and compassion like this is
SPEAKER_0:  Doesn't that seem sort of analogous to the eddy current of counter entropy that has us here in the first place?
SPEAKER_0:  And I think that's where I pin meaning and that meaning then.
SPEAKER_0:  going back to the initial question, right, is generated in us through
SPEAKER_0:  Emotion through what we feel that leads us to feel something that is mysterious. I don't know why I feel it
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, in some sense, emotion is kind of the fuel of that creative imperative.
SPEAKER_1:  We have.
SPEAKER_1:  But if you step back...
SPEAKER_1:  and look at the tapestry a little bit.
SPEAKER_1:  It does seem that the creation and destruction are the yin and yang of life.
SPEAKER_1:  that it all works only if...
SPEAKER_1:  the main engine is towards creativity.
SPEAKER_1:  but destruction also...
SPEAKER_1:  makes way for new things.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's the.
SPEAKER_1:  this kind of struggle. It seems like life is-
SPEAKER_1:  between the different forces that make up the individual human, they make up society, all these tensions.
SPEAKER_1:  are necessary.
SPEAKER_1:  for growth, for development, this kind of...
SPEAKER_1:  inner conflict and outer conflict.
SPEAKER_1:  are necessary for growth.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not just the...
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, in some sense, it's from the logic aspect, you kind of want everything to be perfect and-
SPEAKER_1:  and just.
SPEAKER_1:  for nobody to suffer for everything to be perfect. But just like we talked about with trauma, it just seems like...
SPEAKER_1:  It's such a big giant mess.
SPEAKER_1:  What is it Bukowski said? Find what you love and let it kill you.
SPEAKER_1:  There's some aspect of...
SPEAKER_1:  the negative aspect of passion and pursuit and obsession.
SPEAKER_1:  The... the... the... the turmoil.
SPEAKER_1:  of the pursuit.
SPEAKER_1:  Avada...
SPEAKER_1:  happiness, of the creative pursuits and all of that. I mean that's part of life as well.
SPEAKER_1:  That's, and I don't know what to do with that.
SPEAKER_1:  from an individual perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of figuring out how do you live a good life, how do you live a healthy life?
SPEAKER_1:  C'est un sim.
SPEAKER_1:  That bit of hardship.
SPEAKER_1:  or sometimes a lot of hardship.
SPEAKER_1:  can make a pretty interesting life.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it brings us back to the discussion that we're having.
SPEAKER_0:  before about what does it mean, like the challenges of trauma, right, and of overcoming.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think here we gotta be careful with the language, right? Because
SPEAKER_0:  I would then say...
SPEAKER_0:  Let's take destruction, right?
SPEAKER_0:  separated into two things, right? One is
SPEAKER_0:  You say destruction is like the breaking down, the tearing down of something.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, versus...
SPEAKER_0:  a process that has malice in it. So just like when we were talking about-
SPEAKER_0:  a trauma and, and, um,
SPEAKER_0:  No, it's setbacks, things to overcome. We might say, okay, if you say, hey, you have it harder than the next person and you have more to overcome.
SPEAKER_0:  or someone put a barrier in front of you for you to overcome.
SPEAKER_0:  that there can be a lot of growth in that, including the times when you don't know, gosh, can I do this, right? Can I get over it?
SPEAKER_0:  Right? If you're saying like that's, that could be, that's challenge.
SPEAKER_0:  and something to overcome that's very positive. But we're saying, but there's no benefit of throwing a racial slur in there, right? We're saying, because that's all bad. Like that's not, even the princess, I'm angry about that and I'm gonna overcome that. It's like, that didn't need to be, that didn't make anything better.
SPEAKER_0:  If the person sees that and says, I'm going to, I'm going to overcome that. It makes things less worse.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? But there's no...
SPEAKER_0:  There's no good to something that's created as destructive. We may look at forest fires, like look, controlled burns. You say there's a forest burning down.
SPEAKER_0:  But that's, okay, there's some, there's some we could say destruction there. There's a tearing down there.
SPEAKER_0:  but it's in the service of the next fire not running through the community, the town that's on the other side of it. That's very different than a forest fire, as they started by arson.
SPEAKER_0:  So you might say they're both a tearing down, they're a tearing down of the forest.
SPEAKER_0:  But one is in the service of goodness, even though...
SPEAKER_0:  It's hurting the animals and the plants is not all good, right? But it's in the service of something as opposed to something else that's wantonly destructive. I think there's no good.
SPEAKER_0:  To the racial slur, there's no good to the arson.
SPEAKER_0:  That's destruction in a way that's incorporating, I think, the malice of envy, something that's really—
SPEAKER_0:  purely if there's a yin and yang.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the destruct, that's the destruct, that's the badness end.
SPEAKER_1:  So racial slurs.
SPEAKER_1:  is a surface wave.
SPEAKER_1:  of a deeper thing.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, the reason I bring that up is like, all right, well, you have these discussions of censorship. What good does allowing racial slurs?
SPEAKER_1:  in public communication.
SPEAKER_1:  do, right?
SPEAKER_1:  And it's like.
SPEAKER_1:  our communication would surely be better if we don't say bad things to each other.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like...
SPEAKER_1:  It seems like the truth is...
SPEAKER_1:  Our communication will be better if the amount of bad things is a small fraction of communication. It seems to be more true.
SPEAKER_1:  Because another aspect of human nature with power, the moment you start censoring and removing bad words that everyone agrees are bad words.
SPEAKER_1:  Then the people at the top, they're doing the censoring, start getting greedy.
SPEAKER_1:  It starts, it starts expanding and this is the giant mess of human civilization where we can't.
SPEAKER_1:  The nice piles you created are kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  overlapping
SPEAKER_0:  That's the gray area. That's the problem with it. No, I agree completely. There's a control of language. There are slippery slopes there. I think there's a very big problem.
SPEAKER_0:  So I agree.
SPEAKER_0:  I think.
SPEAKER_0:  again, split parsing out the language, I'm not saying, hey, we shouldn't have racial slurs as if like, let's stop saying the words. I mean, the idea is.
SPEAKER_0:  the premise behind it, right? Like, you know, the prejudices, we could eliminate the prejudice behind it.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I was struck-
SPEAKER_0:  I do almost nothing about medicine. I get to medical school and start with anatomy.
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's remarkable as
SPEAKER_0:  You know, to see...
SPEAKER_0:  where as the bodies are being dissected, that like we're all humans. here it is!
SPEAKER_0:  It doesn't matter any of these things on the outside. And that's true.
SPEAKER_0:  not just like in our bodies, but in our minds, and the part of the person that's not there, right? Because now we're trying to learn from the body.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it shows how.
SPEAKER_0:  Ridiculous it is if you think that we're 99.9% all alike genetically. By the way, it's only like take another 10th off and we're all orangutans. Somehow!
SPEAKER_0:  We have to see these differences between us, right? And where does that come from? And I think...
SPEAKER_0:  that I believe that all comes from envy in that classical sense that if I don't feel good enough
SPEAKER_0:  I'm gonna want someone to feel better.
SPEAKER_0:  about and so there can be visual things.
SPEAKER_0:  that that person looks different, right?
SPEAKER_0:  Or you think about the...
SPEAKER_0:  I spent some time in Great Britain and when there's a lot of conflict between Northern Ireland and Ireland right and you thought wow there's not
SPEAKER_0:  There's not even a look difference, right? It's the same general religious umbrella, same ethnicity, right? But now there's some religious difference. And I thought...
SPEAKER_0:  It's not me trying to be denigrating.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, around the Irish complex, like that's human of, oh, there's no actual difference between us. If I don't feel good about myself.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm gonna find one.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? It's that.
SPEAKER_0:  that I believe could go away. It's driven by maybe the trauma of just being alive in the world and things can happen to us, but we certainly promote in the human created trauma.
SPEAKER_0:  people feeling not good enough, finding differences, there's a place for the envy to attach.
SPEAKER_0:  and we're off to the races of.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, wars. We're talking about the Second World War and we think, well, what have we learned?
SPEAKER_0:  It would take us a day to map out all the wars since then, right? Not alone, for goodness sake, because everything that's sailing right now.
SPEAKER_0:  So we're not pretty, we're not good at learning.
SPEAKER_0:  from
SPEAKER_0:  what seemed to be some very salient lessons.
SPEAKER_1:  I should mention one thing is that I also know that you're interested in Russian culture a little bit.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Churchill said, I cannot forecast to you the action of Russia.
SPEAKER_1:  It is a riddle wrapped in a mystery inside an enigma.
SPEAKER_1:  What to you are some interesting differences between
SPEAKER_1:  So this.
SPEAKER_1:  Eastern part of the world of
SPEAKER_1:  Russia, Ukraine, the Slavic countries, the former Soviet Union.
SPEAKER_1:  All of that versus sort of the US culture.
SPEAKER_1:  what stands out to you from the literature, from the music.
SPEAKER_1:  from the science.
SPEAKER_0:  All that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  I think there's so much.
SPEAKER_0:  Intensity.
SPEAKER_0:  the intensity.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  And I guess I would say fearlessness of.
SPEAKER_0:  Expression.
SPEAKER_0:  that I see.
SPEAKER_0:  in
SPEAKER_0:  a Slavic culture, maybe it's across cultures, because there's a different way that expression occurs. We say like, oh, it's different in the French than the Spanish, or it's different than in parts of Africa. And I think when you take that part of the world for whatever reason, and maybe it's just totally random, or maybe it's
SPEAKER_0:  It's aspects of geography and experience and migration, but there's such an intensity. And I remember listening to Tchaikovsky.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, very early on, maybe not for the very first time, but early on in my life, reading Dostoevsky and feeling like...
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, Dostoevsky's willingness, his ability and his willingness.
SPEAKER_0:  to express.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Create!
SPEAKER_0:  such powerful aberrant states of human experience. Tchaikovsky in his music, the depths of
SPEAKER_0:  suffering that it
SPEAKER_0:  expresses has always stood out to me.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  as a way that like with the, if that's like the brightest light, so to speak, communicating information that that's a place.
SPEAKER_0:  look and it's also a place that resonated with me so strongly because I think for some people who are
SPEAKER_0:  informative years and having very difficult
SPEAKER_0:  of like a depth of feeling of like fear and.
SPEAKER_0:  How's the world going to be? Am I going to be annihilated? What do I even want? What do I feel inside of me?
SPEAKER_0:  to encounter that being expressed so intensely.
SPEAKER_0:  I found to be very, very
SPEAKER_0:  Moving.
SPEAKER_0:  So I don't know if that's a good answer or not, but I think there's an intensity of expression and a fearlessness You know Dostoevsky wrote about
SPEAKER_0:  terrible things, you know, what happens in the person. Is there a person who is
SPEAKER_0:  brilliant intellectually and very persuasive.
SPEAKER_0:  and very capable of being effective.
SPEAKER_0:  who also just chooses to be a child rapist.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, he wrote about that. He wrote about the truth of this is what we can be.
SPEAKER_0:  as humans and I think there's so many lessons, including the truth. People will tend to think, oh, evil's not very bright or not very intelligent.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a way to let evil propagate, right? Evil can be effective and attractive and-
SPEAKER_0:  um... very compelling but evil nonetheless and i i just think is it
SPEAKER_0:  fearless willingness.
SPEAKER_0:  to look at that and to describe it, that I see primarily I've studied in.
SPEAKER_0:  Russian culture.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, the fearless exploration of this whole...
SPEAKER_1:  A human drama.
SPEAKER_1:  Definitely just the Yefsky and others since in the 20th century and the 19th century have done.
SPEAKER_1:  Incredible job with that some of that just like you said is the language the culture
SPEAKER_1:  I think that intense romanticism is there.
SPEAKER_1:  that is almost an overdramatic
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  exploration.
SPEAKER_1:  of human nature.
SPEAKER_1:  it can err on the side or falter when it goes into.
SPEAKER_1:  kind of cynical view of life.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, life is suffering.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that also has to do with the way you deal with the trauma of the World Wars.
SPEAKER_1:  and so on. This is something the different nations throughout Europe had to deal with that in different ways.
SPEAKER_1:  Some of them have channeled into envy and resentment, some of them...
SPEAKER_1:  channeled into a kind of...
SPEAKER_1:  Nihilism or cynicism?
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Ultimately, the intensity of feeling is there, which is sort of interesting.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  to see and interesting how that manifests itself in the kind of
SPEAKER_1:  I'll-
SPEAKER_1:  in the kind of governments it builds up.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, there's more.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  authoritarianism in that part of the world.
SPEAKER_1:  versus the Western world that's more
SPEAKER_1:  Focus on the individual versus the collective.
SPEAKER_1:  And when more focused on the individual, you have a propensity to value individual rights with democracy and so on.
SPEAKER_1:  It's interesting to watch.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, to reconstruct how that all came to be.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Is it in the blood? Is it in the mind?
SPEAKER_1:  Is it in some kind of thing that more ethereal, a collective set of ideas that we pass from generation to generation between each other, sort of the collective of it?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's fascinating to see.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, but now...
SPEAKER_1:  reinvigorated because there's conflict in that part of the world.
SPEAKER_1:  Evosel
SPEAKER_1:  uh... thought about the cold war
SPEAKER_0:  What lessons about...
SPEAKER_0:  the
SPEAKER_1:  human mind about psychiatry, psychology.
SPEAKER_1:  and about looking at the Cold War.
SPEAKER_1:  can we take forward in the 21st century?
SPEAKER_1:  so that we can.
SPEAKER_1:  Avoid.
SPEAKER_0:  World War III.
SPEAKER_1:  a major.
SPEAKER_0:  Colder.
SPEAKER_0:  Hot War.
SPEAKER_0:  in the 21st century.
SPEAKER_0:  I think unspoken animosities are very...
SPEAKER_0:  very, very dangerous.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, right, it was a.
SPEAKER_0:  Cold War, there was...
SPEAKER_0:  There was...
SPEAKER_0:  fighting through proxies, right? the superpowers were fighting.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... surrogate wars to proxies which of course
SPEAKER_0:  in and of itself causes immense suffering.
SPEAKER_0:  but it becomes the opposite of an exchange of.
SPEAKER_0:  ideas or an exchange of.
SPEAKER_0:  thought, you know, maybe even the Chris Jeff, right?
SPEAKER_0:  not believing that the kitchen...
SPEAKER_0:  look like it did at the World's Fair, right? And some of the misconceptions here of what things were like in Russia, right? It was an utter...
SPEAKER_0:  It was a thought that those other people are not actually people, right? There's an enemy society of evil.
SPEAKER_0:  which then paints with a broad brush.
SPEAKER_0:  in a way that makes it easy, too easy for the cold war, or to go from being cold.
SPEAKER_0:  right to have it boiling over into utter.
SPEAKER_0:  destruction. You know, I wrote, it was-
SPEAKER_0:  It's really a true story that when I...
SPEAKER_0:  was in, it was still the Soviet Union, but it was right around the time of the Soviet Union coming to an end.
SPEAKER_0:  and had gone on a trip for students from England, and we got to go places that people hadn't gone.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, if foreigners had gone in many, many years, it was just kind of the right timing to experience that.
SPEAKER_0:  And it really is true that someone said on short notice to these
SPEAKER_0:  kids that...
SPEAKER_0:  that like these group of Americans were coming and I have a picture somewhere of the kid in a gas mask.
SPEAKER_0:  Like they went into their desks and put on gas masks and they thought...
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_0:  That's what, I mean that's what.
SPEAKER_0:  They're taught to think about us and we're taught to think about them.
SPEAKER_0:  Now we're back in an us them, right? When we're all trying to survive and we're all such-
SPEAKER_0:  Human life is so...
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  delicate, right? Let alone human happiness. We make these divisions and we create this aggression and latent aggression. During the Cold War, we developed the ability to destroy the earth, right? Then just sat looking at one another with further growing misunderstanding and the opportunity for the proxy fights.
SPEAKER_0:  Cuban Missile Crisis, which I know wasn't a war, but it's an aspect of that, right? We just...
SPEAKER_0:  We have ourselves wildly.
SPEAKER_0:  at risk of destruction.
SPEAKER_0:  without any mutual understanding. And again, I would argue that that is the opposite of.
SPEAKER_0:  the counter entropy, right? Like we are setting everything up for less, lack of communication, lack of understanding. How do those feelings of love and
SPEAKER_0:  and shared humaneness happen.
SPEAKER_0:  They don't, right? If you separate.
SPEAKER_0:  and then we push ourselves more and more and more.
SPEAKER_0:  towards reinstating the state of entropy that's present in the rest of the universe.
SPEAKER_0:  What advice would you give to you?
SPEAKER_1:  young people.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  that are fighting entropy with all their might.
SPEAKER_1:  So, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  young people and people that are wondering how to find their way in life.
SPEAKER_1:  What advice would you give?
SPEAKER_1:  how to have a career, how to have a life.
SPEAKER_0:  they can be proud of.
SPEAKER_0:  I think...
SPEAKER_0:  Starting off
SPEAKER_0:  with the first principles.
SPEAKER_0:  What are my values?
SPEAKER_0:  How do I want to live life because
SPEAKER_0:  I'm in my early 50s and when I was a kid, we waited for the newspaper came in the afternoon and then we'd see something, okay, what's going on in the world? We'd learn something. We're the West Coast baseball scorers, right?
SPEAKER_0:  and learn about, oh, here's what happened in different parts of the world.
SPEAKER_0:  And by and large, I and everyone else there, adult or child, we're like living in
SPEAKER_0:  a reality that was largely, our conception was largely what was around us.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Now, in many ways, it is.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm not saying it's entirely negative, of course, that we have more information, we can sort of think globally, so to speak, right?
SPEAKER_0:  The other side of that is so much of the world's problems are on us all the time.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Like here's this awful thing that happened. How many awful things happen each day and they're right in front of us and there's such an immediacy to it all?
SPEAKER_0:  that I think it can be like.
SPEAKER_0:  paralyze us with terror, right? And for someone who's young and trying to make their way, it's like, how do you figure your way out in this world that your word isn't even gonna exist, right? And then you see how profligate.
SPEAKER_0:  the generations before you.
SPEAKER_0:  are in so many ways.
SPEAKER_0:  and there can become, I think, a push towards extremes, either nihilism,
SPEAKER_0:  or I'm gonna change everything.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? And it's like, how about, let's start from, how do I want to behave in my own?
SPEAKER_0:  community, right? Which starts with, how do I want to behave in my household?
SPEAKER_0:  What kind of neighbor do I want to be? I mean, it might seem like things like that are.
SPEAKER_0:  still you're small in comparison to the big things, but I don't think they are. I think that's how not small.
SPEAKER_0:  That's how we start building foundations that let us tackle.
SPEAKER_0:  the big things. I do find myself saying when I'm working with, sometimes doing therapy with,
SPEAKER_0:  younger people of helping them.
SPEAKER_0:  to bring back their...
SPEAKER_0:  thoughts, their strivings, their decisions.
SPEAKER_0:  more to themselves and living.
SPEAKER_0:  with and around themselves more instead of in something that becomes very
SPEAKER_0:  theoretical and therefore very
SPEAKER_0:  threatening and unnerving.
SPEAKER_1:  So focusing on the people around them, taking one small step at a time.
SPEAKER_1:  to form deeper connections.
SPEAKER_1:  to build something.
SPEAKER_0:  locally.
SPEAKER_0:  How do I want to be today if I go into the grocery store and
SPEAKER_0:  person in front of me drops something, you know, I can, I can scowl because I'm in a rush, right, and I could be like that, right?
SPEAKER_0:  I can be like that. I've done that way many, many times in my life, right?
SPEAKER_0:  It's never done anyone a damn bit of good, including me. Or I can realize, like, the 10 seconds aren't gonna matter. Can I help pick that thing up? Or just smile? These are the seemingly small things that I think make the tenor of our lives.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I moved, I think I mentioned to you offline, uh, one of the-
SPEAKER_1:  really the main reason I moved to.
SPEAKER_1:  Austin, Texas.
SPEAKER_1:  I just remember deciding it when I went to Walmart.
SPEAKER_1:  And a lady said...
SPEAKER_1:  Bye.
SPEAKER_1:  You look handsome in that tie.
SPEAKER_1:  or in that suit and tie or whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I don't think anyone's ever said older lady. She was very sweet. There's kindness in her eyes. She said that I don't think anyone ever said anything like that.
SPEAKER_1:  to me in my entire life.
SPEAKER_1:  And it was just.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, it was like, wow, there's kindness in this world. I know it sounds ridiculous, but like-
SPEAKER_1:  does not sound ridiculous. It's like those you could be that for somebody.
SPEAKER_1:  Go walk around in Walmart.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, think that you remember that, and it's pivotal, you're citing it as, hey, that was a big part of me moving here. So think about the branch point in your life.
SPEAKER_0:  that comes from the simple kindness.
SPEAKER_0:  right, of a person who had goodness to give.
SPEAKER_0:  right and wasn't scared.
SPEAKER_0:  that you're going to be upset by it or whatever, right? Take the risk. Right, right. You probably didn't have the...
SPEAKER_0:  the thought that you could be a sailing, right? Probably she looks at you, she's got goodness to give, it's simple to give it, it's that.
SPEAKER_0:  Simple and it's beautiful and it's worth more to you than like how many studies would be on, where's it right to live or this and that. None of that matters, what mattered was just that freedom to be kind and.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's emotion, that's not logic at all. That's purely just human emotion and a little bit of humanness, that little bit of connection.
SPEAKER_1:  And then, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  That's what makes life great.
SPEAKER_0:  that you moved here that way instead of one could say, well,
SPEAKER_0:  I can't believe you did that instead of looking at all the data and hiring consultants of what's the best place to live. But that would be wrong, right? You made a good decision.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, like that was good data, it was impactful data, even in your thoughts about how you're happy living here.
SPEAKER_0:  Right, it's not that, oh, you discount, you shortchange yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  by not relying on all the logic, right? You felt something about the place and you felt it as symbolized in a person and that made the choice for you.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a balance of course.
SPEAKER_1:  but you also have to know yourself a little bit sometimes.
SPEAKER_1:  You can find stability and comfort in kind of.
SPEAKER_1:  reasoning things out a little bit.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe as people close to me have...
SPEAKER_1:  Sometimes criticized in that I'm a little bit
SPEAKER_1:  too romantic.
SPEAKER_1:  where I'll just follow the feeling.
SPEAKER_1:  and you know life.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, there's physics.
SPEAKER_1:  There's a reality to this world.
SPEAKER_1:  And sometimes...
SPEAKER_1:  reality.
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't allow you to flourish.
SPEAKER_1:  if you just follow your feelings, but there's a dance there.
SPEAKER_1:  And happiness is ultimately found in that landscape of.
SPEAKER_1:  feeling and emotion versus.
SPEAKER_1:  facts.
SPEAKER_1:  and reason.
SPEAKER_0:  logic.
SPEAKER_0:  As you said, have their place, right? Everything, yeah. They have their place. They do, they do. They're not to be all in end of.
SPEAKER_1:  You're an incredible person.
SPEAKER_1:  Andrew Huberman is a friend of yours. He said you absolutely must talk.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  called Dicerathe.
SPEAKER_1:  The number of people you know, they're just incredible people. There's just this.
SPEAKER_1:  group of folks.
SPEAKER_1:  that somehow helped each other flourish and grew together.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm just, I'm so happy you exist. I'm so happy you're doing the work you're doing. I can't wait for your second book.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_1:  and thanks for talking to-
SPEAKER_0:  This is really cool.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you so much. Proud to be.
SPEAKER_0:  among the group of people that you...
SPEAKER_0:  excited, proud to be their friend and proud that you've had me on today. Thank you so much.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with Paul Conte.
SPEAKER_1:  To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now, let me leave you with some words from Viktor Frankl.
SPEAKER_1:  Everything can be taken from a man.
SPEAKER_1:  the last of the human freedoms.
SPEAKER_1:  choose one's attitude in any given set of circumstances.
SPEAKER_1:  Thank you for listening.
SPEAKER_1:  and hope to see you.
SPEAKER_1:  next time.