SPEAKER_1:  if Scientology was just.
SPEAKER_1:  Getting auditing.
SPEAKER_1:  when you want it.
SPEAKER_1:  about the subjects you wanted.
SPEAKER_1:  and you could take it or leave it.
SPEAKER_1:  That would be fine.
SPEAKER_1:  It's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's the fact that it's part and parcel to this entire organization and this entire experience.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  has.
SPEAKER_1:  as a part of that experience, taking everything from you, demanding everything from you, controlling who you can speak with.
SPEAKER_1:  controlling who you can have relationships with, who you have to erase from your life.
SPEAKER_1:  This is where, and it's hard to, it's hard to-
SPEAKER_1:  place one.
SPEAKER_1:  pinpoint on this is where Scientology goes wrong. It's really hard to do that.
SPEAKER_1:  because the good parts of Scientology and the bad parts of Scientology
SPEAKER_1:  are all just Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  Following is a conversation with Aaron Smith, 11.
SPEAKER_0:  a former Scientologist raised in Scientology and have worked in organization full time.
SPEAKER_0:  for many years.
SPEAKER_0:  as a staff member.
SPEAKER_0:  and a C-ORG member, including the job of training Scientology auditors.
SPEAKER_0:  Today he educates the public about Scientology on his YouTube channel.
SPEAKER_0:  growing up in Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  This is the Lex Freedman Podcast.
SPEAKER_0:  to support it.
SPEAKER_0:  please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_0:  And now...
SPEAKER_0:  Dear friends,
SPEAKER_0:  Here's Aaron Smith Levin.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's do a full overview of Scientology, its ideas, how it operates, how it wields its power and influence.
SPEAKER_0:  And let's start at the very basics. What is Scientology?
SPEAKER_1:  Scientology is a belief system.
SPEAKER_1:  Created by L. Ron Hubbard.
SPEAKER_1:  that does.
SPEAKER_1:  Fundamentally.
SPEAKER_1:  believe that we are all immortal spiritual beings.
SPEAKER_1:  called Thetans.
SPEAKER_1:  that we have.
SPEAKER_1:  Native godlike.
SPEAKER_1:  potential.
SPEAKER_1:  that there is nothing more powerful in the universe than a theta.
SPEAKER_1:  So Godlike is quite literal here.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  that through various
SPEAKER_1:  decisions that they have made. They have fallen away from their native godlike power.
SPEAKER_1:  too.
SPEAKER_1:  falling down to a state.
SPEAKER_1:  where most they ends on even where that they are they can sign even where that they ever.
SPEAKER_1:  have lived before.
SPEAKER_1:  or have these powers.
SPEAKER_1:  and that things are now in a state where they're trapped in bodies.
SPEAKER_1:  trapped here on Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  trapped in this prison of a physical universe, trapped on this prison of a planet.
SPEAKER_1:  and that only Scientology can restore a thing to its.
SPEAKER_1:  Native State.
SPEAKER_0:  Are these multiple beings? Like is there one Thetan?
SPEAKER_0:  inside of me that's trapped in this prison.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, the thing would be you.
SPEAKER_1:  The thing would be me. The Thetan is you.
SPEAKER_0:  presumably limited in some fundamental way. So this statement that is me is limited. So there's like.
SPEAKER_0:  8 billion.
SPEAKER_0:  Satan's on the planet.
SPEAKER_1:  There's one primary thing in animating each body.
SPEAKER_1:  Later in Scientology, you learn there's actually like tens of thousands or hundreds of thousands of like
SPEAKER_1:  Sick.
SPEAKER_1:  unconscious, half dead.
SPEAKER_1:  they've been stuck to you that are now an additional cause of problems for you.
SPEAKER_1:  But fundamentally at the lower levels
SPEAKER_1:  the non-confidential levels. There's just one Thetan per body.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's an interesting idea. I just would like to kind of explore.
SPEAKER_0:  the philosophy of that. So there's a being that's all powerful, that's immortal.
SPEAKER_0:  and it's.
SPEAKER_0:  projectionist manifestation on this earth is
SPEAKER_0:  Fundamentally Limited.
SPEAKER_0:  and you're trying to.
SPEAKER_0:  the process of Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  is the process of letting go of those limitations.
SPEAKER_0:  you know that's an interesting idea i mean a lot of religions have this kind of idea that there's a
SPEAKER_0:  not just religion, but like we have the capacity.
SPEAKER_0:  as human beings to do.
SPEAKER_0:  to achieve greatness in all kinds of ways.
SPEAKER_0:  And that's the question we have with our cognitive abilities. We start with an embryo and build up into this organism.
SPEAKER_0:  and like this world of opportunities before us, what are we capable of?
SPEAKER_0:  And the idea that we're capable of almost anything is a really powerful one. And there's a lot of
SPEAKER_0:  religions there's a lot of philosophies there's a lot of
SPEAKER_0:  Advice.
SPEAKER_0:  of hope.
SPEAKER_0:  that kind of explore those ideas. And so.
SPEAKER_0:  It seems like with Scientology, the application of this religious philosophy means...
SPEAKER_0:  that there's, we're limited.
SPEAKER_0:  and we have to break through those limitations. And there's a process to break through those limitations.
SPEAKER_1:  That would be correct.
SPEAKER_1:  So what can make it challenging to.
SPEAKER_1:  adequately and completely.
SPEAKER_1:  described Scientology in the beginning is what Scientologists believe actually changes.
SPEAKER_1:  as they progress.
SPEAKER_1:  further into or further up.
SPEAKER_1:  in Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  The explanation is I've given is pretty consistent with what you would get at the lowest levels.
SPEAKER_1:  Right. You're a Thetan. I'm a Thetan.
SPEAKER_1:  Everyone's a Thetan.
SPEAKER_1:  and we have...
SPEAKER_1:  A reactive mind.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll run Hubbard Wood.
SPEAKER_1:  say the reactive mind is a collection.
SPEAKER_1:  of these recordings.
SPEAKER_1:  mental recordings of any moments of pain and unconsciousness.
SPEAKER_1:  you've ever had in your life. It's like the subconscious.
SPEAKER_1:  Mind.
SPEAKER_1:  It's always recording in moments of pain and unconsciousness.
SPEAKER_1:  and that these recordings are called, I'll run Hubbard called them NGRIP.
SPEAKER_1:  Now when L. Ron Hubbard first wrote Dianetics in 1950, this was before Scientology came along a couple years later, right? So in 1950 when he wrote Dianetics.
SPEAKER_1:  It wasn't a spiritual.
SPEAKER_1:  Endeavor it was supposed to be a mental
SPEAKER_1:  a science of mental health.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  As of that time, the earliest engram you could have was the incident of birth.
SPEAKER_1:  being born.
SPEAKER_1:  was an engram.
SPEAKER_1:  And technically in Dianetics, they said you could have prenatal engrams, like when you're still in the womb.
SPEAKER_1:  but there was no concept of past lives.
SPEAKER_1:  as of 1950 version of Dianetics, right?
SPEAKER_1:  And so the idea there was.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... the reactive mind is essentially a stimulus response mechanism
SPEAKER_1:  created through evolution millions of years ago to protect the individual from
SPEAKER_1:  things that would harm them, in other words, things that would bring about pain.
SPEAKER_1:  and unconsciousness.
SPEAKER_1:  So you have these recordings of things that hurt you.
SPEAKER_1:  create a pain in unconsciousness, and in present time these things will react upon you.
SPEAKER_1:  in a way.
SPEAKER_1:  to cause you to.
SPEAKER_1:  Avoid similar things.
SPEAKER_1:  reacting upon you in a subconscious, unconscious.
SPEAKER_0:  So the ReactiMind protects you.
SPEAKER_0:  from the trauma that is inside your subconscious mind.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  And the idea is...
SPEAKER_1:  We've now as human beings evolved to a state where it no longer serves us.
SPEAKER_1:  Beneficially, it only serves us negatively.
SPEAKER_1:  This was Hubbard's Dairy.
SPEAKER_1:  And he said, so you can get rid of these engrams by, you know, basically recalling them and going over them again and again, using Dianetics auditing therapy. And if you get back to the moment of birth and erase the earliest engram, all the other subsequent engrams on the chain.
SPEAKER_1:  would vanish.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh nice, so there's a ch-
SPEAKER_1:  Early, similar, early, similar, early, similar, early, similar.
SPEAKER_1:  So that gives you a pretty good understanding of how Elrond Hubbard thought of...
SPEAKER_1:  the mind.
SPEAKER_1:  because that carries on.
SPEAKER_1:  has applicability later on in Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean that's a pretty-
SPEAKER_0:  powerful model of the mind. I mean Freud had...
SPEAKER_0:  similar conceptions that a lot of our traumas.
SPEAKER_0:  are grounded in
SPEAKER_0:  sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  Uhhh...
SPEAKER_0:  Poor formulation of sexuality or imperfect formulation of sexuality in our childhood.
SPEAKER_0:  something like this.
SPEAKER_0:  And then we're trying to figure out the puzzle of whatever we formed in early childhood and similar, similar.
SPEAKER_1:  It is similar.
SPEAKER_1:  That's probably what Hubbard took it from.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  in the early days of Dianetics before he decided psychiatry was evil.
SPEAKER_1:  He actually credited Sigmund Freud.
SPEAKER_1:  with.
SPEAKER_1:  some of the shoulders he was standing on.
SPEAKER_1:  in writing Dianetics.
SPEAKER_0:  So the.
SPEAKER_0:  So he still admired psychiatry at that time. So that's an interesting moment of Dynetics. So what else? You mentioned Dynetics. Auditing was there too.
SPEAKER_0:  So if we just before Scientology, what are the ideas that formed?
SPEAKER_0:  what we know as Dynetics.
SPEAKER_1:  As I've just described, that is the fundamental. That is pretty much the nuts and bolts of Dianetics.
SPEAKER_0:  Ride.
SPEAKER_1:  Was it applied often?
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah, no, that's what dietetics in the early days was all about, was just auditing. Auditing is the process of the one-on-one counseling. Recall a moment of pain and unconsciousness, run through the anagram over and over and over again.
SPEAKER_1:  find something earlier, Simo, that is Dianetics auditing.
SPEAKER_1:  One of the main things that changed with Scientology is that birth
SPEAKER_1:  or prenatal angriams were no longer.
SPEAKER_1:  the earliest angrams on the chain.
SPEAKER_1:  The idea is you have to get the earliest ingram on the chain for the later ones to blow, which is a race.
SPEAKER_1:  And so, but all of a sudden now...
SPEAKER_1:  with.
SPEAKER_1:  The, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  addition of an immortal spiritual being into the equation.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, now the earliest incident could be trillions of years ago in other galaxies and universes.
SPEAKER_1:  other universes.
SPEAKER_0:  before the end of this universe. Yes!
SPEAKER_0:  Is there a model of physics integrated in any of this?
SPEAKER_1:  No.
SPEAKER_1:  The model is you have the physical universe.
SPEAKER_1:  And then above that you have the theta universe.
SPEAKER_1:  So we used the word thing earlier.
SPEAKER_1:  So in Scientology, we'll use the word theta.
SPEAKER_1:  Theta is just basically Thetan power. Thetans collectively.
SPEAKER_1:  Sorry.
SPEAKER_1:  Hubbard would say you have the theta universe.
SPEAKER_1:  which is senior.
SPEAKER_1:  to the physical universe and creates the physical universe.
SPEAKER_1:  And remember, I said, I said native godlike potentials.
SPEAKER_1:  So we're not talking about the God who created the earth.
SPEAKER_1:  We're just like, scientists don't believe in a God, but we'll get into that later.
SPEAKER_1:  We're talking about just creating universes. Like just think like Matrix. Like just when I say creating a universe, essentially just creating different things simulations.
SPEAKER_0:  But it sounds like a little bit more like the ideas of Play-Doh, which is there's these
SPEAKER_0:  platonic forms, there's abstract forms that are...
SPEAKER_0:  bigger more general than our
SPEAKER_0:  particular.
SPEAKER_0:  Reality here
SPEAKER_0:  and those forms are used to construct the reality.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I grew up in a cult, so I'm not familiar with the works of Play-Doh.
SPEAKER_0:  Hahaha.
SPEAKER_0:  You can't use that as an excuse for everything.
SPEAKER_0:  I would like to, you know, non jokingly, steal man the case because a lot of philosophies.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of religions.
SPEAKER_0:  a lot of even scientific endeavors.
SPEAKER_0:  are a little bit full of.
SPEAKER_0:  uncertainty.
SPEAKER_0:  You can call it bullshit.
SPEAKER_0:  but you're on sturdy ground because we're surrounded by mystery. And you have to take these ideas.
SPEAKER_0:  somewhat seriously.
SPEAKER_0:  and see where those ideas go wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  This happens with communism, this happens with capitalism. These ideas sound beautiful in their ideal forms, and then they somehow go wrong, and some go more wrong than others.
SPEAKER_0:  And so I don't think.
SPEAKER_0:  sort of, it's easy to...
SPEAKER_0:  sort of caricature and make fun of the ideas, I think if we take them seriously, you'll start to understand like-
SPEAKER_0:  When you're in it, it was serious. It can be very convincing.
SPEAKER_0:  The devil is going to be a charismatic person, he's not going to be a caricature of ridiculous.
SPEAKER_0:  So that helps us understand which ideas.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... will sound appealing but will be
SPEAKER_1:  come dangerous.
SPEAKER_1:  thrusts.
SPEAKER_1:  I have on my channel is wanting to talk about Scientology in a way that would actually resonate with.
SPEAKER_1:  current Scientologists, not just resonate with former Scientologists.
SPEAKER_1:  I want people who are still in to be able to hear how I talk about it and go.
SPEAKER_1:  Wow, he's being really fit.
SPEAKER_1:  and really accurate.
SPEAKER_1:  He's not just a hater, you know what I mean?
SPEAKER_0:  If you look at the, let's take one of the worst places on earth is North Korea.
SPEAKER_0:  You have Kim Jong Un.
SPEAKER_0:  And the reality is there's a lot of
SPEAKER_0:  citizens of that nation that deeply love
SPEAKER_0:  the leader.
SPEAKER_0:  because they grew up in that way. I mean, through fear, through all kinds of manipulation, through propaganda and so on, they're not allowed to love.
SPEAKER_0:  Members of their own family, they're not allowed to have romantic love, they're only allowed to have love for the leader.
SPEAKER_0:  And to reach those people you have to empathize with the fact that
SPEAKER_0:  in their eyes.
SPEAKER_0:  in some sense, this is a great man, this is a god.
SPEAKER_0:  messianic figure.
SPEAKER_0:  You can't just make fun of...
SPEAKER_0:  the ridiculousness of the situation that this pudgy person.
SPEAKER_0:  Waltzing around creating propaganda.
SPEAKER_1:  with a funny haircut.
SPEAKER_0:  haircut like it's so easy.
SPEAKER_0:  Hitler too to make fun of to make a caricature of the person, but this is a real person
SPEAKER_0:  A real person that
SPEAKER_0:  influenced the minds of millions of people. In the case of Hitler.
SPEAKER_0:  of tens of millions of people.
SPEAKER_0:  and created a huge amount of suffering.
SPEAKER_0:  Not because of-
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  the caricature version, but because he was a charismatic leader, he was somebody that people deeply, deeply loved. And that just over time, I mean, with the
SPEAKER_0:  the abuse of any kind of
SPEAKER_0:  ideology this happens over and over. So it's interesting because.
SPEAKER_0:  Scientology is so close to the...
SPEAKER_0:  to the core of what is America because so many Americans are involved with it. So it's interesting to study.
SPEAKER_0:  The.
SPEAKER_0:  the beauty and the power of the ideas that underlie it and where things go wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll just say it's interesting to note you would never get a representative of the Church of Scientology to sit down and have a conversation with you.
SPEAKER_1:  and even be as fair and accurate about Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  as I'm going to be.
SPEAKER_1:  which is noteworthy.
SPEAKER_0:  I honestly deeply believe that's the case. There's not going to be a high level official.
SPEAKER_0:  that would sit down.
SPEAKER_0:  for conversation.
SPEAKER_0:  I disagree with you.
SPEAKER_0:  I hope you're right.
SPEAKER_0:  because I think that given the current dynamics of what's happening
SPEAKER_0:  I think in order to save from their perspective, in order to save the
SPEAKER_0:  the Church of Scientology, they have to.
SPEAKER_0:  be transparent and authentic.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, steel man their case, but better.
SPEAKER_0:  You would think so.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, we'll talk about the other ways you could do that was just the manipulation through propaganda, through control media and all that kind of stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  They paint themselves into a corner.
SPEAKER_1:  of not being able to send a representative out into the world to speak honestly about it because
SPEAKER_1:  you're literally not allowed to.
SPEAKER_1:  So when faced, you know, if you're just sitting down with an entertainment journalist.
SPEAKER_1:  representative might be able to fudge their way through an interview.
SPEAKER_1:  by sitting down.
SPEAKER_1:  for a long form.
SPEAKER_1:  format.
SPEAKER_1:  interview.
SPEAKER_1:  with someone who.
SPEAKER_1:  is going to ask them about Xenu.
SPEAKER_1:  and the body Phaetons and Leah Remini and Lisa McPherson.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a no-go zone.
SPEAKER_1:  So I'm representing why it will never happen, but shit, I would tune in for that interview. I mean, I hope you do get someone.
SPEAKER_0:  You don't think David Miscavige would sit down for an interview.
SPEAKER_1:  I would love to be wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, in general, journalists in these kinds of situations can be.
SPEAKER_0:  We'll catch you next time.
SPEAKER_0:  attack.
SPEAKER_0:  in a way that doesn't empathize and doesn't come from a place of deep knowledge and understanding.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think it's possible to have serious conversations with people.
SPEAKER_0:  like that in an empathetic way, but it's also in a challenging way.
SPEAKER_0:  I think there's a huge amount of trust required.
SPEAKER_0:  and obviously for us, a very secretive organization.
SPEAKER_0:  The amount of trust, yes, might be too much.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes, anyone over there, if they've done their homework, knows.
SPEAKER_1:  you're going to be as fair as anyone in the world is going to be.
SPEAKER_1:  And yet...
SPEAKER_1:  They're simply things they're not allowed.
SPEAKER_1:  to talk about and they're not even allowed to say I'm not allowed to talk about it.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's a fundamental part.
SPEAKER_0:  of the Church of Scientology is the secrecy. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So that's where you're trained as you go up through the ranks Secretly, secrecy
SPEAKER_1:  It's not even a matter of training, it's that there's...
SPEAKER_1:  an entire the entire upper half of Scientology's bridge is simply confidential.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, and I never even did those levels when I was in Scientology. I didn't learn.
SPEAKER_1:  what Scientologists actually believe on those upper levels.
SPEAKER_1:  Until after I got out of Scientology and I was freaking born and raised in it.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's go there. Let's go to your personal story. So you've spent 30 years in cytology.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I was four years old when my mom.
SPEAKER_1:  Got in.
SPEAKER_0:  And then.
SPEAKER_0:  about seven years ago, got out. Yeah. on what YouTube channel now.
SPEAKER_0:  and you're an educator.
SPEAKER_1:  So I was four years old when my mom got introduced to Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  and she got in really fast really quick. So I was 12 years old when I was taken out of school and started officially full-time working for Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so in various capacities, I worked with them from the ages of 12.
SPEAKER_1:  to the age of 26.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  And then I was 34 when I officially.
SPEAKER_1:  ways with Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  which was really more them officially parting ways with me, but we can get into all that later. That's just kind of how Scientology does it.
SPEAKER_0:  And what do you do now in terms of Scientology?
SPEAKER_1:  So now I run growing up in Scientology, the YouTube channel, but what I primarily do.
SPEAKER_1:  is I help run an organization that helps people who are escaping from Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm the Vice President of the Aftermath Foundation.
SPEAKER_1:  And we created the foundation after the television show, the Aramne Scientology in the aftermath.
SPEAKER_1:  And there was such an outpouring of support from non-scientologists all over the world.
SPEAKER_1:  What can we do to help people?
SPEAKER_1:  Leave Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  that we decided to create a foundation.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's been incredibly successful. We've helped people escape from all regions and echelons of Scientology. We've accomplished...
SPEAKER_1:  What we've accomplished is far beyond what we actually.
SPEAKER_1:  envisioned would be possible. It's been a huge success.
SPEAKER_0:  So we'll talk about the negative aspect, the abuses of power, but let's just explore the ideas a little bit more.
SPEAKER_0:  So the public facing.
SPEAKER_0:  Three fundamental truths of.
SPEAKER_0:  Scientology, maybe correct me if I'm wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  Man is an immortal spiritual being, like we said with thetans.
SPEAKER_0:  His experience extends well beyond a single lifetime.
SPEAKER_0:  So infinite memory backwards.
SPEAKER_0:  His capabilities are unlimited even if not presently realized.
SPEAKER_0:  the capabilities are limited.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so that when I say Godlike, I really just mean.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, Thanos.
SPEAKER_1:  like unlimited.
SPEAKER_1:  Scientologists don't believe in a God. So when I say God-like, I just mean the most powerful entity, the creator, the prime mover unmoved, except we are all that.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, a thetan in signatology has no position in space or time. A thetan does not actually exist in the physical universe.
SPEAKER_1:  it might choose to locate itself.
SPEAKER_1:  in the physical universe, right? And then forget that it made that decision and then sort of get caught and trapped in the physical universe.
SPEAKER_1:  but that once the Thain is restored to its native.
SPEAKER_1:  powers.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... everything you see in the physical universe is just i think i'm playing a game
SPEAKER_1:  Like literally, we are in a simulation right now of some fate.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like physics.
SPEAKER_1:  doesn't have to make sense when we're talking about it this way. Like technically you're a Thayton, I'm a Thayton, we're here, but this could also all just be another Thayton's game.
SPEAKER_1:  with Tatans all the way down.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's just things everywhere things all comes down to the thing.
SPEAKER_0:  Is there an idea of a god?
SPEAKER_0:  I read there is a sense of a supreme being.
SPEAKER_0:  is that basically...
SPEAKER_0:  the fate and that's at the core at the bottom of it all yes not
SPEAKER_0:  Not defined. Undefined.
SPEAKER_1:  Correct.
SPEAKER_1:  Scientology has this concept of the dynamics when a cell around our blood is warning someone about another virus in your body and how it can get your body and you feel that your ability to reason with each other is marked as necessary
SPEAKER_1:  a different dynamics and the dynamic meaning a thrust towards survival.
SPEAKER_1:  So he would say, you know, the first dynamic is you yourself. Second dynamic is your family. Third dynamic is any other group.
SPEAKER_1:  that you're a part of other than your family.
SPEAKER_1:  Forth dynamic is all humankind.
SPEAKER_1:  The fifth dynamic is plant and animal life, all non-human life.
SPEAKER_1:  sixth dynamic is the physical world.
SPEAKER_1:  Seventh dynamic is sort of like spirituality collectively, Thetans as a Thetans.
SPEAKER_1:  and the eighth dynamic.
SPEAKER_1:  L. Ron Hubbard says, Scientology doesn't deal with the 8th.
SPEAKER_1:  but we recognize that people have this idea.
SPEAKER_1:  of a supreme being.
SPEAKER_1:  And so Scientology says you can call the eighth dynamic the supreme being dynamic.
SPEAKER_1:  but we call it infinity.
SPEAKER_1:  Just...
SPEAKER_1:  the allness of everything without having to define it. And then they sort of do a little dance and they're like,
SPEAKER_1:  Scientology, the purpose of Scientology is to get you to the point where you have your own understandings or realizations about the nature of the eighth dynamic. We don't tell you what you have to believe about that. And technically speaking, that is true.
SPEAKER_1:  Technically speaking, that is true.
SPEAKER_1:  There's no point in Scientology where they sit you down and say you're now required to revoke your belief in a supreme being.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just that everything in Scientology is inconsistent.
SPEAKER_1:  with a belief in the Supreme Being.
SPEAKER_1:  You can still find Scientologists who through cognitive dissonance will tell you they believe in a supreme being. Mostly they're lying to you.
SPEAKER_0:  How is this inconsistent with the supreme being?
SPEAKER_1:  like things because they ins have created everything not God.
SPEAKER_0:  So things creative, they're also creative force. They're not just the force that runs everything.
SPEAKER_0:  But can't those be just the fingertips of a god?
SPEAKER_1:  Sure the only way.
SPEAKER_1:  you could reconcile a supreme being.
SPEAKER_1:  is if you say
SPEAKER_1:  A single supreme being created?
SPEAKER_1:  all theta.
SPEAKER_1:  like the spiritual Big Bang.
SPEAKER_1:  But that's not what most people think when they talk about God.
SPEAKER_1:  They're talking about a creator.
SPEAKER_1:  of.
SPEAKER_0:  the physical universe. Yes. We'll be right back.
SPEAKER_1:  Right.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, even as I've described Scientology so far.
SPEAKER_1:  None of what I've said is something I even subject.
SPEAKER_1:  to ridicule. This is pretty common sense stuff actually. I mean, if you believe in spirituality,
SPEAKER_1:  or spirits at all, there's nothing I've described so far that's crazy.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, believing in past lives isn't particularly unique or special.
SPEAKER_1:  The fact that Scientology does this little dance of.
SPEAKER_1:  pretending to believe in a God. I mean, it's even like a PR line, Scientology representatives will tell you, you can be a Christian and be a Scientologist.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me tell you what.
SPEAKER_1:  Christians don't believe in past lives.
SPEAKER_1:  lives on other galaxies and planets and universes.
SPEAKER_1:  But in Scientology knows that Scientology knows you can't be a Christian and be a Scientologist, but they will say that it's just an example of sort of the fundamental baked in dishonesty.
SPEAKER_0:  because it's so important to Scientology on the organizational level to have
SPEAKER_0:  hex exempt status.
SPEAKER_0:  I wonder...
SPEAKER_0:  How do you-
SPEAKER_0:  Do you know the process of what it takes to prove that an organization is a religion?
SPEAKER_1:  while going through that process with the IRS for the second time, by the way. Scientology actually had tax exemption in the early days when the IRS pulled it.
SPEAKER_1:  and then they got it back in 1993.
SPEAKER_1:  while going through that process again.
SPEAKER_1:  the IRS actually took issue.
SPEAKER_1:  with the fact that Scientology was claiming you could be a Scientologist and a member of another religion. The IRS actually said.
SPEAKER_1:  Pump the brakes there. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  If you're gonna say that...
SPEAKER_1:  we're gonna say you're not a religion. yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  and they actually put in writing to the IRS. No, no, no, no, no, that's not what we meant. That's not what we meant.
SPEAKER_1:  We meant in the beginning you can be both, but eventually you just have to be a Scientologist.
SPEAKER_0:  So you mentioned the eight.
SPEAKER_0:  the eight dynamics, but y'all so much as survival.
SPEAKER_0:  So that seems to be a core-
SPEAKER_0:  principle that
SPEAKER_0:  that human existence is about survival.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you elaborate what is meant by survival? We're talking about the survival of the human species.
SPEAKER_0:  survival of the individual humans.
SPEAKER_0:  Survival of the...
SPEAKER_0:  the manifestation of
SPEAKER_0:  tens in human form, what survival?
SPEAKER_1:  So it would be all of that because survival is.
SPEAKER_1:  the dominant force across all the dynamics.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, L. Ron Hubbard, it was either Dianetics or Science of Survival.
SPEAKER_1:  Hehehe.
SPEAKER_1:  as he discovered.
SPEAKER_1:  the principle.
SPEAKER_1:  upon which.
SPEAKER_1:  All life exists and that is.
SPEAKER_1:  all life no matter what it is trying to do.
SPEAKER_1:  Are you ready, Lex?
SPEAKER_1:  trying to survive.
SPEAKER_0:  That's pretty powerful.
SPEAKER_0:  That's pretty powerful. Here's the thing. Is it? No, I got it.
SPEAKER_1:  tell you I got it might get me back in
SPEAKER_0:  I'm trying to get you back in. I'm trying to get you to take seriously the power of the ideas behind Scientology because I think those ideas are not bad ideas.
SPEAKER_0:  They resonate with a lot of ideas throughout philosophy, throughout religions, throughout the history of human civilization.
SPEAKER_0:  The interesting aspect is how it goes wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  But here's the thing, Lex, here's the thing. It is consistent.
SPEAKER_1:  with Prior.
SPEAKER_1:  efforts.
SPEAKER_1:  or studies.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just that L. Ron Hubbard said this was a watershed breakthrough that was being discovered for the first time. That's kind of what I'm mocking, really. Yeah, but you can mock n-
SPEAKER_0:  Nietzsche for saying
SPEAKER_0:  Man is will to power, you can mo-
SPEAKER_1:  But did he claim to be the first person to ever say it?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, Nietzsche, he's had a bit of an ego, so. Like, and he's full of contradictions, but I'm pretty sure.
SPEAKER_0:  The implied thing is that he was the first to...
SPEAKER_0:  first to say it. There's a lot of scientists. There's one of the people I really admire Stephen Wolfram.
SPEAKER_0:  who wrote a book called A New Kind of Science that explores complex systems in cellular automata and these mathematical systems that have been explored before.
SPEAKER_0:  but he boldly kind of defined, I am presenting to you a whole new way to look at the world.
SPEAKER_0:  And if you just set.
SPEAKER_0:  a little bit of the ego behind that aside, there's actually beautiful ideas in there. They have of course been done before and explored before, so there are several kinds that you could use.
SPEAKER_0:  People declare this.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the coolest. That's the only thing I'm really mocking is that this discovery that life is trying to survive is greater than the discovery of fire. Okay, I mean, again, it's a little silly, but that's fine. We can agree that the fact that life is trying to survive has meaning and is meaningful and is valuable.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean life is trying to survive.
SPEAKER_0:  Montreal definition of what is life.
SPEAKER_0:  here.
SPEAKER_0:  So this idea of a thing, the thing that permeates.
SPEAKER_0:  through lifetimes.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Through people. There's some...
SPEAKER_0:  some fabric that is bigger than the individual.
SPEAKER_0:  biological.
SPEAKER_0:  bags of meat.
SPEAKER_0:  That's a...
SPEAKER_0:  Philosophically-initial idea, of course, if it's not grounded in...
SPEAKER_0:  a little bit more.
SPEAKER_0:  physical reality then it becomes a little too woo-woo.
SPEAKER_1:  And the way L. Ron Hubbard in Scientology defines survival is very much intertwined with how they define ethics. Ethics anything.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, to be ethical.
SPEAKER_1:  is pro survival.
SPEAKER_1:  to be unethical.
SPEAKER_1:  counter-survival.
SPEAKER_1:  But we were talking about just the concept of the dynamics, like what does survival refer to? And it actually does refer to all of them, but just keep in mind when it comes to the seventh dynamic.
SPEAKER_1:  faytans collectively.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  involved in here is the idea that a thing cannot.
SPEAKER_1:  die.
SPEAKER_1:  There's no such thing as killing a thing. A thing can only.
SPEAKER_1:  can only survive.
SPEAKER_1:  And so, um...
SPEAKER_1:  Anyway, this concept of the dynamics is one of the most fundamental and important concepts in Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  But, but because I mentioned that it also gets tied up with ethics.
SPEAKER_1:  And this probably speaks to what you're just talking about is you can have the ideas and the concepts and you can have how do they go wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  Because...
SPEAKER_1:  They hold.
SPEAKER_1:  that Scientology, applying Scientology, getting people into Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  is the key.
SPEAKER_1:  to basically saving.
SPEAKER_1:  Every.
SPEAKER_1:  spiritual being in existence.
SPEAKER_1:  when you're analyzing what is ethical.
SPEAKER_1:  it becomes whatever's good for Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  becomes by definition ethical.
SPEAKER_1:  because anything that's good for Scientology...
SPEAKER_1:  which is a third dynamic.
SPEAKER_1:  is inherently good for all the dynamics.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's where you get.
SPEAKER_1:  the ends justifying the means to do anything possible and use any means necessary.
SPEAKER_1:  to forward the aims of Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of where a lot of Soviet implementation of communism went wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  as the ends justify the means.
SPEAKER_0:  the equality, the justice for the workers.
SPEAKER_0:  If we have to...
SPEAKER_0:  kill murder and prison censor.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. In the name of that, then it's.
SPEAKER_0:  is for the greater good in the long term to achieve the
SPEAKER_0:  the ideal of communism.
SPEAKER_1:  In some respects, Scientology created a near-perfect communist experiment in its organization.
SPEAKER_1:  What is it? From everyone according to their ability to each according to their need or something like that.
SPEAKER_1:  Scientology C organization is damn near a perfect communist experiment.
SPEAKER_1:  coming from someone who doesn't necessarily know what the perfect communist experiment really is, because I grew up in a cult, Lex. You can't keep using that as an excuse. It's a funny tagline I use in my videos. I like it. But it is interesting that an organization that is so hyper-capitalist and so money-hungry and is known to be very wealthy, at its core is run by these group of Searge members that live a communist.
SPEAKER_1:  Lifestyle.
SPEAKER_1:  We're gonna jump around.
SPEAKER_0:  go what is C-ORG? What is C-Organization? What is...
SPEAKER_1:  This organization is the most dedicated version, the most dedicated brand of Scientologists.
SPEAKER_1:  There's three like echelons.
SPEAKER_1:  of Scientologists.
SPEAKER_1:  There's public.
SPEAKER_1:  live normal lives in the real world and they pay to do Scientology courses and auditing.
SPEAKER_1:  then they're staff members.
SPEAKER_1:  who also live in the real world.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... but work on two and a half year contracts are five-year contracts at their local Scientology organization and then once they finish their contract there their debt is paid or whatever
SPEAKER_1:  And then there's the Sea Org members. These are the guys who signed the billion year contract.
SPEAKER_1:  They don't have lives in the outside world. They don't own property. They live in Scientology provided housing. They eat Scientology run cafeterias.
SPEAKER_0:  Actual contract that says a billion years?
SPEAKER_1:  It's symbolic, but yes.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, no, it's not a legally enforceable contract.
SPEAKER_1:  Ha ha ha!
SPEAKER_1:  They haven't succeeded in enforcing it in any subsequent lifetimes yet.
SPEAKER_0:  Marriage contracts should be like that. Please describe the sedative video.
SPEAKER_0:  Not until death do us part, but a billion years, it really makes it very concrete of what you're signing up for.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Those are the billion year guys. You hear a lot about the billion year contract, the billion year contract. That's the Sea Org.
SPEAKER_1:  and and uh... all of Scientology management international management middle management continental management
SPEAKER_1:  and even some lower level service orgs.
SPEAKER_1:  are composed 100% of Sea York members.
SPEAKER_1:  You're not allowed to.
SPEAKER_1:  marry or date someone who's not in the sea or.
SPEAKER_1:  You're also not allowed to have children.
SPEAKER_0:  with anybody outside of C.O.G.O. in general, you're not allowed to have children.
SPEAKER_1:  Sea Org members are not allowed to have children unless they leave the Sea Org.
SPEAKER_1:  They're expected to.
SPEAKER_1:  have an abortion and stay in the sea or because it's the greatest good for Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  if you accidentally get pregnant.
SPEAKER_0:  interesting because it distracts from the focus of the work.
SPEAKER_0:  What about sexual relations?
SPEAKER_1:  only once married, but that's why people get married after like three days. y  bring up a a an
SPEAKER_1:  Hey you, you look, you look all right, let's get married. Are you allowed to have divorce?
SPEAKER_1:  You get divorced a lot in the sea or.
SPEAKER_1:  I've known people who get married and divorced three times by the age of 25.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh wow.
SPEAKER_1:  because in this year getting married is practically like dating.
SPEAKER_1:  Also.
SPEAKER_1:  Unless you're married, you're living in dorms with a bunch of other people.
SPEAKER_1:  So in order to get your own room, you also have to get married.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's many benefits.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh wow, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  So you mentioned communism, in which way?
SPEAKER_0:  Is there a hierarchy inside C-ORG?
SPEAKER_0:  Is there a redistribution of...
SPEAKER_0:  Influence position.
SPEAKER_0:  money.
SPEAKER_0:  Power is S-Yorg.
SPEAKER_1:  Everyone in the sea org makes $50 a week.
SPEAKER_1:  everybody.
SPEAKER_1:  except David Miscavige, but. And, and some.
SPEAKER_1:  Some posts might have a cash bonus incentive structure, but fundamentally their pay is $50 a week.
SPEAKER_1:  So even the head of...
SPEAKER_1:  a big Scientology organization.
SPEAKER_1:  is getting 50 bucks a week.
SPEAKER_0:  Are celebrities also part of C-Org? Well, no, not usually.
SPEAKER_0:  So this is really the management layer.
SPEAKER_0:  So what's the idea behind $50 a week? Is that basically live a humble life?
SPEAKER_1:  They don't have to give you anything at all. It's just, oh, you mean like, what's the idea behind not paying?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, basically nothing.
SPEAKER_1:  Everything you need is already being provided for you. You're not here for the money.
SPEAKER_1:  You're working all the time anyway. It's not like you don't have days off. I mean, you're working all the time. There's not.
SPEAKER_1:  There's no concept of the weekends. There's no- thank God it's Friday.
SPEAKER_1:  Friday's just another day.
SPEAKER_0:  And how are the positions, the tasks, the jobs allocated within the C-ORG?
SPEAKER_0:  What do you mean? What kind of tasks you're doing, what kind of-
SPEAKER_1:  Mmm, it's very similar to just any other.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, business?
SPEAKER_1:  as far as you can have your human resources, you can have your sales, you can have your accounting, your operations.
SPEAKER_1:  your quality control, it's just that in Scientology, your operations.
SPEAKER_1:  is delivering courses and auditing.
SPEAKER_1:  So your operations and your quality control where most of the activity occurs as far as.
SPEAKER_1:  Delivering Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  And then you've got your.
SPEAKER_1:  you'd call it business development, but that's just bringing in new members, right?
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Look at that.
SPEAKER_1:  the function of a Scientology organization is very...
SPEAKER_1:  uh... very comparable to a a normal business in the normal world
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's talk about the products of this business, auditing and courses.
SPEAKER_1:  but what's auditing?
SPEAKER_1:  So auditing is, so we described earlier, Dianetics auditing.
SPEAKER_1:  Scientology auditing is very similar to that.
SPEAKER_0:  So at first glance, it's.
SPEAKER_0:  it looks like psychotherapy.
SPEAKER_0:  a kind of therapy.
SPEAKER_1:  All Scientology auditing is going to look like that.
SPEAKER_1:  It's one on one.
SPEAKER_1:  talk therapy.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, you're now.
SPEAKER_1:  A room by yourselves, no distraction, no noise.
SPEAKER_0:  One on one? Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  like this.
SPEAKER_1:  But in Scientology they have what's called an emeter.
SPEAKER_1:  All right, almost all auditing.
SPEAKER_1:  implies the use of an E-meter. What's an E-meter?
SPEAKER_1:  So an E-meter.
SPEAKER_1:  is.
SPEAKER_1:  a device.
SPEAKER_1:  just measures the resistance to a small electrical flow.
SPEAKER_1:  except Scientologists believe that this emitter can be used to simply direct the progress of an auditing session to determine whether
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhhhhh
SPEAKER_1:  The auditing has reached a good.
SPEAKER_1:  Satisfactory.
SPEAKER_1:  Conclusion.
SPEAKER_1:  All auditing sessions have to.
SPEAKER_1:  and on a satisfactory conclusion.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the job of the auditor. There's you don't just.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not like, sorry, the session sucked. See you next week. Like that.
SPEAKER_1:  Every auditing session has to end.
SPEAKER_1:  Amen.
SPEAKER_1:  on a positive note.
SPEAKER_1:  And if it doesn't...
SPEAKER_1:  uh... there's corrections to be made
SPEAKER_1:  So the emitter. What does it look like visually? Oh, you can pull it up.
SPEAKER_1:  Pull up Mark 8, emitter Mark 8.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's a few dials.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a...
SPEAKER_0:  basic information about time and duration I presume and then a dial that just goes zero to something
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so let's say that the meter's in front of me and you're the one holding the cans.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm holding the cancer, you're doing the auditing of me. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm holding the cans. No, literally in the beginning of an auditing session when you're calibrating the sensitivity of the emitter, you do a can squeeze. So I go squeeze the cans please. Okay, so I'm just like squeezing the cans. And I'm just changing the sensitivity because when you squeeze the cans, I want to get about a one third of a dial drop on the needle.
SPEAKER_1:  The idea is you don't want if the needle is too sensitive, then every time you shift around in your chair, the needle is gonna bounce all over the place. So you're trying to set the sensitivity of this thing.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's all the knob there on the.
SPEAKER_1:  bottom to the left, that's the sensitivity knob.
SPEAKER_1:  And that determines just.
SPEAKER_1:  How much
SPEAKER_1:  how sensitive the needle's gonna be.
SPEAKER_1:  and the
SPEAKER_1:  The bigger dial.
SPEAKER_1:  It's called the tone arm.
SPEAKER_1:  And that is changing.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I want to say voltage or current, but I'm not intending. I'm going to get one of those words is wrong.
SPEAKER_0:  But it is a real device. It's a real device. That you can actually calibrate.
SPEAKER_0:  add to.
SPEAKER_0:  Probably.
SPEAKER_0:  you know, get an outcome that you want.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so here's even how just how a Scientology auditor believes it works.
SPEAKER_1:  You're holding the cans, there's a tiny little battery in that emitter that's sending and you're completing the circuit when you pick up the cans, right? So you got a little thing.
SPEAKER_1:  going there.
SPEAKER_1:  and that needle.
SPEAKER_1:  will respond.
SPEAKER_1:  to your physical movement, but that's not what we want. We want you to sit the hell still so that we can read this thing when I'm asking you questions.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  So you're sitting there still, very still.
SPEAKER_1:  As still as you can, comfortable, right?
SPEAKER_1:  and I'm gonna go, is there something you're withholding from me?
SPEAKER_1:  And what I'm looking for is right when I say at the end of me, I'm looking for the needle to dip to the right.
SPEAKER_0:  having a needle even if it's kind of random.
SPEAKER_0:  can really be like a...
SPEAKER_0:  a catalyst for a conversation.
SPEAKER_1:  That's what it's used for.
SPEAKER_1:  except it's an enforced conversation. So I'll give you a really good example of this.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  You're holding the cans. Say, is there anything you're withholding from me?
SPEAKER_1:  and I get an instant read.
SPEAKER_1:  And I go, is there anything you're withholding from me?
SPEAKER_1:  You're gonna go, I don't think so.
SPEAKER_1:  And I don't see the needle. No, you don't see the needle.
SPEAKER_1:  I go, whoa.
SPEAKER_1:  What did you think of when I asked you the question? Now, if you've already had a lot of auditing, you know how this goes. It means I got an instant read and we're not going.
SPEAKER_1:  to move on until this question gets resolved.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so you're gonna go, you know what I was thinking of.
SPEAKER_1:  And then I'm gonna.
SPEAKER_1:  be like, you know, take a look and I'll help you out here. I'll try to steer you.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so I'm looking to get roughly the same read while you're-
SPEAKER_1:  thinking about whatever. What was that?
SPEAKER_1:  What was that right there?
SPEAKER_0:  And you can start digging to what you can start.
SPEAKER_1:  I just want an answer to the question.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, I can go to memory.
SPEAKER_1:  and you can give me any answer you want. There's no way for me to know if you're giving me the right answer, but I want you to give me something.
SPEAKER_1:  If you say you can't give me anything, I'm going to keep using the email until you give me something. Yeah. Okay, so let's say you give me something.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm gonna get all the details about that.
SPEAKER_1:  And until...
SPEAKER_1:  like time, place, form an event. I want to know everything that happened. I want to know all the details. And by the way, I'm writing all this down. So I'm taking notes of everything you're telling me that it's a bad thing that you did that you haven't told me about.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so I'm keeping notes.
SPEAKER_1:  when you represent to me that you've told me everything there is to tell.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm looking for the needle.
SPEAKER_1:  to give like a smooth back and forth motion like this.
SPEAKER_1:  and Scientology calls that a floating needle.
SPEAKER_1:  That means...
SPEAKER_1:  in Scientology land.
SPEAKER_1:  We're done with that.
SPEAKER_1:  So now I might go back to check the question. Okay, good, I'll check the question again. Is there anything you're withholding from me?
SPEAKER_1:  If I get another read, we've got to go through the process again.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  If you tell me I've told you everything and I don't get a floating needle, I've got to go, okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there an earlier?
SPEAKER_1:  similar.
SPEAKER_1:  Have you basically done an earlier similar thing? Is there an earlier similar time you haven't told someone something or is there an earlier similar thing?
SPEAKER_1:  that you did the thing that you just told me.
SPEAKER_1:  We're gonna keep going earlier, similar, earlier, similar, until I get a floating needle.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's where...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm explaining it this way you can see how.
SPEAKER_1:  no matter what the specific auditing session happens to be about.
SPEAKER_1:  there's still the potential in any auditing session that you're going into past lives.
SPEAKER_1:  just because.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to go earlier similar until you get a floating needle.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Now.
SPEAKER_1:  Here's how Scientologists think.
SPEAKER_1:  the emitter actually works, meaning.
SPEAKER_1:  why does the emitter work? so we talked before about these um
SPEAKER_1:  these mental pictures.
SPEAKER_1:  right, these recordings.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, well we spoke about engrams, just recordings of pain and unconsciousness.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, Scientology would hold.
SPEAKER_1:  the bad recordings aren't the only recordings.
SPEAKER_1:  that you have. Those are just the recordings in your reactive mind.
SPEAKER_1:  You also have an analytical mind.
SPEAKER_1:  which is just your conscious memory.
SPEAKER_1:  conscious recording of everything from present time to...
SPEAKER_1:  the last 76 trillion years.
SPEAKER_1:  And Hubbard would say that these memories are actually perfectly detailed.
SPEAKER_1:  recording and these are like 56 perceptions or something.
SPEAKER_1:  and that it's perfect.
SPEAKER_1:  and you can access that information.
SPEAKER_1:  You just have trouble doing so.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  So he says that these recordings, these mental pictures, have actual electrical charge and mass.
SPEAKER_1:  Now you asked before, is there any actual physics in this?
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know, where are you supposed to store the pictures of your last 76 trillion years that have charge in mass?
SPEAKER_1:  I don't see it.
SPEAKER_1:  But Hubbard says it's there.
SPEAKER_1:  So he says that these things have mass.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  when you recall them or put attention on them.
SPEAKER_1:  You create an electrical flow.
SPEAKER_1:  which maybe through magnetic fields or whatever, impinges upon the electrical flow.
SPEAKER_1:  of the emeter.
SPEAKER_1:  and it shows up as a read on the needle.
SPEAKER_1:  That's how Scientologists believe that's why the needle reads.
SPEAKER_1:  Now, Cinex would say the needle only reads on palm sweat.
SPEAKER_1:  and movement.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I know that's not true.
SPEAKER_1:  Right, I can't tell you everything the needle.
SPEAKER_1:  does read on.
SPEAKER_1:  But I can tell you it's not just.
SPEAKER_1:  moving your hands and sweaty hands.
SPEAKER_0:  It does correlate to thoughts probably.
SPEAKER_0:  someway somehow.
SPEAKER_0:  Because if it didn't correlate to thoughts that this process would be way
SPEAKER_0:  Way too inefficient.
SPEAKER_0:  Because it would be too, there's going to be a bunch of people who are just not, you're not going to get the, what is it called, the floating needle.
SPEAKER_0:  Like no matter what.
SPEAKER_1:  I can't explain to you how you get a floating needle.
SPEAKER_1:  but it sure as hell isn't hand sweat.
SPEAKER_1:  and it sure as hell isn't squeezing the cans. Right, so you eventually-
SPEAKER_0:  most people will get to the floating needle.
SPEAKER_1:  And somehow you get floating needles.
SPEAKER_0:  There's like a feed, there probably is a feedback mechanism that you will-
SPEAKER_0:  Each person realizes how their mind and body.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. Because you want a resolution, right? It's probably a-
SPEAKER_1:  your needle to float. For both people...
SPEAKER_0:  Yes. And it's probably a great experience when you're like, yes, it's a game of.
SPEAKER_1:  feeling, right? Well, when you're training on how to use the emitter, there are drills where you practice.
SPEAKER_1:  you generating with your mind.
SPEAKER_1:  various needle reactions. So, you know, there is a drill where you sit there and you consciously try to create a floating needle by recalling happy thoughts.
SPEAKER_1:  Go to your happy place.
SPEAKER_1:  And at the end of every auditing session, you actually have to go to a third party.
SPEAKER_1:  sit down in front of a knee meter and verify that your knee is floating.
SPEAKER_1:  Every single auditing session not only has to end on a floating needle, but then you have to go to someone else and have the floating needle verified.
SPEAKER_1:  Any Scientologist who's
SPEAKER_1:  a seasoned recipient of auditing knows how to make their needle float at the exam.
SPEAKER_0:  But I gotta be honest though, this process again.
SPEAKER_0:  Sorry to be going there, but.
SPEAKER_0:  It feels like this is a very rigorous talk.
SPEAKER_0:  therapy session.
SPEAKER_0:  Is there good aspects to this?
SPEAKER_1:  Sure.
SPEAKER_1:  A lot of people find auditing very helpful. I mean, I've heard some describe it as.
SPEAKER_1:  thoroughly addictive.
SPEAKER_1:  Me personally, I never enjoyed getting auditing.
SPEAKER_1:  That's probably more a function of having.
SPEAKER_1:  been raised in it and it was never something I wanted to do, something that was forced on me as a child, you know, and also I was never.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't like talking about private secret stuff. Like you kind of have to want to be an open book.
SPEAKER_1:  Sure. Just playing the channel.
SPEAKER_1:  honestly and thoroughly participate in an auditing session.
SPEAKER_0:  Because there's not necessarily a belief that this is going to be private.
SPEAKER_1:  There's no expectation of privacy, but there's no expectation that your stuff's gonna be leaked or blackmail either.
SPEAKER_1:  You kinda-
SPEAKER_1:  You trust the people in the organization.
SPEAKER_0:  even despite rumors and stuff like that. But the rumors are coming from people that are lying to you, essentially.
SPEAKER_1:  if you're a Scientologist.
SPEAKER_1:  and you're participating in an auditing session.
SPEAKER_1:  You know that any one in the organization is.
SPEAKER_1:  has the ability to.
SPEAKER_1:  know the stuff that you talk. It's not like, oh my God, I'm only telling my auditor because I think no one's ever gonna know. You know that people know.
SPEAKER_1:  but you also trust the organization.
SPEAKER_0:  How quickly does it go to past memories?
SPEAKER_1:  For people who are seasoned...
SPEAKER_1:  Like they actually like going past life.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. I hated it. I would make sure-
SPEAKER_1:  I was really good at making my needle float.
SPEAKER_1:  I didn't want to have some auditor because I never believed in the best life memory.
SPEAKER_1:  So I didn't want to be in that impassable, reach an impasse in an auditing session where I was being asked for something I couldn't provide. Cause I knew this auditing session has to end on a good point.
SPEAKER_1:  But Scientologists enjoy!
SPEAKER_1:  for the most part, going, they call it whole track. Whole track is past life.
SPEAKER_1:  going whole track.
SPEAKER_1:  Your time track, they call it the time track.
SPEAKER_1:  is your whole memory, but whole track refers to anything past life.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay. So going whole track or deep whole track with high reality, meaning it's not like, oh, I have a fuzzy memory and I'm not sure if it's real. Like your real season Scientologists are like.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah, I was on this planet this time circling this garden. This is what I was eating for breakfast.
SPEAKER_0:  Fascinating before the origin of life on Earth.
SPEAKER_0:  So billions of years ago.
SPEAKER_0:  on a distant planet where you were eating for breakfast. Or other universes. I wonder if this is-
SPEAKER_0:  Nice shortcut.
SPEAKER_0:  to sneak up to actual trauma that happened to you as a therapy device.
SPEAKER_0:  I just, so putting Scientology aside is just.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm thinking about.
SPEAKER_0:  as a technique for therapy.
SPEAKER_0:  discussing.
SPEAKER_0:  Basically, you know, some people have trauma and one of the things you do with therapy is like bring the trauma to the surface. The stuff that happened to you childhood.
SPEAKER_0:  Maybe it's a more convenient thing to do.
SPEAKER_0:  kind of map that indirectly onto
SPEAKER_0:  fictitious.
SPEAKER_0:  telling.
SPEAKER_0:  of what happened to you.
SPEAKER_0:  something like that trauma on a distant planet elsewhere.
SPEAKER_0:  Could be a nice way to sneak up to it.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  And it goes both flows there, not just things that have happened to you, but things that you've done.
SPEAKER_1:  So, you know, you could be being asked for it.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, you'd be going back, I wiped out a civilization.
SPEAKER_1:  I committed genocide on
SPEAKER_1:  this race on this planet.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  So you can actually take on a whole new-
SPEAKER_0:  guilt.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yeah. Eh, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Alright, you might actually take on a lot more guilt than I go off.
SPEAKER_0:  Because if you feel...
SPEAKER_0:  Like that's a critical aspect.
SPEAKER_0:  of the brain.
SPEAKER_0:  Boy, because my brain is really self-critical.
SPEAKER_0:  so I could see myself manufacturing if I was forced to over time, some kind of story where I didn't.
SPEAKER_0:  genocide a whole population of like Pluto or something a different distant is somewhere in office and tarry
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so I mean, now I walk around with that guilt.
SPEAKER_0:  way I'm actually a horrible
SPEAKER_1:  person. So imagine though, if you had not only are you looking at, you know, if someone's being self-critical, trying to identify destructive patterns of behavior in your present life, but what if you really internalize the fact that
SPEAKER_1:  I haven't only been this way.
SPEAKER_1:  for 40 years.
SPEAKER_1:  I've been this way for 40 trillion years.
SPEAKER_1:  But Scientology would argue.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  As a Thayton, you're inherently good.
SPEAKER_1:  All things are basically good.
SPEAKER_1:  So the goal of the auditing procedure there would be essentially to figure out, find the moment.
SPEAKER_1:  Find what it was that caused you.
SPEAKER_1:  to make that shift.
SPEAKER_1:  as a being.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  dramatize evil intentions and stuff like that.
SPEAKER_1:  So even if you're going whole track.
SPEAKER_1:  looking at all the horrible things you've done.
SPEAKER_1:  The goal is to find like...
SPEAKER_1:  Well, what happened just prior to that? What was like the prior confusion and-
SPEAKER_1:  What did you misunderstand just before that and whatnot? So the goal is basically, so Scientologists after a lot of auditing are also convinced that they have fixed.
SPEAKER_1:  The reason.
SPEAKER_1:  for any non-optimum.
SPEAKER_1:  conduct.
SPEAKER_0:  And underlying this is a belief that at the core.
SPEAKER_0:  We're all good.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes. There's a lot of really powerful ideas in Scientology. That's true. Which is so interesting that it goes wrong. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, what about the training you mentioned? The training of the auditor, that's really interesting. So how lengthy is that process? It can take years.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, one of that.
SPEAKER_0:  Question I want to ask is are people in Sea Org, like as an auditor, do you-
SPEAKER_0:  believe everything how much
SPEAKER_0:  Is there a crisis of faith?
SPEAKER_0:  creeps in.
SPEAKER_0:  Religion you have a crisis of faith when you
SPEAKER_0:  start to wonder like does God even exist?
SPEAKER_0:  So in this case.
SPEAKER_0:  How often do you start to doubt?
SPEAKER_0:  that some of the core beliefs of Scientology are false.
SPEAKER_1:  Scientology would say that Scientology is not about beliefs, it's about.
SPEAKER_1:  application of the techniques of Scientology auditing to improve someone's spiritual awareness and ability.
SPEAKER_1:  So the belief level of Scientology is pretty much.
SPEAKER_1:  the stuff we've already discussed.
SPEAKER_0:  the effectiveness of the audit across
SPEAKER_1:  So the effectiveness of the auditing process is one of the things Hubbard says is that
SPEAKER_1:  standard.
SPEAKER_1:  standard Scientology, they call it the tech, the technology of how to deliver auditing, standard tech, worth $100,000.
SPEAKER_1:  100.
SPEAKER_1:  percent of the time?
SPEAKER_1:  When applied, 100% correctly.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, that's kind of unfalsifiable, right?
SPEAKER_1:  because anytime it doesn't work, it wasn't applied correctly. Exactly.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a nice little, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  escape hatch to pull on having a crisis of faith.
SPEAKER_1:  But it didn't work.
SPEAKER_1:  and obviously it wasn't applied correctly. That's where quality control comes in.
SPEAKER_1:  Their job is to nitpick.
SPEAKER_1:  And you can always find one thing that wasn't done correctly.
SPEAKER_0:  communism.
SPEAKER_0:  uh, didn't work because it wasn't implemented correctly. That's the.
SPEAKER_0:  It's always an escape hatch with ideologies.
SPEAKER_1:  That's right. That's right. I would probably argue that auditors.
SPEAKER_1:  um... are not
SPEAKER_1:  in a position of having many crisis of faith, because actually they're usually seeing people.
SPEAKER_1:  for the most part.
SPEAKER_1:  improve in some ways.
SPEAKER_1:  it through the process of auditing.
SPEAKER_1:  Now.
SPEAKER_1:  Auditing can create like a state of somewhat of a euphoric state.
SPEAKER_1:  You feel.
SPEAKER_1:  You're just blown out of your head.
SPEAKER_1:  You know you feel fear on top of the world i've had that in some of my auditing.
SPEAKER_1:  as an auditor so you know as a person receiving on it
SPEAKER_1:  And so my point is that as an auditor doing a lot of auditing, you know, you're going to have someone in front of you called the pre clear is the person in front of you who's getting the auditing called the PC or the pre clear.
SPEAKER_1:  They see over and over and over again, these pieces having these sort of euphoric states and floating needles, and I feel great and fantastic. Thanks, you saved my life and da da da da da.
SPEAKER_1:  I've always said if people didn't find Scientology helpful, nobody would ever stay in Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  And so auditors are pretty much the ones doing the heavy lifting of what it even means to be a Scientologist. Those guys aren't the ones that you end up.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm having crisis of faith. I mean, doing Scientology, auditing, it doesn't require.
SPEAKER_1:  that you believe just.
SPEAKER_1:  have faith that you believe something.
SPEAKER_1:  You just have to go through these motions. And Scientologists, one of the reasons Scientologists think this is all scientific is because it's like.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't care if you believe why this works.
SPEAKER_1:  I care how you feel at the end of an auditing session.
SPEAKER_0:  and empirically speaking.
SPEAKER_0:  like anecdotal data is it actually seems to improve people's lives within the context.
SPEAKER_0:  taking the outside world out of it.
SPEAKER_0:  within this particular organization.
SPEAKER_0:  you're actually...
SPEAKER_0:  measurably seeing improvement. Yes. Is that to some degree real?
SPEAKER_0:  Because like, if you look at a book like Animal Farm.
SPEAKER_0:  where the pigs start to rule the other animals.
SPEAKER_0:  And over time the life of the animals gets worse and worse and worse while the pigs keep saying that it's actually getting better and better and better. Again, communism, same thing.
SPEAKER_0:  the rationing was getting worse and worse and worse, less and less food.
SPEAKER_0:  but there's constant reporting.
SPEAKER_0:  that there's more and more food where
SPEAKER_0:  We're winning. Hashtag.
SPEAKER_1:  I would argue that what you've just described could be.
SPEAKER_1:  an identical description of what it feels like and what it means to go up Scientology's bridge to total freedom.
SPEAKER_1:  You are reinforcing to yourself that everything's getting better and better and better and
SPEAKER_1:  and you'd be like...
SPEAKER_1:  You don't spend time with your family anymore. You're broke even though you make a lot of money.
SPEAKER_1:  You're always stressed. You're at the beck and call of these people who seem to run your...
SPEAKER_1:  run your lives like.
SPEAKER_1:  how a Scientologist feels about their own life.
SPEAKER_1:  is.
SPEAKER_1:  It's very interesting to compare that to how that.
SPEAKER_1:  person's life looks.
SPEAKER_1:  to their non-scientology family members.
SPEAKER_1:  I get contacted by a lot of people.
SPEAKER_1:  who've never been in Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  but like I got a family member who's really deep and I just, can you help me understand some things? Why is this person's life like this? Why is this person's life like this?
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't want to say that
SPEAKER_1:  Scientologists.
SPEAKER_1:  Do not actually.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't want to say, oh, it's all in their heads. They think they're being helped, but they're really not.
SPEAKER_1:  That doesn't feel honest.
SPEAKER_1:  You know?
SPEAKER_1:  but it's this thing where if Scientology was just.
SPEAKER_1:  Getting auditing.
SPEAKER_1:  when you want it.
SPEAKER_1:  about the subjects you wanted.
SPEAKER_1:  and you can take it or leave it.
SPEAKER_1:  That would be fine.
SPEAKER_1:  It's.
SPEAKER_1:  It's the fact that it's part and parcel to this entire organization and this entire experience.
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  has.
SPEAKER_1:  as a part of that experience, taking everything from you, demanding everything from you, controlling who you can speak with.
SPEAKER_1:  controlling who you can have relationships with, who you have to erase from your life.
SPEAKER_1:  This is where and it's hard to it's hard to.
SPEAKER_1:  place one.
SPEAKER_1:  pinpoint on this is where Scientology goes wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  It's really hard to do that.
SPEAKER_1:  because the good parts of Scientology and the bad parts of Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  are all just Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so there's definition of what's bad for you and it's probably in the beginning is bad for you.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, it's almost just.
SPEAKER_0:  sounds like a template of a toxic relationship.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, there's a bunch of stuff in this world that are just not good for you.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  the authoritarian says like, I'm just protecting you by.
SPEAKER_0:  blocking you off from those negative things. And they're probably negative, they are probably negative things.
SPEAKER_0:  But then this like...
SPEAKER_0:  This freedom starts closing in
SPEAKER_0:  to where you can't no longer.
SPEAKER_0:  Speak freely, think freely, act freely.
SPEAKER_0:  And there's some, I mean, that's why I sort of power corrupts.
SPEAKER_0:  and absolute power corrupts absolutely that person doing the controlling
SPEAKER_0:  actually starts getting
SPEAKER_0:  that like dopamine rush.
SPEAKER_0:  of the controller that's exciting. It's a vicious negative cycle. So you start out.
SPEAKER_0:  as a-
SPEAKER_0:  It starts out.
SPEAKER_0:  Good.
SPEAKER_0:  because he's trying to do good for the person.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, but then it
SPEAKER_0:  somehow goes to shit.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. So what, what, uh, what are the aspects that just, that are often controlled about.
SPEAKER_0:  about a person who's in cytology, especially C-work.
SPEAKER_1:  Well...
SPEAKER_1:  Information control access to the internet access to any information critical of Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  Is some Internet access allowed?
SPEAKER_1:  public Scientologists.
SPEAKER_1:  has no.
SPEAKER_1:  restrictions to their access to the internet.
SPEAKER_1:  They're just not allowed.
SPEAKER_1:  to read anything critical of Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, okay, so they're supposed to self control.
SPEAKER_0:  what they read or not.
SPEAKER_0:  And what's the explanation?
SPEAKER_0:  Is it always assumed that anything critical of Scientology is a lie?
SPEAKER_1:  They really pushed this thing.
SPEAKER_1:  that uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Unless you've...
SPEAKER_1:  been in a Scientology organization yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  or unless you've actually been a Scientologist.
SPEAKER_1:  You couldn't possibly know the truth about Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  If you're only getting information.
SPEAKER_1:  from people who aren't members or former members, then you couldn't possibly be getting the correct information.
SPEAKER_1:  Now, they don't...
SPEAKER_1:  realize the math there doesn't make sense. If you can find out the true information.
SPEAKER_1:  by becoming and being a Scientologist.
SPEAKER_1:  then that means...
SPEAKER_1:  you can get the correct information from a former Scientologist because they traveled that path and they got the correct information. So they still create this, they try to create this unfalsifiable loop where unless you are personally...
SPEAKER_1:  doing it.
SPEAKER_1:  you don't have correct information.
SPEAKER_1:  And you go, what about the people who did personally do it?
SPEAKER_1:  got the correct information.
SPEAKER_1:  laugh.
SPEAKER_1:  and are now sharing that with others. Well, no, those are lies. Well, okay, so just anything you don't like is a lie then. You go, yeah, pretty much, that's kind of how it.
SPEAKER_1:  That's kind of how it works.
SPEAKER_0:  So what about the control of negative information on the internet?
SPEAKER_0:  What like the actual operations I've, you know, preparing, I should admit I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  much about Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  doing a bunch of reading and...
SPEAKER_0:  The Wikipedia page on Scientology, interestingly enough, is not that negative about Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  So like, it made me ask.
SPEAKER_0:  yet if you would be careful how you can send stuff from a computer here to
SPEAKER_0:  consider because money can buy things there. There's certain special interests and so on. But like it made me wonder like.
SPEAKER_0:  Like with a lot of controversial topics, what is true and where do I look?
SPEAKER_0:  where do I go for truth? So like how much
SPEAKER_0:  sort of deliberate action is there to control what is true on the internet by Scientology
SPEAKER_1:  Well, these days they've pretty much, I think, thrown in the towel, but they have the Scientology middle management.
SPEAKER_1:  was.
SPEAKER_1:  Editing Wikipedia so often from IP addresses that were traced back to the Scientology buildings that
SPEAKER_1:  uh... wikipedia lock them out from any i p addresses associated with Scientology from being able to edit it.
SPEAKER_1:  It's like.
SPEAKER_1:  Scientology was so infatuated with trying to control the information
SPEAKER_1:  And in the early days of the internet, they had a certain degree of success with that. It's just hopeless these days.
SPEAKER_0:  the scale the scales not that but actually i'm very surprised
SPEAKER_0:  how
SPEAKER_0:  bot farms, how effective that can be at a very small scale. If you just pay.
SPEAKER_0:  100 people.
SPEAKER_0:  Just spread narratives.
SPEAKER_0:  But the...
SPEAKER_0:  the bad stuff, the.
SPEAKER_0:  The reason that's effective is you can kind of...
SPEAKER_0:  create conspiracy theories.
SPEAKER_0:  that create chaos and nobody knows what is true.
SPEAKER_0:  that bot farms can do.
SPEAKER_0:  but actually really nicely control a narrative is hard.
SPEAKER_0:  So to create chaos.
SPEAKER_0:  it's easier to do to basically say like.
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, do PR control is very hard.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, so especially on the internet, especially when...
SPEAKER_0:  The Critical Eye.
SPEAKER_0:  is there. The internet can smell bullshit, which is one of the really really powerful things about the internet. And I gotta tell ya, it- expect-
SPEAKER_1:  It's one of the reasons I do my YouTube channel.
SPEAKER_1:  It's one of the reasons I decided to upload every day. I've uploaded every day for the last six months.
SPEAKER_1:  I just wanted there to be a non stop.
SPEAKER_1:  flow.
SPEAKER_1:  of information.
SPEAKER_1:  of any kind and any variety.
SPEAKER_1:  As long as it's fair.
SPEAKER_1:  and balanced, intelligent.
SPEAKER_1:  Interesting that Scientologists who stumble upon the internet
SPEAKER_1:  We're going, oh look!
SPEAKER_1:  Someone's talking about my thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's see what they got going on.
SPEAKER_1:  And I know this guy.
SPEAKER_1:  The fact that Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  so much information before before YouTube before like I have the only like
SPEAKER_1:  big Scientology channel. And that only got big in the last six months.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so before that there were channels, there was things, but it's almost like.
SPEAKER_1:  It took a lot of.
SPEAKER_1:  Like people felt like it took a lot of bravery and courage to like say something.
SPEAKER_1:  on the internet about Scientology and so people would pop up and there weren't very many voices and I was like I want this to be prolific.
SPEAKER_1:  I want to be prolific. I want to have 30 or 40 other channels being prolific so that Scientology couldn't.
SPEAKER_1:  Possibly.
SPEAKER_1:  successfully control.
SPEAKER_1:  the narrative about it.
SPEAKER_1:  Have you been personally attacked? AaronSmithLevin.com is a website created by the Church of Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  Have you seen it?
SPEAKER_1:  what kind of content is on there.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, Aaron's an abusive father and a horrible husband and the worst staff member we've ever had and gave him adrenaline cm
SPEAKER_1:  I openly talk about it because I think the fact that Scientology even does things like that is.
SPEAKER_1:  Fucking hilarious.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... anything that tried to do me a mark i get the way i think about it is
SPEAKER_1:  you know you're just giving me an opportunity to turn the mirror back on you and show everyone how horrible you are
SPEAKER_0:  Does it stick?
SPEAKER_0:  Do you find that there is ineffective? It's completely ineffective.
SPEAKER_1:  They're so over the top.
SPEAKER_1:  And I'll tell you how the website even came into being.
SPEAKER_1:  So I was on the first season of Leah Remini Scientology in the aftermath.
SPEAKER_1:  Every
SPEAKER_1:  single person who participated in that show got a website.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just that everyone else's website is like.
SPEAKER_1:  Who is MarkHedley.com?
SPEAKER_1:  Who is MikeRender.com?
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I bought who is Aaron Smith Levin dot com, but I was too stupid to buy Aaron. I didn't buy Aaron Smith Levin.
SPEAKER_1:  So I'm actually the only one.
SPEAKER_1:  who has a website in their name. Oh, nice. best seller.
SPEAKER_1:  And I'm like, I can't really get a lawyer to get it back for me. But I'm like, why?
SPEAKER_1:  I want everyone to see what a nasty, petty
SPEAKER_1:  disgusting organization that this is. And nobody believes anything Scientology says anyway. does object.
SPEAKER_0:  on public know that it comes from scientific research.
SPEAKER_1:  Pull it up. It says right on the bottom, copyright 2000 whatever, Church of Scientology International. They didn't even try to hide it.
SPEAKER_0:  So AaronSmithLevin.com. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  A man with no moral compass. Annismith, who is he really?
SPEAKER_0:  Aaron Smith Levin, a man with no moral compass.
SPEAKER_0:  Read about Aaron Smith-Levins, an angry man spreading hate from an-
SPEAKER_0:  from the internet's shadows.
SPEAKER_0:  Open mouth shot.
SPEAKER_0:  And you're saying like at the, wow, there's testimony.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, there's videos from former
SPEAKER_0:  This latest thing just sets him off.
SPEAKER_0:  and he just goes totally nuts.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, that one is true. I didn't understand why you slapped me before the interview.
SPEAKER_1:  I thought that... They got links to everyone else's website on the bottom. It's so funny. Who is, okay. See,  icked.
SPEAKER_1:  2021 Church of Scientology International, all rights reserved. Here's an example of just Scientology's complete lack of self-awareness.
SPEAKER_1:  So me and Mike Render, we went and have these on like a house flip project, right?
SPEAKER_1:  wait, Mike Rinder? You know Mike Rinder.
SPEAKER_1:  Do I? anyway? Brother?
SPEAKER_0:  Bobblehead of the guy
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know him, I would like to talk to him about him.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a very fine...
SPEAKER_0:  gentleman here with a bobblehead.
SPEAKER_1:  The reason we created the bobblehead is because on Mike Rinder's hate site.
SPEAKER_1:  Scientology created a GIF or a GIF. How do you say it? Scientology created a GIF or a GIF.
SPEAKER_1:  The correct way is GIF. GIF, good. Scientology created a GIF of Mike Rinder as a bobblehead. It was an insult like, oh, all he does is sit next to Leah Remini and go, yes, Leah, yes, Leah.
SPEAKER_1:  and so they they made a gift of him with a bobblehead.
SPEAKER_1:  So we were like.
SPEAKER_1:  We're gonna make mic render bobbleheads and we're gonna sell them on the spshop.com to raise money for the Aftermath Foundation. Love it.
SPEAKER_1:  And now that I go out and buy, yeah, go to thescreenshop.com and get yourself a mic render bobblehead. Now look, now that my profile is getting a little higher, this head was made to bobble. Like this.
SPEAKER_1:  smooth shiny head needs its own bobble head now. It does. 100%
SPEAKER_0:  it does i can't believe it doesn't
SPEAKER_1:  So, but let me show you. So here's what's happening here. We just hired some day laborers off of what like Craigslist or something.
SPEAKER_1:  So what Scientology did?
SPEAKER_1:  was
SPEAKER_1:  They had.
SPEAKER_1:  private investigator.
SPEAKER_1:  Stake out.
SPEAKER_1:  the house flip project.
SPEAKER_1:  They were clearly running license plates of anyone.
SPEAKER_1:  who visited the property.
SPEAKER_1:  because otherwise, otherwise, how would they find out the laborer's names, look, do background checks on them?
SPEAKER_1:  to find out they had criminal records.
SPEAKER_1:  and they publish this as if it's gonna reflect negatively on me.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, we hired someone to do work who had a
SPEAKER_1:  Criminal Record?
SPEAKER_1:  Giz-a-shit.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, one of the biggest problems people with records have is finding employment.
SPEAKER_1:  There's nothing bad about hiring someone who's got a criminal record.
SPEAKER_1:  It doesn't reflect negatively on me, but it shows you what they think about those people.
SPEAKER_1:  It shows you what they think about people who are trying to put their lives back together.
SPEAKER_1:  maybe, you know, actually work for a living. And it also shows that there are
SPEAKER_1:  surveilling us.
SPEAKER_1:  You like to...
SPEAKER_1:  They don't realize that putting this up, they're publishing information that they could only have if they're surveilling.
SPEAKER_1:  me and Mike and it doesn't occur to them.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe we shouldn't put that up.
SPEAKER_0:  Just a general process.
SPEAKER_0:  sad to say, of journalism.
SPEAKER_0:  where they're looking for any kind of dirt and it's, they're trying to conjure up a story.
SPEAKER_0:  and there's something about drama and negative stories that get clicks and so on. So this is a general process.
SPEAKER_0:  The more, especially the more of celebrity you become, the more these kinds of attacks come and they look for any kind of thing.
SPEAKER_0:  that could be, you know, it doesn't even have to be facts. It could be.
SPEAKER_0:  Just asking who is he really?
SPEAKER_0:  seems to have traction on the internet.
SPEAKER_0:  What is the actual truth?
SPEAKER_0:  of the man you keep claiming you are, of the good man you keep claiming you are.
SPEAKER_0:  is fascinating.
SPEAKER_0:  but sometimes that can be effective.
SPEAKER_0:  But I think if you're being transparent and authentic and just putting yourself out there completely in their story completely then...
SPEAKER_0:  That's the best way to fight it.
SPEAKER_1:  That's the other reason to be prolific on the internet, right? The reason Joe Rogan can't get cancelled.
SPEAKER_1:  is because.
SPEAKER_1:  anyone can watch thousands of hours of the authentic Joe Rogan. You can't misrepresent him because he spent thousands of hours representing himself genuinely.
SPEAKER_0:  The nice thing.
SPEAKER_0:  when you're representing yourself generally.
SPEAKER_0:  You should be a good person.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're a good person, then the internet will know.
SPEAKER_0:  You can smell out the bullshit.
SPEAKER_0:  Who is David Muskovic? It's even like, because you said Elron Hubbard.
SPEAKER_0:  Founded Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  Let's go to the story.
SPEAKER_0:  of how we transition from that to do.
SPEAKER_1:  The current leader of Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  He was actually not selected by L. Ron Hubbard to take over.
SPEAKER_1:  but ended up usurping power and taking over.
SPEAKER_0:  like Stalin and Trotsky and communism, similar story. It's the person.
SPEAKER_0:  Oftentimes in situation.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... it's not the natural
SPEAKER_0:  successor.
SPEAKER_0:  Power, it's the one that
SPEAKER_0:  takes power.
SPEAKER_1:  I think the quote sometimes gets attributed to David Miscavige is
SPEAKER_1:  power.
SPEAKER_1:  Power is not given, it is assumed.
SPEAKER_1:  Something like that.
SPEAKER_1:  The last six years of L. Ron Hubbard's life, he was often in seclusion, essentially hiding from lawsuits.
SPEAKER_1:  now.
SPEAKER_1:  By the time Hubbard went off into seclusion.
SPEAKER_1:  Miscavige had sort of already risen up through the ranks of the C organization.
SPEAKER_1:  Now Miscavige was like a teenager, either like 11, 12, 13, or something like that. Miscavige was not born into Scientology, but he was a young-
SPEAKER_1:  a young boy.
SPEAKER_1:  when his father got into Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  So, Ms. Gavage did start working as a C-ORG member.
SPEAKER_1:  So there's one organization that existed to essentially serve Hubbard directly.
SPEAKER_1:  and to represent his interest and that was called the Commodore he was the Commodore of the Sea Organization.
SPEAKER_1:  the Commodore's Messengers Organization, and call it the CMO.
SPEAKER_1:  Miscavige started working for the CMO pretty early on in his C-Org.
SPEAKER_1:  career. You are probably expecting a subject overview, but if you do have them, put them together
SPEAKER_1:  Mini Mic.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  And so.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... he just became not known as it as a doer
SPEAKER_1:  like a guy who'll get it done.
SPEAKER_1:  No excuses, no stops, you know, get it done.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  he had made a name for himself in the CMO.
SPEAKER_1:  Around the time.
SPEAKER_1:  by the time Hubbard and Ruff into seclusion.
SPEAKER_1:  Now when he went off into seclusion, he took two other CMO, or I'm gonna call them messengers, right? Commodore's messengers. He took two other messengers with him.
SPEAKER_1:  Patent Any Broker.
SPEAKER_1:  Now, it has been said...
SPEAKER_1:  Bye people. Mike, Mike Rinder has told me.
SPEAKER_1:  He goes.
SPEAKER_1:  The reason Pat and Annie went off with LRH...
SPEAKER_1:  isn't necessarily because he desperately wanted them to.
SPEAKER_1:  but partly because.
SPEAKER_1:  we could afford to let them go, we didn't.
SPEAKER_1:  necessarily need them. Sure.
SPEAKER_1:  And between the two of them, Annie was the one who was like a really compassionate person.
SPEAKER_1:  intelligent person, caring person.
SPEAKER_0:  Was there a possible trajectory of this world where she was the one that took over? Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  In fact, Pat and any broker.
SPEAKER_1:  were the two people that were supposed to take over.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  because Pat and Amy were with Hubbard in seclusion.
SPEAKER_1:  Miscavige?
SPEAKER_1:  Basically.
SPEAKER_1:  head.
SPEAKER_1:  the complete run of the operation without any oversight from Hubbard.
SPEAKER_1:  the only way any information would get from.
SPEAKER_1:  Scientology World.
SPEAKER_1:  to Hubbard.
SPEAKER_1:  Is Ms. Scavage and Pet Broker would meet at a confidential location?
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  Miscavige would give broker.
SPEAKER_1:  any information he wanted to go to LRH.
SPEAKER_1:  So if Ms. Cavich wanted to get rid of somebody.
SPEAKER_1:  All he had to do was feed LRH false information that this person had been caught doing something treasonous.
SPEAKER_1:  and then he would get in response some order from L. Ron Hubbard to
SPEAKER_1:  get rid of this person.
SPEAKER_1:  Are there so many similarities between various communist regimes?
SPEAKER_1:  and fascist regimes.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, Hitler did the same thing when he became the supreme leader. He had to take power.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, you had to wait for the president to die, but the whole time there's a control and information and a slow aggregation of power. Of course, with nations it's different because if you control the military you control a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's you have to also get the generals on your side and so on, but I'm sure in this situation there is.
SPEAKER_0:  similar kind of dynamics.
SPEAKER_0:  You have to get certain.
SPEAKER_0:  people on your side.
SPEAKER_0:  control the flow of information.
SPEAKER_0:  Let the original
SPEAKER_0:  founder, the original leader, die off?
SPEAKER_0:  and make sure that you are the one that's left with the power.
SPEAKER_1:  Right.
SPEAKER_1:  So, whereas Pat and Annie are off with LRH.
SPEAKER_1:  all of Scientology's attorneys and accountants and lobbyists and whatever.
SPEAKER_1:  They all know.
SPEAKER_1:  Dave.
SPEAKER_1:  Dave's the one they deal with.
SPEAKER_1:  So, you know, LRH passes away, Pat and Nanny make this appearance.
SPEAKER_1:  Nobody knows Pat and Annie.
SPEAKER_1:  Everybody knows Dave.
SPEAKER_1:  And so he ended up getting rid of Pat and Nanny. This is a very short, perhaps slightly bastardized version of it.
SPEAKER_1:  of miscavige basically they had been.
SPEAKER_1:  They had been ushering just suitcases of cash.
SPEAKER_1:  to L. Ron Hubbard during this time.
SPEAKER_1:  And you know, like so you have Miscavige handing boatloads of cash.
SPEAKER_1:  to.
SPEAKER_1:  Pat Broker.
SPEAKER_1:  Pat would do crazy things like hide the money in the walls of houses and dig pits and everything. So.
SPEAKER_1:  Miscavige basically threatened to
SPEAKER_1:  turn pet broker over to the IRS for tax evasion.
SPEAKER_1:  That's part pet brokers still alive.
SPEAKER_0:  is yes i thought
SPEAKER_1:  No
SPEAKER_1:  He basically went away and kept his mouth shut. She died a handful of years ago. She stayed a loyal.
SPEAKER_1:  See you, org member, until the very end.
SPEAKER_1:  But literally, like, Ms. Gavage put her on menial tasks, like...
SPEAKER_1:  Like she had no authority whatsoever. She was just put.
SPEAKER_1:  on menial tasks, washing dishes, but not really groundskeeper, just, just stupid low-level assistant paper pusher stuff.
SPEAKER_1:  She never.
SPEAKER_1:  but she never operated with any actual authority, even though she was supposed to be the one to take over her impact.
SPEAKER_0:  So I'm David Muscarriage.
SPEAKER_0:  Difficult question, but can you make?
SPEAKER_0:  both the case that he is a good man who's misunderstood and the case that he's not a good man.
SPEAKER_1:  First of all, I believe that Miscavige is a true believer in Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  I do believe that. I do believe that.
SPEAKER_0:  important questions. Do you think he believes in all the phatens and all of that?
SPEAKER_1:  He definitely believes in that.
SPEAKER_1:  I think he believes in Scientology but in a different way than all other Scientologists because he's aware of a lot more.
SPEAKER_1:  information, damaging information about.
SPEAKER_1:  of Ron Hubbard and the true story of Scientology than most people. So his version of belief is different. I'll give you one example here.
SPEAKER_1:  So Scientology's bridge to total freedom goes up to what they call OT8, operating thing in level 8.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Scientologists have all been told.
SPEAKER_1:  that L ran Hubbard before he passed.
SPEAKER_1:  Finished, completed, putting together OT9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, and 15.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just sitting in the vault.
SPEAKER_1:  waiting to be released.
SPEAKER_1:  This is part of.
SPEAKER_1:  the Scientology belief system, because remember, I said growing up Scientology's bridge to total freedom is how you're supposed to get back to your native godlike state.
SPEAKER_1:  while all the Scientologists in the world already know that they haven't gotten there.
SPEAKER_1:  they still believe in Scientology because they're told.
SPEAKER_1:  There's more.
SPEAKER_1:  But wait, there's more!
SPEAKER_1:  Miscavige knows there is no more.
SPEAKER_1:  So Miscavige knows.
SPEAKER_1:  the fundamental.
SPEAKER_1:  of being able to achieve full operating Thetan.
SPEAKER_1:  is a lie.
SPEAKER_1:  He knows L. Ron Hubbard didn't accomplish that.
SPEAKER_1:  So therefore...
SPEAKER_1:  no one else is going to accomplish it as well.
SPEAKER_1:  If L. Ron Hubbard had accomplished it.
SPEAKER_1:  Miss Gavage knows, well, he didn't write it up. He didn't.
SPEAKER_1:  but leave instructions for anyone else would accomplish it.
SPEAKER_1:  So no matter what...
SPEAKER_1:  Miscavige knows.
SPEAKER_1:  that the fundamental promise that's not what Scientology is saying, they will be able to deliver to mankind.
SPEAKER_1:  is a lie.
SPEAKER_1:  Now it's gonna sound like I'm contradicting myself because it sounds like I'm saying, he knows it's bullshit.
SPEAKER_1:  I think.
SPEAKER_1:  He believes that L. Ron Hubbard just failed.
SPEAKER_1:  to finish his work.
SPEAKER_1:  and he's kind of hoping that Ron Hubbard's gonna come back to finish the job.
SPEAKER_1:  because L. Ron Hubbard did tell.
SPEAKER_1:  the people at the international management base, at least a core of them.
SPEAKER_1:  that he was coming back.
SPEAKER_1:  Now we know that David Miscavige believed this because right around the 21 year mark, he was supposed to come back like 21 years after he died.
SPEAKER_1:  right around the twenty one year mark
SPEAKER_1:  David Miscavige was getting busy putting some things in place that.
SPEAKER_1:  had to get done in case L. Ron Hubbard came back. So we know he.
SPEAKER_1:  at least believe to that level.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you believe that Elrond and Hubbard can-
SPEAKER_0:  sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  Enter his own body? No.
SPEAKER_1:  That's not how.
SPEAKER_1:  in Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  So you can't have a transfer.
SPEAKER_0:  Satan's.
SPEAKER_1:  If you were full OT, you could.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you describe the OT again? So OT levels OT 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 to the 8.
SPEAKER_0:  What, uh, what are they? What's, how do you get to level one?
SPEAKER_1:  I'm gonna answer this question by first connecting some dots. Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  We spoke early in the interview about achieving your native godlike.
SPEAKER_1:  Yes. State that in Scientology is called native state.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, native state.
SPEAKER_1:  and full operating Thetan mean the exact same thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, because that native state, you are a fully.
SPEAKER_1:  operating.
SPEAKER_1:  Theta.
SPEAKER_1:  operating in your full capacity.
SPEAKER_1:  So OT means Operating Thing.
SPEAKER_1:  So the upper confidential half of Scientology's bridge called the OT levels, the operating Thain levels.
SPEAKER_1:  And these...
SPEAKER_1:  And remember, they're confidential, so.
SPEAKER_1:  Most Scientologists have not done these levels.
SPEAKER_1:  They don't know what's on them.
SPEAKER_1:  It is on these levels that you learn.
SPEAKER_1:  about the Xenu and the body Phaeton story. When you wanna hear more about the story please support critter series website at click then click 202 L Campus bonus by clicking t yrowth
SPEAKER_0:  And practising Absten Rico plus.
SPEAKER_1:  We spoke earlier about how at the lower.
SPEAKER_1:  non-confidential levels of Scientology's bridge, Hubbard is saying that what's wrong with you is your reactive mind.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, in Scientology, once you've gotten rid of your reactive mind, that is what's called the state of clear.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so after you finish state of clear, the next thing on the bridge is the OT levels.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, if you've already gotten rid of your active mind, what the heck are you supposed to do now? Well now, L. Ron Hubbard says.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, first what was wrong with you was just your reactive mind.
SPEAKER_1:  but now the next thing you have to resolve, the next thing that's wrong with you is you actually have tens of thousands
SPEAKER_1:  of Phaetons stuck to your body.
SPEAKER_1:  and they all have their own reactive minds.
SPEAKER_1:  You have to audit.
SPEAKER_0:  the Phaetans.
SPEAKER_0:  How do you audit the things, these like different?
SPEAKER_0:  shades of your inner mind.
SPEAKER_0:  and you have to try to access them somehow.
SPEAKER_1:  You use the emitter.
SPEAKER_1:  like we spoke about except now you've got a divider that separates the cans so they don't short-circuit and you hold both cans in one hand
SPEAKER_1:  and you have the emitter in front of you. So now you're auditing yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  you're telepathically.
SPEAKER_1:  talking.
SPEAKER_1:  to the things that are stuck to you.
SPEAKER_1:  you are thinking the commands instead of saying them out loud.
SPEAKER_1:  and you sort of do drills where you practice looking for emitter reads at the instant you have a thought.
SPEAKER_1:  You're telepathically
SPEAKER_1:  auditing spirits that L. Ron Hubbard says are stuck to your body.
SPEAKER_1:  Does this sound like a recipe for a mental breakdown?
SPEAKER_0:  or a head governmental journey.
SPEAKER_0:  Wherever that leads, it could lead anywhere. It probably leads to a very bad place, right?
SPEAKER_1:  very often does.
SPEAKER_1:  And you combine that with the fact that Scientology is against any forms of mental help or health.
SPEAKER_1:  outside of Scientology and you have a recipe for disaster.
SPEAKER_1:  Now.
SPEAKER_1:  You might go, where did all these spirits come from that are stuck to your body?
SPEAKER_1:  This is where Xenu comes into play.
SPEAKER_1:  So Hubbard says that 75 million years ago...
SPEAKER_1:  Zinu was basically...
SPEAKER_1:  A Dictator app.
SPEAKER_1:  The Galactic Confederation is like 70 something or 80 something planets somewhere in the Milky Way. And Xenu was like.
SPEAKER_1:  A dictator and overlord for either one of these planets or the whole system.
SPEAKER_1:  and they had a population problem.
SPEAKER_1:  And Xenu was like...
SPEAKER_1:  we need to get rid of like half the people.
SPEAKER_1:  So we called them all in for tax audits.
SPEAKER_1:  Alron Hubbard didn't like the IRS. So of course the story has to do with tax audits.
SPEAKER_1:  Call them all in for tax audits.
SPEAKER_1:  Said psych bitches!
SPEAKER_1:  froze them in glycol.
SPEAKER_1:  Loaded them up on space planes.
SPEAKER_1:  flew them to Earth.
SPEAKER_1:  Remember the story has to be earth because the story is what's wrong with us.
SPEAKER_1:  dropped them in volcanoes, blew them up with hydrogen bombs.
SPEAKER_1:  and then captured them with like spirit magnets. I'm making up words because okay.
SPEAKER_1:  uh...
SPEAKER_1:  and these
SPEAKER_1:  disembodied.
SPEAKER_1:  spirits of these people that got blown up.
SPEAKER_1:  have just been blown in the wind here on Earth and they attach themselves to things.
SPEAKER_1:  and they can be in the environment and they stick to bodies and everything.
SPEAKER_1:  And so, and they all have reactive minds.
SPEAKER_1:  So at Scientology's upper levels, if you get sick or you have cancer or there's something wrong with you...
SPEAKER_1:  Scientology will say.
SPEAKER_1:  That's one of your body things. You need to get some auditing to fix the body thing. PoWadk Je  children asd, hisste
SPEAKER_0:  story.
SPEAKER_0:  You do it with a bit of a chuckle.
SPEAKER_0:  But when done seriously...
SPEAKER_0:  So it's just told in a serious way.
SPEAKER_0:  Like to, like, or written down. It's right.
SPEAKER_1:  and you read it. By most accounts, Scientologists struggle when they read this for the first time because this is not consistent with what
SPEAKER_1:  Scientologists are hoping for is on the RT levels. They're hoping for some real life changing magic. The way these things are described and sold there.
SPEAKER_1:  Remember, they're hoping that these OT levels are going to give them the ability to go completely.
SPEAKER_1:  independent of their body at will. Yeah. Steer eyes from your body, go back into your body, you know, like.
SPEAKER_1:  have some real spirit powers.
SPEAKER_0:  The first is kind of a shock.
SPEAKER_0:  But then you still probably believe you hope.
SPEAKER_0:  And you might turn it on yourself, self-critical that this is, I'm just not.
SPEAKER_0:  strong enough yet.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, because also part of the Scientology member, it works 100% of the time when used 100% correctly. And if it doesn't...
SPEAKER_1:  It could be because something's not being done right, but it also could be because.
SPEAKER_1:  You're doing bad things that you're not telling people about.
SPEAKER_1:  Like if you're committing present time.
SPEAKER_1:  over its crimes, sins,
SPEAKER_1:  Scientologists would be like, that's part of the reason auditing isn't working on you is because you're
SPEAKER_1:  committing criminal behavior that you're not being honest about.
SPEAKER_1:  So every Scientologist is sort of incentivized to
SPEAKER_1:  to make auditing work on them.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Now Lex this is where it gets a little crazy.
SPEAKER_1:  On OT3 you learn about the body things for the first time.
SPEAKER_1:  When you finish OT3, you attest to having achieved this state of having no more body things.
SPEAKER_1:  and then you start O2-4.
SPEAKER_1:  And he's like, psych.
SPEAKER_1:  You got more.
SPEAKER_1:  You got more BTs.
SPEAKER_1:  except those other BTs, they had drug problems and that's why you couldn't find them the first time.
SPEAKER_1:  So we're gonna do a little something a little different here, do something a little different there. Gotta get rid of these BTs that were addicted to drugs. Okay, then you finish OT4 and you're thinking.
SPEAKER_1:  Man, I hope we get to the good stuff soon.
SPEAKER_1:  and then you get to OT5 and he's like, Sike, you got more BTs.
SPEAKER_1:  You couldn't find these BTs because they were all bunched up together in clusters. And first you have to break up the clusters and then you can get rid of the BTs. And you're like, okay.
SPEAKER_0:  Gotta do that.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is all Elrond Howard approved.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, this is from L.R.
SPEAKER_1:  and then after you finish OT5 you get rid of all the BT clusters. OT6 is just a training course to teach how to auto OT7.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, T7...
SPEAKER_1:  Is now more BTs except it's in the environment and stuff. You're trying to locate BTs. You can find them on your body, but it's just more BTs.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  and then OT8.
SPEAKER_1:  is remember we talked about in all these auditing sessions throughout the entire Scientology bridge.
SPEAKER_1:  You have people who've run hundreds or thousands of past life, whole track incidents.
SPEAKER_1:  These memories have become part of their self-identity of who they even think they are.
SPEAKER_1:  OT8.
SPEAKER_1:  You go through all these past life recalls and essentially I'm oversimplifying this a little bit. He goes, psych.
SPEAKER_1:  All those past life memories weren't yours.
SPEAKER_1:  They were your BTs.
SPEAKER_1:  And he goes, now.
SPEAKER_1:  that you've discovered this.
SPEAKER_1:  Now you know who you are not.
SPEAKER_1:  and you are ready to find out who you really are.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, now you're supposed to find out who you really are on OT9 and 10.
SPEAKER_1:  Those don't exist!
SPEAKER_1:  Do we know they don't exist? Yes.
SPEAKER_1:  In fact, the whole story of how that became known.
SPEAKER_1:  is part of how.
SPEAKER_1:  David Miscavige was able to get rid of Pat Broker.
SPEAKER_1:  and take over power because.
SPEAKER_1:  It was believed that Pat Broker had been, was in possession of the upper unreleased OT levels and when Miscavige determined
SPEAKER_1:  that he was not and there weren't in fact any levels?
SPEAKER_1:  That was bad. That was a bad day to be David Miscavige because he now knew he had something on his hands he could not get himself out of. He's like, oh, sh-
SPEAKER_0:  So there's no gap.
SPEAKER_0:  for faith to seep in that there is.
SPEAKER_0:  level 9 and 10 11 and 12. Oh the f-
SPEAKER_1:  faith is there.
SPEAKER_1:  Scientologists believe that these things do exist. Zbar however is incredibly hahaha
SPEAKER_1:  Rod Hubbard didn't leave anything.
SPEAKER_0:  behind? Does David Miscavige believe they exist?
SPEAKER_1:  Oh no, he knows they don't exist.
SPEAKER_1:  No, I mean, when I say exist, oh, I don't mean do advanced.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... levels of spiritual awareness exists
SPEAKER_1:  When I said, is it, means did L Ron Hubbard write down.
SPEAKER_1:  what anyone is supposed to do that's called OT9.
SPEAKER_1:  That doesn't exist. These.
SPEAKER_0:  David Miscavige believes.
SPEAKER_0:  the day.
SPEAKER_0:  can be written down so they exist in a platonic sense.
SPEAKER_0:  and
SPEAKER_0:  Elrond Harbert is the only one that can
SPEAKER_0:  Write it down? So his face is really deep.
SPEAKER_1:  You mean his faith that only Elron Hubbard could have ever been the one to do it? The f-
SPEAKER_0:  The full principles, beliefs of Scientology, he is...
SPEAKER_0:  Jeff
SPEAKER_0:  Are you sure, he believes?
SPEAKER_0:  That what exactly?
SPEAKER_0:  everything about Scientology that is true.
SPEAKER_1:  To the best of my ability to know that, I believe it to be true.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I'll give you some all even stupid examples like Mike renders told a story.
SPEAKER_1:  where at the international base, Miscavige actually had like
SPEAKER_1:  Hopper.
SPEAKER_1:  a contraption built into the ground.
SPEAKER_1:  grounded into the ground.
SPEAKER_1:  come out where you could.
SPEAKER_1:  and here's something he sort of came up with too.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... your bt your because ground your bt's
SPEAKER_1:  could get your BTs that if you're feeling over stimulated or something, I'm probably slightly bastardizing this story.
SPEAKER_1:  He came up with this as a great idea, something to help someone.
SPEAKER_1:  destimulate if their BTs were getting a little too overactive. Now, so that's a stupid story that's sort of like...
SPEAKER_1:  It shows you he believes in the concept of BTs of his creating little rods to get rid of them to ground them into the earth.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, he could be conjuring up the stories because...
SPEAKER_0:  He understands the power of myth and narrative and so on to...
SPEAKER_0:  inspire.
SPEAKER_0:  Sure, but like.
SPEAKER_0:  but also if we look at history.
SPEAKER_0:  both with, this is an interesting thing because I've been reading a lot about Hitler installing
SPEAKER_0:  It seems like...
SPEAKER_0:  both of them in different ways.
SPEAKER_0:  believed.
SPEAKER_0:  in the stories they were telling.
SPEAKER_0:  Even when the stories, this is the fascinating, especially with Hitler and propaganda.
SPEAKER_0:  where they were literally conjured up at first.
SPEAKER_0:  but then you start to believe you're in propaganda.
SPEAKER_0:  With Stalin, I think what he always believed is the bigger ideal of pure communism.
SPEAKER_0:  and anything justifies.
SPEAKER_0:  the journey to communism because it will ultimately be.
SPEAKER_0:  Good.
SPEAKER_0:  for humanity to achieve the state of pure communism. And then he's a godlike figure that can...
SPEAKER_0:  can bring.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... can bring humanity there
SPEAKER_0:  But like...
SPEAKER_0:  Well, Hitler is interesting because like this constant propaganda.
SPEAKER_0:  that he knows is not true.
SPEAKER_0:  A little bit. There's gotta be doubt.
SPEAKER_0:  But then he like did all doubt is removed very quickly.
SPEAKER_0:  I guess humans are just this.
SPEAKER_1:  how they operate.
SPEAKER_1:  The conversation about David Miscavige gets really interesting because I could give you a- if I wanted to make the argument that he didn't believe-
SPEAKER_1:  I could give you a dozen examples to make that argument. I just happen.
SPEAKER_1:  to think that.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, he believes.
SPEAKER_1:  in a different
SPEAKER_1:  way.
SPEAKER_1:  Whereas your average Scientologist
SPEAKER_1:  believes that Alvarran Hubbard was practically infallible, that he thought of everything in advance, he took care of everything before he left.
SPEAKER_1:  and Miscavige still believes in like the main structure of this thing.
SPEAKER_1:  But he's like, ah shit.
SPEAKER_1:  It's falling to me to figure out how to actually.
SPEAKER_1:  make this thing happen.
SPEAKER_1:  I think Miscavige sees himself as someone who has to a certain degree had to go back and fix all of Hubbard's mistakes.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you think he sees himself as doing good for the world? I do.
SPEAKER_0:  What about for the people of Scientology?
SPEAKER_1:  I think in his own way he does.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't think he wakes up thinking he's.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  screwing Scientologists.
SPEAKER_1:  I think he sees everyone else as screwing him.
SPEAKER_1:  I think he sees.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... that it that it is his job to expand scientology throughout the world and accomplish the ends of scientology and he sees that it's not happening
SPEAKER_1:  and he thinks if everyone else would just stop.
SPEAKER_1:  If everyone else would get out of his way and stop creating problems for him, it would happen like-
SPEAKER_1:  Uh-uh.
SPEAKER_1:  I do think he sees himself as someone who is doing.
SPEAKER_1:  Good.
SPEAKER_1:  I think that's fair to say.
SPEAKER_1:  I think the evidence shows that.
SPEAKER_0:  What about the effects of...
SPEAKER_0:  clearly power and influence that he's had and money.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, without question that has served as a corrupting force.
SPEAKER_0:  It has without question. Have you seen sort of evidence of that, that he's changed over time?
SPEAKER_1:  after the 1993 IRS exemption.
SPEAKER_1:  that Scientology won back.
SPEAKER_1:  and this information comes from Mike Rinder.
SPEAKER_1:  That's when
SPEAKER_1:  David Miscavige.
SPEAKER_1:  As soon as the checks on his power were removed, Ms. Gavish's behavior changed markedly.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you tell the story of Shelley, Miss Gavage, and the mystery surrounding her? I saw that there is quite a bit of mystery.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  So Shelley Miscavige.
SPEAKER_1:  for many years held the job.
SPEAKER_1:  host in this organization was.
SPEAKER_1:  David Miscavige's assistant.
SPEAKER_1:  That was her post.
SPEAKER_1:  It's important to truly understand.
SPEAKER_1:  that and what that means because
SPEAKER_1:  The fact that she was Miss Gavage's wife.
SPEAKER_1:  is meaningless.
SPEAKER_1:  And this is something that's hard to.
SPEAKER_1:  for regular people in the regular world to truly grasp how meaningless it is in Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  for Sea Org members who are spouses.
SPEAKER_1:  It means nothing.
SPEAKER_1:  your role matters more.
SPEAKER_1:  Within C-Worg. Your role is the only thing that matters.
SPEAKER_1:  So let's say if Shelly was married to Dave.
SPEAKER_1:  But she...
SPEAKER_1:  worked in a different organization.
SPEAKER_1:  she would never be seen with him.
SPEAKER_1:  ever. who have microchipped their
SPEAKER_1:  Wouldn't travel with him.
SPEAKER_1:  Wouldn't go to events with him, nothing.
SPEAKER_1:  Sometime around.
SPEAKER_1:  2016-2007.
SPEAKER_1:  and i'm very oversimplifying
SPEAKER_1:  Shelly basically pissed off Dave to the point where he's like, okay, I'm done with you.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm going to take you off of your post.
SPEAKER_1:  At that point, she was reassigned to another.
SPEAKER_1:  Confidential Scientology Base up in Twin Peaks, California.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, why am I the reason I'm providing
SPEAKER_1:  this type of detail is because we hear that Shelley's missing.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  You realize the same people who report that Shelly's missing are also the same people who will tell you exactly where she is.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, she works at this secretive CST.
SPEAKER_1:  Church of Spiritual Technology Bay-Soutan.
SPEAKER_1:  Twin Peaks, California.
SPEAKER_1:  I have-
SPEAKER_1:  personal confirmation.
SPEAKER_1:  that she was seen.
SPEAKER_1:  and spoken with.
SPEAKER_1:  by someone who knew her well.
SPEAKER_1:  in.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll say 2019.
SPEAKER_1:  Shelley Miscavige is missing in the sense that.
SPEAKER_1:  She hasn't been seen with David Miscavige since about 2006.
SPEAKER_1:  but because she's no longer his assistant.
SPEAKER_1:  You would never see her with him.
SPEAKER_0:  As opposed to the mystery of a person that might be murdered, this is more of a...
SPEAKER_0:  reallocation within the organization.
SPEAKER_1:  Certain people.
SPEAKER_1:  who cover Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  who have published stories.
SPEAKER_1:  where Shelley's Miscavige's family member told.
SPEAKER_1:  A story to another family member who told the story to a friend who told the story to a former Scientologist who told the story to a journalist who published the story.
SPEAKER_1:  has created the impression that some of Shelley Miscavige's family members are actually talking to the press.
SPEAKER_1:  when in fact that has never occurred.
SPEAKER_1:  And so the very people who are publishing about Shelley Miscavige missing have contributed to the fact that Shelley Miscavige does no longer speak to those family members.
SPEAKER_1:  because she thinks they're talking to the press.
SPEAKER_1:  when they never have.
SPEAKER_1:  pretty messed up.
SPEAKER_0:  It's sad that she, because those family members, what would be a way for her to...
SPEAKER_0:  to recover to...
SPEAKER_0:  to flourish as a human being to escape.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  I believe.
SPEAKER_1:  the information that I have that I verified. I'm putting out, I'm the one representing it's true without revealing my sources. Culture
SPEAKER_1:  that Shelley was still actively in touch regularly.
SPEAKER_1:  with family members outside of the C organization until about 2014.
SPEAKER_1:  So, I mean, regularly.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so there's no question about her safety.
SPEAKER_1:  during that period.
SPEAKER_1:  and then someone else who knew Shelley very well.
SPEAKER_1:  Did see her and actually have a conversation with her in a public place
SPEAKER_1:  in 2019 or 2020.
SPEAKER_1:  Now somebody could still come along and be like, how do we know she's okay? It's been three years. Yeah, okay, you can say that about anybody. There's the nature of working in the highest levels of Scientology management at the super secretive basis.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a very weird and unique situation. It has isolation baked in.
SPEAKER_0:  house secrecy enforced.
SPEAKER_0:  Why is everybody...
SPEAKER_0:  holding on to their stories so intensely.
SPEAKER_0:  people that are within the organization. Like this for hard to leak.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, they wouldn't want to leak. They're true believers.
SPEAKER_1:  They see.
SPEAKER_1:  They see like there's sort of a conspiracy theory that runs right through all of Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  which is that Scientology represents an existential threat.
SPEAKER_1:  to the powers that really control this planet.
SPEAKER_0:  Do they have a...
SPEAKER_0:  Face to the powers that are really controlled. FACE TO THE POWERS THAT ARE REALLY CONTROLLED.
SPEAKER_0:  Names to it? Like who's controlling? It's Znews Homies.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I'm sure that's not what they say. Xeno...
SPEAKER_1:  embodied in it's actually sort of a multifaceted
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  conspiracy in that on the one hand
SPEAKER_1:  L. Ron Hubbard points his fingers at the international bankers.
SPEAKER_1:  which has shades of antisemitism to it.
SPEAKER_0:  And then the IRS is going to be quickly.
SPEAKER_1:  Big 10 or no? The IRS, no, the IRS is so low on the totem pole as far as the, I mean, the international bankers, he would say runs everything.
SPEAKER_1:  But use that these bankers also use big pharma.
SPEAKER_1:  and big psych.
SPEAKER_1:  to control the population.
SPEAKER_1:  and Scientology is famously against.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Pharma and Psych. And so this is sort of how L. Ron Hubbard characterizes like this big war between Scientology that's trying to set everyone free and Big Pharma and Big Psych that's trying to enslave everyone on the planet.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  controlling their mind, controlling their body through chemical
SPEAKER_1:  and who controls the press.
SPEAKER_1:  Big Pharma and Big Psych.
SPEAKER_0:  So there's a lot of correlation to other kinds of conspiracy theories. So my name's William Walker and I've joined you in the
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Ah, that's fascinating.
SPEAKER_1:  But you asked the question.
SPEAKER_1:  where, uh,
SPEAKER_1:  why would all these people hold onto their stories? they would never want to leak
SPEAKER_1:  like.
SPEAKER_1:  by even
SPEAKER_1:  Anyone who would want to leak?
SPEAKER_1:  would not even want to be a Scientologist anymore.
SPEAKER_1:  Like if you truly believe in Scientology and you got your shoulder to the wheel and you're a CERC member.
SPEAKER_1:  You think Scientology is literally the only thing.
SPEAKER_1:  that can save every being on this planet from a fate of eternal amnesia.
SPEAKER_1:  and slavery.
SPEAKER_1:  Right? So it's like, I mean, you've seen the matrix, right?
SPEAKER_1:  So you've got everyone once you're unplugged from the matrix.
SPEAKER_1:  And you realize, yeah, you can get plugged back in.
SPEAKER_1:  and live your nice life, but you're a slave.
SPEAKER_1:  That's how Scientologists see this planet.
SPEAKER_1:  Next time.
SPEAKER_1:  they refer to Earth as a prison planet.
SPEAKER_1:  Just an-
SPEAKER_0:  Individual level, how is it possible to reach a person like that?
SPEAKER_0:  Is there something you could say to that? What's the journey of reaching a person like that?
SPEAKER_1:  I personally...
SPEAKER_1:  because.
SPEAKER_1:  because of when I was in those shoes.
SPEAKER_1:  I say there's nothing anybody could have said to me.
SPEAKER_1:  to get me to change.
SPEAKER_1:  how I felt and thought about Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  It's almost foolproof.
SPEAKER_1:  that the more evidence you try to present that there's something.
SPEAKER_1:  wrong with what Scientology is doing.
SPEAKER_1:  the more you're just working for the psychs.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  It's very, very difficult. I mean, most people.
SPEAKER_1:  who leave Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  leave because they have.
SPEAKER_1:  had some personal experience that was just such a grave injustice.
SPEAKER_1:  that it just pushed them.
SPEAKER_1:  Beyond.
SPEAKER_1:  the point of what they're willing to experience.
SPEAKER_1:  Very rare, I've never, I'm not sure I've really ever heard a story of someone going, yeah, I just woke up, you know, I just gradually realized it was all BS and drifted away.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, it's usually like.
SPEAKER_1:  No.
SPEAKER_1:  I really believed and they treated me so horribly.
SPEAKER_1:  I almost had no choice.
SPEAKER_1:  but to leave. And then the stories get pretty crazy.
SPEAKER_0:  Meaning you don't care what's true anymore. You just have to leave with this, the unpleasant feeling, the suffering. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  And this sort of goes back to...
SPEAKER_1:  the conversation we're having about like, well, does Miscavige really believe?
SPEAKER_1:  And I said I could make an argument for the fact that he doesn't, right?
SPEAKER_1:  because I go.
SPEAKER_1:  It wouldn't be that hard.
SPEAKER_1:  to change the way Scientology treats people.
SPEAKER_1:  just a little bit.
SPEAKER_1:  and you'd probably stop losing.
SPEAKER_1:  anyone because Scientologists already believe to such a strong degree. You have to be pretty freaking horrible to people to make him leave.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's where you go.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, does Miscavige even want Scientology to expand? Cause if he was really being clever about it, it seems like he could at least stop the bleeding.
SPEAKER_1:  And yet he doesn't.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's where you make the argument, well if he doesn't then he must not want to.
SPEAKER_0:  So his mind is corrupted to the point where he's not able to actually...
SPEAKER_0:  be a good businessman essentially.
SPEAKER_1:  It seems that way.
SPEAKER_1:  The numbers of Scientologists have been going down and down and down since the early 90s.
SPEAKER_0:  Is there a good?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, it's very difficult to get to this number.
SPEAKER_0:  but is there a good estimate of what the current number of scientists or practicing Scientologists is?
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah, I did a video about this. It's actually quite easy to get some of the number.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not more than 35,000 in the entire world.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's being very generous and charitable. I was intentionally generous. I broke it all down in a spreadsheet and everything.
SPEAKER_0:  What can you give like some insights of how you get that?
SPEAKER_1:  Sure, there's about 175 to 200 Scientology organizations in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  anybody who's
SPEAKER_1:  ever worked at these organizations, no.
SPEAKER_1:  There's not more than 35 to 50 staff members per org.
SPEAKER_1:  There's not more than one to 200 public Scientologists per org.
SPEAKER_1:  I broke down the number of Sea Org members who'd be working at every continental management unit.
SPEAKER_1:  middle management.
SPEAKER_1:  international management.
SPEAKER_1:  I broke it on the Mission Network and I was generous.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, my numbers were like, if L. Ron Hubbard came back.
SPEAKER_1:  and they were doing an event.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  L. Ron Hubbard was coming back and announcing OT9 and 10? How many Scientologists could we scrape together in every city to come to this event?
SPEAKER_1:  It wasn't more than 35,000.
SPEAKER_1:  Now contrast that to what Scientology says.
SPEAKER_1:  millions, 10 million.
SPEAKER_1:  people.
SPEAKER_0:  Is this less people than there used to be?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, at its peak it was about 100,000 active members.
SPEAKER_0:  but never the millions.
SPEAKER_0:  has David Miscavige.
SPEAKER_0:  used violence.
SPEAKER_0:  ballpark message, haserb. Hey, BirdieBoy. Here to help saving Pokemon Wilson's ? ongoing feedback from Link. We need to find out if it works working for According to its power pouch. Let's see if this works. Let's see. It works, it's working. It works. It works, it's working. Hello? Over yet again. You gave me a solution. Did you you teach me how to cook and cook it myself? WOW. Last time. Yes, I did. First time. First time. Thank you for watching and please subscribe to my channel. You can say so yourself. As ever. We're going
SPEAKER_0:  in your understanding of it and your estimation sort of.
SPEAKER_0:  harassment assault and actual
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know how to define assault, but violence. Oh yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  dozens.
SPEAKER_1:  of former Sea Org members from the International Base.
SPEAKER_1:  have told stories of being assaulted by Miscavige. In fact,
SPEAKER_1:  Mic Render.
SPEAKER_1:  is probably the one person who's been assaulted by...
SPEAKER_1:  Miscavige more than anyone else.
SPEAKER_1:  He's personally probably been assaulted dozens of times.
SPEAKER_0:  Who is Mike Rinder?
SPEAKER_1:  So man, you're one of the highest ranking executives in Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  The Author
SPEAKER_1:  There you go, a billion years. A billion years.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a really is a fantastic book. Just like the guy.
SPEAKER_1:  If the guy was born and raised in Scientology and worked personally with L. Ron Hubbard and worked personally with David Miscavige for decades, it doesn't get much more insider than that.
SPEAKER_0:  A candid and deeply felt memoir of a life lost to false belief.
SPEAKER_0:  and courageously regained.
SPEAKER_0:  Lawrence Wright.
SPEAKER_0:  A billion years my escape from a life in the highest ranks of Scientology, my grander.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a fantastic book.
SPEAKER_1:  He also narrates his own audio book too. I know you like the audio books. That's how I listen to it. Thank you for listening.
SPEAKER_1:  So Mike, famously, you know, I just said a moment ago, like.
SPEAKER_1:  someone who's treated so horribly, even though he still believes in Scientology, he had no choice but to leave.
SPEAKER_1:  And he tells the story in that book, and he still believed in Scientology for years after he escaped.
SPEAKER_1:  for years.
SPEAKER_1:  Because there's this thing called the independent Scientology movement or the free zone or whatever. There are people who do Scientology outside of the Church of Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  There's just not many of them.
SPEAKER_1:  but Mike was one of those people.
SPEAKER_1:  who was actually doing Scientology even after he left. Now he no longer believes in that anymore and he doesn't do it.
SPEAKER_1:  but even though he still believed, even though.
SPEAKER_1:  Everything he knew.
SPEAKER_1:  was what he was leaving behind.
SPEAKER_1:  He still had to leave it behind.
SPEAKER_0:  And by the way, I just opened a random page and he says.
SPEAKER_0:  when I signed on for C-ORG in Adelaide in 1973.
SPEAKER_0:  The recruiter promised I would train as a Scientology executive under the direct tutelage of Hubbard on the Apollo.
SPEAKER_0:  This is another thing I should probably ask you about this.
SPEAKER_1:  We can go for days.
SPEAKER_0:  I was also told that after I learned all I needed to learn at the foot of the Master,
SPEAKER_0:  I would return to Australia to help expand Scientology in my home country.
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_0:  What was the thing that really broke him?
SPEAKER_1:  The final thing.
SPEAKER_1:  is when
SPEAKER_1:  He got to a point where he was no longer being forced to lie to protect a run Hubbard.
SPEAKER_1:  He was now being forced to lie to protect David Miscavige.
SPEAKER_1:  And specifically, it was about the allegations of having been assaulted by Miscavige.
SPEAKER_1:  Mic render.
SPEAKER_1:  was at some event. It might have been a grand opening for a building, a Scientology building in London.
SPEAKER_1:  And I believe it was John Sweeney, at that time a BBC journalist.
SPEAKER_1:  who stuck a camera and a microphone in Mike's face. Is it true David Miscavige assaulted you? Is it true?
SPEAKER_1:  and Mike denied it on camera.
SPEAKER_1:  and then turned around and to himself is like.
SPEAKER_1:  This is what.
SPEAKER_1:  my life has been reduced to?
SPEAKER_1:  lying to protect David Miscavige?
SPEAKER_1:  This used to be about Elrond Hobbird.
SPEAKER_1:  This used to be about.
SPEAKER_1:  Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  Now it's about protecting this douchebag?
SPEAKER_1:  and Miscavige had just issued orders.
SPEAKER_1:  that was gonna send Mike.
SPEAKER_1:  Off to Australia.
SPEAKER_1:  Miscavige is sadistic.
SPEAKER_1:  That is.
SPEAKER_1:  That is without question.
SPEAKER_1:  Sadistic meaning he enjoys inflicting pain upon others
SPEAKER_1:  So he very specifically was gonna tell Mike, tell Render, or tell that cocksucker, we're shipping him off to Australia. He's never gonna see his wife and his kids again, essentially.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's what Mike was like.
SPEAKER_1:  They were the only reason I hadn't already left.
SPEAKER_1:  So if I follow the orders...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm gonna lose them.
SPEAKER_1:  If I leave Scientology, I'm gonna lose them.
SPEAKER_1:  At least if I leave Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll be free of something.
SPEAKER_1:  fucking sad.
SPEAKER_0:  and he still believed.
SPEAKER_0:  Scientology to some degree after you left, is what you're saying.
SPEAKER_0:  Has he spoken about what it took to let go of believing in Scientology?
SPEAKER_1:  He does a very good job talking about all of this in the book.
SPEAKER_1:  It took him like four or five years to get that book done.
SPEAKER_1:  polished version.
SPEAKER_1:  polished version of his story. And I think Mike's about getting ready to start his own YouTube channel, so that'll be a lot of fun. Actually, Mike comes on my channel all the time.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, you guys do a thing together, right? Yeah, we do. Three amigos with me and Mike Rinder and Mark Headley. That's why I gave you Mark's book. I thought maybe you would know him from our little three amigos, our Mondays with Mike and Mark videos. Mark Headley.
SPEAKER_0:  BALONE FOR GOOD
SPEAKER_0:  behind the Iron Curtain of Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  So he escaped from the international base on a motorcycle. It's a wild story.
SPEAKER_1:  I won't even try to do it justice, but. Who's a better writer?
SPEAKER_0:  out of the tooth.
SPEAKER_1:  You're not gonna get me there, like.
SPEAKER_0:  I'm trying to be investigative journalist.
SPEAKER_1:  Mike and Mark are both on the board of the Aftermath Foundation with me.
SPEAKER_1:  So who's better looking?
SPEAKER_0:  Knives. W lemonade.
SPEAKER_1:  It's one of my justifications for just putting up content every day is every video is just an excuse to
SPEAKER_1:  in some little way promote the Aftermath Foundation. And I do that again.
SPEAKER_1:  One, to genuinely help people escape.
SPEAKER_1:  And two, because I know it drives David Miscavige crazy.
SPEAKER_0:  If you look in your own heart, is there anger there?
SPEAKER_1:  I don't think it's anger.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't hate, I don't hate Scientology. I don't hate David Miscavige.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't even hate my experience in Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  be able to.
SPEAKER_0:  Accept the good.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. From your experience. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Absolutely.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's also the only path that I traveled.
SPEAKER_1:  So I tend.
SPEAKER_1:  No, I'm okay, a little less so these days, but.
SPEAKER_1:  earlier in life.
SPEAKER_1:  I tended to attribute all positive characteristics in me to Scientology because in my simplistic way of thinking I was like...
SPEAKER_1:  what else could it possibly be attributed to? that's a very black and white way of saying it
SPEAKER_0:  Beautiful way to see life. No matter what happens to you, you attribute.
SPEAKER_0:  Like you focus on the positive. Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  And you feel like sometimes people have traumatic experiences with parents and so on. Yeah. And if you focus on the positive.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a good way to let go. Right.
SPEAKER_0:  of the trauma associated with it. True
SPEAKER_1:  But like another example would be like, I didn't go to school. Like I stopped going to school in the seventh grade, but people go, but you sound so smart.
SPEAKER_1:  And what am I supposed to do? Am I supposed to say, well, that's because of Scientology?
SPEAKER_1:  How do I answer that question?
SPEAKER_1:  Like, if it's the only path I traveled.
SPEAKER_1:  How do I answer that question? I don't necessarily wanna give Scientology credit, but what the hell am I supposed to point to?
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, you said.
SPEAKER_0:  There's...
SPEAKER_0:  you kind of enjoy, I mean part of it is you joking and trolling, that you enjoy knowing that your YouTube channel
SPEAKER_0:  drives David Miscavige crazy.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, what?
SPEAKER_0:  That means you still, I mean, there is a joy.
SPEAKER_1:  You have. There is a joy. I'm not going to deny that.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know what to make of that, because I suppose there's an intimacy.
SPEAKER_0:  when you're part of a tribe of that kind.
SPEAKER_1:  It's almost like, let me try it out.
SPEAKER_1:  Let me try to frame it.
SPEAKER_1:  I wasn't trying to get kicked out of Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  I was trying to not get kicked out of Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  I, you know, so what happened first? First, my mom got kicked out for basically talking some smack about David Miscavige.
SPEAKER_1:  And then they go to me and they go, okay, you've got a disconnect from your mom or you're gonna get kicked out.
SPEAKER_1:  And I lied about that. I was like, okay, I'll disconnect. But I never did. For a couple years, I lied my ass off about it.
SPEAKER_1:  Eventually they were like
SPEAKER_1:  This guy's gonna keep lying to us, right?
SPEAKER_1:  And they're like, yeah, like, all right, you're out.
SPEAKER_1:  So then they go to my wife, say you gotta divorce your husband you're gonna get kicked out.
SPEAKER_1:  And she goes, no.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a hell of a statement from her.
SPEAKER_1:  It's going to get harder from here. It's okay, ifuk yeah, If tell acknowledgement that
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not quite sure how to...
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, I'll try to get, I'll try to do my best. I don't seem like a man who's afraid of hard things.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  So she's like.
SPEAKER_1:  No.
SPEAKER_1:  then they go to her parents.
SPEAKER_1:  and they say, you've got a disconnect from your daughter.
SPEAKER_1:  and your three granddaughters.
SPEAKER_1:  or you're gonna get kicked out.
SPEAKER_1:  but they have three other kids who are Scientologists.
SPEAKER_1:  who have spouses who are Scientologists, who have grandkids.
SPEAKER_1:  So I feel like.
SPEAKER_1:  Up until that point, everybody was sort of making a decision for themselves and what would be best for themselves.
SPEAKER_1:  until they get to her parents.
SPEAKER_1:  And then they're like
SPEAKER_1:  Which grandkids are we going to lose?
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  at the part where they were trying to get me to disconnect from my mom.
SPEAKER_1:  They work.
SPEAKER_1:  that I spent talking to them going...
SPEAKER_1:  You know guys.
SPEAKER_1:  There's another way.
SPEAKER_1:  It doesn't have to go this way.
SPEAKER_1:  There's another way that ends well for all of us.
SPEAKER_1:  and that wasn't even considered.
SPEAKER_1:  And I go like.
SPEAKER_1:  They created this monster.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's a fact.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's why I take joy in it.
SPEAKER_1:  When people ask me is Scientology a destructive cult? I don't even have to get into all the academic discussions of what's a religion and what's a cult and what's the difference. I go as long as they destroy families like that.
SPEAKER_1:  their cult.
SPEAKER_0:  Julz.
SPEAKER_0:  Cut people off.
SPEAKER_0:  deliberately, one by one.
SPEAKER_0:  And it doesn't have to be that way.
SPEAKER_0:  And why is it that way?
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, it started with.
SPEAKER_1:  L. Ron Hubbard laying out a policy framework, a policy structure.
SPEAKER_1:  that
SPEAKER_1:  if interpreted and applied.
SPEAKER_1:  in the worst.
SPEAKER_1:  possible way.
SPEAKER_1:  with the worst possible judgment can be abused in that way.
SPEAKER_1:  I would make the argument.
SPEAKER_1:  that if an anti-broker had taken over.
SPEAKER_1:  that Scientology policy.
SPEAKER_1:  does have enough.
SPEAKER_1:  little um caveats baked into it that
SPEAKER_1:  even the policies about disconnection could be interpreted and implemented in a
SPEAKER_1:  non-destructive way.
SPEAKER_1:  There is room for judgment and discretion.
SPEAKER_1:  and Miscavige has just created the worst
SPEAKER_1:  possible version of Scientology and that's where you sort of get that argument of.
SPEAKER_1:  Does he even want Scientology to succeed? Because he seems to be hell bent.
SPEAKER_1:  on making sure that he doesn't.
SPEAKER_1:  And I don't want to see him make it succeed, but it.
SPEAKER_1:  does bring that question up of like.
SPEAKER_1:  What are his motivations?
SPEAKER_1:  Can he not see that he's destroying the thing he's supposed to be?
SPEAKER_1:  Expanding.
SPEAKER_0:  That's also, you know, there's ways to measure.
SPEAKER_0:  cost.
SPEAKER_0:  That would probably be the most costly aspect of Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  is the suffering associated with the separating of families.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean that actually just puts, makes it very concrete what we value in human life.
SPEAKER_0:  is the connection to our loved ones.
SPEAKER_0:  Like everything else doesn't matter. I like getting 50 bucks a week.
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Like that, like.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh.
SPEAKER_0:  getting money stolen from you.
SPEAKER_0:  getting the truth stolen from you, none of that compares.
SPEAKER_0:  You can even frame that as the good, there could be a lot of positives, whatever, in the tribe.
SPEAKER_0:  But separating families, separating loved ones, that's the destructive thing.
SPEAKER_0:  So no hate.
SPEAKER_0:  No, I genuinely don't hate them.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you forgive them?
SPEAKER_1:  100%
SPEAKER_1:  There's no one I look at in Scientology that I go.
SPEAKER_1:  How dare you. Julian's going to be dough, mommy.
SPEAKER_1:  having to.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, operate under David Miscavige's orders, I would have done.
SPEAKER_1:  The same thing.
SPEAKER_1:  and I would have loved it.
SPEAKER_1:  Truthfully.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't blame any of them. I mean, I take the opposite approach.
SPEAKER_1:  If they knew.
SPEAKER_1:  What I knew.
SPEAKER_1:  they'd be doing what I'm doing.
SPEAKER_1:  If they knew what I knew and believed it.
SPEAKER_1:  They'd be doing what I'm doing.
SPEAKER_1:  They're not dumb. It's not dumb people in Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  They're ambitious. Third.
SPEAKER_0:  Dreamers they got
SPEAKER_0:  They're driven, all that kind of stuff. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's one of the reasons I like.
SPEAKER_1:  Putting up.
SPEAKER_1:  content on my channel so they can see, hey, like if you are a Scientologist.
SPEAKER_1:  You look at that and you go, hey.
SPEAKER_1:  He seems like he's doing well, he's happy, he's a positive guy, he's a good communicator, he knows what he's talking about, he's not lying, he's not exaggerating. I don't exaggerate anything.
SPEAKER_1:  on my channel. I don't make up anything.
SPEAKER_1:  And this actually comes from an experience I had.
SPEAKER_1:  from 1998 to 2000, I was living in LA. I sort of had a two year period in my life where I actually had almost no contact with Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  And during that time, I found my way onto the internet.
SPEAKER_1:  and there was a website, it might've been.
SPEAKER_1:  ESMB ex-scientology message, but whatever it was, it was.
SPEAKER_1:  At that time, the main source of
SPEAKER_1:  critical information about Scientology on the internet.
SPEAKER_1:  And I looked at it and remember I was still a true believer.
SPEAKER_1:  And I looked at this and it was so.
SPEAKER_1:  offensive
SPEAKER_1:  Um, insulting, uh, hyperbolic exaggerated. I was like.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a bunch of bullshit.
SPEAKER_1:  I was in Scientology for 16 more years.
SPEAKER_1:  IF
SPEAKER_1:  what I had seen on the internet about
SPEAKER_1:  of Scientology, if what I had seen when I had seen it was something that actually resonated with me.
SPEAKER_1:  that I was like, oh.
SPEAKER_1:  that I believed was true. Does that seem credible?
SPEAKER_1:  I would have gotten out of Scientology 16 years earlier.
SPEAKER_1:  So I was like.
SPEAKER_1:  How can I help create an experience on the internet?
SPEAKER_1:  that if a Scientologist stumbles upon it,
SPEAKER_1:  it will resonate with them.
SPEAKER_1:  instead of repelling them.
SPEAKER_1:  And that is exactly.
SPEAKER_1:  what I have set out to do and what I believe I've accomplished.
SPEAKER_0:  There's the content, the message, but.
SPEAKER_0:  Also just showing that you can be happy outside of Scientology. Exactly. You can have a fulfilling life, you can be a good man.
SPEAKER_0:  All that.
SPEAKER_0:  What benefit do you think Tom Cruise gets from Scientology? So why is he still in Scientology?
SPEAKER_1:  He genuinely loves it. And also Miscavige does. There's one celebrity who does have.
SPEAKER_1:  the most unique experience in Scientology, and that is Tom.
SPEAKER_1:  Scientology hires all of Tom's staff.
SPEAKER_1:  There are no
SPEAKER_1:  All of Tom's staff are subject to interrogations by Scientology, not only in the hiring process, but during the employment, like.
SPEAKER_1:  David Miscavige on Scientology runs Tom Cruise's life and his production company and his household staff. Did you imagine this?
SPEAKER_0:  personal connection there where
SPEAKER_0:  They're just, they like each other a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  Best friends.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, it's them against the world is how they see it. I think it's pretty easy to see.
SPEAKER_1:  how that works between the two of them.
SPEAKER_0:  I think this idea of...
SPEAKER_0:  them against the world us against the world
SPEAKER_0:  It's a really powerful, intimate.
SPEAKER_0:  I kind of see like friendships and relationships that way.
SPEAKER_0:  that I'm not in a dark sense, but it's like.
SPEAKER_0:  the world is full of cruelty and absurdity and unfairness and so on. It's nice to huddle together like the penguins in March of the Penguins against the cold. 100%, and one hundred percent.
SPEAKER_0:  Especially with the ideology of
SPEAKER_0:  of Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  It, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  this idea that
SPEAKER_0:  You can be anything. You can essentially
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, you can manifest it essentially through like believing it.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... manually put into those words
SPEAKER_0:  but believing that you're
SPEAKER_0:  You're a god.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a really like inspiring positive thing to think.
SPEAKER_1:  If they could figure out how to do all that without destroying families and bankrupting its members, they might actually have a future.
SPEAKER_1:  That's why like it's funny because sometimes I feel like it's like.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I'm rooting for them to like succeed and do it right. And I'm not, but it's an interesting academic discussion and a half of like.
SPEAKER_1:  We can all see how much people will sacrifice in the names of belief and religion. Yeah. We can see how much Scientologists sacrifice.
SPEAKER_1:  based on what they already believe.
SPEAKER_1:  If he would just start.
SPEAKER_1:  treating people less horribly.
SPEAKER_1:  You know what I'm saying? It might actually have a future.
SPEAKER_1:  But it's not that I wanted to.
SPEAKER_0:  It seems like this dark lesson of human nature that
SPEAKER_0:  date.
SPEAKER_0:  that like.
SPEAKER_0:  There's something about
SPEAKER_0:  you know, to use the word cults, that you just stop seeing reality for what it is. There's a lot of things that could make this a better organization that's actually helping people flourish
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  and be a little bit more like.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... loose about membership
SPEAKER_0:  not dividing families, not causing suffering, not causing financial harm, but actually inspiring people.
SPEAKER_0:  and helping people, but then maybe it did fundamentally change what the organization is.
SPEAKER_0:  And maybe that means somebody like David Miscavige loses power too.
SPEAKER_0:  which might be very difficult or people that are close to him lose power.
SPEAKER_0:  and people hold onto power. So, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Whatever the human force is here, it seems to...
SPEAKER_0:  become worse and worse over time.
SPEAKER_0:  What about, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  Let me ask a conspiracy question. Is there a chance that Tom Cruise is being blackmailed? That there's information from auditing?
SPEAKER_0:  So that kind of stuff is
SPEAKER_1:  That's very conspiratorial. I've actually come out and said definitively.
SPEAKER_1:  I do not know of a single person who stays in Scientology because they're afraid of being blackmailed. It's just not a thing.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just not a thing.
SPEAKER_1:  Does Scientology have enough information to blackmail someone if they wanted to? Well sure!
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, and it doesn't have to be true. It could just be lies. Who cares? Who knows? I can say whatever the hell they want.
SPEAKER_1:  So that's the thing, it doesn't even have to be true.
SPEAKER_1:  And actually that would be the argument against blackmailing.
SPEAKER_1:  Like in order for Scientology to blackmail you with that information, they'd actually have to represent that, yes, he really did tell us this. And it's like, well, then why are you spilling secrets of members, right? That's a bad precedent.
SPEAKER_0:  What are some of the sins according to Scientology?
SPEAKER_1:  Most of the sins from a Scientology perspective are just doing or saying anything that brings repute to Scientology itself.
SPEAKER_1:  Right.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Remember, it's not like Christianity where there's rules. If you break this rule, you're not getting into heaven.
SPEAKER_1:  to scientists and think about things.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, there's the drug. You can't do drugs, right?
SPEAKER_1:  can't do.
SPEAKER_1:  are drugs.
SPEAKER_1:  and you can't take any psychotropic medications.
SPEAKER_1:  and no medications almost at all.
SPEAKER_1:  you're allowed to take medications. It's just, there's no rules expressly prohibiting it. It's just most Scientologists tend not to.
SPEAKER_1:  You can take Advil.
SPEAKER_1:  but many Scientologists won't.
SPEAKER_1:  You just can't take anything prescribed by a psychiatrist, a psychologist or any drugs that are.
SPEAKER_1:  psychotropic drugs. I mean SSRIs are considered
SPEAKER_1:  Probably the closest thing too.
SPEAKER_1:  Pure evil.
SPEAKER_1:  in the world of Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  What about weird question? What about sex?
SPEAKER_0:  Is there boundaries on what's...
SPEAKER_1:  They're used to not be. It's become very puritanical.
SPEAKER_1:  in the last many decades for a reason I can't actually explain.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, Miscavige does seem to be infatuated.
SPEAKER_1:  with controlling sex.
SPEAKER_1:  Like that is one thing about Miscavige version of Scientology that's gotten very strange.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, L. Ron Hubbard even specifically wrote a policy that says...
SPEAKER_1:  We are no longer going to.
SPEAKER_1:  regulate in
SPEAKER_1:  Anyway.
SPEAKER_1:  the bedroom activities of people.
SPEAKER_1:  He literally said, from this point on, no one is allowed to be subject to any justice actions of any kind whatsoever for anything they do.
SPEAKER_1:  in their sexual lives.
SPEAKER_1:  but that still did not give permission for gay relationships. That was still referring to straight stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  and monogamous only.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you do open marriages and open relationships?
SPEAKER_1:  According to that over on Hubbard Policy, you can...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, but you know
SPEAKER_1:  I think he wrote that policy before he created the C organization. And then what happened is this is actually how this came into effect.
SPEAKER_1:  He created this new organization.
SPEAKER_1:  You had a lot of people on a ship.
SPEAKER_1:  and everybody was just banging each other and it created.
SPEAKER_1:  just a nightmare of personal relationship. It was making production impossible. Not because everybody was spending so much time banging, but because everybody was so upset.
SPEAKER_1:  about who was paying.
SPEAKER_0:  I was like, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean sex and that kind of dynamic is really...
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, humans do what humans do, and then there's drama and all that. It's understandable, because everybody's so intimate, it's a closed...
SPEAKER_0:  tribe.
SPEAKER_0:  It makes sense to limit sex otherwise everyone's but otherwise it becomes a sex cult. Yeah, which a lot of them
SPEAKER_0:  becoming on that topic, would you classify Scientology as a cult?
SPEAKER_1:  100%.
SPEAKER_1:  but not because I'm like.
SPEAKER_1:  fully conversant with the academic.
SPEAKER_1:  differentiations between what's a religion and what's a cult. I mean, Scientology would say, well, all small new religions are cults. And I don't know, that's probably true. Some people would say all religions are cults. And I'd be like.
SPEAKER_1:  depends on how you define religion and it depends on how you define cult. But I just fall back on my thing of like...
SPEAKER_1:  If you're destroying families and bankrupting your members.
SPEAKER_1:  You're a cult.
SPEAKER_1:  That's all.
SPEAKER_1:  That's.
SPEAKER_0:  How I look at it. Versus them and.
SPEAKER_0:  to them could be your family, could be your loved ones that...
SPEAKER_0:  that's deeply destructive and one of the things you would probably throw into the definition of a cult is something that's actually destructive. It's like I do a lot of stuff that's cult-like, like Jiu-Jitsu.
SPEAKER_0:  Like there's a lot of really close knit tribes.
SPEAKER_0:  but there's no negative toxicity to it. There's no-
SPEAKER_0:  divide.
SPEAKER_0:  divisions or if there is
SPEAKER_0:  It's more.
SPEAKER_0:  Boy.
SPEAKER_0:  Try being a fan of a certain soccer team and then becoming a fan of another soccer team. That's hardcore. N designing your photography version without any editing involved.
SPEAKER_1:  But I'll tell you, I trained jiu-jitsu as well and I have found...
SPEAKER_1:  that community of people.
SPEAKER_1:  to be one of the most loving.
SPEAKER_1:  and helpful.
SPEAKER_1:  a group of people.
SPEAKER_1:  Shout out to John Keller, Gracie Baja Clearwater.
SPEAKER_1:  No, but seriously, it's one of the reasons I continue to do it.
SPEAKER_1:  despite.
SPEAKER_1:  my back, my hip, my shoulder. It's like, it's just such a cool group of guys.
SPEAKER_0:  on. It used to not, I think it was much more divisive in the beginning from those Brazilian roots.
SPEAKER_0:  One of the things that's really hard is the team oriented.
SPEAKER_0:  If you're this team, you're out of die with this team and there's no, there's the Crayonches, they go to another team.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think that aspect, that was actually a turnoff for me in the beginning, that the toxicity of that because
SPEAKER_0:  I understand that.
SPEAKER_0:  a little bit for the elites.
SPEAKER_0:  for the highest of the highest.
SPEAKER_0:  That there is, I like the brotherhood and the loyalty of the people, like the Olympic gold medalists, the best in the world, yes, but for recreational fun. I know. This is ultimately about the camaraderie of all human beings together, not some.
SPEAKER_0:  whatever label you put on it.
SPEAKER_0:  and yourself.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't think we actually talked about the organization itself. We talked about tax exempt status.
SPEAKER_0:  which is really important.
SPEAKER_0:  We talked about some of the control, like through the propaganda control.
SPEAKER_0:  of what's out there.
SPEAKER_0:  It's actually interesting that you said that like.
SPEAKER_0:  Scientologists pretty much lost the battle with the internet
SPEAKER_0:  Oh yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Which is kind of inspiring that it's hard to defeat the internet.
SPEAKER_0:  but then there's like.
SPEAKER_0:  botster.
SPEAKER_0:  I think if you're sophisticated, I'm not sure that's true.
SPEAKER_1:  But if you're not, it's kind of remarkable. They haven't been able to capitalize on these bot armies because there's one thing that they have. It's a lot of tax-free money that they got nothing else better to do. Yeah, right.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, they just, they should give you a call. Like they just don't have the right people apparently.
SPEAKER_0:  Heh.
SPEAKER_0:  uh
SPEAKER_0:  But that said, how do they wield?
SPEAKER_0:  influence with government agencies with you've talked about the local police enforcement also federal agencies anything
SPEAKER_1:  That is the one way they effectively put their money to use is lobbyists and attorneys.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, you know, judges very rarely have they ever ever been able just to get a politician on their side.
SPEAKER_1:  It's the behind the scenes people.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, Greta Van Susteren's a very high-level, long-term Scientologist.
SPEAKER_1:  and her husband, I always get it wrong, either Jim Cole or John Cole, I always get it wrong.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, he's a very powerful attorney.
SPEAKER_1:  who has a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  wields a lot of influence behind the scenes.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's just one example. Like the reason why that's an interesting example is because he's actually a Scientologist and he travels in those circles.
SPEAKER_1:  Scientology though, it's money.
SPEAKER_1:  goes to good use.
SPEAKER_1:  by hiring non-scientologists, retired judges, attorneys, lobbyists. It really is.
SPEAKER_1:  how they get almost anything done.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, Miscavige himself is not hobnobbing and glad-hanging and shaking hands and meeting these folks. It's...
SPEAKER_1:  the non-scientologist professionals.
SPEAKER_1:  who work behind the scenes on Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  behalf.
SPEAKER_0:  Can you describe the dynamics of how that actually happens?
SPEAKER_0:  Like why would the police department work on behalf of Scientology?
SPEAKER_1:  I meant more the courts and regulators, not the police department. But well, for example, it can come down to something as simple as this.
SPEAKER_1:  In Clearwater, Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  hires Clearwater Police to do off-duty work for them.
SPEAKER_1:  They pay like three times the normal off-duty rate.
SPEAKER_1:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  They will, even though I'm not aware of anyone on the Clearwater PD who's actually a Scientologist.
SPEAKER_1:  They basically end up with, they would call them allies or safe points. Got it. Right. People.
SPEAKER_0:  Who?
SPEAKER_1:  like will literally operate a Scientology spies.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  someone comes in and follows a report about some child sex case, someone in the Clearwater PD is calling Sarah Heller at the Office of Special Affairs at the Flying Gladden Base to let her know.
SPEAKER_1:  Hey, heads up.
SPEAKER_1:  We got a thing coming in and then Scientology can run around and go talk to all the Scientologists who have knowledge about this and either get them out of Clearwater.
SPEAKER_0:  But you know, so it's not like a direct explicit corruption, but more.
SPEAKER_0:  just friends and coworkers integrated deeply in the community. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  I call it soft corruption.
SPEAKER_1:  So another example, you have...
SPEAKER_1:  the mayor of Clearwater, Frank Hibbard.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, he used to...
SPEAKER_0:  Hello.
SPEAKER_1:  when you
SPEAKER_1:  won his recent election, he stepped down from some of these nonprofits that he served on.
SPEAKER_1:  but the nonprofits that he served on also gets.
SPEAKER_1:  millions of dollars of donations from some of Scientology's richest Clearwater.
SPEAKER_1:  members right you have one of the mayors.
SPEAKER_1:  best friends.
SPEAKER_1:  Chobordet.
SPEAKER_1:  Literally a paid lobbyist for Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  So that creates a chilling effect.
SPEAKER_1:  on to anyone who's gonna be talking smack about Scientology because
SPEAKER_1:  his friends are on their damn payroll.
SPEAKER_1:  So I call it soft corruption. It's not illegal.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not illegal.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  but it's how Scientology wields influence.
SPEAKER_1:  And what's ironic is that a lot of these people who work on Scientology's behalf actually secretly hate Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  They kind of see.
SPEAKER_0:  through it but...
SPEAKER_0:  It's part of the community. I mean, it's deeply integrated in the community in this financial leverage.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  Are you ever?
SPEAKER_0:  Afraid?
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, afraid for your well-being, afraid for your...
SPEAKER_0:  ability to function in society because of the pressures from Scientology? NO.
SPEAKER_0:  Is that because you're genetically malfunctioning or?
SPEAKER_0:  or mentally or is there speaking out as a kind of protection?
SPEAKER_1:  I think it's one of those things that once you've seen behind the curtain, you see the Wizard of Oz is just a silly man.
SPEAKER_1:  You just don't.
SPEAKER_1:  have any fear. Now it's one of these things like people say, oh, you're so brave.
SPEAKER_1:  And I go, eh.
SPEAKER_1:  What's that quote? 80th century is b-
SPEAKER_1:  you know, being a soldier and being afraid and going in any way.
SPEAKER_1:  It's not brave to run in if you don't think nothing's gonna happen to you.
SPEAKER_1:  Like I'm just trying to like I do not hold myself up as an example of bravery because
SPEAKER_1:  It's not like, oh, they could destroy me, but I don't care. No, there's not a damn thing they can do to me.
SPEAKER_1:  And it's one of, that's one of the reasons I continue to put out content every day.
SPEAKER_1:  So just basically go.
SPEAKER_1:  Hey!
SPEAKER_1:  Still here. I dare you to try to do something about it, but you can't and hope.
SPEAKER_1:  that that also serves as kind of an example for other people to go.
SPEAKER_1:  If this shmo can do it.
SPEAKER_1:  and they can't do anything else to him, then maybe I can do it too.
SPEAKER_1:  because I would love it. I would love there for me to be a 20.
SPEAKER_1:  channels where former Scientologists talk about their experience.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, that is bravery because what happens is fear seeps in even if it's not grounded in reality.
SPEAKER_0:  But at the same time, like, you know...
SPEAKER_0:  My grandfather who...
SPEAKER_0:  uh...
SPEAKER_0:  in World War II.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, the story.
SPEAKER_0:  is very convinced and sure most of the people he fought alongside with died.
SPEAKER_0:  Use the machine gutter.
SPEAKER_0:  But he believes that bullets can't hit him.
SPEAKER_0:  Right.
SPEAKER_0:  Mm-hmm.
SPEAKER_0:  What?
SPEAKER_0:  You know.
SPEAKER_0:  Sir.
SPEAKER_0:  He was right.
SPEAKER_0:  We'll see you next time.
SPEAKER_0:  Right? Because you survived.
SPEAKER_0:  So.
SPEAKER_1:  There's some sense like you're ever biased that he's like, just like you are. I was like.
SPEAKER_0:  See, I'm not brave, I just, the bullets can't hit me.
SPEAKER_0:
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, there's a dark kind of truth to that. There's some, you know, it's like a.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a feedback loop where if you have the confidence and you push on forward,
SPEAKER_0:  and you're brave in that way to not let your and three
SPEAKER_0:  gives you less things to be scared about. Yeah, I mean, but that initial few steps might be.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... for people
SPEAKER_0:  It might be a very difficult step to take to talk about.
SPEAKER_1:  The fear.
SPEAKER_1:  was.
SPEAKER_1:  knowing how the family was going to be destroyed.
SPEAKER_1:  and trying to prevent that.
SPEAKER_1:  I was.
SPEAKER_1:  terrified of that happening.
SPEAKER_1:  But it happened.
SPEAKER_1:  There's nothing left to be afraid of.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's kind of the thing, like they created this beast.
SPEAKER_1:  And the same is true for Mark Headley. The same is true for Mike Reinder.
SPEAKER_1:  I said they've essentially created a Scientology proof virus, a Scientology resistant strain.
SPEAKER_1:  by throwing everything they have.
SPEAKER_1:  at us for so many years.
SPEAKER_1:  They have just
SPEAKER_1:  through natural selection.
SPEAKER_1:  created people who just.
SPEAKER_1:  do not give a damn about anything they could or would do. And maybe there is something a little wrong with me, because when I get a phone call from someone like, I just got this phone call about you, and it's clear that it's Scientology PIs doing work behind the scenes.
SPEAKER_1:  I get really excited.
SPEAKER_1:  I get really excited. I don't get nervous. I'm like, oh no, what's happening? I'm like, oh yeah, this is gonna be exciting. I'm like, okay, because everything they try to do to me.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm gonna figure out.
SPEAKER_1:  how to reflect it back on them and make them look ridiculous.
SPEAKER_0:  And that pales in comparison to the separating from family. Exactly.
SPEAKER_0:  Is there parts of your family that...
SPEAKER_0:  You've lost because of Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  If you...
SPEAKER_1:  Most.
SPEAKER_1:  of my episode.
SPEAKER_1:  on the Leah Remini in the Aftermath show.
SPEAKER_1:  was talking about me and my twin brother.
SPEAKER_1:  It's just a pretty horrible story.
SPEAKER_1:  This is a pretty horrible story. So I do have a younger brother who's still in Scientology and disconnected from me.
SPEAKER_1:  but I never had much of a relationship with that brother.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  Really, to begin with.
SPEAKER_1:  Right.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, ahem.
SPEAKER_1:  But my twin brother died.
SPEAKER_1:  when I was like 23 or 24.
SPEAKER_1:  And that was without any question a direct result.
SPEAKER_1:  of um.
SPEAKER_1:  our Scientology experience.
SPEAKER_1:  You know.
SPEAKER_1:  He died in a car accident that wasn't technically his fault or anything. He wasn't even the one driving.
SPEAKER_1:  Bye!
SPEAKER_1:  The specific fact of his death was not meaning, the fact and the manner of his death was not specifically because of Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  but our story.
SPEAKER_1:  and how.
SPEAKER_1:  where our relationship got to.
SPEAKER_1:  and how he was even in a position.
SPEAKER_1:  of having something like that happen to him is directly attributable
SPEAKER_1:  to Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  Do you think about them?
SPEAKER_0:  Miss him?
SPEAKER_0:  is part of what you're doing in memory of him.
SPEAKER_0:  for short.
SPEAKER_0:  And this is such a...
SPEAKER_1:  You know, we were identical twins. Can you imagine two of me?
SPEAKER_1:  Hahahah!
SPEAKER_0:  Barely handled one.
SPEAKER_0:  I love it.
SPEAKER_0:  Ugh.
SPEAKER_0:  losing him, would that be the darkest moment in this whole journey of Scientology for you?
SPEAKER_1:  Two moments would.
SPEAKER_1:  equal the darkest moment.
SPEAKER_1:  It would be that.
SPEAKER_1:  and also just
SPEAKER_1:  The
SPEAKER_1:  period of, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  6, 9, 12 months of impending doom.
SPEAKER_1:  knowing that my wife's whole family was going to be obliterated.
SPEAKER_1:  and that there's nothing we could do about it.
SPEAKER_1:  and uh
SPEAKER_1:  and kind of telling ourselves every step of the way it wasn't really going to happen.
SPEAKER_1:  You know?
SPEAKER_1:  And I really felt like.
SPEAKER_1:  You ever watch the Ozarks?
SPEAKER_1:  I felt like Marty Byrd.
SPEAKER_1:  Now this was happening before the Ozarks, but when I watched the Ozarks...
SPEAKER_1:  and I see that character.
SPEAKER_1:  the entire world is crumbling down around him and all he can-
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, I did, like...
SPEAKER_1:  All right, what's the next step?
SPEAKER_1:  I watch Marty Bird and I go, that's my fucking spirit animal.
SPEAKER_1:  because you can only control what you can control.
SPEAKER_1:  And, um...
SPEAKER_1:  You can't keep Scientology from destroying your family.
SPEAKER_1:  And literally, like, it's funny, I mention this show a lot because I watch that and I go like, that's exactly how I felt.
SPEAKER_1:  You know?
SPEAKER_1:  I talk about this six months or nine, 12 months, whatever it was of impending doom. It's not like I was an emotional wreck during that time.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, in private I was, but it's not like...
SPEAKER_1:  I was just freaking out. It was like.
SPEAKER_1:  The sun's gonna come up tomorrow.
SPEAKER_1:  The world's gonna keep spinning?
SPEAKER_1:  I can't control it. This is horrible. I can't believe this is happening.
SPEAKER_1:  but tomorrow's a new day.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  I've never personally, even at the darkest times, I've never experienced anything.
SPEAKER_1:  that I would characterize as depression. Certainly not ever any suicidal thoughts or anything.
SPEAKER_1:  and even in the darkest of times.
SPEAKER_1:  And again, this one thing I go, is it because of Scientology or is it just me?
SPEAKER_1:  There really is an emotional detachment.
SPEAKER_1:  There-
SPEAKER_0:  almost has to be.
SPEAKER_0:  And it's a cold calculation. What are my options?
SPEAKER_0:  What do I do here?
SPEAKER_1:  And then once I figure out the answer to that question.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm actually quite chipper and happy.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, like that's sort of my default.
SPEAKER_1:  Like you could give me six horrible options. Once I figure out the best of those six, I'm going to feel like
SPEAKER_1:  I just had a pretty good day.
SPEAKER_0:  Brilliant.
SPEAKER_0:  Because just watching Ozarks is so stressful.
SPEAKER_0:  It is, right? So stressful watching it.
SPEAKER_0:  Is it?
SPEAKER_0:  and he usually finds a way.
SPEAKER_0:  And usually it is a set of really bad options is one of the bad options.
SPEAKER_0:  What's the best of the bad o-
SPEAKER_1:  options.
SPEAKER_1:  and he almost gets pissed off at everyone around him for being so pouty about it.
SPEAKER_1:  BYE
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, but you know, it's the show again the same way again.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, that's beautiful. But you know, it's like, you know, it's still simmering there right under the surface, like pretty damn close to the surface. Do you know what I mean?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. And, um.
SPEAKER_1:  people sometimes ask about recovery and whatnot and like, what does that look like and what does that mean? And sort of goes back to kind of the emotional detachment as I go.
SPEAKER_1:  the fuck does recovery even mean?
SPEAKER_1:  If you're an alcoholic and you're recovering, you know what that means. I used to drink, I don't drink now.
SPEAKER_1:  Well, I used to be an occult and I'm not an occult now.
SPEAKER_1:  How else am I supposed to feel about this for someone to be like, it seems like you've recovered. What the fuck does that even mean?
SPEAKER_1:  Like, I'm sure some academic has an answer to that question.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not someone who particularly, I don't spend any time thinking about that.
SPEAKER_1:  My recovery is success.
SPEAKER_1:  and a little bit of trolling and revenge.
SPEAKER_1:  but mostly success.
SPEAKER_1:  You know?
SPEAKER_1:  What does it mean to be a recovered former cult member? What, you don't cry when people ask you about your brother?
SPEAKER_1:  know what it means.
SPEAKER_1:  I've never had therapy, but not because I'm still like against it from Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  I just like.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not gonna pay to talk to someone.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you know where else I could do that? That is where I'm gonna sign up for Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  Now I know there's a lot of people going like, oh boy.
SPEAKER_1:  I know there's a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm not shitting on therapy.
SPEAKER_1:  I would rather have a beer with my friend and talk about this shit than talk to a professional for $200 an hour.
SPEAKER_0:  That's the kind of therapy, yeah.ENTE forecasting, yes.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, listen, that's the important part of the reason I do this podcast. It's talking to people they care about.
SPEAKER_0:  that you're close with, it's a really powerful, powerful thing.
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know what recovery looks like. Success to you is defined.
SPEAKER_0:  Just be, find happiness, find happiness outside the.
SPEAKER_0:  closed bubble.
SPEAKER_0:  that defines what happiness looks like, or Scientology.
SPEAKER_1:  If I can make my kids happy, that's success to me.
SPEAKER_0:  What advice would you give to your kids on how to live?
SPEAKER_0:  travel the world. A life they can be proud of. Travel the world.
SPEAKER_1:  the world.
SPEAKER_1:  Um, get rid of friends who don't push you up and.
SPEAKER_1:  Don't celebrate your success. It's hard to give that advice to young children because kids are always so catty.
SPEAKER_1:  But honestly, it's like.
SPEAKER_1:  when I see.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... that that really is i i just think not just a nice to my kids but some of the best advice
SPEAKER_1:  If you got anyone.
SPEAKER_1:  around you who doesn't celebrate your success.
SPEAKER_1:  Spend less time.
SPEAKER_1:  With those people.
SPEAKER_1:  Surround yourself with people who actually.
SPEAKER_1:  want to celebrate your success and push you to succeed. I think that's true. I think it's even more important at a young age because if at a young age you get used to being around people who kind of take joy in tearing you down, then that's what you become accustomed to.
SPEAKER_1:  You know?
SPEAKER_1:  And I just think, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  Having friends will love you in support use.
SPEAKER_1:  just about.
SPEAKER_1:  closest thing to.
SPEAKER_1:  the true meaning of life.
SPEAKER_0:  and who believe in you, who believe in your potential. And some of those ideas underlie...
SPEAKER_0:  the good parts of Scientology.
SPEAKER_0:  and accept.
SPEAKER_0:  There's a lot of dark parts of Scientology that separate you from the people that believe in you and that love you.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, this is a beautiful conversation. You're a beautiful human being.
SPEAKER_0:  who I came full of.
SPEAKER_0:  gifts.
SPEAKER_0:  And I mean, I genuinely, first of all, you're an aspiring human being.
SPEAKER_0:  uh... but most important i can't wait until i can purchase a bobblehead
SPEAKER_0:  On the store.
SPEAKER_0:  So I can keep that inspiration on my desktop.
SPEAKER_0:  Aaron, thank you so much for talking to me. Thank you for being you, for being brave. I know you said you're not, but.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you for being brave, for talking about this. You're an inspiration and you help a lot of people. Thank you, brother. Alright.
SPEAKER_0:  Thanks for listening to this conversation with Aaron Smith Levin.
SPEAKER_0:  To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_0:  And now...
SPEAKER_0:  Let me leave you with some words from Ralph Waldo Emerson.
SPEAKER_0:  Be not the slave of your own past.
SPEAKER_0:  plunge into the sublime seas.
SPEAKER_0:  Dive deep and swim far.
SPEAKER_0:  so you will come back with new self-respect.
SPEAKER_0:  with new power.
SPEAKER_0:  and with an advanced experience.
SPEAKER_0:  that will explain.
SPEAKER_0:  and overlook.
SPEAKER_0:  old.
SPEAKER_0:  Thank you for listening.
SPEAKER_0:  and hope to see you.
SPEAKER_0:  next time.