SPEAKER_1:  How would a kangaroo attack a human? Knock them down and then they choke them. The kangaroos do? They choke each other, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  They don't choke each other. You don't believe me?
SPEAKER_1:  You want to watch a video? They check each other out.
SPEAKER_1:  I've seen this, yeah. I mean, probably the most annoying one was obviously the one where I had Gordon Anamba I was like, tap bro.
SPEAKER_1:  and he wouldn't have, so I let him out.
SPEAKER_1:  I didn't get surgery. I didn't do essentially any rehab. I just have noise yell in my left leg. So what's it like having no surgery goes. You've got two options, surgery rehab only. Nikki goes, I'll do nothing. Yeah. I mean, what could possibly go wrong? If you're the world's best grappler hates you and you're gently provoking him behind the scenes every day. Well, I mean in Texas and you've stolen his brother, held him for ransom.
SPEAKER_1:  It is like a story of a shitty Western. The last part of a difficult wake up for me.
SPEAKER_1:  I try to find a sad movie and at least cry.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm about a pound out. That really gets me over the line. What are the rules in the streets? Do you think if you're on steroids, you would have finished the joke?
SPEAKER_1:  I- I mean, for sure. Who knew?
SPEAKER_1:  That the cure.
SPEAKER_1:  to the Dagestani Wrestling.
SPEAKER_1:  Wadi Aziz.
SPEAKER_1:  The following is a conversation with Craig Jones.
SPEAKER_1:  Nicky Rod and Nicky Ryan.
SPEAKER_1:  who together with Ethan Kralsten.
SPEAKER_1:  and others.
SPEAKER_1:  Make up the B team.
SPEAKER_1:  a legendary jiu-jitsu team here in Austin, Texas.
SPEAKER_1:  It was formed.
SPEAKER_1:  after the so-called Donahart Death Squad.
SPEAKER_1:  the team headed by John Donahue split up.
SPEAKER_1:  Continue with Jiu Jitsu.
SPEAKER_1: B-Team Jijitsu
SPEAKER_1:  both located here in Austin, Texas.
SPEAKER_1:  There's been a lot of trash talk.
SPEAKER_1:  back and forth.
SPEAKER_1:  including accusations of greasing and steroid use.
SPEAKER_1:  And I...
SPEAKER_1:  as a practitioner and fan of grappling jiu-jitsu in.
SPEAKER_1:  martial arts in general.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  here for it.
SPEAKER_1:  to see the best grapplers in history.
SPEAKER_1:  Go at it, both on the mat.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  on Instagram.
SPEAKER_1:  I like the people on both teams.
SPEAKER_1:  and train with both.
SPEAKER_1:  and
SPEAKER_1:  I'm really happy to see the exciting, rapid evolution of the sport, that these athletes and coaches are.
SPEAKER_1:  catalyzing.
SPEAKER_1:  This is the Lex Freedman Podcast.
SPEAKER_1:  support it, please check out our sponsors in the description.
SPEAKER_1:  And now, to your friends.
SPEAKER_1:  Here's Craig Jones.
SPEAKER_1:  Nicky Rod.
SPEAKER_1:  and Nicky Ryan.
SPEAKER_1:  Craig, can you introduce everyone?
SPEAKER_1:  Yep, so we got.
SPEAKER_1:  Nicky Rodd here.
SPEAKER_1:  Brown bow.
SPEAKER_1:  two-time 80cc silver medalist.
SPEAKER_1:  Nicky Ryan here.
SPEAKER_1:  That's it. Who are you?
SPEAKER_1:  And I'm Craig Jones, also a two-time ADCC silver medalist.
SPEAKER_1:  Silver medalist, so the number one loser.
SPEAKER_1:  Number one loser.
SPEAKER_1:  and maybe a little bit more. Your bio says.
SPEAKER_1:  Widely known as the Black Belt Slayer, hails from New Jersey, the land of pizza and biceps.
SPEAKER_0:  Yes, that's pretty accurate.
SPEAKER_1:  You also do carry a gun on you a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I keep it loaded.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh huh, yeah I won today.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, in the car?
SPEAKER_1:  That was a mistake. That was your first mistake. Yeah, I think you're too close. Very uncultured.
SPEAKER_1:  And you are Nikki Ryan. What else is there?
SPEAKER_1:  What else do you know?
SPEAKER_1:  Gordon Ryan's brother. Gordon Ryan's brother. Look at that one. I'm give up.
SPEAKER_1:  Alright, so in your altogether.
SPEAKER_1:  part of the leadership of the B team here in Austin.
SPEAKER_1:  Let's just get out some introductory questions. What in general accomplishment of the things you mentioned you're most proud of?
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I'm proud just to not have to work a full-time job just to get by on the bullshit I've done so far.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. Honestly. Just making money off a thing you love. Exactly, yeah. When was the first time you made money on a thing you love?
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, probably a jujitsu tournament. I think maybe in Abu Dhabi, where I won a thousand dollars, thought I was rich. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, what'd you spend a thousand dollars on?
SPEAKER_1:  Probably something bad, probably drugs or something at the time. Maybe blew it at the after party.
SPEAKER_1:  That's a good introduction, Craig. So what about you? When's the first time you made money with Anji Jitsu or what was actually stepping back? Like, what's the thing you're most proud of? Is it a similar kind of thing?
SPEAKER_1:  I think I think I'm most proud.
SPEAKER_0:  of is uh i mean for sure two 80cc silver metals which
SPEAKER_0:  hurts because you're so close to getting that gold but uh...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, it takes time. I'm understanding that.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, Sportive Jiu Jitsu takes quite a while to be at the...
SPEAKER_0:  tip top to be the absolute best. So, uh.
SPEAKER_0:  And I'm just being consistent in my training and my craft and...
SPEAKER_0:  and we'll get that number one spot one day.
SPEAKER_1:  what failure or loss is the most painful to you?
SPEAKER_0:  I don't know, I probably have a pretty short term memory. So my losses, I just like, I'll just forget about them. Yeah, I mean, for sure, my loss at this past 80cc in the finals, I don't know.
SPEAKER_0:  You know, that one's sung a bit because I definitely thought I was going to win. I mean, like.
SPEAKER_0:  It takes a while to produce the skills or the reactions more so that you need to have to be, you know, to have as Pitt 沒有將 cup 許濟
SPEAKER_0:  be that number one pound for pound guy.
SPEAKER_0:  Um.
SPEAKER_0:  And you know, pre ADCC, I was coming off an injury. So it took me a little bit to find the right mentality and physicality that I needed in order to, you know, get the wins that required gold. So, my job is I make a stand for myself in the practice between my friends about where können everywhere
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's just a process.
SPEAKER_1:  Interesting. You keep saying process like it takes a while to build up. You're not like thinking of a loss like a DCC is like.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh.
SPEAKER_1:  specific failures you're not you haven't gone long enough in a particular process to being a champ.
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I mean, for me, I'm coming, I'm closing in on five years of specifically jiu jitsu training. I'm about four and a half right now.
SPEAKER_0:  And um...
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, it's just the, you kind of, you constantly have these ups and downs in training where like, as long as you stay consistent, you'll have a gradual raise.
SPEAKER_0:  you know it's still you have these peaks and lows and
SPEAKER_0:  You know, just trying to get better every day. I'm definitely not where I will be in a few years from now, but I'm striving to get there.
SPEAKER_1:  Are you actually a brown belt? Was that a joke?
SPEAKER_1:  Brown Belt. Yeah, you're a brown boat.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, how many stripes?
SPEAKER_1:  No stripes. No stripes. Stripes. No stripes.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, is that part of the process that you're working through?
SPEAKER_0:  Definitely part of the process. I mean, I think a black belt is just based upon how much knowledge you have.
SPEAKER_0:  Obviously, if you're talking competitive wise, from when I started, I was able to beat most black belts. It's just...
SPEAKER_0:  kind of how I was gifted from my wrestling experience.
SPEAKER_0:  and uh...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, the time will come when it's right, but I'm not in a rush at all. I'm continuing. I just kind of take every day for what it is and try to improve upon that.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I want to give him the black belt. Nikki Ryan says he's not ready. What is it?
SPEAKER_1:  I guess, like us no-gi folks, do you take that seriously?
SPEAKER_1:  Like the black belt or like how much does it come into play into?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean, it's like Nikki Rott said, you know, it's based off of knowledge.
SPEAKER_1:  Not just you know what you do out on the competition mats because you know Like he said he had years of wrestling experience and obviously he's very physically gifted So we great based off of the amount of knowledge that you have
SPEAKER_1:  How do you measure knowledge?
SPEAKER_1:  I think teaching is a good measurement of it, like how well you're able to show the moves and really make sure that you have an understanding of what you're doing.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, it's an interesting rank. It's like, um...
SPEAKER_1:  It's something that takes many years to accomplish. And for a lot of people, it's truly meaningful. It's like it represents...
SPEAKER_1:  particular step in a journey.
SPEAKER_1:  But for you guys, it's almost like
SPEAKER_1:  different because you've been so focused on competition.
SPEAKER_1:  that.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess if you take it seriously, it is a big step for you too. Like as martial artists, that's bigger than just being.
SPEAKER_1:  like top of the world competitors, right?
SPEAKER_1:  So I thought it was a joke. You guys are actually taking this seriously.
SPEAKER_1:  Like that he's a Brown bow. They's a Brown belt and he's in your taking seriously the rank of black belt. like It's going to be a fun day, no? I know, nevermind. You're going to have some fun life to yourself.
SPEAKER_1:  It's part of your journey.
SPEAKER_0:  Think by the time I get a black belt, I'll be no more pound for pound. I think it'd be pretty.
SPEAKER_0:  Nice to accomplish that as a brown belt.
SPEAKER_0:  and then maybe toss a black ball on top.
SPEAKER_1:  maybe get promoted on the podium.
SPEAKER_1:  What do you guys, do you love winning?
SPEAKER_1:  or hate losing more.
SPEAKER_1:  I definitely don't hate losing.
SPEAKER_1:  If it pays the bills, I don't mind. Oh really? Yeah, but honestly, if I win, I feel more relief than anything rather than like excitement and stuff. I'm like, oh fuck, thank God that's over.
SPEAKER_0:  I hate losing for sure.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, but I understand that it's necessary to get, you know, to get to where you want to be.
SPEAKER_0:  And then winning is like
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, what I think winning is probably the closest you can think you can get to like heroin or something. Because I mean, we're on a like if you do have extreme success in a tournament that you've been adamant about training for and competing in for a while and you end up winning it I mean I feel like you're on that high for days at a time after.
SPEAKER_1:  Heron's gonna be better.
SPEAKER_0:  You think so? I'ma stick with no.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm looking at sucked it to win.
SPEAKER_1:  I guess that's a good boy, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  But you know, like because you come from a little bit of a wrestling culture.
SPEAKER_1:  One of the things I really love is at the end of the match when they lose, they just, there's no...
SPEAKER_1:  They just run off.
SPEAKER_1:  They're like almost pissed off. It's like some mixture of.
SPEAKER_1:  anger and frustration at themselves.
SPEAKER_0:  I think sometimes people freak out on the mat.
SPEAKER_0:  And I think that's just a.
SPEAKER_0:  to show everybody like.
SPEAKER_0:  They're acting like they care it a lot.
SPEAKER_0:  and really maybe they didn't work enough to get to where they want to, to where they-
SPEAKER_0:  expected to be and they lost and then they had this big boost of emotion like after
SPEAKER_0:  after the loss, but uh...
SPEAKER_0:  YAMIN
SPEAKER_0:  I think you just cry in the mirror and not to everybody else.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  What, have you ever cried watching a movie? I don't think I've ever cried, period. Okay could you close your plug for me tonight please, hello, okay
SPEAKER_1:  Have you cried watching a movie?
SPEAKER_1:  Not yet.
SPEAKER_1:  the notebook.
SPEAKER_1:  I try to avoid those. My protection.
SPEAKER_1:  I lie actually. Titanic. The last part of a difficult wake up for me.
SPEAKER_1:  I try to find a sad movie and at least cry.
SPEAKER_1:  I better pound out. That really gets me over the line. Low energy cutting.
SPEAKER_1:  The tears.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  Um, there's other following, uh, liquids I could talk to you about, but let's just, let's just, let's just continue on. No energy.
SPEAKER_1:  What about you, Nikki? Love of winning versus hate of losing.
SPEAKER_1:  I'm a very competitive person, so I for sure hate losing more than I like winning.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  I do think it's something that's kind of held me back over the past few years.
SPEAKER_1:  Cuz uh...
SPEAKER_1:  It makes it so that I'm not as active as I should be.
SPEAKER_1:  because it's like, I really hate that feeling of, you know, after a match that you just lost.
SPEAKER_1:  So it kind of prevents me from competing. So it's definitely something I need to work past So like when you think about a competition the possibility of losing which is always there in competition?
SPEAKER_1:  is the thing that like weighs heavy on you in the months and weeks leading up to it. Yeah, my whole life, you know, my financial stability, everything depends on, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  my ability to go out there and compete and my ability to teach.
SPEAKER_1:  So, you know, it's a huge hit to the brand if you lose. So, you know, leading up to matches, that's definitely something that's in my mind.
SPEAKER_1:  I know you see you guys are like world-class athletes, but for me more like a hobbyist competitor
SPEAKER_1:  I compete a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  The thing I was, uh, is I really wanted to win.
SPEAKER_1:  The thing I was probably most afraid of was not just losing.
SPEAKER_1:  but like, embarrassing myself.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, even even actually.
SPEAKER_1:  winning by stalling.
SPEAKER_1:  That was the thing I hated the most about myself.
SPEAKER_1:  in terms of crying in the mirror.
SPEAKER_1:  is like being too afraid.
SPEAKER_1:  I take risks after I'm up on two points or something.
SPEAKER_0:  I think you got to, in competition, sometimes it's good to take the emotion out of it.
SPEAKER_0:  It's too easy sometimes to like, uh...
SPEAKER_0:  think about all my girls and in the crowd, my family's watching, like I want to win because they're there.
SPEAKER_0:  But at the highest level, if you're emotional at all, no, that's affecting you.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  It's tough though.
SPEAKER_1:  That's tough. Especially like leading up to one year on the map maybe, but...
SPEAKER_0:  leading up to it.
SPEAKER_0:  I think it's okay to be emotional.
SPEAKER_0:  prior, like, you know, if we know ADCC or it's coming up and we have a big match, like definitely, I'll go out and, and practice and I'll, I'll visualize, I'll put myself in that competition. That way when it's game time, it's like, I've been there a thousand times already.
SPEAKER_1:  So not the actual competition, but even leading up to it, like stepping on the mat, like all the walk, walk towards it, all that.
SPEAKER_0:  all that stuff, like I'll do the same exact warmup for weeks on end until my competition day comes. That way, you know, when I compete, I'm just like, oh, it's another Tuesday at practice.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, what about you, Craig? How do you prepare mentally for a tournament like ADCC?
SPEAKER_1:  I push it completely out of my mind. Don't even think about it.
SPEAKER_1:  try to avoid any visualization.
SPEAKER_1:  any rituals, warmups, anything like that.
SPEAKER_1:  Block it out until the last second. Yeah, trying not to think about it.
SPEAKER_1:  I just go to training to have fun.
SPEAKER_1:  Learn a bit.
SPEAKER_1:  So I try to approach competition the exact same way.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't warm up training.
SPEAKER_1:  to very little warm up for competition.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh huh. And you just step on the mat. Step on the mat. My philosophy is there's no warm ups on the street.
SPEAKER_0:  We're so vastly dem-
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks.
SPEAKER_1:  EAR RAPE
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  Alright, so you like legit don't warm up.
SPEAKER_1:  No, I probably should now I'm 31, but I would just like in the gym.
SPEAKER_1:  It easy the first round you know like if I look around the room and Nicky Ryan's down my go I will have an easier first round today.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  So even for like the most high stakes matches.
SPEAKER_1:  you try to push it up.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I didn't even think about it.
SPEAKER_1:  What about like all the social Instagram posts you have to do about that match? You just make a joke out of it and kinda... Yeah, I mean that's kinda pretty.
SPEAKER_1:  silly, you know, we're just.
SPEAKER_1:  wrestling each other, you know? We put the meaning into it, but to someone that doesn't follow the sport, it looks stupid. Well, all of human existence is pretty silly.
SPEAKER_1:  Like, what are we doing?
SPEAKER_1:  None of us really know what's going on.
SPEAKER_1:  We'll kind of have sex to reproduce.
SPEAKER_1:  We'll get hungry when we eat.
SPEAKER_1:  and then we're all chasing money and cars and whatever the hell.
SPEAKER_1:  in a capitalist society or we worship a dictator in a.
SPEAKER_1:  authoritarian regime.
SPEAKER_1:  and it would get off on.
SPEAKER_1:  We'll let power abuse us and then we just.
SPEAKER_1:  murder others.
SPEAKER_1:  because we get off on it.
SPEAKER_1:  and then eventually all of us will die.
SPEAKER_1:  because the sun will run out of energy.
SPEAKER_1:  because colonizing other planets is very difficult.
SPEAKER_1:  That's another what matters.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a good philosophy. It's pretty good.
SPEAKER_1:  That's exactly what I was gonna say.
SPEAKER_0:  the sun run out of energy.
SPEAKER_1:  You caught me there. It's a nuclear fusion engine and eventually burns out.
SPEAKER_1:  Like when you get tired of training, it's never happened.
SPEAKER_0:  I try to get tired. I was like, dude, it's not working.
SPEAKER_1:
SPEAKER_1:  All right, cool. So you legit don't care about losing.
SPEAKER_1:  It doesn't weigh heavy on you.
SPEAKER_1:  I try not to list, like if I win, I try to block out all the compliments, all the niceties and stuff. So I try to do the same with losing. It's happened. Move on to the next one, you know, don't dwell on it too much. And sometimes make a joke out of it. Yeah, exactly. Losing?
SPEAKER_1:  With the right joke, we can make money.
SPEAKER_1:  or for the event that's just transpired.
SPEAKER_1:  That's what's most important.
SPEAKER_1:  Excellent. Thank you. I have a bunch of your merch.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, nice.
SPEAKER_1:  This one's the Jordan Byers ripoff.
SPEAKER_1:  Thanks for watching!
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  All I see is silver.
SPEAKER_1:  The way he pronounces broils is very, very sexy. Okay. I throw lines at people and I try to gauge their reaction. Like sometimes I'll say something to Nikki and I'll be like.
SPEAKER_1:  Alright, that's probably crossing the line.
SPEAKER_1:  You know, I mean, we'll tone it down for the public. So, yeah, so it's not just right. You have to think is this crossing the line?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, yeah, I get as close to it as possible.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I feel like he can't really cross it.
SPEAKER_1:  Just a little bit. Just a little bit, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of which...
SPEAKER_1:  You said that I'm Switzerland in World War II since I'm friends with both you and Gordon.
SPEAKER_1:  and John.
SPEAKER_1:  Very rich country. Are you a Hitler or a Stalin by the way in this analogy?
SPEAKER_1:  Would you like to be Hitler or Stalin?
SPEAKER_1:  And should you make a t-shirt out of it or?
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, a Nazi t-shirt, I don't know how well that sells. I think it would, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  I think let's brainstorm out on this one offline. I think since Hitler lost.
SPEAKER_1:  So you got second place in World War II. That's true. That's true.
SPEAKER_1:  Anyway, to the degree that you can.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you tell the story of how the time you've had with the Donahue Death Squad and why you split up?
SPEAKER_1:  I competed against Gordon for ADCC.
SPEAKER_1:  and EBI.
SPEAKER_1:  in 2017.
SPEAKER_1:  And I remember I competed against him at ADCC and then we had...
SPEAKER_1:  the EBOI event, and then...
SPEAKER_1:  I had a kiss eye. I used to compete.
SPEAKER_1:  All the time, every week. I wouldn't even.
SPEAKER_1:  do the preparation or anything. I just feel like trying to disseminize, make money.
SPEAKER_1:  and then jump in and compete. I remember I showed up to Kasai after I faced him twice.
SPEAKER_1:  And they were like four locker rooms and they put me...
SPEAKER_1:  with all the DDS guys.
SPEAKER_1:  It was just me.
SPEAKER_1:  and all of DDS and I think we competed.
SPEAKER_1:  the week, weekend before.
SPEAKER_1:  So I thought it was gonna be super rock cool, but I'm zeshy.
SPEAKER_1:  It was actually pretty chill.
SPEAKER_1:  and the Casai was in New York.
SPEAKER_1:  And they suggested to come train that way.
SPEAKER_1:  So I came trains, hung out with them a bit.
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  Ultimately the goal was...
SPEAKER_1:  to move to America, enjoy the big attain just cause.
SPEAKER_1:  That flight to Australia is death. Australia is so far away from everywhere. That's kind of like.
SPEAKER_1:  Not realistic.
SPEAKER_1:  to base yourself in Australia with all the tournaments.
SPEAKER_1:  Hire in America.
SPEAKER_1:  And then I went and trained with the guys and they just had a massive
SPEAKER_1:  Uh...
SPEAKER_1:  massively deep talent pool in that room.
SPEAKER_1:  Like show up to like a.
SPEAKER_1:  Meant to be 7am, actual 8am class, Brazilian time.
SPEAKER_1:  It'll be like a hundred people in there maybe.
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know how many black belts, but a ton of elite guys and I was coming from Australia.
SPEAKER_1:  uh
SPEAKER_1:  training with Lachlan Giles, but really that room was pretty shallow and like most people had.
SPEAKER_1:  serious jobs and stuff. So it was like, basically me just training with Loughlin.
SPEAKER_1:  Maybe a couple of other guys.
SPEAKER_1:  and then to go to New York and have access to it.
SPEAKER_1:  What a ray.
SPEAKER_1:  of training partners and guys that are training.
SPEAKER_1:  us each day.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like that's what you really need. You need people that can train as much as you are. Works again…
SPEAKER_1:  You get humbled in that room at first? For sure. Because my style at the time was basically-
SPEAKER_1:  a rip-off version.
SPEAKER_1:  of what they were doing. Leg locks came in, I remember just-
SPEAKER_1:  watching Eddie Cummings nonstop and just seeing this guy.
SPEAKER_1:  rip people's legs off and I was like, you know what? That's probably a good move. You know, that looks like an easier path.
SPEAKER_1:  to victory.
SPEAKER_1:  than trying to beat these guys at what they're good at already.
SPEAKER_1:  My philosophy at the time was...
SPEAKER_1:  If it's bothering old Brazilians, it's bothering them for a reason.
SPEAKER_1:  It's probably effective.
SPEAKER_1:  And that's the path I took to sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  Try to rip off their moves.
SPEAKER_1:  And then obviously to go into that room, try to do them.
SPEAKER_1:  to them.
SPEAKER_1:  it's going to be a bit more difficult.
SPEAKER_1:  Alright, so...
SPEAKER_1:  That's how it started.
SPEAKER_1:  How did you end up here?
SPEAKER_1:  How do we end up here? We're in Austin, Texas. I mean...
SPEAKER_1:  I like to think of Puerto Rico.
SPEAKER_1:  as Apocalypse Now.
SPEAKER_1:  John Danaher as Colonel Kurtz.
SPEAKER_1:  Things got very weird in the jungle.
SPEAKER_1:  and the teams went in two.
SPEAKER_1:  different directions.
SPEAKER_1:  But honestly, I mean, it's not really my story to tell. I had some issues with some of those people. At the time of the split, I got along very well with Jon.
SPEAKER_1:  I feel like me and him connected very well. I don't know.
SPEAKER_1:  Well that was maybe it was just because he missed.
SPEAKER_1:  Oh, I may miss the familiar accent, Australian New Zealand accent.
SPEAKER_1:  Uhhh...
SPEAKER_1:  But I mean, I basically followed Nicky.
SPEAKER_1:  Left with Nikki?
SPEAKER_1:  Sort of.
SPEAKER_1:  that core group of guys left with Nikki.
SPEAKER_1:  And I mean.
SPEAKER_1:  I just back, there was personal problems. So I just back Nikki, basically.
SPEAKER_1:  Got it.
SPEAKER_1:  just sticking on you for a bit.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there a part of you that...
SPEAKER_1:  you know, finds it heartbreaking that DDS split up.
SPEAKER_1:  This party you miss working with John and everybody.
SPEAKER_1:  Now can you steal me on the case for that?
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I miss certain aspects of it, but I also do prefer the freedom of being apart from it. It's obviously a very strict regime.
SPEAKER_1:  Under.
SPEAKER_1:  John Dana her, you know, obviously it's possible. I miss.
SPEAKER_1:  The past the public doesn't see of John.
SPEAKER_1:  the behind the scenes banter, I feel like he's very conscious.
SPEAKER_1:  of the image he portrays to the world.
SPEAKER_1:  But basically...
SPEAKER_1:  He closed doors. He's always making jokes, always funny, I guess more in line.
SPEAKER_1:  with the Australian.
SPEAKER_1:  Kiwi sort of culture, but you don't really see that.
SPEAKER_1:  in the public eye. that perspective.
SPEAKER_1:  I do miss that relationship with John.
SPEAKER_1:  In terms of setting aside personal differences, Gordon was.
SPEAKER_1:  a good training partner.
SPEAKER_1:  Definitely a good training partner to train with.
SPEAKER_1:  but obviously the
SPEAKER_1:  Negative things we can't really talk about outweighed all of those things.
SPEAKER_1:  and we obviously had to make a decision.
SPEAKER_1:  to leave.
SPEAKER_1:  But yeah. It's happening in the jungle.
SPEAKER_1:  the things happen to the jungle. Should never be spoken of. But I personally...
SPEAKER_1:  Cannot speak up. Yeah, but obviously I do miss certain aspects. Like, I mean, nothing's all bad. Nothing's so good, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, this goes back to your like, uh...
SPEAKER_1:  Everything we're doing is silly.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, exactly. That's why I don't get people take it so serious. Smash lights are serious. It's just...
SPEAKER_1:  It's just pretty stupid really, especially in the gate looks just...
SPEAKER_1:  It looks bad. And then I mean, it's pretty silly with, with and without the Ghee. It's just a bunch of apes. What's silly about no Ghee and what's silly about the Ghee and just mixed and matched bottoms there. You know what I mean?
SPEAKER_1:  Wait, which one? What?
SPEAKER_1:  I see what you're doing.
SPEAKER_1:  Brother, you come...
SPEAKER_1:  to my house and defend my people.
SPEAKER_1:  All right.
SPEAKER_1:  This is
SPEAKER_1:  We're going to go to every dark place apparently.
SPEAKER_1:  Nick, how did you get with DDS? What was that journey like? Is there—
SPEAKER_1:  Try to see if there's things that you remember fondly that you've gotten from the experience.
SPEAKER_0:  Alright, so the way I started training with DDS...
SPEAKER_0:  Um, initially I was training for like,
SPEAKER_0:  Well, initially I was...
SPEAKER_0:  I was a bouncer, right? I dropped out of college to pursue this fitness modeling career I ended up signing with a
SPEAKER_0:  Willamina models up in New York. And I was like, try to get in better shape.
SPEAKER_0:  And while I was bouncing kind of the talk of like, you know, who's tougher came up between the wrestlers and a few of the bouncers that train jiu-jitsu.
SPEAKER_0:  And, uh, you know, they convinced me to go to a practice and, and I went to my first practice over there.
SPEAKER_0:  And uh, I-
SPEAKER_0:  And for the most part, I just controlled everybody got on top of them was able to avoid like kind of like you know shitty submissions because I had
SPEAKER_0:  I had an awareness of the sport and I'm a fan of fighting and what not.
SPEAKER_0:  I kind of understood it pretty well.
SPEAKER_0:  And then soon after that, I joined a school and.
SPEAKER_0:  My second week of Jiu Jitsu I started.
SPEAKER_0:  repeating.
SPEAKER_0:  had pretty good success. I was subbin a few black belts and beating everybody pretty decisively with points and stuff.
SPEAKER_0:  And about three months into training locally, I got connected with a Gordon, Gordon Ryan and John Danner up in New York. And I started.
SPEAKER_0:  I committed to make the drive up there as many days as I could.
SPEAKER_0:  At the time I live in South Jersey and it was about two and a half hour, three hour drive without traffic to New York.
SPEAKER_1:  We're in South Jersey.
SPEAKER_0:  Gloucester County.
SPEAKER_0:  I'll talk about New Jersey specifically, but Gloucester County.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah. So it was about, it was about 130 miles and without traffic, you know, about two or two and a half hours or so, but on the way back, man, we, it'd be three plus sometimes, you know, you're catching that rush.
SPEAKER_1:  What year was this do you remember? this was 2018
SPEAKER_1:  to get how young.
SPEAKER_1:  I was there before all that. All right, cool. Anyway, you're doing the long drive and then.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, doing a long drive. And then, uh, you know, once I went 80 CC trials, I was able to make a couple of bucks and then, you know, I got my silver medal at 80 CC and I was able to afford to live up there in New York and North Jersey area. So I lived up there, trained there full time every day. And, uh, you know, it was kind of stuck with the team throughout, throughout the turbulent times and
SPEAKER_0:  found ourselves in Austin.
SPEAKER_1:  in the jungle.
SPEAKER_1:  in the jungle. Things we shall not speak of.
SPEAKER_1:  What, uh, what's.
SPEAKER_1:  Are there things that you remember that you've learned from John Donahue from Italy?
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, I mean, I definitely learned a ton from John and the team as a whole.
SPEAKER_0:  It's you have to be the guy that asks questions in, in the type of environment, right? Cause there's not, it's not, you're not going to get singled out to be that specific, uh, like star or the, the best guy in the room when you have all these other, you know, stud athletes. So I really had to seek out and figure out the kind of questions that I needed to ask.
SPEAKER_0:  And once I became a bit more verbal with my training, and you know, I
SPEAKER_0:  I'm expressing all my curiosities about grappling to these guys. Definitely help boost my technique and my career as a whole.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, did you understand what kind of stuff like technically you want to get good at? What fits your body? Leave a comment below and I will try to answer all of those questions in one segment!
SPEAKER_1:  Like what would be good for you? What are your weaknesses and all that?
SPEAKER_0:  So initially, when I started grappling, I had...
SPEAKER_0:  and innate ability to just get to opponents back. So I was like, all right, I'm good at getting to the back. Let me get.
SPEAKER_0:  Let me perfect controlling the back and then submitting opponent via reneged choke.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, and then besides that, I really focused on leg lock defense. And then eventually came the Roddy lock pass where, you know, I'm, uh, I'm really good at body lock passing my opponents now. And then, and, um, yeah, it just takes a quite a long time because you have to find, uh, different sequences and then there's always these, uh, an abundance of opportunities that your opponent gets from these specific sequences. So.
SPEAKER_0:  Take care.
SPEAKER_1:  Is there part of you that finds the fact that DGS split up heartbreaking?
SPEAKER_0:  Um...
SPEAKER_0:  I definitely...
SPEAKER_0:  You know, having one person to go to that runs practice every day that's, you know, consistent.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, it was definitely, it was definitely, definitely a gift, but now I've also gifted with many, many other partners have Nikki Ryan, um, you know, Craig Jonesy.
SPEAKER_1:  You're RIGHT.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  We have Ethan Crellison, Damian Anderson, so a full team of knowledgeable athletes that I can continue to go to with multiple questions. But yeah, definitely, definitely it took me some time to adjust to training or to learning from you know, snogging
SPEAKER_0:  Specifically my team and not just one person
SPEAKER_1:  We should mention for people just listening, because you can't visually see that Nicky Ryan is currently terrified.
SPEAKER_1:  And Craig Jones's.
SPEAKER_1:  currently enjoying the fact that they characterized it. But anyway, can you talk about your, Nikki, can you talk about your time with DDS?
SPEAKER_1:  I started training when I was like around 13. You know, my brother Gordon had started prior to me and I really just went into training just as like a means to exercise and lose weight at the beginning because I was pretty fat as a kid.
SPEAKER_1:  So I went to the first class, loved it, and then just started training every day at Gary Shimm Brunswick.
SPEAKER_1:  And then during the summer when I'd get off from school.
SPEAKER_1:  they would take me up to New York to train under John.
SPEAKER_1:  And you know, I just absolutely loved it. I knew what I wanted to do with my life at a young age. So I ended up dropping out of school actually after my freshman year in high school.
SPEAKER_1:  So yeah, 15 I ended up dropping out and just pursuing Jiu-Jitsu full-time, you know, training every day up in the Blue Basement.
SPEAKER_1:  Like what aspect of the jet too was this?
SPEAKER_1:  Um, made you-
SPEAKER_1:  know that this is the thing for you.
SPEAKER_1:  It was just something I just enjoyed being, you know, like on the mats every day. I love that there's, you know, a problem solving aspect to it. Um, so it's, you know, it's mentally challenging. It's physically challenging.
SPEAKER_1:  me get in shape so I just yeah right off the bat I knew I loved it.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so then we'll go to the jungle.
SPEAKER_1:  what happened in the jungle. And in general, like, uh,
SPEAKER_1:  I like this. I like this. This is like this like shroud of mystery.
SPEAKER_1:  that she'll never be penetrated. That she'll never be like. We've got a book deal, it's coming. A book deal? Obviously left high school, he's not riding it.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll do the Russian translation. Okay. So what are.
SPEAKER_1:  What are things that you enjoy that you remember from work on John Donahue?
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, I mean, you know, obviously he's considered one of the best coaches in the world.
SPEAKER_1:  you know, very charismatic guy when you see him in person. You know, I pretty much was, you know, kind of raised in the DDS, you know, that's where I spent the majority of my time every day. So I obviously had very deep connections, you know, with John, my brother, Gary, you know, even Eddie Cummings and stuff back then. So obviously I miss interacting with those guys every day. And, you know, it's like they said, it's good to have somebody to kind of crack the whip at you every day. And John was very good at that.
SPEAKER_1:  When you're like younger in your teenage years, you can kinda...
SPEAKER_1:  You have to get humbled, right? There's like a process to that.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, for sure. And uh, it's a pretty good room to get humbled in. I guess. Yeah, exactly. I mean I was uh,
SPEAKER_1:  I started training with them just when like everybody started to break out. Gary was like the biggest name at the time, uh, just cause he had one ADCC trials already. And, uh, he had a crazy match with Kron at a Kron Gracie at a ADCC.
SPEAKER_1:  But Eddie was just starting to break out. Gordon just started winning EBI. So I started training under John, you know, right when everything was exploding.
SPEAKER_1:  What are the good things?
SPEAKER_1:  about life, about Jiu-Jitsu, you learn from your brother.
SPEAKER_1:  Both me and my brother never really wanted to, you know, work a full-time job doing something that we hate.
SPEAKER_1:  And he was always, you know, a very confident person. So he just went, you know.
SPEAKER_1:  fully started pursuing Jiu-Jitsu.
SPEAKER_1:  So I'm very happy that you know he did that and I ended up following in his footsteps because you can ask these guys I'm a lazy sack of shit out of outside of the the mat
SPEAKER_1:  So that's definitely one thing that...
SPEAKER_1:  I'm very grateful for.
SPEAKER_1:  that he paved the way, like you can make money doing the stuff you love. Yeah, exactly, and he was a big reason, you know, why my parents eventually let me drop out of school because, you know, one...
SPEAKER_1:  When they were coming up, there was no money in the sport. It was very hard to make a full living.
SPEAKER_1:  Like if you wanted.
SPEAKER_1:  to actually make a living, you'd eventually have to transfer to MMA.
SPEAKER_1:  And I feel like Gordon and Gary and those guys were, you know, some of the first people to make a very good living off of just jiu-jitsu.
SPEAKER_1:  At this party you find it heartbreaking.
SPEAKER_1:  that you've split up.
SPEAKER_1:  from GDS, but also from your brother in terms of spending time in the mat every day.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, for sure. You know, I mean growing up, you know, obviously he's my big brother I looked up to him a lot. So I definitely like I said, I'm misinteracting with those guys I was pretty much raised, you know in that blue basement, you know that
SPEAKER_1:  John was like, you know, a father figure to me.
SPEAKER_1:  Um.
SPEAKER_1:  So I definitely miss seeing those guys every day.
SPEAKER_1:  Do you have animosity towards Gordon and does he have animosity toward you?
SPEAKER_1:  And what is the source of that?
SPEAKER_1:  and do you think you'll ever be able to forgive each other?
SPEAKER_1:  Definitely initially during the
SPEAKER_1:  dead.
SPEAKER_1:  Initial split we definitely hated each other at the beginning
SPEAKER_1:  Um, but it's definitely started to, uh, to calm down actually just prior to, you know, all this social media drama that's going on currently.
SPEAKER_1:  He had reached out to me and that was literally like the first time that we have actually talked since spirit.
SPEAKER_1:  since the split happened. So we didn't talk to each other for, what is it now, like almost two years?
SPEAKER_1:  And that was the first time that we interacted again.
SPEAKER_1:  Overall, you know, he wasn't, you know, aggressive towards me. I wasn't aggressive towards him. You were cracking some jokes. So.
SPEAKER_1:  Hopefully the animosity is going down.
SPEAKER_1:  There's this Godfather quote.
SPEAKER_1:  That wrote down. I recently rewatched it.
SPEAKER_1:  from the Don, from Don Corleone, Vito Corleone.
SPEAKER_1:  The strength of a family, like the strength of an army, lies in its loyalty to each other. Is there some aspect of...
SPEAKER_1:  family that you miss.
SPEAKER_1:  of the blood that kind of connects you.
SPEAKER_1:  They can count on.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, my parents, you know, they both raised us that, you know, like family is everything. You never, you know
SPEAKER_1:  betray your family or anything like that.
SPEAKER_1:  So I definitely, you know, miss him from time to time.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, imagine you're like 40 years from now.
SPEAKER_1:  sitting on a porch with a shotgun.
SPEAKER_1:  drink your whiskey.
SPEAKER_1:  looking over like all the land you've conquered.
SPEAKER_1:  uh... looking back to this moment is the reason you split up a bullshit reason
SPEAKER_1:  Is it a good reason from the perspective of the king who has now conquered the lands?
SPEAKER_1:  have proven themselves have done everything.
SPEAKER_1:  I think it was definitely like a justifiable reason for the team splitting. Like it just...
SPEAKER_1:  with the way things were going, it just was not going to work with, you know, all of us in the same room together. It started, you know, affecting training, people didn't feel comfortable in things. So I definitely think that it was a justifiable reason to split.
SPEAKER_1:  The things that happen in the jungle.
SPEAKER_1:  to be told about in the.
SPEAKER_1:  Is it gonna be an audio book or is it just gonna be, who's gonna voice it?
SPEAKER_1:  Might be a play.
SPEAKER_1:  A musical? Yeah, a musical. Broadway.
SPEAKER_1:  Um...
SPEAKER_1:  How's your singing voice? Mine's not so good, but Nikki has a beautiful voice. Does he? Of an angel? That girl had bat.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  Speaking of the social media drama, I should mention that I've talked recently to Gordon a bunch.
SPEAKER_1:  I've talked about talking to you guys.
SPEAKER_1:  and he's had nothing but really nice things to say about you, Nicky Ryan.
SPEAKER_1:  and he has had nothing but bad things.
SPEAKER_1:  What was some of the things?
SPEAKER_1:  Well, let's just go to the social media first. Because the social media stuff that he said publicly is just like a warm up. It's like...
SPEAKER_1:  uh... for play yes
SPEAKER_1:  So Gordon sent...
SPEAKER_1:  You, Nekuad.
SPEAKER_1:  Flowers for Valentine's Day.
SPEAKER_1:  posting on Instagram, quote.
SPEAKER_1:  I've been fucking him in every round in competition since we met in 2018.
SPEAKER_1:  The least I can do is buy him flowers.
SPEAKER_1:  We didn't get the flowers. No, that was the question. Did you get the flowers? You never got the flowers. He sent it to the wrong address.
SPEAKER_1:  He did?
SPEAKER_1:  Where do you think he sent it?
SPEAKER_1:  It was close, but it was wrong. Did you appreciate the romantic gesture?
SPEAKER_0:  I did, I was looking forward to the flowers and-
SPEAKER_0:  potentially chocolates in there.
SPEAKER_0:  But you know, it was a bit of a let down.
SPEAKER_1:  Can you describe your recent match against Gordon, the EBR match?
SPEAKER_0:  Okay so EBI match on UFC Fight Pals was a 20 minute match.
SPEAKER_0:  And immediately...
SPEAKER_0:  No match starts, I pull guard.
SPEAKER_0:  And then I stand up, he pulls guard.
SPEAKER_0:  And we have this kind of like back and forth where he's trying to dig for underhooks, trying to get on top of me and he can't really find success.
SPEAKER_0:  Uh, and out and, and then in the midst of me trying to work my body lock pass, uh, Gordon's able to under hook a leg and we end up in a.
SPEAKER_0:  Like entanglement?
SPEAKER_0:  And then I'm able to transfer that leg entanglement to a 50-50 position, still in the leg entanglement.
SPEAKER_0:  From that 50-50 position, I'm able to separate his feet and actually get a few pops. And he actually said I broke his foot in that exchange.
SPEAKER_0:  With a toehold. A toehold, yep. And after that, we had a.
SPEAKER_0:  A bit more, I was just being working on top position, trying to get my body locked. Time runs out and we go to overtime.
SPEAKER_0:  And overtime,
SPEAKER_1:  Hold on a second, actually, what does it mean to break a leg? I was very confused about-
SPEAKER_1:  Okay, so is this like a expression or what do you mean? What when you broke it? What which part breaks in a toll?
SPEAKER_0:  Okay, so on a toehold, there's a few different grades of it. Like you could get a few pops and have some walking issues.
SPEAKER_0:  And people consider that break and then you could break it fully and have your foot be like a limp noodle
SPEAKER_0:  You know, I think what goes at Achilles?
SPEAKER_0:  We'll get to the front of the Achilles.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, probably the ligaments. I mean, it's funny, like, a lot of people say they broke something, but like to me, you break bones, you tear ligaments. So I would imagine you probably had a...
SPEAKER_1:  Grade 3 tear.
SPEAKER_1:  Grade three.
SPEAKER_1:  How hard do you think is it to, I always wondered that with, um,
SPEAKER_1:  with like a straight foot lock, how hard is it to break the shin? or like the actual bones versus the teres though?
SPEAKER_1:  Depends how many steroids there are.
SPEAKER_1:  and obviously how much you're on.
SPEAKER_0:  You're one of the few guys that have actually broken bones in competition.
SPEAKER_1:  Uh, yeah, have I?
SPEAKER_1:  Oh yeah, a video? BYE
SPEAKER_1:  Which bone did you break?
SPEAKER_1:  Spiral fracture of the fibula.
SPEAKER_1:  Very specific. A lot of power. Is it like a twist thing? How did you break it? Oh, it was a heel hook. Benny always used to say heel hooks.
SPEAKER_1:  Leg locks don't work.
SPEAKER_1:  But unfortunately...
SPEAKER_1:  Age gets the best of all of us.
SPEAKER_1:  I think he had some mileage on those ligaments.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah. And the bone, I guess. So it's actually what the bone.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, his ankle like disconnected from the tibia and the fibula, but the fibula definitely.
SPEAKER_1:  Snaps pretty bad though. I fell off. N constipation?
SPEAKER_1:  the dynamics of that. Okay, anyway, it went over time. What happened in overtime? Okay.
SPEAKER_0:  We're having overtime. Let's see.
SPEAKER_0:  trying to hang, oh, okay, I go defense first. whistle blows, I'm able to escape in like 17 seconds.
SPEAKER_0:  And then immediately after I go on his back and.
SPEAKER_0:  he gets out in exactly 17 seconds. I'm like, shit, all right, I thought I had a good start.
SPEAKER_0:  And then...
SPEAKER_0:  He gets on my back right after that, and he's able to ride me out for pretty much the entire round.
SPEAKER_0:  After that, I go back on his back, he escapes in maybe like a minute and some change.
SPEAKER_0:  I think where I went wrong in the overtime is I should have been less adamant about chasing the submission and more aware of collecting time.
SPEAKER_0:  I kind of diverted my attention towards acquiring, you know.
SPEAKER_0:  time on the clock it would have been more my favor. But yeah, at the end of my overtime round, I'm able to lock up a renegade choke over the face.
SPEAKER_0:  but there just wasn't enough time to fully finish. You know, I got a few seconds of squeeze in there. I didn't have enough time to adjust and f***.
SPEAKER_0:  God, oh, dude.
SPEAKER_1:  think if you're on steroids, you would have finished the joke.
SPEAKER_0:  I mean, for sure, for sure. That's what I thought too. If you're on gear, you're changing the biology of your body. You're adjusting your DNA.
SPEAKER_0:  for sure if I adjust in my DNA, I mean.
SPEAKER_1:  It's a finish. You're implying you're a natural athlete, is what you're saying.
SPEAKER_0:  Oh, I'm definitely a natural athlete, yeah.
SPEAKER_0:  Have immigration.
SPEAKER_1:  Okay.
SPEAKER_1:  So for people who don't know that the EBI rules, it's an interesting rule structure where the overtime you put
SPEAKER_1:  yourself in the worst possible position and the task is to escape and the other person gets the same thing
SPEAKER_1:  What do you guys think about that rule set?
SPEAKER_0:  I like it just because...
SPEAKER_0:  First of all, I don't like the idea of having to put somebody on my back, but I do like the definitive answer in the match. Either you escaped in time or you got ridden out. So you get to define a winner, that's great. I'd much rather have that than a close decision.
SPEAKER_1:  or why you.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, honestly, there's all the different rules. When I look at the rule sets, I just try to think of what rules that I could beat that individual in.
SPEAKER_1:  and I sort of gear myself towards that.
SPEAKER_1:  That's really the strategy there. I think there's some guys that like, uh,
SPEAKER_1:  that stole a lot.
SPEAKER_1:  that you would love to have EBI overtime with at the end, you know, they're stalling until...
SPEAKER_1:  They have to give us a good position.
SPEAKER_1:  But then there's some guys that are so good in those positions. I'm like, oh, maybe we just do a regular match, you know?
SPEAKER_1:  What are the rules in the streets? No time limit.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  That's one of it.
SPEAKER_1:  There's also like
SPEAKER_1:  concrete and cars and stuff. They have lots of things to
SPEAKER_1:  Biting, yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  talking.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, so you don't like that rule set?
SPEAKER_1:  Are there some people you would prefer in the street as a rule set?
SPEAKER_1:  Me? Probably not.
SPEAKER_1:  Hahahaha
SPEAKER_1:  I don't know the EBI. I mean, it's tricky, you know, it depends on the opponent, which rules that I'd want to do.
SPEAKER_1:  What about you, Nicker? What do you think about the ruleset of EBI? Yes, I think EBI is very good from a spectator point of view. You know, people find it very entertaining to watch, you know, because you're...
SPEAKER_1:  people want to see submissions and you're putting people, you're putting the athletes in a position where, you have like the highest percentage submission in the sport.
SPEAKER_1:  So obviously you're gonna get a lot of submissions.
SPEAKER_1:  My issue with it is it is a rule set that allows somebody that's overall worse at jiu-jitsu to win a match
SPEAKER_1:  A guy can go out there and just stall and just get completely dominated for the entirety of regulation and then he gets to start on the guy's back. So that's my one issue with it.
SPEAKER_1:  but also...
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, it's interesting to see.
SPEAKER_1:  Like the best people in the world have to be put in a really bad position.
SPEAKER_1:  and to see how good their escapes are, for example. Yeah.
SPEAKER_1:  But it doesn't feel like a realistic, it's a fun thing to watch but it doesn't feel like
SPEAKER_1:  The real fight.
SPEAKER_1:  It feels weird.
SPEAKER_1:  I'll claim it. If I start an overtime on someone and finish them, I'll claim it. But if they submit me an overtime, I'm like, I asked them. You're good to know. Yeah. It's not a real submission. It's good.
SPEAKER_1:  If you have a good one, stay well.
SPEAKER_0:  The issue is people stalling to just win overtime. You got this guy that his whole training camp is just
SPEAKER_0:  not get subbed and win overtime.
SPEAKER_0:  It's a bit boring.
SPEAKER_1:  By the way, I have a rose behind you.
SPEAKER_1:  Somebody gave me a Valentine's flower. So if you miss the one from Gordon, I got one for you.
SPEAKER_0:  Appreciate that.
SPEAKER_1:  It's good to feel loved. Yeah. All right. Um,
SPEAKER_1:  Funny Facts
SPEAKER_1:  So what did you learn from that match? Like takeaways, technically speaking, like what do you need to work on?
SPEAKER_0:  Well, I learned that I am pretty good.
SPEAKER_1:  I mean, I would.
SPEAKER_0:  Yeah, pretty good. I got a few, I know exactly what my weakness is. It's the leg lock department and I'm doing a lot to get better in that specific aspect. Attack and defense? I would say yeah, attack, defense, reattacks.
SPEAKER_0:  Um, even if I wanted to offensively enter a leg, you know, I could use some work there as well.
SPEAKER_0:  But I feel like once I solidify like
SPEAKER_0:  my like if I come up become a black belt specifically in the leg lock department, I feel like I'd be unstoppable.
SPEAKER_1:  If you...
SPEAKER_1:  Nicky Rod definitively beat Gordon Ryan. How'd you do it?
SPEAKER_1:  Buggy check.
SPEAKER_1:  Puggy choke. Puggy choke.
SPEAKER_1:  The listener
SPEAKER_1:  I don't even know how to describe Bucky choke. What's the definitive conclusion on that choke?
SPEAKER_1:  Does it work? It's a choke.
SPEAKER_1:  that you do when you're in a...
SPEAKER_1:  uh... what's the opposite of dominance not submissive and not on the position
SPEAKER_1:  bottom of sight control.
SPEAKER_1:  Yeah, just an embarrassing submission to get caught with, really.
SPEAKER_1:  But does it work?
SPEAKER_1:  It works on...
SPEAKER_1:  certain people. For the listener, he glassed over a Niki. It's embarrassing, but it's also what is a way to frustrate the opponent.
SPEAKER_1:  For sure. Yeah. It's a new part of the spot. I feel like the Rotolo has brought it back into fashion and
SPEAKER_1:  Even if you don't get it.
SPEAKER_1:  because it's one of those movies that's so embarrassing.
SPEAKER_1:  at the first sign of danger.